<?xml version="1.0"?>
<Bill RHead_reign="59 Eliz. II" RHead_ParlYear="2010" DocumentTitle="BILL C-11" Bill_No="C-11" Document_No="90554" xml:lang="EN" Bill_Type="Non-amending" Stage_Name="Assented-to" Reprint="No" xml:space="preserve" ChapterNo_E="C. 8" ChapterNo_F="ch. 8" Bill-Origin="commons"><Bill_Part Part_Type="Cover" CountLines="No"><Block><Para TopMargin="24" Size="9" Leading="10" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0" TextAlign="Center">Third Session, Fortieth Parliament,</Para></Block><Block><Para Size="9" Leading="10" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0" TextAlign="Center">59 Elizabeth II, 2010</Para></Block><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="COV@StatutesTitle">STATUTES OF CANADA 2010<br/>CHAPTER 8</Para></Block><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="CovLongTitle">An Act to amend the Immigration and Refugee Protection Act and the Federal Courts Act</Para></Block><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="COV_StageLine"></Para></Block><Block><Para BottomMargin="14" Size="11" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0" Bold="Yes" TextAlign="Center">ASSENTED TO</Para></Block><Block><Para Size="8" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0" TextAlign="Center">29th JUNE, 2010</Para></Block><Block><Para TopMargin="4" Size="8" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0" TextAlign="Center">BILL C-11</Para></Block><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="COV_StageLine"></Para></Block></Bill_Part><Bill_Part CountLines="No" Part_Type="InsideCover"><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="BPT_InsideCoverE">Also available on the Parliament of Canada Web Site at the following address:<br/><B>http://www.parl.gc.ca</B></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><Para TopMargin="108" BottomMargin="4" Size="10" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">RECOMMENDATION</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" Size="8" Leading="9" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">Her Excellency the Governor General recommends to the House of Commons the appropriation of public revenue under the circumstances, in the manner and for the purposes set out in a measure entitled “<I>An Act to amend the Immigration and Refugee Protection Act and the Federal Courts Act</I>”.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><Para TopMargin="60" BottomMargin="4" Size="10" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">SUMMARY</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" Size="8" Leading="9" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">This enactment amends the <I>Immigration and Refugee Protection Act</I>, primarily in respect of the processing of refugee claims referred to the Immigration and Refugee Board. In particular, the enactment</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" Size="8" Leading="9" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">(<I>a</I>) provides for the referral of a refugee claimant to an interview with an Immigration and Refugee Board official, who is to collect information and schedule a hearing before the Refugee Protection Division;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" Size="8" Leading="9" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">(<I>b</I>) provides that the members of the Refugee Protection Division are appointed in accordance with the <I>Public Service Employment Act</I>;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" Size="8" Leading="9" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">(<I>c</I>) provides for the coming into force, no more than two years after the day on which the enactment receives royal assent, of the provisions of the <I>Immigration and Refugee Protection Act</I> that permit a claimant to appeal a decision of the Refugee Protection Division to the Refugee Appeal Division;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" Size="8" Leading="9" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">(<I>d</I>) authorizes the Minister to designate, in accordance with the process and criteria established by the regulations certain countries, parts of countries or classes of nationals;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" Size="8" Leading="9" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">(<I>e</I>) provides clarification with respect to the type of evidence that may be put before the Refugee Appeal Division and the circumstances in which that Division may hold a hearing;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" Size="8" Leading="9" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">(<I>f</I>) prohibits a person whose claim for refugee protection has been rejected from applying for a temporary resident permit or applying to the Minister for protection if less than 12 months have passed since their claim was rejected;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" Size="8" Leading="9" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">(<I>g</I>) authorizes the Minister, in respect of applications for protection, to exempt nationals, or classes of nationals, of a country or part of a country from the 12-month prohibition;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" Size="8" Leading="9" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">(<I>h</I>) provides clarification with respect to the Minister’s authority to grant permanent resident status or an exemption from any obligations of the Act on humanitarian and compassionate grounds or on public policy grounds;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" Size="8" Leading="9" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">(<I>i</I>) limits the circumstances in which the Minister may examine requests for permanent resident status or for an exemption from any obligations of the Act on humanitarian and compassionate grounds; and</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" Size="8" Leading="9" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">(<I>j</I>) enacts transitional provisions respecting the processing of pending claims by the Minister or the Immigration and Refugee Board.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" Size="8" Leading="9" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">The enactment also amends the <I>Federal Courts Act</I> to increase the number of Federal Court judges.</Para></Block></Bill_Part><Bill_Part Part_Type="MainText" CountLines="No" RunningHead_E="Immigration and Refugee Protection and Federal Courts"><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="MAIN@RoyalAssentTitle">59 ELIZABETH II</Para></Block><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="MAIN@RoyalAssentTitle">——————</Para></Block><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="MAIN@RoyalAssentTitle">CHAPTER 8</Para></Block><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="LongTitleAssent">An Act to amend the Immigration and Refugee Protection Act and the Federal Courts Act</Para></Block><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="MAIN@RoyalAssentDate">[<I>Assented to 29th June, 2010</I>]</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">Her Majesty, by and with the advice and consent of the Senate and House of Commons of Canada, enacts as follows:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:SHORT TITLE--><Para TopMargin="10" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">SHORT TITLE</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Short title<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>1.</B> This Act may be cited as the <I>Balanced Refugee Reform Act</I>.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:IMMIGRATION AND REFUGEE PROTECTION ACT--><MarginalNote>2001, c. 27<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="10" Bold="Yes" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">IMMIGRATION AND REFUGEE PROTECTION ACT</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>2.</B> Paragraph 16(2)(<I>b</I>) of the <I>Immigration and Refugee Protection Act</I> is replaced by the following:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>b</I>) subject to the regulations, the foreign national must submit to a medical examination.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>3.</B> Section 24 of the Act is amended by adding the following after subsection (3):</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Restriction<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(4) A foreign national whose claim for refugee protection has been rejected or determined to be withdrawn or abandoned by the Refugee Protection Division or the Refugee Appeal Division may not request a temporary resident permit if less than 12 months have passed since their claim was last rejected or determined to be withdrawn or abandoned.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>2008, c. 28, s. 117<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>4.</B> (1) Subsection 25(1) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Humanitarian and compassionate considerations — request of foreign national<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>25.</B> (1) The Minister must, on request of a foreign national in Canada who is inadmissible or who does not meet the requirements of this Act, and may, on request of a foreign national outside Canada, examine the circumstances concerning the foreign national and may grant the foreign national permanent resident status or an exemption from any applicable criteria or obligations of this Act if the Minister is of the opinion that it is justified by humanitarian and compassionate considerations relating to the foreign national, taking into account the best interests of a child directly affected.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Payment of fees<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(1.1) The Minister is seized of a request referred to in subsection (1) only if the applicable fees in respect of that request have been paid.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Exceptions<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(1.2) The Minister may not examine the request if the foreign national has already made such a request and the request is pending.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Non-application of certain factors<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(1.3) In examining the request of a foreign national in Canada, the Minister may not consider the factors that are taken into account in the determination of whether a person is a Convention refugee under section 96 or a person in need of protection under subsection 97(1) but must consider elements related to the hardships that affect the foreign national.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes">(2) Subsection 25(2) of the French version of the Act is replaced by the following:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Critères provinciaux<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><AltLang xml:lang="fr">(2) Le statut de résident permanent ne peut toutefois être octroyé à l’étranger visé au paragraphe 9(1) qui ne répond pas aux critères de sélection de la province en cause qui lui sont applicables.</AltLang></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>5.</B> The Act is amended by adding the following after section 25:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Humanitarian and compassionate considerations — Minister’s own initiative<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>25.1</B> (1) The Minister may, on the Minister’s own initiative, examine the circumstances concerning a foreign national who is inadmissible or who does not meet the requirements of this Act and may grant the foreign national permanent resident status or an exemption from any applicable criteria or obligations of this Act if the Minister is of the opinion that it is justified by humanitarian and compassionate considerations relating to the foreign national, taking into account the best interests of a child directly affected.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Exemption<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(2) The Minister may exempt the foreign national from the payment of any applicable fees in respect of the examination of their circumstances under subsection (1).</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Provincial criteria<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(3) The Minister may not grant permanent resident status to a foreign national referred to in subsection 9(1) if the foreign national does not meet the province’s selection criteria applicable to that foreign national.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Public policy considerations<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>25.2</B> (1) The Minister may, in examining the circumstances concerning a foreign national who is inadmissible or who does not meet the requirements of this Act, grant that person permanent resident status or an exemption from any applicable criteria or obligations of this Act if the Minister is of the opinion that it is justified by public policy considerations.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Exemption<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(2) The Minister may exempt the foreign national from the payment of any applicable fees in respect of the examination of their circumstances under subsection (1).</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Provincial criteria<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(3) The Minister may not grant permanent resident status to a foreign national referred to in subsection 9(1) if the foreign national does not meet the province’s selection criteria applicable to that foreign national.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>6.</B> The portion of section 26 of the Act before paragraph (<I>a</I>) is replaced by the following:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Regulations<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>26.</B> The regulations may provide for any matter relating to the application of sections 18 to 25.2, and may include provisions respecting</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>2008, c. 3, s. 3<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>7.</B> Paragraph 36(3)(<I>e</I>) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>e</I>) inadmissibility under subsections (1) and (2) may not be based on an offence</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="4" FirstLineIndent="0">(i) designated as a contravention under the <I>Contraventions Act</I>,</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="4" FirstLineIndent="0">(ii) for which the permanent resident or foreign national is found guilty under the <I>Young Offenders Act</I>, chapter Y-1 of the Revised Statutes of Canada, 1985, or</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="4" FirstLineIndent="0">(iii) for which the permanent resident or foreign national received a youth sentence under the <I>Youth Criminal Justice Act.</I></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>8.</B> Section 91 of the Act is replaced by the following:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Regulations<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>91.</B> The regulations may govern who may or may not represent, advise or consult with a person who is the subject of a proceeding or application before the Minister, an officer or any Division of the Board, including an interview before an official referred to in subsection 100(4.1).</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>9.</B> Paragraph 94(2)(<I>e</I>) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>e</I>) the number of persons granted permanent resident status under each of subsections 25(1), 25.1(1) and 25.2(1); and</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>10.</B> Paragraphs 95(1)(<I>a</I>) and (<I>b</I>) of the French version of the Act are replaced by the following:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0"><AltLang xml:lang="fr"><I>a</I>) sur constat qu’elle est, à la suite d’une demande de visa, un réfugié au sens de la Convention ou une personne en situation semblable, elle devient soit un résident permanent au titre du visa, soit un résident temporaire au titre d’un permis de séjour délivré en vue de sa protection;</AltLang></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0"><AltLang xml:lang="fr"><I>b</I>) la Commission lui reconnaît la qualité de réfugié au sens de la Convention ou celle de personne à protéger;</AltLang></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>11.</B> (1) Section 100 of the Act is amended by adding the following after subsection (1):</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Burden of proof<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(1.1) The burden of proving that a claim is eligible to be referred to the Refugee Protection Division rests on the claimant, who must answer truthfully all questions put to them.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes">(2) Subsection 100(4) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Duty of claimant<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(4) A person whose claim is referred to the Refugee Protection Division must attend an interview with an official of the Board on a date fixed by the referring officer in accordance with the rules of the Board and must at the interview produce all documents and information required by those rules. The date fixed for the interview must not be earlier than 15 days after the day on which the claim is referred, unless the claimant consents to an earlier date.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Hearing — Refugee Protection Division<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(4.1) The official of the Board who conducts the interview must, in accordance with the regulations and any directions of the Chairperson of the Board, fix the date on which the claimant is to attend a hearing before the Refugee Protection Division.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>11.1</B> The Act is amended by adding the following after section 107:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Manifestly unfounded<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>107.1</B> If the Refugee Protection Division rejects a claim for refugee protection, it may state in its reasons for the decision that the claim is manifestly unfounded if it is of the opinion that the claim is clearly fraudulent.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>12.</B> The Act is amended by adding the following after section 109:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:Designated Countries of Origin--><Para TopMargin="10" Italic="Yes" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">Designated Countries of Origin</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Designation of countries of origin<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>109.1</B> (1) The Minister may, by order, for the purposes of section 111.1, designate a country or part of a country or a class of nationals of a country.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Limitation<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(1.1) The Minister may make a designation only if</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>a</I>) the number of claims for refugee protection made in Canada by nationals of the country in question is equal to or greater than the number set out in the regulations; and</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>b</I>) the rate of acceptance by the Refugee Protection Division of claims made by nationals of the country in question is equal to or lower than the rate set out in the regulations.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Criteria to be considered<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(1.2) In making a designation, the Minister must take the following criteria into account:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>a</I>) the human rights record of the country in question as it relates to</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="4" FirstLineIndent="0">(i) the factors set out in sections 96 and 97, and</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="4" FirstLineIndent="0">(ii) the international human rights instruments specified in the regulations and any other international instrument that the Minister considers relevant;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>b</I>) the availability in the country in question of mechanisms for seeking protection and redress;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>c</I>) the number of claims for refugee protection made in Canada by nationals of the country in question;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>d</I>) the rate of acceptance by the Refugee Protection Division of claims made by nationals of the country in question and the rate of appeals allowed by the Refugee Appeal Division in respect of appeals made by nationals of the country in question; and</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>e</I>) any other criteria set out in the regulations.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote><I>Statutory Instruments Act</I><br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(2) An order referred to in subsection (1) is not a statutory instrument for the purposes of the <I>Statutory Instruments Act</I>. However, it must be published in the <I>Canada Gazett</I><I>e</I>.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>13.</B> (1) Subsection 110(1) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Appeal<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>110.</B> (1) A person or the Minister may appeal, in accordance with the rules of the Board, on a question of law, of fact or of mixed law and fact, to the Refugee Appeal Division against a decision of the Refugee Protection Division to allow or reject the person’s claim for refugee protection, or a decision of the Refugee Protection Division rejecting an application by the Minister for a determination that refugee protection has ceased or an application by the Minister to vacate a decision to allow a claim for refugee protection.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes">(2) Subsection 110(3) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Making of appeal<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(2.1) The appeal must be filed and perfected within the time limits set out in the regulations.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Procedure<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(3) Subject to subsections (3.1), (4) and (6), the Refugee Appeal Division must proceed without a hearing, on the basis of the record of the proceedings of the Refugee Protection Division, and may accept documentary evidence and written submissions from the Minister and the person who is the subject of the appeal and written submissions from a representative or agent of the United Nations High Commissioner for Refugees and any other person described in the rules of the Board.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Time limits<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(3.1) Unless a hearing is held under subsection (6), the Refugee Appeal Division must make a decision within the time limits set out in the regulations.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Evidence that may be presented<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(4) On appeal, the person who is the subject of the appeal may present only evidence that arose after the rejection of their claim or that was not reasonably available, or that the person could not reasonably have been expected in the circumstances to have presented, at the time of the rejection.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Exception<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(5) Subsection (4) does not apply in respect of evidence that is presented in response to evidence presented by the Minister.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Hearing<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(6) The Refugee Appeal Division may hold a hearing if, in its opinion, there is documentary evidence referred to in subsection (3)</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>a</I>) that raises a serious issue with respect to the credibility of the person who is the subject of the appeal;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>b</I>) that is central to the decision with respect to the refugee protection claim; and</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>c</I>) that, if accepted, would justify allowing or rejecting the refugee protection claim.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>14.</B> Subsection 111(2) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Manifestly unfounded<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(1.1) For greater certainty, if the Refugee Appeal Division does not set it aside, the Refugee Protection Division’s determination under section 107.1 is confirmed.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Referrals<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(2) The Refugee Appeal Division may make the referral described in paragraph (1)(<I>c</I>) only if it is of the opinion that</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>a</I>) the decision of the Refugee Protection Division is wrong in law, in fact or in mixed law and fact; and</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>b</I>) it cannot make a decision under paragraph 111(1)(<I>a</I>) or (<I>b</I>) without hearing evidence that was presented to the Refugee Protection Division.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>14.1</B> The Act is amended by adding the following after section 111:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:Regulations--><Para TopMargin="10" Italic="Yes" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">Regulations</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Regulations<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>111.1</B> (1) The regulations may provide for any matter relating to the application of this Division, and may include provisions</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>a</I>) relating to the criteria referred to in subsection 109.1(1.2) and the process to be followed with respect to a designation made under subsection 109.1(1);</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>b</I>) establishing criteria for the purposes of paragraph 109.1(1.2)(<I>e</I>); and</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>c</I>) respecting the time limits</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="4" FirstLineIndent="0">(i) for the hearing referred to in subsection 100(4.1),</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="4" FirstLineIndent="0">(ii) for the filing and perfecting of an appeal under subsection 110(2.1), and</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="4" FirstLineIndent="0">(iii) for the making of a decision by the Refugee Appeal Division, the extension of those time limits and the circumstances under which they do not apply.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Clarification — regulations made under subparagraph <keep>(1)(<I>c</I>)(i)</keep><br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(2) Regulations made under subparagraph (1)(<I>c</I>)(i) may provide for time limits for any of the following claimants that are different from the time limits for other claimants:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>a</I>) claimants who are nationals of a country that is, on the date of their interview referred to in subsection 100(4), a country designated under subsection 109.1(1);</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>b</I>) claimants who are nationals of a country of which a part is, on the date of their interview referred to in subsection 100(4), a part designated under subsection 109.1(1); or</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>c</I>) claimants who belong to a class of nationals of a country that is, on the date of their interview referred to in subsection 100(4), a class designated under subsection 109.1(1).</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Clarification — regulations made under subparagraph <keep>(1)(<I>c</I>)(ii)</keep><br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(3) Regulations made under subparagraph (1)(<I>c</I>)(ii) may provide for time limits for the filing and perfecting of appeals by any of the following claimants that are different from the time limits for other claimants:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>a</I>) claimants whose claims are found by the Refugee Protection Division to be manifestly unfounded under section 107.1;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>b</I>) claimants who are nationals of any country that is, on the day on which the decision being appealed is made, a country designated under subsection 109.1(1);</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>c</I>) claimants who are nationals of a country of which a part is, on the day on which the decision being appealed is made, a part designated under that subsection and who lived in that designated part before they left the country; or</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>d</I>) claimants who belong to a class of nationals of a country that is, on the day on which the decision being appealed is made, a class designated under that subsection.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Clarification — regulations made under subparagraph <keep>(1)(<I>c</I>)(iii)</keep><br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(4) Regulations made under subparagraph (1)(<I>c</I>)(iii) may provide for time limits for making decisions in respect of appeals by claimants referred to in paragraphs (3)(<I>a</I>) to (<I>d</I>) that are different from the time limits for other claimants.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>15.</B> (1) Subsection 112(1) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Application for protection<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>112.</B> (1) Subject to subsection (1.1), a person in Canada, other than a person referred to in subsection 115(1), may, in accordance with the regulations and the rules of the Board, apply to the Refugee Protection Division for protection if they are subject to a removal order that is in force.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Application to Minister<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(1.1) In the case of a person described in subsection (3), the application for protection must be made to the Minister in accordance with the regulations.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Suspension of application<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(1.2) Proceedings of the Refugee Protection Division in respect of an application are suspended on notice by an officer that</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>a</I>) a report has been referred to the Immigration Division for a determination of whether the applicant is inadmissible on grounds of security, violating human or international rights, serious criminality — as referred to in paragraph (3)(<I>b</I>) — or organ- ized criminality; or</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>b</I>) the applicant is the subject of an authority to proceed issued under section 15 of the <I>Extradition Act</I>.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Transfer — inadmissibility<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(1.3) On notice by an officer that the Immigration Division has made a determination that the applicant is inadmissible on the grounds referred to in paragraph (1.2)(<I>a</I>), consideration of the application is transferred to the Minister.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Continuation<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(1.4) On notice by an officer that the Immigration Division has made a determination that the applicant is not inadmissible on the grounds referred to in paragraph (1.2)(<I>a</I>), consideration of the application is continued by the Refugee Protection Division.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Termination after surrender under <I>Extradition Act</I><br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(1.5) If the applicant is ordered surrendered by the Minister of Justice under the <I>Extradition Act</I>, consideration of the application is terminated.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Continuation<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(1.6) If the applicant is finally discharged under the <I>Extradition Act</I>, consideration of the application is continued by the Refugee Protection Division.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Transfer: Refugee Convention<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(1.7) If the Refugee Protection Division makes a determination that the applicant is referred to in section F of Article 1 of the Refugee Convention, consideration of the application is transferred to the Minister.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes">(2) The portion of subsection 112(2) of the Act before paragraph (<I>a</I>) is replaced by the following:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Exception<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(2) Despite subsections (1) and (1.1), a person may not apply for protection if</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes">(3) Subsection 112(2) of the Act is amended by adding the following after paragraph (<I>b</I>):</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>b.1</I>) subject to subsection (2.1), less than 12 months have passed since their claim for refugee protection was last rejected — unless it was rejected on the basis of section E or F of Article 1 of the Refugee Convention — or determined to be withdrawn or abandoned by the Refugee Protection Division or the Refugee Appeal Division;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes">(4) Section 112 of the Act is amended by adding the following after subsection (2):</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Exemption<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(2.1) The Minister may exempt from the application of paragraph (2)(<I>b.1</I>)</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>a</I>) the nationals — or, in the case of persons who do not have a country of nationality, the former habitual residents — of a country;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>b</I>) the nationals or former habitual residents of a country who, before they left the country, lived in a given part of that country; and</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>c</I>) a class of nationals or former habitual residents of a country.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Application<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(2.2) However, an exemption made under subsection (2.1) does not apply to persons in respect of whom, after the day on which the exemption comes into force, a decision is made respecting their claim for refugee protection by the Refugee Protection Division or, if an appeal is made, by the Refugee Appeal Division.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Regulations<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(2.3) The regulations may govern any matter relating to the application of subsection (2.1) or (2.2) and may include provisions establishing the criteria to be considered when an exemption is made.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes">(5) Subsection 112(3) of the Act is amended by striking out “or” at the end of paragraph (<I>c</I>) and by adding the following after paragraph (<I>c</I>):</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>c.1</I>) made an application for protection and the consideration of that application was transferred to the Minister under subsection (1.7); or</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>16.</B> Paragraphs 113(<I>a</I>) and (<I>b</I>) of the Act are replaced by the following:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0"><AltLang xml:lang="fr">(<I>a</I>) an applicant whose claim for refugee protection or whose most recent application for protection, as the case may be, has been rejected may present only evidence that arose after the rejection or was not reasonably available, or that the applicant could not reasonably have been expected in the circumstances to have presented, at the time of the rejection;</AltLang></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0"><AltLang xml:lang="fr">(<I>b</I>) in the case of an applicant described in subsection 112(3), a hearing may be held if the Minister, on the basis of prescribed factors, is of the opinion that a hearing is required;</AltLang></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0"><AltLang xml:lang="fr">(<I>b.1</I>) subject to paragraphs (<I>a</I>) and (<I>b.3</I>), in the case of an applicant not described in subsection 112(3), the Refugee Protection Division must proceed without a hearing and may accept documentary evidence and written submissions from the Minister and the applicant;</AltLang></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0"><AltLang xml:lang="fr">(<I>b.2</I>) in the case of an applicant not described in subsection 112(3), paragraph (<I>a</I>) does not apply in respect of evidence that is presented in response to evidence presented by the Minister;</AltLang></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0"><AltLang xml:lang="fr">(<I>b.3</I>) in the case of an applicant not described in subsection 112(3), the Refugee Protection Division may hold a hearing if, in its opinion, there is documentary evidence referred to in paragraph (<I>b.1</I>)</AltLang></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="4" FirstLineIndent="0"><AltLang xml:lang="fr">(i) that raises a serious issue with respect to the credibility of the applicant,</AltLang></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="4" FirstLineIndent="0"><AltLang xml:lang="fr">(ii) that is central to the decision with respect to the application, and</AltLang></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="4" FirstLineIndent="0"><AltLang xml:lang="fr">(iii) that, if accepted, would justify allow- ing the application;</AltLang></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>16.1</B> The Act is amended by adding the following after section 114:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Limitation<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>114.1</B> (1) Subsections 114(3) and (4) apply in respect of a decision to allow an application for protection only if the application was made to the Minister under subsection 112(1.1) or transferred to the Minister under subsection 112(1.3) or (1.7). </Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Application of section 109<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(2) Section 109 applies to a decision made by the Refugee Protection Division to allow an application for protection as if it were a decision to allow a claim for refugee protection.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>17.</B> The Act is amended by adding the following after section 152:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Oath or affirmation of office<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>152.1</B> The Chairperson and other members of the Board must swear the oath or give the solemn affirmation of office set out in the rules of the Board.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>18.</B> (1) The portion of subsection 153(1) of the Act before paragraph (<I>a</I>) is replaced by the following:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Chairperson and other members<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>153.</B> (1) The Chairperson and members of the Refugee Appeal Division and Immigration Appeal Division</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes">(2) Paragraph 153(1)(<I>b</I>) of the Act is repealed.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>19.</B> (1) Paragraphs 159(1)(<I>b</I>) to (<I>d</I>) of the Act are replaced by the following:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>b</I>) may at any time assign a member appointed under paragraph 153(1)(<I>a</I>) to the Refugee Appeal Division or the Immigration Appeal Division;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>c</I>) may at any time, despite paragraph 153(1)(<I>a</I>), assign a member of the Refugee Appeal Division or the Immigration Appeal Division to work in another regional <keep>or district</keep> office to satisfy operational <keep>requirements, but</keep> an assignment may not exceed 120 days without the approval of the Governor in Council;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>d</I>) may designate, from among the full-time members appointed under paragraph 153(1)(<I>a</I>), coordinating members for the Refugee Appeal Division or the Immigration Appeal Division;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes">(2) Paragraph 159(1)(<I>h</I>) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>h</I>) may issue guidelines in writing to members of the Board and identify decisions of the Board as jurisprudential guides, after consulting with the Deputy Chairpersons, to assist members in carrying out their duties; and</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes">(3) Subsection 159(2) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Delegation<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(2) The Chairperson may delegate any of his or her powers under this Act to a member of the Board, except that</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>a</I>) powers referred to in subsection 161(1) may not be delegated;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>b</I>) powers referred to in paragraphs (1)(<I>a</I>) and (<I>i</I>) may be delegated to the Executive Director of the Board;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>c</I>) powers in relation to the Immigration Appeal Division and the Refugee Appeal Division may only be delegated to the Deputy Chairperson, the Assistant Deputy Chairpersons, or other members, including coordinating members, of either of those Divisions; and</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>d</I>) powers in relation to the Immigration Division or the Refugee Protection Division may only be delegated to the Deputy Chairperson, the Assistant Deputy Chairpersons or other members, including coordinating members, of that Division.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>20.</B> The portion of subsection 161(1) of the Act before paragraph (<I>b</I>) is replaced by the following:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Rules<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>161.</B> (1) Subject to the approval of the Governor in Council, and in consultation with the Deputy Chairpersons, the Chairperson may make rules respecting</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>a</I>) the referral of a claim for refugee protection to the Refugee Protection Division and the conduct of the interview referred to in subsection 100(4);</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>a.1</I>) the factors to be taken into account in fixing or changing the date of an interview referred to in subsection 100(4);</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>a.2</I>) the activities, practice and procedure of each of the Divisions of the Board, including the periods for appeal, other than in respect of appeals of decisions of the Refugee Protection Division, the priority to be given to proceedings, the notice that is required and the period in which notice must be given;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>21.</B> Section 163 of the Act is replaced by the following:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Composition of panels<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>163.</B> Matters before a Division must be conducted before a single member unless, with respect to a matter before the Refugee Appeal Division or the Immigration Appeal Division, the Chairperson is of the opinion that a panel of three members should be constituted.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>22.</B> Section 165 of the Act is replaced by the following:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Powers of a commissioner<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>165.</B> The Refugee Protection Division, the Refugee Appeal Division and the Immigration Division and each member of those Divisions have the powers and authority of a commissioner appointed under Part I of the <I>Inquiries Act</I> and may do any other thing they consider necessary to provide a full and proper hearing.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>23.</B> Subsection 167(1) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Right to counsel<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>167.</B> (1) A person who is the subject of proceedings before any Division of the Board, including the interview referred to in subsection 100(4), and the Minister may, at their own expense, be represented by legal or other counsel.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>24.</B> Subsection 168(1) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Abandonment of proceeding<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>168.</B> (1) A Division may determine that a proceeding before it has been abandoned if the Division is of the opinion that the applicant is in default in the proceedings, including by failing to attend the interview referred to in subsection 100(4), to appear for a hearing, to provide information required by the Division or to communicate with the Division on being requested to do so.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>25.</B> (1) Paragraph 169(<I>c</I>) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>c</I>) the decision may be rendered orally or in writing, except for a decision of the Refugee Protection Division in respect of an application for protection under subsection 112(1), which must be rendered in writing;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes">(2) Section 169 of the Act is amended by striking out “and” at the end of paragraph (<I>e</I>) and by adding the following after paragraph (<I>e</I>):</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>e.1</I>) notice of a decision of the Refugee Protection Division in respect of an application for protection, as well as written reasons for the decision, must, in accordance with the regulations, be provided to the Minister, who must then provide the notice and reasons to the applicant in accordance with the regulations; and</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes">(3) Section 169 of the Act is renumbered as subsection 169(1) and is amended by adding the following:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Regulations<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(2) The regulations may govern the time within which and the manner in which notice of a decision of the Refugee Protection Division in respect of an application for protection, as well as written reasons for the decision, must be provided.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>26.</B> The Act is amended by adding the following before section 170:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Composition<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>169.1</B> (1) The Refugee Protection Division consists of the Deputy Chairperson, Assistant Deputy Chairpersons and other members, including coordinating members, necessary to carry out its functions.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote><I>Public Service Employment Act</I><br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(2) The members of the Refugee Protection Division are appointed in accordance with the <I>Public Service Employment Act</I>.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>27.</B> (1) The portion of section 170 of the Act before paragraph (<I>a</I>) is replaced by the following:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Proceedings<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>170.</B> Except in respect of an application for protection made under subsection 112(1), the Refugee Protection Division, in any proceeding before it,</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>(2)</B> Section 170 of the Act is amended by adding the following after paragraph (<I>d</I>):</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>d.1</I>) may question the witnesses, including the person who is the subject of the proceeding;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>27.1</B> The Act is amended by adding the following after section 170:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Application for protection<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>170.1</B> In respect of an application for protection under subsection 112(1), the Refugee Protection Division</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>a</I>) may inquire into any matter that it considers relevant to establishing whether an application is well-founded;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>b</I>) must provide the Minister, on request, with the documentary evidence and written submissions of the applicant that are referred to in paragraph 113(<I>b.1</I>);</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>c</I>) must give notice of any hearing to the Minister and the applicant;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>d</I>) subject to paragraph 113(<I>a</I>), must — if a hearing is held — give the applicant and the Minister the opportunity to present evidence, question witnesses and make submissions;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>e</I>) may question the witnesses, including the applicant;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>f</I>) is not bound by any legal or technical rules of evidence;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>g</I>) may receive and base a decision on evidence that is adduced in the proceedings and considered credible or trustworthy in the circumstances; and</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>h</I>) may take notice of any facts that may be judicially noticed and of any other generally recognized facts and any information or opinion that is within its specialized knowledge.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>28.</B> (1) Paragraph 171(<I>a</I>) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>a</I>) the Division must give notice of any hearing to the Minister and to the person who is the subject of the appeal;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>a.1</I>) subject to subsection 110(4), if a hearing is held, the Division must give the person who is the subject of the appeal and the Minister the opportunity to present evidence, question witnesses and make submissions;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>a.2</I>) the Division is not bound by any legal or technical rules of evidence;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>a.3</I>) the Division may receive and base a decision on evidence that is adduced in the proceedings and considered credible or trustworthy in the circumstances;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>a.4</I>) the Minister may, after giving notice in accordance with the rules, intervene in the appeal, including for the purpose of filing submissions;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes">(2) Paragraph 171(<I>c</I>) of the French version of the Act is replaced by the following:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0"><AltLang xml:lang="fr"><I>c</I>) la décision du tribunal constitué de trois commissaires a la même valeur de précédent pour le tribunal constitué d’un commissaire unique et la Section de la protection des réfugiés que celle qu’une cour d’appel a pour une cour de première instance.</AltLang></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>29.</B> Section 172 of the Act is replaced by the following:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Composition<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>172.</B> (1) The Immigration Division consists of the Deputy Chairperson, Assistant Deputy Chairpersons and other members necessary to carry out its functions.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote><I>Public Service Employment Ac</I><I>t</I><br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(2) The members of the Immigration Division are appointed in accordance with the <I>Public Service Employment Act</I>.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>30.</B> Subsection 176(1) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Request<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>176.</B> (1) The Chairperson may request the Minister to decide whether any member of the Immigration Appeal Division or the Refugee Appeal Division should be subject to remedial or disciplinary measures for a reason set out in subsection (2).</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>31.</B> Section 275 of the Act is replaced by the following:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Coming into force<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>275.</B> Sections 73, 110, 111, 171, 194 and 195 come into force two years after the day on which the <I>Balanced Refugee Reform Act</I> receives royal assent or on any earlier day that may be fixed by order of the Governor in Council.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:TRANSITIONAL PROVISIONS--><Para TopMargin="10" Bold="Yes" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">TRANSITIONAL PROVISIONS</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Humanitarian and compassionate considerations<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>32.</B> Every request that is made under section 25 of the <I>Immigration and Refugee Protection Act</I>, as that Act read immediately before the day on which this Act receives royal assent, is to be determined in accord- ance with that Act as it read immediately before that day.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Refugee protection claim — Personal Information Form not yet submitted<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>33.</B> (1) The <I>Immigration and Refugee Protection Act</I>, as amended by this Act, applies to every claim for refugee protection made before the day on which this section comes into force if, before that day, the claimant has not submitted a Personal Information Form, as defined in section 1 of the <I>Refugee Protection Division Rules</I>, as they read immediately before that day, and the time limit for submitting that Form has not expired.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Day of interview<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes">(2) The day of the interview that the claimant referred to in subsection (1) must attend under subsection 100(4) of the <I>Immigration and Refugee Protection Act</I>, as enacted by subsection 11(2), is to be fixed by an official of the Immigration and Refugee Board.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Refugee protection claim — Personal Information Form submitted<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>34.</B> (1) The <I>Immigration and Refugee Protection Act</I>, as amended by this Act, except subsections 100(4) and (4.1), applies to every claim for refugee protection made before the day on which this section comes into force if, before that day,</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0" Bold="Yes">(<I>a</I>) the claimant has submitted a Personal Information Form, as defined in section 1 of the <I>Refugee Protection Division Rules</I>, as they read immediately before that day; and</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0" Bold="Yes">(<I>b</I>) there has been no hearing before the Refugee Protection Division in respect of the claim or, if there has been a hearing, no substantive evidence has been heard.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Interview<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes">(2) The claimant referred to in subsection (1) must attend an interview with an official of the Immigration and Refugee Board, if required to do so, on the date fixed by the official in accordance with the <I>Refugee Protection Division Rules</I> and must produce any supplementary documents and information that the official considers necessary.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Substantive evidence heard<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>35.</B> (1) Every claim for refugee protection in respect of which substantive evidence has been heard before the day on which subsection 18(1) comes into force by a single member or a panel of three members of the Refugee Protection Division appointed under paragraph 153(1)(<I>a</I>) of the <I>Immigration and Refugee Protection Act</I>, as it read immediately before that day, must continue to be heard by that single member or panel in accordance with that Act, as it read immediately before that day.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Single member unable to continue<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes">(2) If the single member is unable to continue to hear the claim, the claim must be referred to a member of the Refugee Protection Division referred to in section 169.1 of the <I>Immigration and Refugee Protection Act</I>, as enacted by section 26, and that member must commence a new hearing in accordance with that Act, as amended by this Act.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Member of panel unable to continue<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes">(3) If a member of the panel referred to in subsection (1) is unable to continue to hear the claim, the claim must continue to be heard by one of the two remaining members in accordance with the <I>Immigration and Refugee Protection Act</I>, as it read immediately before the day on which subsection 18(1) comes into force.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>No appeal to Refugee Appeal Division<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>36.</B> (1) A decision made by the Refugee Protection Division before the day on which this section comes into force is not subject to appeal to the Refugee Appeal Division.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>No waiting period<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes">(2) The person in respect of whom the decision was made is not required to wait for the expiry of the 12-month period referred to in paragraph 112(2)(<I>b.1</I>) of the <I>Immigration and Refugee Protection Act</I>, as enacted by subsection 15(3), before making an application under subsection 112(1) or (1.1) of that Act.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Decision set aside in judicial review<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>37.</B> If a decision referred to in subsection 36(1) is set aside in a judicial review, the claim for refugee protection must be referred to a member of the Refugee Protection Division referred to in section 169.1 of the <I>Immigration and Refugee Protection Act</I>, as enacted by section 26.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Application for protection<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>37.1</B> An application for protection that is made before the day on which subsection 15(1) comes into force is to be considered in accordance with the <I>Immigration and Refugee Protection Act</I>, as that Act read immediately before that day.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Application for protection<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>38.</B> For greater certainty, paragraph 112(2)(<I>b.1</I>) of the <I>Immigration and Refugee Protection Act</I>, as enacted by subsection <keep>15(3),</keep> does not apply if, before the day on which this section comes into force, an application for protection is made under subsection 112(1) of that Act.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Non-application<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>39.</B> Paragraph 25(1.2)(<I>b</I>) of the <I>Immigration and Refugee Protection Act</I>, as enacted by subsection 4(1), does not apply to a refugee claimant whose claim is pending before the Refugee Protection Division on the day on which section 36 comes into force.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Non-application<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>40.</B> Paragraph 25(1.2)(<I>c</I>) of the <I>Immigration and Refugee Protection Act</I>, as enacted by subsection 4(1), does not apply to a refugee claimant whose claim is rejected or determined to be withdrawn or abandoned by the Refugee Protection Division before the day on which section 36 comes into force.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:FEDERAL COURTS ACT--><MarginalNote>R.S., c. F-7; 2002, c. 8, s. 14<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="10" Bold="Yes" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">FEDERAL COURTS ACT</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>2001, c. 41, par. 144(2)(<I>b</I>)<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>41.</B> Subsection 5.1(1) of the <I>Federal Courts Act</I> is replaced by the following:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Constitution of Federal Court<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>5.1</B> (1) The Federal Court consists of a chief justice called the Chief Justice of the Federal Court, who is the president of the Federal Court, and 36 other judges.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:COMING INTO FORCE--><Para TopMargin="10" Bold="Yes" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">COMING INTO FORCE</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Order in council<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>42.</B> (1) Subject to subsection (2), the provisions of this Act, except sections 3 to 6, 9, 13, 14, 28, 31, 32, 39 and 40, come into force two years after the day on which this Act receives royal assent or on any earlier day or days that may be fixed by order of the Governor in Council.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Coming into force of certain provisions<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes">(2) Subsections 15(1), (2) and (5) and sections 16, 16.1, 27.1 and 37.1 come into force 12 months after the day on which subsection 15(3) comes into force, or on any earlier day that may be fixed by order of the Governor in Council.</Para></Block><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="BPT_ImprintE">Published under authority of the Speaker of the House of Commons<br/>Available from:<br/>Publishing and Depository Services<br/>Public Works and Government Services Canada<br/>Ottawa, Ontario K1A 0S5<br/>Telephone: 613-941-5995 or 1-800-635-7943<br/>Fax: 613-954-5779 or 1-800-565-7757<br/>publications@tpsgc-pwgsc.gc.ca<br/>http://publications.gc.ca</Para></Block><Block Align="Yes" LineCnt="N"><Para NoLineBreak="Yes" NoHtml="Yes" Leading="0" Size="0" TopMargin="0" BottomMargin="0"></Para></Block></Bill_Part></Bill>
