<?xml version="1.0"?>
<Bill RHead_reign="59 Eliz. II" RHead_ParlYear="2010" DocumentTitle="BILL C-27" Bill_No="C-27" Document_No="90556" xml:lang="EN" Bill_Type="Amending" Stage_Name="First-Reading-House" Reprint="No" xml:space="preserve" ChapterNo_E="C. " ChapterNo_F="ch. " Bill-Origin="commons"><Bill_Part Part_Type="Cover" CountLines="No"><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="CovBillNo">C-27</Para></Block><Block><Para TopMargin="24" Size="9" Leading="10" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0" TextAlign="Center">Third Session, Fortieth Parliament,</Para></Block><Block><Para Size="9" Leading="10" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0" TextAlign="Center">59 Elizabeth II, 2010</Para></Block><Block><Para TopMargin="48" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0" Bold="Yes" TextAlign="Center">HOUSE OF COMMONS OF CANADA</Para></Block><Block><Para TopMargin="42" Size="18" Leading="20" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0" Bold="Yes" TextAlign="Center">BILL C-27</Para></Block><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="CovLongTitle">An Act to amend the Canadian Wheat Board Act</Para></Block><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="COV_StageLine"></Para></Block><Block><Para Size="9" AllCaps="Yes" Hyphenate="OFF">first reading, May 14, 2010</Para></Block><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="COV_StageLine"></Para></Block><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="Cover_Sponsors">MINISTER OF AGRICULTURE AND AGRI-FOOD AND MINISTER FOR THE CANADIAN WHEAT BOARD</Para></Block><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="Cover_DocNo">90556</Para></Block></Bill_Part><Bill_Part CountLines="No" Part_Type="InsideCover"><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="BPT_InsideCoverE">Also available on the Parliament of Canada Web Site at the following address:<br/><B>http://www.parl.gc.ca</B></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><Para TopMargin="108" BottomMargin="4" Size="10" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">SUMMARY</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" Size="8" Leading="9" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">This enactment amends the <I>Canadian Wheat Board Act</I> by changing the eligibility criteria for voting in the election of directors of the Canadian Wheat Board. It also amends that Act to allow the Minister of Agriculture and Agri-Food, being the Minister designated for the purposes of that Act, with the concurrence of the Minister of Finance — instead of the Governor in Council — to establish amounts to be paid, and to authorize and direct that certain payments or transactions be made, by the Canadian Wheat Board.</Para></Block></Bill_Part><Bill_Part Part_Type="MainText" CountLines="Yes" RunningHead_E="Canadian Wheat Board"><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="MainText_DocNo">90556</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes"><Para Style="Session_Reign">3rd Session, 40th Parliament,</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes"><Para Style="Session_Reign">59 Elizabeth II, 2010</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes"><Para Style="MainBillOrigin">house of commons of canada</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes"><Para Bold="Yes" Style="MAIN@BillNo_Title">BILL C-27</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes"><Para Style="MAIN@ti;04">An Act to amend the Canadian Wheat Board Act</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">Her Majesty, by and with the advice and consent of the Senate and House of Commons of Canada, enacts as follows:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:SHORT TITLE--><Para TopMargin="10" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">SHORT TITLE</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Short title<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>1.</B> This Act may be cited as the <I>Canadian Wheat Board Payments and Election Reform Act</I>.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:CANADIAN WHEAT BOARD ACT--><MarginalNote>R.S., c. C-24<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="10" Bold="Yes" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">CANADIAN WHEAT BOARD ACT</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>1998, c. 17, s. 3<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>2.</B> Subsection 3.02(1) of the <I>Canadian Wheat Board Act</I> is replaced by the following:</Para><ExplNote><Para Align="Yes" TopMargin="10" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0" Italic="Yes" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">Canadian Wheat Board Act</Para><Para Align="Yes" TopMargin="10" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><I>Clause 2</I>: Existing text of subsection 3.02(1):</Para><Para Align="Yes" TopMargin="5" Size="8" Leading="9" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>3.02</B> (1) Four directors are appointed by the Governor in Council on the recommendation of the Minister. Ten directors are elected by producers in accordance with sections 3.06 to 3.08 and the regulations. The president is appointed by the Governor in Council in accordance with section 3.09.</Para></ExplNote></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Directors<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>3.02</B> (1) Four directors are appointed by the Governor in Council on the recommendation of the Minister. Ten directors are elected, in accordance with sections 3.06 to 3.08 and the regulations, by producers <change>who produced – or were entitled to – at least 40 tonnes of grain in the crop year in which an election occurs or in either of the two previous crop years</change>. The president is appointed by the Governor in Council in accordance with section 3.09.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>1995, s. 31, s. 2(1); 1998, c. 17, s. 28(E)<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>3.</B> (1) Paragraph 32(1)(<I>b</I>) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Para><ExplNote><Para Align="Yes" TopMargin="10" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><I>Clause 3</I>: (1) Relevant portion of subsection 32(1):</Para><Para Align="Yes" TopMargin="5" Size="8" Leading="9" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>32.</B> (1) The Corporation shall undertake the marketing of wheat produced in the designated area in interprovincial and export trade and for that purpose shall</Para><Para Align="No" TopMargin="5" Size="8" Leading="9" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">...  </Para><Para Align="No" TopMargin="5" Size="8" Leading="9" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>b</I>) pay to producers selling and delivering wheat produced in the designated area to the Corporation, at the time of delivery or at any time thereafter as may be agreed on, a sum certain per tonne basis in storage at a pooling point to be fixed from time to time</Para><Para Align="No" TopMargin="5" Size="8" Leading="9" LeftMargin="4" FirstLineIndent="0">(i) by regulation of the Governor in Council in respect of wheat of a base grade to be prescribed in those regulations, and</Para><Para Align="No" TopMargin="5" Size="8" Leading="9" LeftMargin="4" FirstLineIndent="0">(ii) by the Corporation, with the approval of the Governor in Council, in respect of each other grade of wheat;</Para></ExplNote></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>b</I>) pay to producers selling and delivering wheat produced in the designated area to the Corporation, at the time of delivery or at any time <change>after delivery</change> as may be agreed on, a sum certain per tonne basis in storage at a pooling point to be fixed from time to time</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="4" FirstLineIndent="0">(i) by the <change>Minister, with the concurrence of the Minister of Finance,</change> in respect of wheat of a base grade, and</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="4" FirstLineIndent="0">(ii) by the Corporation, with the approval of the <change>Minister and the concurrence of the Minister of Finance</change>, in respect of each other grade of wheat;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>1995, c. 31, s. 2(2); 1998, c. 17, s. 28(E)<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes">(2) Subsection 32(2.1) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Para><ExplNote><Para Align="Yes" TopMargin="10" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(2) Existing text of subsection 32(2.1):</Para><Para Align="Yes" TopMargin="5" Size="8" Leading="9" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(2.1) For the purpose of paragraph (1)(<I>b.1</I>), the Corporation shall, with the approval of the Governor in Council, establish for each delivery point within the designated area an amount that, in the opinion of the Corporation, fairly represents the difference in the cost of transporting wheat from that point as compared to other delivery points.</Para></ExplNote></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Freight adjustment<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(2.1) For the purpose of paragraph (1)(<I>b.1</I>), the Corporation shall, with the approval of the <change>Minister and the concurrence of the Minister of Finance, determine</change> for each delivery point within the designated area an amount that, in the opinion of the Corporation, fairly represents the difference in the cost of transporting wheat from that point as compared to other delivery points.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>R.S., c. 38 (4th Supp.), s. 8; 1998, s. 17, s. 28(E)<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>4.</B> (1) Subsection 33(1.1) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Para><ExplNote><Para Align="Yes" TopMargin="10" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><I>Clause 4</I>: (1) Existing text of subsection 33(1.1):</Para><Para Align="Yes" TopMargin="5" Size="8" Leading="9" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(1.1) With the approval of the Governor in Council and subject to such terms and conditions as the Governor in Council may prescribe, in addition to any payment authorized by section 32, the Corporation may fix and pay in respect of any pool period a sum per tonne to each producer who has sold and delivered wheat to the Corporation in a railway car during the pool period.</Para></ExplNote></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Additional payment<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(1.1) The Corporation may, with the approval of the <change>Minister and the concurrence of the Minister of Finance</change>, and subject to <change>any</change> terms and conditions <change>on which the approval is given</change>, fix and pay in respect of any pool period a sum per tonne to each producer who has sold and delivered wheat to the Corporation in a railway car during the pool period, in addition to any payment authorized by section 32.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>1998, c. 17, s. 28(E)<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes">(2) Subsection 33(3) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Para><ExplNote><Para Align="Yes" TopMargin="10" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(2) Existing text of subsection 33(3):</Para><Para Align="Yes" TopMargin="5" Size="8" Leading="9" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(3) Notwithstanding subsection (1), if the Governor in Council, having regard to a report by the Corporation of the effect on its financial position of an interim payment on account of the distribution of the balance referred to in subsection (2), is of the opinion that an interim payment can be made without loss, the Governor in Council may authorize and direct that payment to be made.</Para></ExplNote></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Interim payments<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(3) <change>Despite</change> subsection (1), if the <change>Minister</change>, having regard to a report by the Corporation of the effect on its financial position of an interim payment on account of the distribution of the balance referred to in subsection (2), is of the opinion that an interim payment can be made without loss, <change>and the Minister of Finance concurs with the Minister’s opinion,</change> the <change>Minister, with the concurrence of the Minister of Finance,</change> may authorize and direct that payment to be made.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>1995, c. 31, s. 3; 1998, c. 17, s. 28(E)<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes">(3) Subsection 33(5) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Para><ExplNote><Para Align="Yes" TopMargin="10" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(3) Existing text of subsection 33(5):</Para><Para Align="Yes" TopMargin="5" Size="8" Leading="9" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(5) The Corporation shall, with the approval of the Governor in Council, determine and fix the amounts to which producers are entitled per tonne according to grade under certificates issued pursuant to this Part so that each producer receives, in respect of wheat sold and delivered to the Corporation during each crop year for the same grade of wheat, the same price basis at a pooling point and that each price bears a proper price relationship to the price for each other grade.</Para></ExplNote></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Determination of amounts<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(5) The Corporation shall, with the approval of the <change>Minister and the concurrence of the Minister of Finance</change>, determine and fix the amounts to which producers are entitled per tonne according to grade under certificates issued <change>under</change> this Part so that each producer receives, in respect of wheat sold and delivered to the Corporation during each crop year for the same grade of wheat, the same price basis at a pooling point and that each price bears a proper price relationship to the price for each other grade.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>1998, c. 17, s. 28(E)<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>5.</B> Section 34 of the Act is replaced by the following:</Para><ExplNote><Para Align="Yes" TopMargin="10" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><I>Clause 5</I>: Existing text of section 34:</Para><Para Align="Yes" TopMargin="5" Size="8" Leading="9" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>34.</B> In taking any action pursuant to section 32, 33 or 37 in respect of a grade of wheat, the Governor in Council or the Corporation may take that action in respect of any wheat within that grade that has an inherent quality characteristic that distinguishes it from any other wheat within that grade as if the wheat having that inherent quality characteristic were wheat of a different grade.</Para></ExplNote></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Action within grade<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>34.</B> In taking any action <change>under</change> section 32, 33 or 37 in respect of a grade of wheat, the Governor in Council, the Corporation or <change>the Minister, with the concurrence of the Minister of Finance</change>, may take that action in respect of any wheat within that grade that has an inherent quality characteristic that distinguishes it from any other wheat within that grade as if the wheat having that inherent quality characteristic were wheat of a different grade.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>1998, c. 17, s. 28(E)<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>6.</B> The portion of section 38 of the Act before paragraph (<I>a</I>) is replaced by the following:</Para><ExplNote><Para Align="Yes" TopMargin="10" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><I>Clause 6</I>: Relevant portion of section 38:</Para><Para Align="Yes" TopMargin="5" Size="8" Leading="9" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>38.</B> The Governor in Council may authorize the Corporation to adjust its accounts at any time by transferring to the then current pool period all wheat delivered during a preceding pool period and then remaining unsold, and the Corporation shall credit to the accounts for that preceding pool period, and charge against the accounts for the current pool period, such amount as the Governor in Council deems to be a reasonable price for the wheat so transferred, and all wheat so transferred shall,</Para></ExplNote></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Transfer of wheat from one pool period to subsequent pool period<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>38.</B> The <change>Minister, with the concurrence of the Minister of Finance,</change> may authorize the Corporation to adjust its accounts at any time by transferring to the then current pool period all wheat delivered during a preceding pool period and then remaining unsold, and the Corporation shall credit to the accounts for that preceding pool period, and charge against the accounts for the current pool period, <change>the</change> amount <change>that</change> the <change>Minister, with the concurrence of the Minister of Finance,</change> deems to be a reasonable price for the wheat so transferred, and all wheat so transferred shall,</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>1998, c. 17, s. 28(E)<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>7.</B> (1) The portion of subsection 39(1) of the Act before paragraph (<I>a</I>) is replaced by the following:</Para><ExplNote><Para Align="Yes" TopMargin="10" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><I>Clause 7</I>: (1) Relevant portion of subsection 39(1):</Para><Para Align="Yes" TopMargin="5" Size="8" Leading="9" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>39.</B> (1) Where producers of any grain sold and delivered during a pool period have been for six years or more entitled to receive from the Corporation payments in respect thereof under certificates issued pursuant to this Act or out of an equalization fund, or otherwise, and there is an undistributed balance remaining in the accounts of the Corporation in respect of that grain, the Governor in Council may authorize the Corporation</Para></ExplNote></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Transfer of undistributed balances<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>39.</B> (1) <change>If</change> producers of any grain sold and delivered during a pool period have been for six years or more entitled to receive from the Corporation payments in respect <change>of that grain</change> under certificates issued <change>under</change> this Act or out of an equalization fund, or otherwise, and there is an undistributed balance remaining in the accounts of the Corporation in respect of that grain, the <change>Minister, with the concurrence of the Minister of Finance</change>, may authorize the Corporation</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>1998, c. 17, s. 28(E)<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes">(2) Subsection 39(2) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Para><ExplNote><Para Align="Yes" TopMargin="10" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(2) Existing text of subsection 39(2):</Para><Para Align="Yes" TopMargin="5" Size="8" Leading="9" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(2) Any balance transferred to the separate account pursuant to subparagraph (1)(<I>a</I>)(ii), other than such part thereof as is required for the payments referred to in paragraph (1)(<I>b</I>), shall be used for such purposes as the Governor in Council, on the recommendation of the Corporation, may deem to be for the benefit of producers.</Para></ExplNote></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>How transferred balances to be used<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(2) Any balance transferred to the separate account <change>under</change> subparagraph (1)(<I>a</I>)(ii), other than <change>any</change> part <change>of it that</change> is required for the payments referred to in paragraph (1)(<I>b</I>), shall be used for <change>the</change> purposes <change>that</change> the <change>Minister, with the concurrence of the Minister of Finance and</change> on the recommendation of the Corporation, may deem to be for the benefit of producers.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:COORDINATING AMENDMENT--><Para TopMargin="10" Bold="Yes" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">COORDINATING AMENDMENT</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>1998, c. 17<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>8.</B> On the first day on which both paragraph 32(1)(<I>b</I>) of the <I>Canadian Wheat Board Act</I>, as enacted by subsection 18(1) of chapter 17 of the Statutes of Canada, 1998, and paragraph 32(1)(<I>b</I>) of the <I>Canadian Wheat Board Act</I>, as enacted by subsection 3(1) of this Act, are in force, paragraph 32(1)(<I>b</I>) of the <I>Canadian Wheat Board Act</I> is replaced by the following:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>b</I>) pay to producers selling and delivering wheat produced in the designated area to the Corporation, at the time of delivery or at any time after delivery that may be agreed on, a sum certain per tonne basis in storage at a pooling point to be fixed</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="4" FirstLineIndent="0">(i) initially, at the beginning of the pool period</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="6" FirstLineIndent="0">(A) by the Minister, with the concurrence of the Minister of Finance, in respect of wheat of a base grade, or</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="6" FirstLineIndent="0">(B) by the Corporation, with the approval of the Minister and the concurrence of the Minister of Finance, in respect of each other grade of wheat, and</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="4" FirstLineIndent="0">(ii) from time to time afterwards, by the Corporation;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:COMING INTO FORCE--><Para TopMargin="10" Bold="Yes" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">COMING INTO FORCE</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Order in council<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>9.</B> (1) Section 2 comes into force on a day to be fixed by order of the Governor in Council.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Order in council<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes">(2) Sections 3 to 7 come into force on a day to be fixed by order of the Governor in Council.</Para></Block><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="BPT_ImprintE">Published under authority of the Speaker of the House of Commons<br/>Available from:<br/>Publishing and Depository Services<br/>Public Works and Government Services Canada<br/>Ottawa, Ontario K1A 0S5<br/>Telephone: 613-941-5995 or 1-800-635-7943<br/>Fax: 613-954-5779 or 1-800-565-7757<br/>publications@tpsgc-pwgsc.gc.ca<br/>http://publications.gc.ca</Para></Block><Block Align="Yes" LineCnt="N"><Para NoLineBreak="Yes" NoHtml="Yes" Leading="0" Size="0" TopMargin="0" BottomMargin="0"></Para></Block></Bill_Part></Bill>
