<?xml version="1.0"?>
<Bill RHead_reign="57-58 Eliz. II" RHead_ParlYear="2009" DocumentTitle="BILL C-300" Bill_No="C-300" Document_No="402168" xml:lang="EN" Bill_Type="Non-amending" Stage_Name="First-Reading-House" Reprint="No" xml:space="preserve" ChapterNo_E="C. " ChapterNo_F="ch. " Bill-Origin="commons"><Bill_Part Part_Type="Cover" CountLines="No"><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="CovBillNo">C-300</Para></Block><Block><Para TopMargin="24" Size="9" Leading="10" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0" TextAlign="Center">Second Session, Fortieth Parliament,</Para></Block><Block><Para Size="9" Leading="10" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0" TextAlign="Center">57-58 Elizabeth II, 2009</Para></Block><Block><Para TopMargin="48" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0" Bold="Yes" TextAlign="Center">HOUSE OF COMMONS OF CANADA</Para></Block><Block><Para TopMargin="42" Size="18" Leading="20" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0" Bold="Yes" TextAlign="Center">BILL C-300</Para></Block><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="CovLongTitle">An Act respecting Corporate Accountability for the Activities of Mining, Oil or Gas in Developing Countries</Para></Block><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="COV_StageLine"></Para></Block><Block><Para Size="9" AllCaps="Yes" Hyphenate="OFF">first reading, February 9, 2009</Para></Block><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="COV_StageLine"></Para></Block><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="Cov_StartBox"></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes"><Para Style="Cov_Box_Heading">NOTE</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes"><Para Style="Cov_Box_Para" TextAlign="Justify">3rd Session, 40th Parliament</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes"><Para Style="Cov_Box_Para" TextAlign="Justify">This bill was introduced during the Second Session of the 40th Parliament. Pursuant to the Standing Orders of the House of Commons, it is deemed to have been considered and approved at all stages completed at the time of prorogation of the Second Session. The number of the bill remains unchanged.</Para></Block><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="Cov_EndBox"></Para></Block><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="Cover_Sponsors"><SC SC_PerCent="85">Mr. McKay</SC></Para></Block><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="Cover_DocNo">402168</Para></Block></Bill_Part><Bill_Part CountLines="No" Part_Type="InsideCover"><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="BPT_InsideCoverE">Also available on the Parliament of Canada Web Site at the following address:<br/><B>http://www.parl.gc.ca</B></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><Para TopMargin="108" BottomMargin="4" Size="10" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">SUMMARY</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" Size="8" Leading="9" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">The purpose of this enactment is to promote environmental best practices and to ensure the protection and promotion of international human rights standards in respect of the mining, oil or gas activities of Canadian corporations in developing countries. It also gives the Minister of Foreign Affairs and Minister of International Trade the responsibility to issue guidelines that articulate corporate accountability standards for mining, oil or gas activities and it requires the Ministers to submit an annual report to both Houses of Parliament on the provisions and operation of this Act.</Para></Block></Bill_Part><Bill_Part Part_Type="MainText" CountLines="Yes" RunningHead_E="Corporate Accountability of Mining, Oil and Gas Corporations in Developing Countries"><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="MainText_DocNo">402168</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes"><Para Style="Session_Reign">2nd Session, 40th Parliament,</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes"><Para Style="Session_Reign">57-58 Elizabeth II, 2009</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes"><Para Style="MainBillOrigin">house of commons of canada</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes"><Para Bold="Yes" Style="MAIN@BillNo_Title">BILL C-300</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes"><Para Style="MAIN@ti;04">An Act respecting Corporate Accountability for the Activities of Mining, Oil or Gas in Developing Countries</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">Her Majesty, by and with the advice and consent of the Senate and House of Commons of Canada, enacts as follows:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:SHORT TITLE--><Para TopMargin="10" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">SHORT TITLE</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Short title<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>1.</B> This Act may be cited as the <I>Corporate Accountability of Mining, Oil and Gas Corporations in Developing Countries Act</I>.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:INTERPRETATION--><Para TopMargin="10" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">INTERPRETATION</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Definitions<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>2.</B> (1) The following definitions apply in this Act.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><MarginalNote>“corporation”<br/>« <I>société</I> »<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0">“corporation” includes any company or legal person incorporated by or under an Act of Parliament or of any province.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><MarginalNote>“developing countries”<br/>« <I>pays en développement</I> »<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0">“developing countries” means countries and territories named in the list of countries and territories eligible for Canadian development assistance established by the Minister of International Cooperation.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><MarginalNote>“gas”<br/>« <I>gaz</I> »<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0">“gas” has the same meaning as in section 2 of the <I>Canada Oil and Gas Operations Act</I>.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><MarginalNote>“IFC”<br/>« <I>SFI</I> »<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0">“IFC” means the International Finance Corporation affiliated with the World Bank Group.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><MarginalNote>“international human rights standards”<br/>« <I>normes internationales en matière de droits de la personne</I> »<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0">“international human rights standards” means standards that are based on international human rights conventions to which Canada is a party and on international customary law.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><MarginalNote>“mineral resources”<br/>« <I>ressources minérales</I> »<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0">“mineral resources” means all naturally occurring minerals, but does not include peat, petroleum, natural gas, bitumen, oil shales, limestone, marble, clay, gypsum, earth, ash, marl, gravel, sand or any element that forms part of the agricultural surface of the land.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><MarginalNote>“mining, oil or gas activities”<br/>« <I>activités minières, pétrolières ou gazières</I> »<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0">“mining, oil or gas activities” means the exploration and drilling for, and the production, conservation, processing or transportation of, mineral resources, oil or gas in the territory of a developing country or on the high seas where such activities are controlled directly or indi- rectly by a Canadian corporation. </Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><MarginalNote>“oil”<br/>« <I>pétrole</I> »<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0">“oil” has the same meaning as in section 2 of the <I>Canada Oil and Gas Operations Act</I>.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><MarginalNote>“Voluntary Principles on Security and Human Rights”<br/>« <I>Principes volontaires sur la sécurité et les droits de l’homme</I> »<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0">“Voluntary Principles on Security and Human Rights” means the set of principles announced in December 2000 by the governments of the United States and the United Kingdom to guide companies in maintaining the safety and security of their activities within an operating framework that ensures respect for human rights and fundamental freedoms.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Meaning of “Ministers” and “either Minister”<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(2) Where the word “Ministers” is used in this Act, it refers to both the Minister of Foreign Affairs and the Minister of International Trade, and where the expression “Minister” or “either Minister” is used in this Act, it refers to either the Minister of Foreign Affairs or the Minister of International Trade.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:PURPOSE--><Para TopMargin="10" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">PURPOSE</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Purpose<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>3.</B> The purpose of this Act is to ensure that corporations engaged in mining, oil or gas activities and receiving support from the Government of Canada act in a manner consistent with international environmental best practices and with Canada’s commitments to international human rights standards.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:POWERS AND FUNCTIONS--><Para TopMargin="10" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">POWERS AND FUNCTIONS</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Complaints<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>4.</B> (1) In carrying out their responsibilities and powers under this Act, the Ministers shall receive complaints regarding Canadian companies engaged in mining, oil or gas activities from any Canadian citizen or permanent resident or any resident or citizen of a developing country in which such activities have occurred or are occurring.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Content of a complaint<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(2) The complaint shall be in writing, shall identify the provisions of section 5 alleged to have been contravened, and shall set out reasonable grounds for the belief that a contravention has occurred.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Frivolous or vexatious complaint<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(3) If the Minister who receives the complaint determines that the request is frivolous or vexatious or is made in bad faith, he or she may decline to examine the matter. Otherwise, he or she shall examine the matter described in the complaint and assess compliance with the guidelines set out in section 5.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Information to consider<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(4) In conducting an examination, the Minister who receives the complaint may consider information from the corporation or from the public, including evidence from witnesses outside of Canada.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Own initiative<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(5) If the Ministers have reason to believe that a company has contravened a guideline set out in section 5, they may examine the matter on their own initiative.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Publication of results<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(6) The Ministers shall publish in the <I>Canada Gazette</I> the results of any examination  undertaken pursuant to this section within eight months following receipt of the complaint.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Publication<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(7) If a complaint is determined to be frivolous or vexatious or made in bad faith as provided for in subsection (3), the Minister shall provide reasons for this determination and publish these reasons in the <I>Canada Gazette</I>.  </Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Notification<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(8) The Ministers shall notify the President of Export Development Canada and the Chairperson of the Canada Pension Plan Investment Board where they determine that a corporation’s mining, oil or gas activities are inconsistent with the guidelines set out in section 5.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Notification<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(9) The Ministers shall notify the Governor in Council of any inconsistency with the guidelines set out in section 5 that has or may give rise to a grave breach of international peace and security or international human rights within the meaning of section 4 of the <I>Special Economic Measures Act</I>.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Information and advice<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(10) The Ministers may prepare, compile, publish and distribute information on mining, oil or gas activities and on international human rights standards and provide advice to Canadian corporations concerning the latter.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:GUIDELINES--><Para TopMargin="10" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">GUIDELINES</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Issuance of guidelines<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>5.</B> (1) Within 12 months of the coming into force of this Act, the Ministers shall issue <keep>guidelines that</keep> articulate corporate accountability standards for mining, oil or gas activities.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Content of guidelines<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(2) The guidelines shall incorporate:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>a</I>) the IFC's <I>Policy on Social &amp; Environmental Sustainability, Performance Stand- ards on Social &amp; Environmental Sustainability, Guidance Notes</I> to those standards, and <I>Environmental, Health and Safety General Guidelines</I>;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>b</I>) the <I>Voluntary Principles on Security and Human Rights</I>;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>c</I>) human rights provisions that ensure corporations operate in a manner that is consistent with international human rights standards; and</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>d</I>) any other standard consistent with international human rights standards.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Consultation<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(3) In carrying out their duties under subsection (1), the Ministers shall offer to consult with government departments or agencies, represent- atives of the mining, oil and gas industries, non-governmental organizations, and other interested persons in or outside Canada as they may see fit.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Notice<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(4) Guidelines issued under this section shall be made available to the public, and the Ministers shall give notice of them in the <I>Canada Gazette</I> and in any other manner that the Ministers consider appropriate.
</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:REVIEW AND REPORT--><Para TopMargin="10" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">REVIEW AND REPORT</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Annual report<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>6.</B> (1) Within three years after the coming into force of this Act and each year thereafter,
the Ministers shall cause to be laid before both Houses of Parliament a report on the provisions and operation of this Act, including any recommendations for amendments to this Act.
</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Review of report<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(2) A committee of the House of Commons as may be designated or established by the <keep>House of</keep> Commons for that purpose shall review the report and submit a report on the review to the House of Commons within 60 days.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Review of the Act<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>7.</B> (1) Five years after the coming into force of this Act, a review of the operation of this Act shall be undertaken by such committee of the House of Commons as may be designated or established by the House for that purpose.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Report<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(2) The committee referred to in subsection 6(2) shall, within one year after a review is undertaken pursuant to that subsection or within such further time as the House of Commons may authorize, submit a report on the review to the House of Commons.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:CONSEQUENTIAL AMENDMENTS--><Para TopMargin="10" Bold="Yes" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">CONSEQUENTIAL AMENDMENTS</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:Export Development Act--><MarginalNote>R.S., c. E-20; 2001, c. 33, s. 2(F)<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" Bold="Yes" SmallCaps="Yes" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">Export Development Act</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>8.</B> The <I>Export Development Act</I> is amended by adding the following after section 10.1:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Mining, oil or gas activities<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><change><B>10.2</B> (1) In the exercise of its powers under subsection 10(1.1), the Corporation shall not enter into, continue or renew a transaction related to mining, oil or gas activities, as that term is defined in the <I>Corporate Accountability of Mining, Oil and Gas Corporations in Developing Countries Act</I>, unless these activities are consistent with the guidelines issued under section 5 of that Act.</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Continued compliance<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><change>(2) Continued compliance with the guidelines issued under section 5 of the <I>Corporate Accountability of Mining, Oil and Gas Corporations in Developing Countries Act</I> shall be a condition in any contract entered into by the Corporation related to mining, oil or gas activities within the meaning of that Act.</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:Department of Foreign Affairs and International Trade Act--><MarginalNote>R.S., c. E-22; 1995, c.5, s.2<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="10" Bold="Yes" SmallCaps="Yes" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">Department of Foreign Affairs and International Trade Act</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>9.</B> Section 10 of the <I>Department of Foreign Affairs and International Trade Act</I> is amended by adding the following after subsection (3):</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Mining, oil or gas  activities<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><change>(4) In carrying out his or her duties and functions under paragraphs 2(<I>d</I>) and (<I>e</I>) and 3(<I>a</I>) that relate to mining, oil or gas activities, as that term is defined in the <I>Corporate Accountability of Mining, Oil and Gas Corporations in Developing Countries Act</I>, the Minister shall ensure that these activities are consistent with the guidelines issued under section 5 of that Act.</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Undertaking<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><change>(5) For greater certainty, with the exception of ordinary consular services available to all Canadian citizens, no undertaking made through a program developed by the Minister in the exercise of his or her powers under this section shall promote or support mining, oil or gas activities, as that term is defined in the <I>Corporate Accountability of Mining, Oil and Gas Corporations in Developing Countries Act</I>, that are inconsistent with the guidelines issued under section 5 of that Act. </change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:Canada Pension Plan Investment Board Act--><MarginalNote>1997, c. 40 <br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="10" Bold="Yes" SmallCaps="Yes" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">Canada Pension Plan Investment Board Act</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>10.</B> Section 36 of the <I>Canada Pension Plan Investment Board Act</I> is renumbered as subsection 36(1) and is amended by adding the following:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Consideration<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><change>(2) In taking into consideration the standards and procedures that a person of ordinary prudence would exercise, every investment manager who invests the assets of the Board shall take into consideration the provisions of section 5 of the <I>Corporate Accountability of Mining, Oil and Gas Corporations in Developing Countries Act</I>.</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Inconsistent activities<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><change>(3) Every investment manager who invests the assets of the Board shall ensure that the assets are not invested in any corporations whose activities have been found by either Minister, as that term is defined in the <I>Corporate Accountability of Mining, Oil and Gas Corporations in Developing Countries Act</I>, to be inconsistent with the guidelines referred to in section 5 of the <I>Corporate Accountability of Mining, Oil and Gas Corporations in Developing Countries Act</I>.</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:SPECIAL ECONOMIC MEASURES ACT--><MarginalNote>1992, c. 17<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="10" Bold="Yes" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">SPECIAL ECONOMIC MEASURES ACT</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>11.</B> Subsection 4(1) of the <I>Special Economic Measures Act</I> is replaced by the following:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Orders and regulations<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>4.</B> (1) The Governor in Council may make such orders <change>and</change> regulations with respect to the restriction or prohibition of any of the activities referred to subsection (2) in relation to a foreign state</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>a</I>) <change>where the Governor in Council deems it necessary</change> for the purpose of implementing a decision, resolution or recommendation of an international organization, of which Canada is a member, that calls on its members to take economic measures against a foreign state;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>b</I>) where the Governor in Council is of the opinion that a grave breach of international peace and security has occurred that has resulted, or is likely to result, in a serious international crisis; and
</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0"><change>(<I>c</I>) where the Governor in Council is of the opinion that grave breaches of human rights have occurred in the foreign state and continue or are likely to continue.</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>For greater certainty<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><change>(1.1) For greater certainty, “grave breaches of human rights” means “crime against humanity”, “genocide” or “war crime” as defined in the <I>Crimes Against Humanity and War Crimes Act</I>.</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:COMING INTO FORCE--><Para TopMargin="10" Bold="Yes" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">COMING INTO FORCE</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Coming into force<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>12.</B> This Act comes into force 30 days after the day on which it receives royal assent. </Para></Block><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="BPT_ImprintE">Published under authority of the Speaker of the House of Commons<br/>Available from:<br/>Publishing and Depository Services<br/>Public Works and Government Services Canada<br/>Ottawa, Ontario K1A 0S5<br/>Telephone: 613-941-5995 or 1-800-635-7943<br/>Fax: 613-954-5779 or 1-800-565-7757<br/>publications@tpsgc-pwgsc.gc.ca<br/>http://publications.gc.ca</Para></Block><Block Align="Yes" LineCnt="N"><Para NoLineBreak="Yes" NoHtml="Yes" Leading="0" Size="0" TopMargin="0" BottomMargin="0"></Para></Block></Bill_Part></Bill>
