<?xml version="1.0"?>
<Bill RHead_reign="59-60 Eliz. II" RHead_ParlYear="2010-2011" DocumentTitle="BILL C-35" Bill_No="C-35" Document_No="90563" xml:lang="EN" Bill_Type="Non-amending" Stage_Name="Assented-to" Reprint="No" xml:space="preserve" ChapterNo_E="C. 8" ChapterNo_F="ch. 8" Bill-Origin="commons"><Bill_Part Part_Type="Cover" CountLines="No"><Block><Para TopMargin="24" Size="9" Leading="10" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0" TextAlign="Center">Third Session, Fortieth Parliament,</Para></Block><Block><Para Size="9" Leading="10" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0" TextAlign="Center">59-60 Elizabeth II, 2010-2011</Para></Block><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="COV@StatutesTitle">STATUTES OF CANADA 2011<br/>CHAPTER 8</Para></Block><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="CovLongTitle">An Act to amend the Immigration and Refugee Protection Act</Para></Block><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="COV_StageLine"></Para></Block><Block><Para BottomMargin="14" Size="11" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0" Bold="Yes" TextAlign="Center">ASSENTED TO</Para></Block><Block><Para Size="8" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0" TextAlign="Center">23rd MARCH, 2011</Para></Block><Block><Para TopMargin="4" Size="8" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0" TextAlign="Center">BILL C-35</Para></Block><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="COV_StageLine"></Para></Block></Bill_Part><Bill_Part CountLines="No" Part_Type="InsideCover"><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="BPT_InsideCoverE">Also available on the Parliament of Canada Web Site at the following address:<br/><B>http://www.parl.gc.ca</B></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><Para TopMargin="108" BottomMargin="4" Size="10" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">SUMMARY</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" Size="8" Leading="9" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">This enactment amends the <I>Immigration and Refugee Protection Act</I> to change the manner of regulating third parties in immigration processes. Among other things it</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" Size="8" Leading="9" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">(<I>a</I>) creates a new offence by extending the prohibition against representing or advising persons for consideration — or offering to do so — to all stages in connection with a proceeding or application under that Act, including before a proceeding has been commenced or an application has been made, and provides for penalties in case of contravention;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" Size="8" Leading="9" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">(<I>b</I>) exempts from the prohibition</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" Size="8" Leading="9" LeftMargin="4" FirstLineIndent="0" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">(i) members of a provincial law society or notaries of the Chambre des notaires du Québec, and students-at-law acting under their supervision,</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" Size="8" Leading="9" LeftMargin="4" FirstLineIndent="0" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">(ii) any other members of a provincial law society or the Chambre des notaires du Québec, including a paralegal,</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" Size="8" Leading="9" LeftMargin="4" FirstLineIndent="0" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">(iii) members of a body designated by the Minister of Citizenship and Immigration, and</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" Size="8" Leading="9" LeftMargin="4" FirstLineIndent="0" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">(iv) entities, and persons acting on the entities’ behalf, acting in accordance with an agreement or arrangement with Her Majesty in right of Canada;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" Size="8" Leading="9" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">(<I>c</I>) extends the time for instituting certain proceedings by way of summary conviction from six months to 10 years;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" Size="8" Leading="9" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">(<I>d</I>) gives the Minister of Citizenship and Immigration the power to make transitional regulations in relation to the designation  or revocation by the Minister of a body;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" Size="8" Leading="9" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">(<I>e</I>) provides for oversight by that Minister of a designated body through regulations requiring the body to provide information to allow the Minister to determine whether it governs its members in the public interest; and</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" Size="8" Leading="9" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">(<I>f</I>) facilitates information sharing with regulatory bodies regarding the professional and ethical conduct of their members.</Para></Block></Bill_Part><Bill_Part Part_Type="MainText" CountLines="No" RunningHead_E="Immigration and Refugee Protection"><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="MAIN@RoyalAssentTitle">59-60 ELIZABETH II</Para></Block><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="MAIN@RoyalAssentTitle">——————</Para></Block><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="MAIN@RoyalAssentTitle">CHAPTER 8</Para></Block><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="LongTitleAssent">An Act to amend the Immigration and Refugee Protection Act</Para></Block><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="MAIN@RoyalAssentDate">[<I>Assented to 23rd March, 2011</I>]</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">Her Majesty, by and with the advice and consent of the Senate and House of Commons of Canada, enacts as follows:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:IMMIGRATION AND REFUGEE PROTECTION ACT--><MarginalNote>2001, c. 27<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="10" Bold="Yes" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">IMMIGRATION AND REFUGEE PROTECTION ACT</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>1.</B> Section 91 of the <I>Immigration and Refugee Protection Act</I> and the heading before it are replaced by the following:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:Representation or Advice--><Para TopMargin="10" Italic="Yes" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">Representation or Advice</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Representation or advice for consideration<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>91.</B> (1) Subject to this section, no person shall knowingly, directly or indirectly, represent or advise a person for consideration — or offer to do so — in connection with a proceeding or application under this Act.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Persons who may represent or advise<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(2) A person does not contravene subsection (1) if they are</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>a</I>) a lawyer who is a member in good standing of a law society of a province or a notary who is a member in good standing of the Chambre des notaires du Québec;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>b</I>) any other member in good standing of a law society of a province or the Chambre des notaires du Québec, including a paralegal; or</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>c</I>) a member in good standing of a body designated under subsection (5).</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Students-at-law<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(3) A student-at-law does not contravene subsection (1) by offering or providing representation or advice to a person if the student-at-law is acting under the supervision of a person mentioned in paragraph (2)(<I>a</I>) who is representing or advising the person — or offering to do so — in connection with a proceeding or application under this Act.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Agreement or arrangement with Her Majesty<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(4) An entity, including a person acting on its behalf, that offers or provides services to assist persons in connection with an application under this Act, including for a permanent or temporary resident visa, travel documents or a work or study permit, does not contravene subsection (1) if it is acting in accordance with an agreement or arrangement between that entity and Her Majesty in right of Canada that authorizes it to provide those services.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Designation by Minister<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(5) The Minister may, by regulation, designate a body whose members in good standing may represent or advise a person for consideration — or offer to do so — in connection with a proceeding or application under this Act.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Revocation of designation<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(5.1) For greater certainty, subsection (5) authorizes the Minister to revoke, by regulation, a designation made under that subsection.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Regulations — required information<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(6) The Governor in Council may make regulations requiring the designated body to provide the Minister with any information set out in the regulations, including information relating to its governance and information to assist the Minister to evaluate whether the designated body governs its members in a manner that is in the public interest so that they provide professional and ethical representation and advice.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Regulations — transitional measures<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(7) The Minister may, by regulation, provide for measures respecting any transitional issues raised by the exercise of his or her power under subsection (5), including measures</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>a</I>) making any person or member of a class of persons a member for a specified period of a body that is designated under that subsection; and</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>b</I>) providing that members or classes of members of a body that has ceased to be a designated body under that subsection continue for a specified period to be authorized to represent or advise a person for consideration — or offer to do so — in connection with a proceeding or application under this Act without contravening subsection (1).</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote><I>An Act respecting immigration to Québec</I><br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(7.1) For greater certainty, <I>An Act respecting immigration to Québec</I>, R.S.Q., c. I-0.2, applies to, among other persons, every person who, in Quebec, represents or advises a person for consideration — or offers to do so — in connection with a proceeding or application under this Act and</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>a</I>) is authorized to do so under regulations made under paragraph (7)(<I>b</I>); or</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>b</I>) is a member of a body designated under subsection (5).</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Persons made members of a body<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(8) For greater certainty, nothing in measures referred to in paragraph (7)(<I>a</I>) exempts a person made a member of a body under the measures from the body’s disciplinary rules concerning suspension or revocation of membership for providing — or offering to provide — representation or advice that is not professional or is not ethical.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Penalties<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(9) Every person who contravenes subsection (1) commits an offence and is liable</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>a</I>) on conviction on indictment, to a fine of not more than $100,000 or to imprisonment for a term of not more than two years, or to both; or</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>b</I>) on summary conviction, to a fine of not more than $20,000 or to imprisonment for a term of not more than six months, or to both.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Meaning of  “proceeding”<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(10) For greater certainty, in this section, “proceeding” does not include a proceeding before a superior court.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>2.</B> The heading after section 129 of the Act is repealed.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>3.</B> The Act is amended by adding the following after section 133:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Limitation period<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>133.1</B> (1) A proceeding by way of summary conviction in respect of an offence under section 117, 126, 127 or 131 may be instituted at any time within, but not later than, 10 years after the day on which the subject-matter of the proceeding arose.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Application<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(2) Subsection (1) does not apply if the subject-matter of the proceeding arose before the day on which this section comes into force.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>4.</B> Subsection 150.1(1) of the Act is amended by striking out “and” at the end of paragraph (<I>a</I>), by adding “and’’ at the end of paragraph (<I>b</I>) and by adding the following after paragraph (<I>b</I>):</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>c</I>) the disclosure of information relating to the professional or ethical conduct of a person referred to in any of paragraphs 91(2)(<I>a</I>) to (<I>c</I>) in connection with a proceeding — other than a proceeding before a superior court — or application under this Act to a body that is responsible for governing or investigating that conduct or to a person who is responsible for investigating that conduct, for the purposes of ensuring that persons referred to in those paragraphs offer and provide professional and ethical representation and advice to persons in connection with such proceedings and applications.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:TRANSITIONAL PROVISION--><Para TopMargin="10" Bold="Yes" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">TRANSITIONAL PROVISION</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Persons authorized to represent, advise or consult<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>5.</B> Despite subsection 91(1) of the <I>Immigration and Refugee Protection Act</I>, as enacted by section 1 of this Act, a person — other than a member in good standing of a bar of a province or of the <AltLang xml:lang="fr">Chambre des notaires du Québec</AltLang> — who, immediately before the coming into force of this section, was authorized under regulations made under the <I>Immigration and Refugee Protection Act</I> to, for a fee, represent, advise or consult with a person who was the subject of a proceeding or application before the Minister of Citizenship and Immigration, an officer designated under subsection 6(1) of that Act or the Immigration and Refugee Board, may represent or advise a person for consideration — or offer to do so — in connection with a proceeding — other than a proceeding before a superior court — or application under that Act until regulations made under subsection 91(5) of that Act, as enacted by section 1 of this Act, come into force.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:COORDINATING AMENDMENTS--><Para TopMargin="10" Bold="Yes" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">COORDINATING AMENDMENTS</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Bill C-11<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>6.</B> (1) Subsections (2) and (3) apply if Bill C-11, introduced in the 3rd session of the 40th Parliament and entitled the <I>Balanced Refugee Reform Act</I> (in this section referred to as the “other Act”), receives royal assent.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes">(2) If section 1 of this Act comes into force before section 8 of the other Act, then that section 8 is repealed.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes">(3) If section 8 of the other Act comes into force on the same day as section 1 of this Act, then that section 8 is deemed to have come into force before that section 1.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:COMING INTO FORCE--><Para TopMargin="10" Bold="Yes" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">COMING INTO FORCE</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Order in council<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>7.</B> The provisions of this Act, other than section 6, come into force on a day to be fixed by order of the Governor in Council.</Para></Block><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="BPT_ImprintE">Published under authority of the Speaker of the House of Commons<br/>Available from:<br/>Publishing and Depository Services<br/>Public Works and Government Services Canada<br/>Ottawa, Ontario K1A 0S5<br/>Telephone: 613-941-5995 or 1-800-635-7943<br/>Fax: 613-954-5779 or 1-800-565-7757<br/>publications@tpsgc-pwgsc.gc.ca<br/>http://publications.gc.ca</Para></Block><Block Align="Yes" LineCnt="N"><Para NoLineBreak="Yes" NoHtml="Yes" Leading="0" Size="0" TopMargin="0" BottomMargin="0"></Para></Block></Bill_Part></Bill>
