<?xml version="1.0"?>
<Bill RHead_reign="59 Eliz. II" RHead_ParlYear="2010" DocumentTitle="BILL C-510" Bill_No="C-510" Document_No="403074" xml:lang="EN" Bill_Type="Non-amending" Stage_Name="First-Reading-House" Reprint="No" xml:space="preserve" ChapterNo_E="C. " ChapterNo_F="ch. " Bill-Origin="commons"><Bill_Part Part_Type="Cover" CountLines="No"><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="CovBillNo">C-510</Para></Block><Block><Para TopMargin="24" Size="9" Leading="10" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0" TextAlign="Center">Third Session, Fortieth Parliament,</Para></Block><Block><Para Size="9" Leading="10" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0" TextAlign="Center">59 Elizabeth II, 2010</Para></Block><Block><Para TopMargin="48" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0" Bold="Yes" TextAlign="Center">HOUSE OF COMMONS OF CANADA</Para></Block><Block><Para TopMargin="42" Size="18" Leading="20" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0" Bold="Yes" TextAlign="Center">BILL C-510</Para></Block><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="CovLongTitle">An Act to amend the Criminal Code (coercion)</Para></Block><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="COV_StageLine"></Para></Block><Block><Para Size="9" AllCaps="Yes" Hyphenate="OFF">first reading, April 14, 2010</Para></Block><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="COV_StageLine"></Para></Block><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="Cover_Sponsors"><SC SC_PerCent="85">Mr. Bruinooge</SC></Para></Block><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="Cover_DocNo">403074</Para></Block></Bill_Part><Bill_Part CountLines="No" Part_Type="InsideCover"><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="BPT_InsideCoverE">Also available on the Parliament of Canada Web Site at the following address:<br/><B>http://www.parl.gc.ca</B></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><Para TopMargin="108" BottomMargin="4" Size="10" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">SUMMARY</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" Size="8" Leading="9" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">This enactment amends the <I>Criminal Code</I> to make it an offence for someone to coerce or attempt to coerce a female person to have an abortion.</Para></Block></Bill_Part><Bill_Part Part_Type="MainText" CountLines="Yes" RunningHead_E="Criminal Code (coercion)"><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="MainText_DocNo">403074</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes"><Para Style="Session_Reign">3rd Session, 40th Parliament,</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes"><Para Style="Session_Reign">59 Elizabeth II, 2010</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes"><Para Style="MainBillOrigin">house of commons of canada</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes"><Para Bold="Yes" Style="MAIN@BillNo_Title">BILL C-510</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes"><Para Style="MAIN@ti;04">An Act to amend the Criminal Code (coercion)</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><MarginalNote>Preamble<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">Whereas Roxanne Fernando was a Winnipeg woman whose boyfriend attempted to coerce her to abort their unborn child and subsequently murdered her for refusing to do so;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">Whereas many pregnant women have been coerced to have an abortion and have suffered grievous physical, emotional and psychological harm as a result;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">Whereas the Supreme Court of Canada recognized in <I>Dobson v. Dobson</I> that ГўВЂВњpregnancy represents not only the hope of future generations but also the continuation of the species.  It is difficult to imagine a human condition that is more important to societyГўВЂВќ;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">And whereas Parliament wishes to ensure pregnant women are able to continue pregnancy free of coercion;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">Now, therefore, Her Majesty, by and with the advice and consent of the Senate and House of Commons of Canada, enacts as follows:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:SHORT TITLE--><Para TopMargin="10" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">SHORT TITLE</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Short title<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>1.</B> This Act may be cited as <I>An Act to Prevent Coercion of Pregnant Women to Abort (RoxanneГўВЂВ™s Law)</I>.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:CRIMINAL CODE--><MarginalNote>R.S., c. C-46<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="10" Bold="Yes" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">CRIMINAL CODE</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>2.</B> The <I>Criminal Code</I> is amended by adding the following after section 264.1:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Coercion in relation to an abortion<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><change><B>264.2</B> (1) Every one who coerces a female person to procure or attempt to procure an abortion for herself is guilty of </change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0"><change>(<I>a</I>) an indictable offence and liable to imprisonment for a term not exceeding five years; or</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0"><change>(<I>b</I>) an offence punishable on summary conviction and liable to imprisonment for a term not exceeding eighteen months.</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Attempted coercion<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><change>(2) Every one who attempts to coerce a female person to procure an abortion for herself is guilty of</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0"><change>(<I>a</I>) an indictable offence and liable to imprisonment for a term not exceeding two years; or</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0"><change>(<I>b</I>) an offence punishable on summary conviction and liable to imprisonment for a term not exceeding six months.</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Definitions<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><change>(3) The following definitions apply in this section.</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><MarginalNote>ГўВЂВњabortionГўВЂВќ<br/>Г‚В« <I>avortement</I> Г‚В»<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0"><change>ГўВЂВњabortionГўВЂВќ means the act of using or prescribing any instrument, medicine, drug or any other substance, device or means with the intent to terminate the clinically diagnosable pregnancy of a female person with knowledge that the termination by those means will with reasonable likelihood cause the death of the child. Such use, prescription or means is not an abortion if done with the intent to save the life or preserve the health of the child or terminate an ectopic pregnancy.</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><MarginalNote>ГўВЂВњcoercionГўВЂВќ<br/>Г‚В« <I>contrainte</I> Г‚В»<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0"><change>ГўВЂВњcoercionГўВЂВќ, in respect of an abortion, means conduct that, directly or indirectly, causes a female person to consent to an abortion that she would otherwise have refused. A person coerces an abortion if he or she knows of or suspects the pregnancy of a female person and engages, or conspires with another to engage in, conduct that is intentionally and purposely aimed at directing the female person who has not chosen to have an abortion to have an abortion, including but not limited to the following conduct:</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0"><change>(<I>a</I>) committing, attempting to commit, or threatening to commit physical harm to the female person, the child or another person;</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0"><change>(<I>b</I>) committing, attempting to commit or threatening to commit any act prohibited by any provincial or federal law;</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0"><change>(<I>c</I>) denying or removing, or making a threat to deny or remove, financial support or housing from a person who is financially dependent on the person engaging in the conduct; and</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0"><change>(<I>d</I>) attempting to compel by pressure or intimidation including argumentative and rancorous badgering or importunity;</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0"><change>but does not include speech that is protected by the <I>Canadian Charter of Rights and Freedoms</I>.</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><MarginalNote>ГўВЂВњcourse of conductГўВЂВќ<br/>Г‚В« <I>agissements</I> Г‚В»<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0"><change>ГўВЂВњcourse of conductГўВЂВќ, for the purposes of the definition ГўВЂВњthreatГўВЂВќ, means a pattern of conduct that consists of a series of two or more separate acts evidencing a continuity of purpose. </change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><MarginalNote>ГўВЂВњthreatГўВЂВќ<br/>Г‚В« <I>menace</I> Г‚В»<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0"><change>ГўВЂВњthreatГўВЂВќ, for the purposes of paragraph (<I>c</I>) of the definition ГўВЂВњcoercionГўВЂВќ, means one or more statements, or a course of conduct, by an individual that would cause a reasonable person to believe that the individual is likely to act in accordance with the statements or as implied by the course of conduct, but does not include speech that is protected by the <I>Canadian Charter of Rights and Freedoms</I> or any generalized statement regarding a lawful pregnancy option. </change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Physician<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><change>(4) This section does not apply in the case of a physician who attempts to convince a pregnant female person to have a medical intervention that results, or may result, in the death of the child when, in the physicianГўВЂВ™s best medical judgment, that medical intervention is necessary to avoid a serious threat to the female personГўВЂВ™s physical health.</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Severability<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><change>(5) Any provision of this section that is held by a court of law to be invalid or unenforceable by its terms, or as applied to any person or circumstance, shall be construed so as to give it the maximum effect permitted by law, unless the court has determined that the provision is utterly invalid or unenforceable, in which case the provision shall be deemed to be severable from this section and shall not affect the application of the other provisions of this section or the application of the provision to other persons not similarly situated or to other, dissimilar circumstances.</change></Para></Block><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="BPT_ImprintE">Published under authority of the Speaker of the House of Commons<br/>Available from:<br/>Publishing and Depository Services<br/>Public Works and Government Services Canada<br/>Ottawa, Ontario K1A 0S5<br/>Telephone: 613-941-5995 or 1-800-635-7943<br/>Fax: 613-954-5779 or 1-800-565-7757<br/>publications@tpsgc-pwgsc.gc.ca<br/>http://publications.gc.ca</Para></Block><Block Align="Yes" LineCnt="N"><Para NoLineBreak="Yes" NoHtml="Yes" Leading="0" Size="0" TopMargin="0" BottomMargin="0">Г‚В„</Para></Block></Bill_Part></Bill>
