<?xml version="1.0"?>
<Bill RHead_reign="59 Eliz. II" RHead_ParlYear="2010" DocumentTitle="BILL C-513" Bill_No="C-513" Document_No="403070" xml:lang="EN" Bill_Type="Non-amending" Stage_Name="First-Reading-House" Reprint="No" xml:space="preserve" ChapterNo_E="C. " ChapterNo_F="ch. " Bill-Origin="commons"><Bill_Part Part_Type="Cover" CountLines="No"><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="CovBillNo">C-513</Para></Block><Block><Para TopMargin="24" Size="9" Leading="10" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0" TextAlign="Center">Third Session, Fortieth Parliament,</Para></Block><Block><Para Size="9" Leading="10" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0" TextAlign="Center">59 Elizabeth II, 2010</Para></Block><Block><Para TopMargin="48" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0" Bold="Yes" TextAlign="Center">HOUSE OF COMMONS OF CANADA</Para></Block><Block><Para TopMargin="42" Size="18" Leading="20" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0" Bold="Yes" TextAlign="Center">BILL C-513</Para></Block><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="CovLongTitle">An Act to amend the Motor Vehicle Safety Act and the Department of Transport Act (safety information)</Para></Block><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="COV_StageLine"></Para></Block><Block><Para Size="9" AllCaps="Yes" Hyphenate="OFF">first reading, April 19, 2010</Para></Block><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="COV_StageLine"></Para></Block><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="Cover_Sponsors"><SC SC_PerCent="85">Mr. Maloway</SC></Para></Block><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="Cover_DocNo">403070</Para></Block></Bill_Part><Bill_Part CountLines="No" Part_Type="InsideCover"><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="BPT_InsideCoverE">Also available on the Parliament of Canada Web Site at the following address:<br/><B>http://www.parl.gc.ca</B></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><Para TopMargin="108" BottomMargin="4" Size="10" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">SUMMARY</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" Size="8" Leading="9" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">This enactment amends the <I>Motor Vehicle Safety Act</I> to require manufacturers of motor vehicles and equipment to report specified safety information to the Minister of Transport, to post this information on their website and to send it to all ascertainable owners and lessees of vehicles in Canada.  It also requires companies that sell or import vehicles or equipment to report any consumer safety complaints to the manufacturer and the Minister of Transport.  In addition, it requires the Minister of Transport to post any safety information that he or she receives from a manufacturer, vendor, importer or owner on the departmental website.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" Size="8" Leading="9" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">This enactment also amends the <I>Department of Transport Act</I> to prohibit a former employee of the Department from accepting employment with a manufacturer or importer of motor vehicles during the one-year period following the termination of their employment with the Department.</Para></Block></Bill_Part><Bill_Part Part_Type="MainText" CountLines="Yes" RunningHead_E="Motor Vehicle Safety (safety information)"><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="MainText_DocNo">403070</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes"><Para Style="Session_Reign">3rd Session, 40th Parliament,</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes"><Para Style="Session_Reign">59 Elizabeth II, 2010</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes"><Para Style="MainBillOrigin">house of commons of canada</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes"><Para Bold="Yes" Style="MAIN@BillNo_Title">BILL C-513</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes"><Para Style="MAIN@ti;04">An Act to amend the Motor Vehicle Safety Act and the Department of Transport Act (safety information)</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">Her Majesty, by and with the advice and consent of the Senate and House of Commons of Canada, enacts as follows:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:MOTOR VEHICLE SAFETY ACT--><MarginalNote>1993, c. 16<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="10" Bold="Yes" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">MOTOR VEHICLE SAFETY ACT</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>1.</B> Subparagraph 5(1)(<I>g</I>)(ii) of the <I>Motor Vehicle Safety Act</I> is replaced by the following:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="4" FirstLineIndent="0">(ii) facilitating the identification and anal- ysis of <change>any</change> defects <change>that may be related to safety information, as that term is defined in section 10</change>; and</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>2.</B> Section 10 of the Act and the heading before it are replaced by the following:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:REPORTING OF SAFETY INFORMATION--><Para TopMargin="10" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center"><change>REPORTING OF SAFETY INFORMATION</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Definitions<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><change><B>10.</B> (1) The following definitions apply in this section.</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><MarginalNote>“equipment”<br/>« <I>équipement</I> »<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0"><change>“equipment” means equipment of a class for which standards are prescribed.</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><MarginalNote>“manufacturer”<br/>« <I>fabricant</I> »<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0"><change>“manufacturer” means a company that is engaged in the business of manufacturing vehicles or equipment in Canada.</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><MarginalNote>“owner”<br/>« <I>propriétaire</I> »<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0"><change>“owner”, in respect of a vehicle, includes a lessee of the vehicle.</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><MarginalNote>“safety information”<br/>« <I>renseignements relatifs à la sécurité</I> »<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0"><change>“safety information” means, in relation to a manufacturer,</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0"><change>(<I>a</I>) a written complaint from a consumer to the manufacturer that relates to the functioning of a vehicle or equipment that it manufactured;</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0"><change>(<I>b</I>) a service bulletin issued by the manufacturer in respect of a vehicle or equipment that it manufactured;</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0"><change>(<I>c</I>) information regarding the recall of any vehicle or equipment by the manufacturer in Canada or by the manufacturer or any company affiliated with the manufacturer outside of Canada;</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0"><change>(<I>d</I>) a safety notice issued outside of Canada that pertains to a vehicle or equipment manufactured by the manufacturer or by any company affiliated with the manufacturer; or</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0"><change>(<I>e</I>) information respecting any judicial or quasi-judicial proceedings that have been commenced in a court of law or before a tribunal in or outside Canada against the manufacturer or any company affiliated with the manufacturer in respect of any matter relating to the functioning of a vehicle or equipment.</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><MarginalNote>“vehicle”<br/>« <I>véhicule</I> »<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0"><change>“vehicle” means a vehicle of a class for which standards are prescribed.</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Duty to report and post safety information<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><change>(2) Every manufacturer shall,</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0"><change>(<I>a</I>) within seven days after producing or receiving any safety information,  report it in writing to the Minister;</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0"><change>(<I>b</I>) within seven days after producing or receiving any information referred to in paragraphs (<I>b</I>) to (<I>e</I>) of the definition “safety information”, post it in a clearly visible and readily accessible location on its website;</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0"><change>(<I>c</I>) within thirty days after producing or receiving any information referred to in paragraphs (<I>b</I>) to (<I>e</I>) of the definition “safety information”, provide the information to each ascertainable owner in Canada of a vehicle or equipment that is manufactured by the manufacturer to which the information pertains</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="4" FirstLineIndent="0"><change>(i) by e-mail, if the manufacturer knows the current e-mail address for the owner, or</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="4" FirstLineIndent="0"><change>(ii) by regular mail at the last known address of the owner.</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Duty to report consumer complaint<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><change>(3) Every company that is engaged in the business of importing or selling vehicles or equipment shall, within seven days after receiving a written complaint relating to the functioning of a vehicle or equipment, report the complaint in writing to the Minister and to the manufacturer of the vehicle or equipment, as the case may be.</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Duty to post vehicle information<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><change>(4) Within seven days after receiving a report under paragraph (2)(<I>a</I>) or subsection (3), the Minister shall</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0"><change>(<I>a</I>) provide the report to the minister or other officer responsible for motor vehicle administration in each province and territory; and</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0"><change>(<I>b</I>) post the information contained in the report, other than any information described in paragraph (<I>a</I>) of the definition “safety information”, in a clearly visible and readily accessible location on the Department of Transport website.  </change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Report to Minister<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><change>(5) The Minister may require a manufacturer to report, in the manner and at the times determined by the Minister, on any action that the manufacturer is taking to address any matters identified by the Minister in relation to safety information provided to the Minister under paragraph (2)(<I>a</I>) or subsection (3).</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Event data recorder<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><change><B>10.1</B> Every vehicle manufacturer shall, on request by the Minister or by the owner, make available the information contained in the event data recorder of a vehicle in an easily understood format.</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>3.</B> Subsection 15(3) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Production of documents<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(3) An inspector may require any person to produce for examination any books, records, reports, test data, shipping bills, bills of lading or other documents or electronically stored data that the inspector believes on reasonable grounds contain any information relevant to the enforcement of this Act or to the identification or analysis of <change>any matter relating to the functioning of a vehicle or equipment of a class for which standards are prescribed</change>, and may make copies of or take extracts from any of them.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>4.</B> Section 17 of the Act is amended by adding the following after subsection (2):</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Offence and punishment<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><change>(2.1) Every officer of a corporation who knowingly contravenes section 10</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0"><change>(<I>a</I>) is guilty of an offence punishable on summary conviction and is liable to a fine not exceeding one hundred thousand dollars or to imprisonment for a term not exceeding six months, or to both; or</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0"><change>(<I>b</I>) is guilty of an indictable offence and is liable to a fine not exceeding one million dollars or to imprisonment for a term not exceeding two years, or to both.</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>5.</B> Section 18 of the Act is amended by adding the following after subsection (1):</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Exception<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><change>(1.1) Subsection (1) does not apply in respect of the prosecution of an offence referred to in subsection 17(2.1).</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:DEPARTMENT OF TRANSPORT ACT--><MarginalNote>R.S., c. T-18<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="10" Bold="Yes" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">DEPARTMENT OF TRANSPORT ACT</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>6.</B> The <I>Department of Transport Act</I> is amended by adding the following after section 20: </Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:POST-EMPLOYMENT PROHIBITIONS--><Para TopMargin="10" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center"><change>POST-EMPLOYMENT PROHIBITIONS</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Post-employment prohibitions<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><change><B>21.</B> No former employee of the Department of Transport shall, during the one-year period following the last day on which they were employed by the Department, enter into a contract of service with, accept an appointment to a board of directors of, or accept an offer of employment with, any company that manufactures or imports motor vehicles.</change></Para></Block><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="BPT_ImprintE">Published under authority of the Speaker of the House of Commons<br/>Available from:<br/>Publishing and Depository Services<br/>Public Works and Government Services Canada<br/>Ottawa, Ontario K1A 0S5<br/>Telephone: 613-941-5995 or 1-800-635-7943<br/>Fax: 613-954-5779 or 1-800-565-7757<br/>publications@tpsgc-pwgsc.gc.ca<br/>http://publications.gc.ca</Para></Block><Block Align="Yes" LineCnt="N"><Para NoLineBreak="Yes" NoHtml="Yes" Leading="0" Size="0" TopMargin="0" BottomMargin="0"></Para></Block></Bill_Part></Bill>
