<?xml version="1.0"?>
<Bill RHead_reign="59 Eliz. II" RHead_ParlYear="2010" DocumentTitle="BILL C-545" Bill_No="C-545" Document_No="403181" xml:lang="EN" Bill_Type="Non-amending" Stage_Name="First-Reading-House" Reprint="No" xml:space="preserve" ChapterNo_E="C. " ChapterNo_F="ch. " Bill-Origin="commons"><Bill_Part Part_Type="Cover" CountLines="No"><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="CovBillNo">C-545</Para></Block><Block><Para TopMargin="24" Size="9" Leading="10" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0" TextAlign="Center">Third Session, Fortieth Parliament,</Para></Block><Block><Para Size="9" Leading="10" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0" TextAlign="Center">59 Elizabeth II, 2010</Para></Block><Block><Para TopMargin="48" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0" Bold="Yes" TextAlign="Center">HOUSE OF COMMONS OF CANADA</Para></Block><Block><Para TopMargin="42" Size="18" Leading="20" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0" Bold="Yes" TextAlign="Center">BILL C-545</Para></Block><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="CovLongTitle">An Act to Eliminate Poverty in Canada</Para></Block><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="COV_StageLine"></Para></Block><Block><Para Size="9" AllCaps="Yes" Hyphenate="OFF">first reading, June 16, 2010</Para></Block><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="COV_StageLine"></Para></Block><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="Cover_Sponsors"><SC SC_PerCent="85">Mr. Martin</SC> (<I>Sault Ste. Marie</I>)</Para></Block><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="Cover_DocNo">403181</Para></Block></Bill_Part><Bill_Part CountLines="No" Part_Type="InsideCover"><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="BPT_InsideCoverE">Also available on the Parliament of Canada Web Site at the following address:<br/><B>http://www.parl.gc.ca</B></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><Para TopMargin="108" BottomMargin="4" Size="10" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">SUMMARY</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" Size="8" Leading="9" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">Part 1 of this enactment provides for the establishment of a Government of Canada strategy to eliminate poverty and promote social inclusion.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" Size="8" Leading="9" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">Part 2 of the enactment establishes the Office of the Poverty Elimination Commissioner independent of Government.</Para></Block></Bill_Part><Bill_Part Part_Type="MainText" CountLines="Yes" RunningHead_E="Poverty Elimination"><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="MainText_DocNo">403181</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes"><Para Style="Session_Reign">3rd Session, 40th Parliament,</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes"><Para Style="Session_Reign">59 Elizabeth II, 2010</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes"><Para Style="MainBillOrigin">house of commons of canada</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes"><Para Bold="Yes" Style="MAIN@BillNo_Title">BILL C-545</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes"><Para Style="MAIN@ti;04">An Act to Eliminate Poverty in Canada</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><MarginalNote>Preamble<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">Whereas poverty is the condition of a human being who does not have the resources, means, choices and power necessary to acquire and maintain economic self-reliance and to facilitate their integration into and participation in society;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">Whereas the federal government, through constitutional and legislative amendments has direct involvement in the reduction of poverty and plays a central role in programs providing social protection and income security, including pensions, the Canada Social Transfer, the Old Age Security Program, child benefits and employment insurance benefits;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">Whereas several provinces and some municipalities have either implemented or are developing poverty reduction strategies that signify a growing poverty-reduction movement across Canada, and those strategies are making a difference;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">Whereas, in 1989, there was a unanimous resolution in the House of Commons to eliminate child poverty by the year 2000 and, in 2009, there were two unanimous motions in Parliament referring to the priority of establishing a poverty-reduction plan, and the Senate and House of Commons have completed major poverty reduction studies;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">Whereas according to the principles set out by the <I>Canadian Charter of Rights and Freedoms</I>, respect for the dignity of human beings, equality of women and men, and recognition of their rights and freedoms constitute the foundation of justice, liberty and peace;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">Whereas the Government of Canada has signed the <I>Universal Declaration of Human Rights</I> and the <I>International Covenant on Economic, Social and Cultural Rights</I> and other relevant international human rights instruments, such as those concerning gender equality, children, racialized and minority groups, and persons with disabilities;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">Whereas poverty and social exclusion may constitute obstacles to protecting and respecting human rights, including those guaranteed in the <I>Canadian Human Rights Act</I>;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">Whereas poverty leads to poor health, such that individuals living in poverty suffer more health problems and have lower life expectancy than those who are not living in poverty;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">Whereas the effects of poverty and social exclusion impede the economic and social development of society as a whole and threaten its cohesion and progress;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">Whereas, while all people including those living in poverty have the primary responsibility to take care of themselves, that responsibility is inextricably linked to the social, cultural and economic development of the entire community and attempts by those living in poverty to improve their own situation and that of their families are often frustrated by barriers in society;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">Whereas the Government of Canada strives for social and economic equality for all Canadians;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">Whereas the underlying factors that put some Canadians at far greater risk of poverty than others need to be addressed and resolved in order to prevent poverty;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">Whereas it is especially imperative to address the living standards and specific historical and structural circumstances of Aboriginal communities so as to empower Aboriginal people and ensure their full participation in Canadian society and the Canadian economy;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">And whereas Canadians aim for a Canada without poverty, a Canada where no one is left behind and where every Canadian lives in dignity and respect and has the opportunity to participate fully in society;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">Now, therefore, Her Majesty, by and with the advice and consent of the Senate and House of Commons of Canada, enacts as follows:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:SHORT TITLE--><Para TopMargin="10" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">SHORT TITLE</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Short title<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>1.</B> This Act may be cited as the <I>Poverty Elimination Act</I>.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:PURPOSE OF ACT--><Para TopMargin="10" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">PURPOSE OF ACT</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Purpose<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>2.</B> The purpose of this Act is to impose on the federal government the obligation to eliminate poverty and promote social inclusion by establishing and implementing a strategy for poverty elimination in consultation with the provincial, territorial, municipal and Aboriginal governments and with civil society organizations.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:INTERPRETATION--><Para TopMargin="10" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">INTERPRETATION</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Definitions<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>3.</B> The following definitions apply in this Act.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><MarginalNote>“Aboriginal community”<br/>« <I>collectivité autochtone</I> »<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0">“Aboriginal community” means a community made up of Métis, Inuit or First Nations peoples, whether or not that community is situated on a reserve.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><MarginalNote>“Commissioner”<br/>« <I>commissaire</I> »<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0">“Commissioner” means the Poverty Elimination Commissioner appointed under section 19.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><MarginalNote>“Council”<br/>« <I>Conseil</I> »<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0">“Council” means the former National Council of Welfare, renamed National Council of Poverty and Social Inclusion in accordance with section 10 of the <I>Department of Social Development Act</I>.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><MarginalNote>“Ministers”<br/>« <I>ministres</I> »<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0">“Ministers” means senior ministers responsible for income security, human development, the labour market, and public health and well-being, with the lead Ministers being those for income security and health.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><MarginalNote>“poverty”<br/>« <I>pauvreté</I> »<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0">“poverty” means the condition of a human being who does not have the resources, means, choices and power necessary to acquire and maintain economic self-reliance and to facilitate their integration into and participation in society.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><MarginalNote>“poverty measures”<br/>« <I>indicateurs de pauvreté</I> »<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0">“poverty measures” means both existing meas- ures of low income, such as the Low Income Measure (LIM), the Market Basket Measure (MBM) and Statistics Canada’s Low Income Cutoff (LICO), and measures of social exclusion or deprivation, such as the Canadian Index of Wellbeing (CIW), and any emerging deprivation indices.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><MarginalNote>“Secretariat”<br/>« <I>secrétariat</I> »<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0">“Secretariat” means the Secretariat for the National Council of Poverty and Social Inclusion established under section 15.1 of the <I>Department of Social Development Act</I>. </Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><MarginalNote>“social condition”<br/>« <I>condition sociale</I> »<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0">“social condition” means the condition of an individual or family that is influenced by physical, social, mental or financial factors that interfere with their ability to acquire the fundamental resources for self-reliance.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><MarginalNote>“social enterprise”<br/>« <I>entreprise sociale</I> »<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0">“social enterprise” means a social-mission-driven organization applying market-based <keep>strategies to</keep> achieve social, cultural, community, economic or environmental outcomes, and includes both non-profit organizations that use business models to pursue their mission and for-profit organizations whose primary purposes are social.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><MarginalNote>“social inclusion”<br/>« <I>inclusion sociale</I> »<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0">“social inclusion” means the ability of an individual or family to participate in their community.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><MarginalNote>“social safety net”<br/>« <I>filet de sécurité sociale</I> »<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0">“social safety net” means the accumulative protection for those vulnerable or at risk provided from non-contributory transfer programs targeted to those at risk or those vulnerable to poverty, which are sometimes referred to as social assistance or social welfare programs.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><MarginalNote>“Strategy”<br/>« <I>stratégie</I> »<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0">“Strategy” means the Government of Canada’s ongoing strategy to eliminate poverty and promote social inclusion in Canada.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:PART 1--><Para TopMargin="10" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">PART 1</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:STRATEGY--><Para TopMargin="5" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">STRATEGY</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:Establishment of Strategy--><Para TopMargin="5" SmallCaps="Yes" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">Establishment of Strategy</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Establishment<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>4.</B> (1) The Government of Canada, through its Ministers, shall seek advice from the Council and shall, in consultation with the provincial and territorial Ministers and with representatives of the municipalities and Aboriginal communities, non-profit and private-sector providers and civil society organizations, establish and maintain a strategy to eliminate poverty and promote social inclusion.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Targets<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(2) The Strategy shall take into account all people living in poverty, the factors that put people at higher-than-average risk of poverty and the consequences of poverty for society at large.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote> Orientation<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(3) The Strategy shall meet the following objectives:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>a</I>) to strengthen the social and economic safety net;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>b</I>) to promote the participation of residents, non-profit organizations 	and the private-sector providers; </Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>c</I>) to respect human rights; and</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>d</I>) to reflect the needs of local communities, including Aboriginal 	communities.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Exemption<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(4) Recognizing the unique nature of the jurisdiction of the Gouvernment of Quebec with regard to proverty elimination in Quebec society, and notwithstanding any other provision of this Act, the Government of Quebec may choose to be exempted from the application of this Act and, notwithstanding any such decision, shall receive the full transfer payment that would otherwise be paid within its territory under this Act</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:Contents of Strategy--><Para TopMargin="10" SmallCaps="Yes" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">Contents of Strategy</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Content<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>5.</B> (1) In order to meet the goal of reducing and eventually eliminating poverty and promoting social inclusion, the Strategy shall</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>a</I>) include the necessary measures to prevent people from falling into poverty, reduce the incidence, depth and duration of poverty and improve the situation of all people currently living in poverty, including those living in deep poverty or poverty of long duration and those who have multiple needs;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>b</I>) include measures to provide income security and access to housing;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>c</I>) include measures to promote the involvement of Canadians in determining and implementing the solutions to poverty;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>d</I>) determine an acceptable measurement of poverty for Canada;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>e</I>) set out targets to eliminate poverty in Canada</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="4" FirstLineIndent="0">(i) in the short term, of one to three years,</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="4" FirstLineIndent="0">(ii) in  the medium term, of four to seven years, and</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="4" FirstLineIndent="0">(iii) in the long term, of eight years or more;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>f</I>) specify actions to be taken by the Government to address the  	causes and consequences of poverty and social exclusion;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>g</I>) set out the terms and schedule for the implementation of the 	actions;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>h</I>) identify the departments responsible for the implementation of the 	actions specified in paragraph (<I>f</I>);</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>i</I>) identify other federal departments, other bodies or interested persons that are to be involved in the implementation of the Strategy;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>j</I>) undertake an ongoing analysis of all policies and programs, including future legislation, that may have an impact on the income and well-being of Canadians to ensure that they contribute to poverty elimination goals; and</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>k</I>) ensure that policies and measures developed under this Strategy are complementary and coherent.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Factors<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(2) The Strategy shall take the following factors into account:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>a</I>) the different realities of men and women, in particular through gender-based analysis; and</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>b</I>) the specific needs of urban, rural and remote communities and the factors that put some people at higher-than-average risk of poverty, including</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="4" FirstLineIndent="0">(i) Aboriginal status and history,</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="4" FirstLineIndent="0">(ii) discrimination and racism,</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="4" FirstLineIndent="0">(iii) child-rearing and single parenthood,</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="4" FirstLineIndent="0">(iv) low-wage, precarious employment,</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="4" FirstLineIndent="0">(v) immigration or refugee status,</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="4" FirstLineIndent="0">(vi) lack of education or lack of recognition of skills and 
		credentials,</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="4" FirstLineIndent="0">(vii) occupational injury,</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="4" FirstLineIndent="0">(viii) inadequate supports and services or limited access to supports and services that allow people to meet their own and their family’s needs and to develop their potential,</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="4" FirstLineIndent="0">(ix) prolonged illness and disability, and</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="4" FirstLineIndent="0">(x) any other factor that is identified.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:Measures--><Para TopMargin="10" SmallCaps="Yes" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">Measures</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Poverty Measures<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>6.</B> The Government of Canada shall use all relevant poverty measures to prepare, monitor and report on the Strategy, including measures of low income and indicators of poverty and social exclusion.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:Research--><Para TopMargin="10" SmallCaps="Yes" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">Research</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Research<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>7.</B> (1) Research for the Strategy should involve the academic sector, those engaged in policy research and groups working with people who are experiencing poverty or social exclusion.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Role of research in the Strategy<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(2) The role of the research shall be to compile, integrate, analyze and disseminate objective information on poverty and social exclusion, as well as on successful and promising practices in poverty reduction and elimination and social inclusion, to various stakeholders engaged in the campaign against poverty and social exclusion.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>New research<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(3) New research should include data that is not currently collected or not readily available, especially on social assistance.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Other poverty research bodies<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>8.</B> The Ministers shall also consult any poverty research bodies that they consider appropriate in preparing the Strategy.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:Support to Council--><Para TopMargin="10" SmallCaps="Yes" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">Support to Council</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Support to Council<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>9.</B> The Ministers shall support the Council to ensure that the Strategy has adequate resources to identify additional indicators of poverty and to promote joint efforts to address poverty and social exclusion across Canada.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:Strategy and First Consultation Paper--><Para TopMargin="10" SmallCaps="Yes" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">Strategy and First Consultation Paper</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Completion of the consultation paper<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>10.</B> A first draft consultation paper leading to the Strategy shall be completed within one year after this Act comes into force.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Consultations<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>11.</B> (1) The Ministers shall submit the draft of the Strategy for review and comment to</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>a</I>) any committee that has been designated or 			established by Parliament for that purpose;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>b</I>) the Council; and</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>c</I>) the Commissioner.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Public consultations<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(2) The Ministers shall undertake public consultations on the Strategy beginning with the first consultation paper.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Government assistance<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(3) The Government of Canada shall provide the necessary resources and support to allow those who live or have lived in poverty to participate in the consultations.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Submission to Governor in Council<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>12.</B> Within six months after the consultations referred to in subsections 11(1) to (3), but no later than one year after the completion of a first draft under section 10, the Ministers shall submit the Strategy to the Governor in Council for approval.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Tabling in each House of Parliament<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>13.</B> The Ministers shall table the Strategy together with all poverty data related to the Strategy in each House of Parliament before the first sitting day of September following the approval by the Governor in Council and shall report on progress in its goals of poverty elimination and social inclusion.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Deemed referred to appropriate committee<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>14.</B> The Strategy that is tabled in the House of Commons is deemed to be referred to the Standing Committee on Human Resources, Skills and Social Development and the Status of Persons with Disabilities or to any other committee that the House may designate for the purposes of this section. The Strategy that is tabled in the Senate is deemed to be referred to the Standing Committee on Social Affairs, Science and Technology or to any other committee that the Senate may designate for the purposes of this section.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:Monitoring Report--><Para TopMargin="10" SmallCaps="Yes" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">Monitoring Report</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Monitoring report<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>15.</B> (1) The Commissioner shall monitor the implementation of the Strategy and shall submit a monitoring report to the Ministers four years after the tabling of the Strategy under section 13, and every four years thereafter.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Consultations<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(2) The Commissioner shall, in preparing the report, consult with</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>a</I>) the Council;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>b</I>) the committee that may be designated or established 	by Parliament for that purpose;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>c</I>) social enterprises; and</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>d</I>) the public, including people who are living or have lived in poverty and their advocates.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Revision of the Strategy<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>16.</B> The Ministers shall, within six months after receiving the monitoring report from the Commissioner, revise the Strategy, taking into account the results of the Strategy to date and any comments received under subsection 15(2).</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Tabling<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>17.</B> The Ministers shall table, in each House of Parliament before the first sitting day of September following the revision of the Strategy, the following documents:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>a</I>) the revised Strategy;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>b</I>) the monitoring report; and</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>c</I>) the comments of the Commissioner made under subsection 15(2).</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:PART 2--><Para TopMargin="10" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">PART 2</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:OFFICE OF THE POVERTY ELIMINATION COMMISSIONER--><Para TopMargin="5" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">OFFICE OF THE POVERTY ELIMINATION COMMISSIONER</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:Poverty Elimination Commissioner--><Para TopMargin="5" SmallCaps="Yes" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">Poverty Elimination Commissioner</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Office of the Poverty Elimination Commissioner<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>18.</B> The Office of the Poverty Elimination Commissioner shall be established under the authority of the Commissioner.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Appointment<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>19.</B> (1) The Commissioner shall be inde- pendent of Government and shall be appointed by the Governor in Council after approval of the appointment by resolution of the Senate and House of Commons.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Tenure of Office<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(2) Subject to this section, the Commissioner holds office during good behaviour for a term of six years, but may be removed for cause by the Governor in Council at any time on address of the Senate and House of Commons.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Further terms<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(3) The Commissioner, on the expiration of a first term of office, is eligible to be re-appointed for one further term not exceeding six years.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Interim appointment<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(4) In the event of the absence or incapacity of the Commissioner, or if that office is vacant, the Governor in Council may appoint any qualified person to hold that office in the interim for a term not exceeding six months, and that person shall, while holding office, be paid the salary or other remuneration and expenses that may be fixed by the Governor in Council.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Powers<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>20.</B> (1) For the purposes of carrying out the Commissioner's functions under this Act, the Commissioner has all the powers that the Commissioner of the Environment and Sustainable Development has under the <I>Auditor General Act</I>, in addition to the powers the Commissioner may exercise under this Act.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Duties and functions<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(2) The Commissioner shall</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>a</I>) review and provide recommendations on the draft of the Strategy;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>b</I>) develop a monitoring system to assess the progress in implementing 	the Strategy;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>c</I>) identify factors that, because of evolving economic and social 	conditions, may create new risks of falling into poverty;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>d</I>) monitor progress toward and provide advice on reaching the goal to 	eliminate poverty in Canada;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>e</I>) prepare a monitoring report and hold the Government accountable 	for its Strategy;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>f</I>) forward his or her reports to the Parliamentary Budget Officer and Auditor General and meet with them to better coordinate the implementation of the  Strategy;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>g</I>) meet in person with the Ministers at least twice a year and advise 	them with respect to the administration of this Act;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>h</I>) work with the Government to develop its monitoring 	and reporting system and the gathering and release of poverty data;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>i</I>) help educate and make the public aware of the Strategy, including 	its human rights component; and</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>j</I>) no later than two years after the first Strategy is tabled in Parliament, 	determine and make recommendations to the Government on whether 	the Commissioner or an independent ombudsman should accept and 	address people’s complaints about how the programs intended to reduce 	and eliminate poverty are working and investigate whether the 	complaints reflect widespread problems or patterns.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Salary and expenses<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(3) The Commissioner shall be paid a salary equal to the salary of a judge of the Federal Court, other than the Chief Justice of that Court, and is entitled to be paid reasonable travel and living expenses incurred in the performance of his or her duties under this Act or any other Act of Parliament.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Pension benefits<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(4) The Commissioner is deemed to be employed in the public service for the purposes of the <I>Public Service Superannuation Act</I>.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Other benefits<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(5) The Commissioner is deemed to be employed in the federal public administration for the purposes of the <I>Government Employees Compensation Act</I> and any regulations made under section 9 of the <I>Aeronautics Act</I>.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:Staff--><Para TopMargin="10" SmallCaps="Yes" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">Staff</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Staff<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>21.</B> (1) Such officers and employees as are necessary to enable the Commissioner to perform the duties and functions of the Commissioner under this Act or any other Act of Parliament shall be appointed in accordance with the <I>Public Service Employment Act</I>.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Technical assistance<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(2) The Commissioner may engage on a temporary basis the services of persons having technical or specialized knowledge of any matter relating to the work of the Commissioner to advise and assist the Commissioner in the performance of the duties and functions of the Commissioner under this Act or any other Act of Parliament and may, subject to any appli- cable Treasury Board requirements, policies or guidelines, fix their remuneration and expenses.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Delegation<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>22.</B> The Commissioner may authorize any person to exercise or perform, subject to such restrictions or limitations as the Commissioner may specify, any of the powers, duties or functions of the Commissioner under this Act except</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>a</I>) the power to delegate under this section; and</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>b</I>) the powers, duties or functions set out in section 23.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:Reports to Parliament--><Para TopMargin="10" SmallCaps="Yes" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">Reports to Parliament</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Report to Parliament<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>23.</B> The Commissioner shall, within three months after the termination of each financial year, submit an annual report to Parliament on the activities of the Office of the Poverty Elimination Commissioner during that financial year.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Transmission of reports<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>24.</B> (1) Every report to Parliament made by the Commissioner under section 23 shall be made by being transmitted to the Speaker of the Senate and to the Speaker of the House of Commons for tabling in those Houses.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Reference to Parliamentary committee<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(2) Every report referred to in subsection (1) shall, after it is transmitted for tabling pursuant to that subsection, be referred to the committee designated or established by Parliament for that purpose.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:General Agreements--><Para TopMargin="10" SmallCaps="Yes" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">General Agreements</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Authority to enter into agreements and arrangements<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>25.</B> The Ministers may</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>a</I>) enter into agreements or arrangements with any department, board or 			agency of the Government of Canada or any other public or private 			organization or agency to assist the Ministers in carrying out the purposes 			and provisions of this 	Act; and</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>b</I>) with the approval of the Governor in Council, enter into agreements or 			arrangements with any provincial, territorial, munic- ipal or Aboriginal government</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="4" FirstLineIndent="0">(i) to facilitate the administration or enforcement of this Act or to 				provide for administrative fees, and</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="4" FirstLineIndent="0">(ii) to harmonize and administer federal or provincial financial 				assistance programs.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:Regulations--><Para TopMargin="10" SmallCaps="Yes" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">Regulations</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Regulations<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>26.</B> The Governor in Council may make regulations that are necessary for carrying out and giving effect to the provisions of this Act.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:CONSEQUENTIAL AMENDMENTS--><Para TopMargin="10" Bold="Yes" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">CONSEQUENTIAL AMENDMENTS</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:Canadian Human Rights Act--><MarginalNote>R.S., c. H-6<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" Bold="Yes" SmallCaps="Yes" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">Canadian Human Rights Act</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>27.</B> Section 2 of the <I>Canadian Human Rights Act</I> is replaced by the following:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Purpose<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>2.</B> The purpose of this Act is to extend the laws in Canada to give effect, within the purview of matters coming within the legislative authority of Parliament, to the principle that all individuals should have an opportunity equal with other individuals to make for themselves the lives that they are able and wish to have and to have their needs accommodated, consistent with their duties and obligations as members of society, without being hindered in or prevented from doing so by discriminatory practices based on race, national or ethnic origin, colour, religion, age, sex, sexual orientation, marital status, family status, <change>social condition,</change> disability or conviction for an offence for which a pardon has been granted.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>28.</B> Subsection 3(1) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Prohibited grounds of discrimination<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>3.</B> (1) For all purposes of this Act, the prohibited grounds of discrimination are race, national or ethnic origin, colour, religion, age, sex, sexual orientation, marital status, family status, <change>social condition,</change> disability and conviction for which a pardon has been granted.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:Department of Social Development Act--><MarginalNote>2005, c. 35<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="10" Bold="Yes" SmallCaps="Yes" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">Department of Social Development Act</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>29.</B> The heading before subsection 10(1) and subsection 10(1) of the <I>Department of Social Development Act</I> are replaced by the following:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes"><!--Heading:National Council of Poverty and Social Inclusion--><Para TopMargin="10" SmallCaps="Yes" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">National Council of Poverty and Social Inclusion</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>National Council of Poverty and Social Inclusion<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>10.</B> (1) The National Council of Welfare, <change>renamed National Council of Poverty and Social Inclusion,</change> is continued, consisting of a <change>full-time</change> Chairperson and <change>of</change> not more than fifteen other members to be appointed by the Governor in Council to hold office during pleasure for the term, not exceeding <change>six</change> years, that will ensure as far as possible the expiration in any one year of the terms of appointment of fewer than half of the members so appointed.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Salary and expenses<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><change>(1.1) The Chairperson shall be paid such salary or other remuneration and expenses as may be fixed by the Governor in Council.</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Absence or incapacity of Chairperson<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><change>(1.2) In the event of the absence or incapac- ity of the Chairperson, or if the office of the Chairperson is vacant, the Governor in Council may appoint another person, on such terms and conditions as the Governor in Council deems appropriate, to act as Chairperson and a person so acting shall have all the powers, duties and functions of the Chairperson under this Part and be paid such salary or other remuneration and expenses as may be fixed by the Governor in Council.</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Superannuation<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><change>(1.3) The provisions of the <I>Public Service Superannuation Act</I>, other than those related to tenure of office, apply to the Chairperson, except that a person appointed as Chairperson from outside the public service may, by notice in writing given to the President of the Treasury Board not more than sixty days after the date of appointment, elect to participate in the <I>Diplomatic Service (Special) Superannuation Act</I>, in which case the provisions of that Act, other than those relating to tenure of office, apply to the Chairperson from the date of appointment and the provisions of the <I>Public Service Superannuation Act</I> do not apply.</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>30.</B> Section 13 of the Act is replaced by the following:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Function<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>13.</B> It is the function of the Council to advise the <change>Government of Canada</change> in respect of any matters relating to <change>poverty and social inclusion</change> that the Minister may refer to the Council for its consideration or that the Council considers appropriate.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Public education and communication<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><change><B>13.1</B> It is also the function of the Council to carry out public education and communications activities with respect to the Government of Canada's strategy to eliminate poverty and promote social inclusion.</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>31.</B> The Act is amended by adding the following after section 15:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:Secretariat--><Para TopMargin="10" SmallCaps="Yes" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center"><change>Secretariat</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Establishment of Secretariat<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><change><B>15.1</B> There is hereby established a Secretariat for the purpose of supporting the Council in carrying out the duties and functions of the National Council of Poverty and Social Inclusion.</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Staff<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><change><B>15.2</B> Council may hire such officers, clerks and employees as are required for the proper conduct of the work of the Secretariat and they shall be appointed in accordance with the <I>Public Service Employment Act</I>.</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>32.</B> Section 39 of the Act is replaced by the following:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>National Council of Poverty and Social Inclusion<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>39.</B> A person who holds office as a member of the National Council of Welfare<change>, renamed the National Council of Poverty and Social Inclusion,</change> immediately before the day on which this section comes into force shall continue in office for the remainder of the term for which they were appointed.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:COORDINATING AMENDMENTS--><Para TopMargin="10" Bold="Yes" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">COORDINATING AMENDMENTS</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Bill C-23<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>33.</B> (1) Subsections (2) and (3) apply if Bill C-23, introduced in the 3rd session of the 40th Parliament and entitled <I>An Act to amend the Criminal Records Act and to make consequential amendments to other Acts</I> (in this section referred to as the “other Act”), receives royal assent.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes">(2) On the first day on which both section 25 of the other Act and section 27 of this Act are in force, section 2 of the <I>Canadian Human Rights Act</I> is replaced by the following:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Purpose<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>2.</B> The purpose of this Act is to extend the laws in Canada to give effect, within the purview of matters coming within the legislative authority of Parliament, to the principle that all individuals should have an opportunity equal with other individuals to make for themselves the lives that they are able and wish to have and to have their needs accommodated, consistent with their duties and obligations as members of society, without being hindered in or prevented from doing so by discriminatory practices based on race, national or ethnic origin, colour, religion, age, sex, sexual orientation, marital status, family status, social condition, disability or conviction for an offence for which a pardon has been granted or in respect of which a record suspension has been ordered.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes">(3) On the first day on which both section 26 of the other Act and section 28 of this Act are in force, subsection 3(1) of the <I>Canadian Human Rights Act</I> is replaced by the following:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Prohibited grounds of discrimination<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>3.</B> (1) For all purposes of this Act, the prohibited grounds of discrimination are race, national or ethnic origin, colour, religion, age, sex, sexual orientation, marital status, family status, social condition, disability and conviction for which a pardon has been granted or in respect of which a record suspension has been ordered.</Para></Block><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="BPT_ImprintE">Published under authority of the Speaker of the House of Commons<br/>Available from:<br/>Publishing and Depository Services<br/>Public Works and Government Services Canada<br/>Ottawa, Ontario K1A 0S5<br/>Telephone: 613-941-5995 or 1-800-635-7943<br/>Fax: 613-954-5779 or 1-800-565-7757<br/>publications@tpsgc-pwgsc.gc.ca<br/>http://publications.gc.ca</Para></Block><Block Align="Yes" LineCnt="N"><Para NoLineBreak="Yes" NoHtml="Yes" Leading="0" Size="0" TopMargin="0" BottomMargin="0"></Para></Block></Bill_Part></Bill>
