<?xml version="1.0"?>
<Bill RHead_reign="59-60 Eliz. II" RHead_ParlYear="2010-2011" DocumentTitle="BILL C-55" Bill_No="C-55" Document_No="90584" xml:lang="EN" Bill_Type="Non-amending" Stage_Name="Assented-to" Reprint="No" xml:space="preserve" ChapterNo_E="C. 12" ChapterNo_F="ch. 12" Bill-Origin="commons"><Bill_Part Part_Type="Cover" CountLines="No"><Block><Para TopMargin="24" Size="9" Leading="10" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0" TextAlign="Center">Third Session, Fortieth Parliament,</Para></Block><Block><Para Size="9" Leading="10" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0" TextAlign="Center">59-60 Elizabeth II, 2010-2011</Para></Block><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="COV@StatutesTitle">STATUTES OF CANADA 2011<br/>CHAPTER 12</Para></Block><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="CovLongTitle">An Act to amend the Canadian Forces Members and Veterans Re-establishment and Compensation Act and the Pension Act</Para></Block><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="COV_StageLine"></Para></Block><Block><Para BottomMargin="14" Size="11" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0" Bold="Yes" TextAlign="Center">ASSENTED TO</Para></Block><Block><Para Size="8" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0" TextAlign="Center">24th MARCH, 2011</Para></Block><Block><Para TopMargin="4" Size="8" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0" TextAlign="Center">BILL C-55</Para></Block><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="COV_StageLine"></Para></Block></Bill_Part><Bill_Part CountLines="No" Part_Type="InsideCover"><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="BPT_InsideCoverE">Also available on the Parliament of Canada Web Site at the following address:<br/><B>http://www.parl.gc.ca</B></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><Para TopMargin="108" BottomMargin="4" Size="10" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">RECOMMENDATION</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" Size="8" Leading="9" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">His Excellency the Governor General recommends to the House of Commons the appropriation of public revenue under the circumstances, in the manner and for the purposes set out in a measure entitled “<I>An Act to amend the Canadian Forces Members and Veterans Re-establishment and Compensation Act and the Pension Act</I>”.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><Para TopMargin="60" BottomMargin="4" Size="10" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">SUMMARY</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" Size="8" Leading="9" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">This enactment amends Part 2 of the <I>Canadian Forces Members and Veterans Re-establishment and Compensation Act</I> by making the permanent impairment allowance available not only to veterans who are eligible for a disability award under that Act, but also to veterans who are eligible for a disability pension under the <I>Pension Act</I>. It also introduces a supplemental amount to the permanent impairment allowance for the most severely and permanently impaired veterans.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" Size="8" Leading="9" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">It amends Part 3 of the <I>Canadian Forces Members and Veterans Re-establishment and Compensation Act</I> to provide Canadian Forces members and veterans with a choice of payment options for a disability award.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" Size="8" Leading="9" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">It also amends the <I>Pension Act</I> by making the exceptional incapacity allowance available not only to veterans and members of the forces who are receiving a disability pension under that Act, but also to veterans and members who are receiving both such a pension and a disability award under the <I>Canadian Forces Members and Veterans Re-establishment and Compensation Act</I>.</Para></Block></Bill_Part><Bill_Part Part_Type="MainText" CountLines="No" RunningHead_E="Canadian Forces Members and Veterans Re-establishment and Compensation and Pension"><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="MAIN@RoyalAssentTitle">59-60 ELIZABETH II</Para></Block><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="MAIN@RoyalAssentTitle">——————</Para></Block><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="MAIN@RoyalAssentTitle">CHAPTER 12</Para></Block><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="LongTitleAssent">An Act to amend the Canadian Forces Members and Veterans Re-establishment and Compensation Act and the Pension Act</Para></Block><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="MAIN@RoyalAssentDate">[<I>Assented to 24th March, 2011</I>]</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">Her Majesty, by and with the advice and consent of the Senate and House of Commons of Canada, enacts as follows:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:SHORT TITLE--><Para TopMargin="10" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">SHORT TITLE</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Short title<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>1.</B> This Act may be cited as the <I>Enhanced New Veterans Charter Act</I>.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:CANADIAN FORCES MEMBERS AND VETERANS RE-ESTABLISHMENT AND COMPENSATION ACT--><MarginalNote>2005, c. 21<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="10" Bold="Yes" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">CANADIAN FORCES MEMBERS AND VETERANS RE-ESTABLISHMENT AND COMPENSATION ACT</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>2.</B> The heading “JOB PLACEMENT” before section 3 of the <I>Canadian Forces Members and Veterans Re-establishment and Compensation Act</I> is replaced by the following:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes"><!--Heading:CAREER TRANSITION SERVICES--><Para TopMargin="10" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">CAREER TRANSITION SERVICES</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>3.</B> Section 3 of the Act is replaced by the following:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Eligibility — members and veterans<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>3.</B> (1) The Minister may, on application, provide career transition services to a member or a veteran who meets the prescribed eligibility requirements if the Minister is satisfied that the member or veteran requires assistance in making the transition to the civilian labour force.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Assistance to spouses, common-law partners and survivors<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(2) The Minister may, on application, provide career transition services to a member’s or a veteran’s spouse, common-law partner or survivor if the spouse, common-law partner or survivor meets the prescribed eligibility requirements.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>4.</B> Subsections 4(2) and (3) of the Act are replaced by the following:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Career transition plan<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(2) The Minister may develop and implement a career transition plan to address the needs that are identified in the assessment.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Development of plan<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(3) In developing a career transition plan, the Minister shall have regard to any prescribed principles.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>5.</B> Section 5 of the Act is replaced by the following:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Refusal to provide services<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>5.</B> The Minister may refuse to provide career transition services to a person under this Part to the extent that the person is entitled to receive those types of services from another organization or body.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>6.</B> The portion of section 12 of the Act before paragraph (<I>a</I>) is replaced by the following:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Eligibility — survivors<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>12.</B> The Minister may, on application, provide rehabilitation services and vocational assistance to a member’s or a veteran’s survivor, if the member or veteran dies as a result of</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>7.</B> (1) Subsection 35(1) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Requirement to participate<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>35.</B> (1) A Canadian Forces income support benefit under section 27 or 28 is only payable for each month that the veteran or survivor participates — to the extent required to meet the objectives of the program — in a career transition services program that is approved by the Minister.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes">(2) Paragraph 35(4)(<I>a</I>) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>a</I>) the first day of the month in which the veteran or the survivor starts a career transition services program referred to in subsection (1), and</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes">(3) Paragraph 35(6)(<I>a</I>) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>a</I>) the last day of the month in which the veteran or survivor ceases to participate in a career transition services program referred to in subsection (1), unless the veteran or survivor is exempt from the application of that subsection,</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>8.</B> (1) Subsection 38(1) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Eligibility — veterans<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>38.</B> (1) The Minister may, on application, pay a permanent impairment allowance to a veteran who has one or more physical or mental health problems that are creating a permanent and severe impairment if the veteran, in respect of each of those health problems,</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>a</I>) has had an application for rehabilitation services approved under this Part; and</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>b</I>) has received a disability award under Part 3 or a pension for disability under the <I>Pension Act</I>, or would have received such an award or pension but has not because</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="4" FirstLineIndent="0">(i) the aggregate of all of the veteran’s disability assessments and deemed disability assessments exceeds 100%, or</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="4" FirstLineIndent="0">(ii) the disability award is not yet payable because, in the opinion of the Minister, the disability has not stabilized.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Ineligibility — exceptional incapacity allowance<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(1.1) A veteran who has received or is receiving an exceptional incapacity allowance under the <I>Pension Act</I> is not eligible to be paid a permanent impairment allowance.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes">(2) Section 38 of the Act is amended by adding the following after subsection (2):</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Total and permanent incapacitation<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(3) The Minister may, on application, increase the permanent impairment allowance that may be paid under subsection (2) by the amount set out in item 2.1, column 2, of Schedule 2, if the Minister determines that the veteran is totally and permanently incapacitated.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>9.</B> Section 39 of the Act is replaced by the following:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>When allowance payable<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>39.</B> The permanent impairment allowance under subsection 38(2) and an increase to the permanent impairment allowance under subsection 38(3) begin to be payable on the later of</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>a</I>) the day on which the application for the allowance or increase, as the case may be, is made, and</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>b</I>) the day that is one year prior to the day on which the application for the allowance or increase, as the case may be, is approved.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>10.</B> Subsection 48(1) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Increase in extent of disability<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>48.</B> (1) If a member or a veteran to whom a disability award under section 45 or 47 has been paid, in whole or in part, establishes that their extent of disability has subsequently increased, the Minister may, on application, pay a disability award to the member or veteran that corresponds to the extent of that increase.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>11.</B> Section 49 of the Act is replaced by the following:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Death of member or veteran<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>49.</B> If a member or a veteran dies as a result of an injury or a disease for which a disability award under section 45 has been paid, in whole or in part, or would be payable and their death occurs more than 30 days after the day on which the injury occurred or the disease was contracted or the injury or disease was aggravated, the member or veteran is deemed to have been assessed, at the time of their death, as having an extent of disability at that time of 100%.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>12.</B> Subsection 50(3) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Rights of survivors and children<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(3) The survivor or child has, in respect of the application referred to in subsection (2), all of the rights that the member or veteran would have had had they lived, other than the right to make an election under subsection 52.1(1).</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>13.</B> The Act is amended by adding the following after section 52:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Election as to payment of award<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>52.1</B> (1) Subject to subsections (4) and (7), a member or a veteran to whom a disability award is to be paid under section 45, 47 or 48 may elect, within the prescribed time and in the prescribed manner,</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>a</I>) to be paid the amount of the disability award as a lump sum;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>b</I>) to be paid each year, in lieu of the amount of the disability award, for up to the number of years indicated by the member or veteran, an amount equal to the amount determined by the formula</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No" KeepWith="Previous"><Para Style="MAIN@Formula">A/B + C</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">where</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="5" FirstLineIndent="-3"><keep>A</keep><Tab/>is the amount of the disability award,</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="5" FirstLineIndent="-3"><keep>B</keep><Tab/>is the number of years indicated by the member or veteran, and</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="5" FirstLineIndent="-3"><keep>C</keep><Tab/>is the amount of interest for that year determined in accordance with the regulations; or</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>c</I>) to be paid the portion, indicated by the member or veteran, of the amount of the disability award as a lump sum and to be paid each year, in lieu of the remainder of the amount of the disability award, for up to the number of years indicated by the member or veteran, an amount equal to the amount determined by the formula set out in paragraph (<I>b</I>) read as though the description of A were the amount of the disability award less the portion that the member or veteran elected to be paid as a lump sum.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Notification<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(2) The Minister shall, in the prescribed manner, inform the member or veteran of their right to make an election under subsection (1).</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Failure to make election<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(3) If the member or veteran fails to make the election, the amount of the disability award is to be paid as a lump sum.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Lump sum if disability is less than five per cent<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(4) If the extent of disability for which the disability award is to be paid is less than five per cent of total disability, the amount of the disability award is to be paid as a lump sum.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Election in respect of remaining payments<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(5) A member or a veteran who has elected to be paid in annual payments and who has received at least one payment may elect, in the prescribed manner, to be paid a lump sum, determined in accordance with the regulations, in lieu of the annual payments remaining to be paid.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Deemed election<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(6) A member or a veteran who dies after having elected to be paid in annual payments is deemed to have elected, on the day before their death, to be paid a lump sum, determined in accordance with the regulations, in lieu of the annual payments remaining to be paid.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Member or veteran currently receiving annual payments<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(7) If a member or a veteran to whom a disability award (in this subsection referred to as the “new disability award”) is to be paid under section 45, 47 or 48 is currently being paid annual payments in respect of another disability award and they make an election referred to in paragraph (1)(<I>b</I>) or (<I>c</I>) in respect of the new award,</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>a</I>) for the purpose of determining the amount of the annual payments in respect of the new disability award,</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="4" FirstLineIndent="0">(i) in the case of an election referred to in paragraph (1)(<I>b</I>), the description of A in that paragraph, is, despite that paragraph, the sum of the amount of the new disability award and the amount of the lump sum that the member or veteran would have received had they made an election under subsection (5) in respect of the other disability award, and</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="4" FirstLineIndent="0">(ii) in the case of an election referred to in paragraph (1)(<I>c</I>), the description of A in paragraph (1)(<I>b</I>), despite paragraph (1)(<I>c</I>), is the sum of the amount of the new disability award and the amount of the lump sum that the member or veteran would have received had they made an election under subsection (5) in respect of the other disability award less the portion of the new disability award to be paid to the member or veteran as a lump sum; and</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>b</I>) no additional payments are to be made in respect of the other disability award.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Amounts deemed to be compensation payable under this Act<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(8) The amounts determined by the application of paragraphs (1)(<I>b</I>) and (<I>c</I>) and the lump sum referred to in subsection (5) or (6) are deemed to be compensation payable under this Act.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>14.</B> Subsection 56(1) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>No award — decision under <I>Pension Act</I><br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>56.</B> (1) No disability award shall be granted in respect of an injury or a disease, or the aggravation of an injury or a disease, if the injury or disease, or the aggravation, has been the subject of an application for a pension under the <I>Pension Act</I> and the Minister, or the Commission as defined in section 79 of that Act, has rendered a decision in respect of the application.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>15.</B> Subsection 76(1) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Application made to Minister<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>76.</B> (1) An application for career transition services, rehabilitation services, vocational assistance or compensation under this Act shall be made to the Minister in the form directed by the Minister and shall include any information that is required by the regulations to accompany the application.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>16.</B> Section 90 of the Act is replaced by the following:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>No interest payable<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>90.</B> Except in the case of amounts payable to a member or a veteran who makes an election referred to in paragraph 52.1(1)(<I>b</I>) or (<I>c</I>) or subsection 52.1(5) or who is deemed to have made an election under subsection 52.1(6), no interest shall be paid in respect of any compensation that is payable under this Act.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>17.</B> (1) Paragraph 94(<I>a</I>) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>a</I>) respecting the time and manner of making an application for career transition services, rehabilitation services, vocational assistance or compensation under this Act, and respecting the information that is required to accompany the application;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes">(2) Paragraph 94(<I>e</I>) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>e</I>) respecting the provision of information or documents to the Minister by persons who are in receipt of career transition services, rehabilitation services, vocational assistance, an earnings loss benefit, a Canadian Forces income support benefit, a permanent impairment allowance or a clothing allowance under this Act, and authorizing the Minister to suspend delivery of the services or assistance or payment of the benefit or allowance until the information or documents are provided;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes">(3) Section 94 of the Act is amended by adding the following after paragraph (<I>i</I>):</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>i.1</I>) respecting the determination of an amount of interest for the purposes of the description of C in paragraph 52.1(1)(<I>b</I>);</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>i.2</I>) respecting the determination of lump sums for the purpose of subsections 52.1(5) and (6);</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes">(4) Section 94 of the Act is amended by striking out “and” at the end of paragraph (<I>j</I>) and by adding the following after that paragraph:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>j.1</I>) prescribing the way in which anything that is required or authorized by this Act to be prescribed is to be determined; and</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>18.</B> Schedule 2 to the Act is amended by replacing <I>(Subsections 38(2) and 58(1), section 61, paragraph 94(<I>c</I>) and subsection 98(2))</I> after the heading “SCHEDULE 2” with <I>(Subsections 38(2) and (3) and 58(1), section 61, paragraph 94(<I>c</I>) and subsection 98(2))</I>.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>19.</B> Schedule 2 to the Act is amended by adding the following after item 2:<PageBreak></PageBreak></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><TABLE space-before="12pt" frame="topbot"><tgroup cols="3"><colspec colname="col1" colwidth="2.70*"/><colspec colname="col2" colwidth="12.50*"/><colspec colname="col3" colwidth="5.50*"/><thead valign="top"><row topdouble="yes" topmarginspacing="6" rowsep="1"><entry colsep="0" rowsep="1"><br/></entry><entry colsep="0" rowsep="1"><Para TopMargin="5" BottomMargin="3pt" Size="9" Leading="10" LeftMargin="0" RightMargin="1.5pt" FirstLineIndent="0" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Left"><B>Column 1</B></Para></entry><entry align="right" colsep="0" rowsep="1"><Para TopMargin="5" BottomMargin="3pt" Size="9" Leading="10" LeftMargin="0" RightMargin="1.5pt" FirstLineIndent="0" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Right"><B>Column 2</B></Para></entry></row><row topmarginspacing="6"><entry colsep="0" rowsep="1"><Para TopMargin="5" BottomMargin="3pt" Size="9" Leading="10" LeftMargin="0" RightMargin="1.5pt" FirstLineIndent="0" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Left"><B>Item</B></Para></entry><entry colsep="0" rowsep="1"><Para TopMargin="5" BottomMargin="3pt" Size="9" Leading="10" LeftMargin="0" RightMargin="1.5pt" FirstLineIndent="0" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Left"><B>Allowance or Benefit</B></Para></entry><entry align="right" colsep="0" rowsep="1"><Para TopMargin="5" BottomMargin="3pt" Size="9" Leading="10" LeftMargin="0" RightMargin="1.5pt" FirstLineIndent="0" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Right"><B>Amount ($)</B></Para></entry></row></thead><tbody valign="top"><row topmarginspacing="6"><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0"><Para TopMargin="5" BottomMargin="3pt" Size="9" Leading="10" LeftMargin="0" RightMargin="1.5pt" FirstLineIndent="0" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Left">2.1</Para></entry><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0"><Para TopMargin="5" BottomMargin="3pt" Size="9" Leading="10" LeftMargin="0" RightMargin="1.5pt" FirstLineIndent="0" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Left">Permanent impairment allowance supplement for total and permanent incapacitation</Para></entry><entry align="right" colsep="0" rowsep="0"><Para TopMargin="5" BottomMargin="3pt" Size="9" Leading="10" LeftMargin="0" RightMargin="1.5pt" FirstLineIndent="0" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Right">12,000.00 (yearly)</Para></entry></row></tbody></tgroup></TABLE></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:PENSION ACT--><MarginalNote>R.S., c. P-6<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="10" Bold="Yes" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">PENSION ACT</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>1999, c. 10, s. 16<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>20.</B> Subsections 72(1) and (2) of the <I>Pension Act</I> are replaced by the following:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Amount of allowance<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>72.</B> (1) In addition to any other allowance, pension or compensation awarded under this Act, a member of the forces shall be awarded an exceptional incapacity allowance at a rate determined by the Minister in accordance with the minimum and maximum rates set out in Schedule III if the member of the forces</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>a</I>) is in receipt of</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="4" FirstLineIndent="0">(i) a pension in the amount set out in Class 1 of Schedule I, or</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="4" FirstLineIndent="0">(ii) a pension in a lesser amount than the amount set out in Class 1 of Schedule I as well as compensation paid under this Act or a disability award paid under the <I>Canadian Forces Members and Veterans Re-establishment and Compensation Act</I>, or both, if the aggregate of the following percentages is equal to or greater than 98%:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="6" FirstLineIndent="0">(A) the extent of the disability in respect of which the pension is paid,</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="6" FirstLineIndent="0">(B) the percentage of basic pension at which basic compensation is paid, and</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="6" FirstLineIndent="0">(C) the extent of the disability in respect of which the disability award is paid; and</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>b</I>) is suffering an exceptional incapacity that is a consequence of or caused in whole or in part by the disability for which the member is receiving a pension or a disability award under that Act.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Ineligibility — permanent impairment allowance<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(1.1) A member of the forces who is eligible for a permanent impairment allowance under the <I>Canadian Forces Members and Veterans Re-establishment and Compensation Act</I> is not eligible to be awarded an exceptional incapacity allowance.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Determination of exceptional incapacity<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(2) Without restricting the generality of paragraph (1)(<I>b</I>), in determining whether the incapacity suffered by a member of the forces is exceptional, account shall be taken of the extent to which the disability for which the member is receiving a pension or a disability award under the <I>Canadian Forces Members and Veterans Re-establishment and Compensation Act</I> has left the member in a helpless condition or in continuing pain and discomfort, has resulted in loss of enjoyment of life or has shortened the member’s life expectancy.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:REVIEW--><Para TopMargin="10" Bold="Yes" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">REVIEW</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Review<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>20.1</B> Within two years after the day on which this section comes into force, a comprehensive review of the provisions and operations of this Act must be undertaken by any committees of the Senate and of the House of Commons that are designated or established by the Senate and the House of Commons for that purpose.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:COMING INTO FORCE--><Para TopMargin="10" Bold="Yes" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">COMING INTO FORCE</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Order in council<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>21.</B> The provisions of this Act come into force on a day or days to be fixed by order of the Governor in Council.</Para></Block><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="BPT_ImprintE">Published under authority of the Speaker of the House of Commons<br/>Available from:<br/>Publishing and Depository Services<br/>Public Works and Government Services Canada<br/>Ottawa, Ontario K1A 0S5<br/>Telephone: 613-941-5995 or 1-800-635-7943<br/>Fax: 613-954-5779 or 1-800-565-7757<br/>publications@tpsgc-pwgsc.gc.ca<br/>http://publications.gc.ca</Para></Block><Block Align="Yes" LineCnt="N"><Para NoLineBreak="Yes" NoHtml="Yes" Leading="0" Size="0" TopMargin="0" BottomMargin="0"></Para></Block></Bill_Part></Bill>
