<?xml version="1.0"?>
<Bill RHead_reign="59 Eliz. II" RHead_ParlYear="2010" DocumentTitle="BILL S-10" Bill_No="S-10" Document_No="90485" xml:lang="EN" Bill_Type="Non-amending" Stage_Name="First-Reading-Senate" Reprint="No" xml:space="preserve" ChapterNo_E="C. " ChapterNo_F="ch. " Bill-Origin="senate"><Bill_Part Part_Type="Cover" CountLines="No"><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="CovBillNo">S-10</Para></Block><Block><Para TopMargin="24" Size="9" Leading="10" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0" TextAlign="Center">Third Session, Fortieth Parliament,</Para></Block><Block><Para Size="9" Leading="10" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0" TextAlign="Center">59 Elizabeth II, 2010</Para></Block><Block><Para TopMargin="48" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0" Bold="Yes" TextAlign="Center">SENATE OF CANADA</Para></Block><Block><Para TopMargin="42" Size="18" Leading="20" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0" Bold="Yes" TextAlign="Center">BILL S-10</Para></Block><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="CovLongTitle">An Act to amend the Controlled Drugs and Substances Act and to make related and consequential amendments to other Acts</Para></Block><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="COV_StageLine"></Para></Block><Block><Para Size="9" AllCaps="Yes" Hyphenate="OFF">first reading, May 5, 2010</Para></Block><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="COV_StageLine"></Para></Block><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="Cover_Sponsors">LEADER OF THE GOVERNMENT IN THE SENATE</Para></Block><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="Cover_DocNo">90485</Para></Block></Bill_Part><Bill_Part CountLines="No" Part_Type="InsideCover"><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="BPT_InsideCoverE">Available on the Parliament of Canada Web Site at the following address:<br/><B>http://www.parl.gc.ca</B></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><Para TopMargin="108" BottomMargin="4" Size="10" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">SUMMARY</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" Size="8" Leading="9" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">This enactment amends the <I>Controlled Drugs and Substances Act</I> to provide for minimum penalties for serious drug offences, to increase the maximum penalty for cannabis (marihuana) production and to reschedule certain substances from Schedule III to that Act to Schedule I.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" Size="8" Leading="9" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">As well, it requires that a review of that Act be undertaken and a report submitted to Parliament.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" Size="8" Leading="9" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">The enactment also makes related and consequential amendments to other Acts.</Para></Block></Bill_Part><Bill_Part Part_Type="MainText" CountLines="Yes" RunningHead_E="Controlled Drugs and Substances"><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="MainText_DocNo">90485</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes"><Para Style="Session_Reign">3rd Session, 40th Parliament,</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes"><Para Style="Session_Reign">59 Elizabeth II, 2010</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes"><Para Style="MainBillOrigin">senate of canada</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes"><Para Bold="Yes" Style="MAIN@BillNo_Title">BILL S-10</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes"><Para Style="MAIN@ti;04">An Act to amend the Controlled Drugs and Substances Act and to make related and consequential amendments to other Acts</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">Her Majesty, by and with the advice and consent of the Senate and House of Commons of Canada, enacts as follows:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:SHORT TITLE--><Para TopMargin="10" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">SHORT TITLE</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Short title<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>1.</B> This Act may be cited as the <I>Penalties for Organized Drug Crime Act</I>.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:CONTROLLED DRUGS AND SUBSTANCES ACT--><MarginalNote>1996, c. 19<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="10" Bold="Yes" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">CONTROLLED DRUGS AND SUBSTANCES ACT</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>2.</B> (1) Paragraph 5(3)(<I>a</I>) of the <I>Controlled Drugs and Substances Act</I> is replaced by the following:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>a</I>) subject to paragraph (<I>a.1</I>), if the subject matter of the offence is a substance included in Schedule I or II, is guilty of an indictable offence and liable to imprisonment for life, and</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="4" FirstLineIndent="0">(i) to a minimum punishment of imprisonment for a term of one year if</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="6" FirstLineIndent="0">(A) the person committed the offence for the benefit of, at the direction of or in association with a criminal organization, as defined in subsection 467.1(1) of the <I>Criminal Code</I>,</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="6" FirstLineIndent="0">(B) the person used or threatened to use violence in committing the offence,</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="6" FirstLineIndent="0">(C) the person carried, used or threat-ened to use a weapon in committing the offence, or</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="6" FirstLineIndent="0">(D) the person was convicted of a designated substance offence, or had served a term of imprisonment for a designated substance offence, within the previous 10 years, or</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="4" FirstLineIndent="0">(ii) to a minimum punishment of impris-onment for a term of two years if</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="6" FirstLineIndent="0">(A) the person committed the offence in or near a school, on or near school grounds or in or near any other public place usually frequented by persons under the age of 18 years,</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="6" FirstLineIndent="0">(B) the person committed the offence in a prison, as defined in section 2 of the <I>Criminal Code</I>, or on its grounds, or</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="6" FirstLineIndent="0">(C) the person used the services of a person under the age of 18 years, or involved such a person, in committing the offence;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>a.1</I>) if the subject matter of the offence is a substance included in Schedule II in an amount that is not more than the amount set out for that substance in Schedule VII, is guilty of an indictable offence and liable to imprisonment for a term of not more than five years less a day;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes">(2) Subsections 5(4) to (6) of the Act are replaced by the following:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Interpretation<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(5) For the purposes of applying subsection (3) in respect of an offence under subsection (1), a reference to a substance included in Schedule I, II, III or IV includes a reference to any substance represented or held out to be a substance included in that Schedule.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Interpretation<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(6) For the purposes of paragraph (3)(<I>a.1</I>) and Schedule VII, the amount of the substance means the entire amount of any mixture or substance, or the whole of any plant, that contains a detectable amount of the substance.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>3.</B> Paragraph 6(3)(<I>a</I>) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>a</I>) if the subject matter of the offence is a substance included in Schedule I in an amount that is not more than one kilogram, or in Schedule II, is guilty of an indictable offence and liable to imprisonment for life, and to a minimum punishment of imprisonment for a term of one year if</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="4" FirstLineIndent="0">(i) the offence is committed for the purposes of trafficking,</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="4" FirstLineIndent="0">(ii) the person, while committing the offence, abused a position of trust or authority, or</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="4" FirstLineIndent="0">(iii) the person had access to an area that is restricted to authorized persons and used that access to commit the offence;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>a.1</I>) if the subject matter of the offence is a substance included in Schedule I in an amount that is more than one kilogram, is guilty of an indictable offence and liable to imprisonment for life and to a minimum punishment of imprisonment for a term of two years;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>4.</B> (1) Paragraphs 7(2)(<I>a</I>) and (<I>b</I>) of the Act are replaced by the following:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>a</I>) if the subject matter of the offence is a substance included in Schedule I, is guilty of an indictable offence and liable to imprisonment for life and to a minimum punishment of imprisonment for a term of three years if any of the factors set out in subsection (3) apply and for a term of two years in any other case;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>a.1</I>) if the subject matter of the offence is a substance included in Schedule II, other than cannabis (marihuana), is guilty of an indictable offence and liable to imprisonment for life, and to a minimum punishment of imprisonment</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="4" FirstLineIndent="0">(i) for a term of one year if the production is for the purpose of trafficking, or</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="4" FirstLineIndent="0">(ii) for a term of 18 months if the production is for the purpose of trafficking and any of the factors set out in subsection (3) apply;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>b</I>) if the subject matter of the offence is cannabis (marihuana), is guilty of an indictable offence and liable to imprisonment for a term of not more than 14 years, and to a minimum punishment of</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="4" FirstLineIndent="0">(i) imprisonment for a term of six months if the number of plants produced is less than 201 and more than five, and the production is for the purpose of trafficking,</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="4" FirstLineIndent="0">(ii) imprisonment for a term of nine months if the number of plants produced is less than 201, the production is for the purpose of trafficking and any of the factors set out in subsection (3) apply,</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="4" FirstLineIndent="0">(iii) imprisonment for a term of one year if the number of plants produced is more than 200 and less than 501,</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="4" FirstLineIndent="0">(iv) imprisonment for a term of 18 months if the number of plants produced is more than 200 and less than 501 and any of the factors set out in subsection (3) apply,</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="4" FirstLineIndent="0">(v) imprisonment for a term of two years if the number of plants produced is more than 500, or</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="4" FirstLineIndent="0">(vi) imprisonment for a term of three years if the number of plants produced is more than 500 and any of the factors set out in subsection (3) apply;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes">(2) Section 7 of the Act is amended by adding the following after subsection (2):</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Factors<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(3) The following factors must be taken into account in applying paragraphs (2)(<I>a</I>) to (<I>b</I>):</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>a</I>) the person used real property that belongs to a third party in committing the offence;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>b</I>) the production constituted a potential security, health or safety hazard to persons under the age of 18 years who were in the location where the offence was committed or in the immediate area;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>c</I>) the production constituted a potential public safety hazard in a residential area; or</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>d</I>) the person set or placed a trap, device or other thing that is likely to cause death or bodily harm to another person in the location where the offence was committed or in the immediate area, or permitted such a trap, device or other thing to remain or be placed in that location or area.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>5.</B> The Act is amended by adding the following after section 7:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:Notice--><Para TopMargin="10" SmallCaps="Yes" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">Notice</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Notice<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>8.</B> The court is not required to impose a minimum punishment unless it is satisfied that the offender, before entering a plea, was notified of the possible imposition of a minimum punishment for the offence in question and of the Attorney General’s intention to prove any factors in relation to the offence that would lead to the imposition of a minimum punishment.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:Report to Parliament--><Para TopMargin="10" SmallCaps="Yes" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">Report to Parliament</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Review<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>8.1</B> (1) Within two years after this section comes into force, a comprehensive review of the provisions and operation of the Act, including a cost benefit analysis of mandatory minimum sentences, shall be undertaken by such committee of the House of Commons or of both Houses of Parliament as may be designated by Parliament for that purpose.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Report<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(2) The committee referred to in subsection (1) shall, within one year after a review is undertaken pursuant to that subsection, submit a report to Parliament including a statement of any changes the committee recommends.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>1999, c. 5, s. 49(1)<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>6.</B> (1) The portion of subsection 10(2) of the Act before paragraph (<I>a</I>) is replaced by the following:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Factors to take into consideration<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(2) If a person is convicted of a designated substance offence for which the court is not required to impose a minimum punishment, the court imposing sentence on the person shall consider any relevant aggravating factors including that the person</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes">(2) Section 10 of the Act is amended by adding the following after subsection (3):</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Drug treatment court program<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(4) A court sentencing a person who is convicted of an offence under this Part may delay sentencing to enable the offender</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>a</I>) to participate in a drug treatment court program approved by the Attorney General; or</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>b</I>) to attend a treatment program under subsection 720(2) of the <I>Criminal Code</I>.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Minimum punishment<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(5) If the offender successfully completes a program under subsection (4), the court is not required to impose the minimum punishment for the offence for which the person was convicted.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>7.</B> Schedule I to the Act is amended by adding the following after item 18:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="-2" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Left">19. <Tab/>Amphetamines, their salts, derivatives, isomers and analogues and salts of derivatives, isomers and analogues including:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="4" FirstLineIndent="-1" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Left">(1) <Tab/>amphetamine (α-methylbenzene-ethanamine)</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="4" FirstLineIndent="-1" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Left">(2) <Tab/>N-ethylamphetamine (N-ethyl-α-methylbenzeneethanamine)</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="4" FirstLineIndent="-1" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Left">(3) <Tab/>4-methyl-2,5-dimethoxyamphetamine (STP) (2,5-dimethoxy-4,α-dimethylbenzeneethanamine)</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="4" FirstLineIndent="-1" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Left">(4) <Tab/>3,4-methylenedioxyamphetamine (MDA) (α-methyl-1,3-benzodioxole-5-ethanamine)</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="4" FirstLineIndent="-1" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Left">(5) <Tab/>2,5-dimethoxyamphetamine (2,5-di-methoxy-α-methylbenzene-ethanamine)</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="4" FirstLineIndent="-1" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Left">(6) <Tab/>4-methoxyamphetamine (4-methoxy-α-methylbenzene­ethanamine)</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="4" FirstLineIndent="-1" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Left">(7) <Tab/>2,4,5-trimethoxyamphetamine (2,4,5-trimethoxy-α-methylbenzene­ethanamine)</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="4" FirstLineIndent="-1" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Left">(8) <Tab/>N-methyl-3,4-methylenedioxy- amphetamine (N,α-dimethyl-1,3-benzodioxole-5-ethanamine)</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="4" FirstLineIndent="-1" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Left">(9) <Tab/>4-ethoxy-2,5-dimethoxyamphetamine (4-ethoxy-2,5-dimethoxy-α-methylbenzeneethanamine)</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="4" FirstLineIndent="-1" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Left">(10) <Tab/>5-methoxy-3,4-methylenedioxy- amphetamine (7-methoxy-α-methyl-1,3-benzo­dioxole-5-ethanamine)</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="4" FirstLineIndent="-1" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Left">(11) <Tab/>N,N-dimethyl-3,4-methylenedioxy- amphetamine (N,N, α-trimethyl-1,3-benzodioxole-5-ethanamine)</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="4" FirstLineIndent="-1" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Left">(12) <Tab/>N-ethyl-3,4-methylenedioxy- amphetamine (N-ethyl-α-methyl-1,3-benzo­dioxole-5-ethanamine)</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="4" FirstLineIndent="-1" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Left">(13) <Tab/>4-ethyl-2,5-dimethoxyamphetamine (DOET) (4-ethyl-2,5-dimethoxy-α-methylbenzeneethanamine)</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="4" FirstLineIndent="-1" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Left">(14) <Tab/>4-bromo-2,5-dimethoxyamphetamine (4-bromo-2,5-dimethoxy-α-methylbenzeneethanamine)</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="4" FirstLineIndent="-1" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Left">(15) <Tab/>4-chloro-2,5-dimethoxyamphetamine (4-chloro-2,5-dimethoxy-α-methylbenzeneethanamine)</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="4" FirstLineIndent="-1" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Left">(16) <Tab/>4-ethoxyamphetamine (4-ethoxy-α-methylbenzene­ethanamine)</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="4" FirstLineIndent="-1" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Left">(17) <Tab/>Benzphetamine (N-benzyl-N,α-dimethylbenzene­ethanamine)</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="4" FirstLineIndent="-1" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Left">(18) <Tab/>N-Propyl-3,4-methylenedioxy- amphetamine (α-methyl-N-propyl-1,3-benzo­dioxole-5-ethanamine)</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="4" FirstLineIndent="-1" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Left">(19) <Tab/>N-(2-Hydroxyethyl)-α-meth-ylbenzene­ethanamine</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="4" FirstLineIndent="-1" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Left">(20) <Tab/>N-hydroxy-3,4-methylenedioxy- amphetamine (N-[α-methyl-3,4-(methylenedioxy)phenethyl]hydroxylamine)</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="4" FirstLineIndent="-1" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Left">(21) <Tab/>3,4,5-trimethoxyamphetamine <keep>(3,4,5-trimethoxy-α-methyl-</keep>benzene­ethanamine)</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="3" FirstLineIndent="-3" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Left">20. <Tab/>Flunitrazepam (5-(o-fluorophenyl)-1,3-dihydro-1-methyl-7-nitro-2H-1,4-benzodiazepin-2-one) and any of its salts or derivatives</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="3" FirstLineIndent="-3" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Left">21. <Tab/>4-hydroxybutanoic acid (GHB) and any of its salts</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>SOR/97-230, s. 7; SOR/2003-32, s. 2; SOR/2005-235, s. 2<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>8.</B> Item 1 of Schedule III to the Act is repealed.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>SOR/98-173, s. 1; SOR/2000-220, s. 1<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>9.</B> Items 25 and 26 of Schedule III to the Act are repealed.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:RELATED AMENDMENTS--><Para TopMargin="10" Bold="Yes" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">RELATED AMENDMENTS</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:An Act to amend the Criminal Code (firearms) and the Firearms Act--><MarginalNote>2003, c. 8<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" Bold="Yes" SmallCaps="Yes" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">An Act to amend the Criminal Code (firearms) and the Firearms Act</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>10.</B> Section 8 of <I>An Act to amend the Criminal Code (firearms) and the Firearms Act</I>, chapter 8 of the Statutes of Canada, 2003, is repealed.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:Criminal Code--><MarginalNote>R.S., c. C-46<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="10" Bold="Yes" SmallCaps="Yes" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">Criminal Code</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>1999, c. 5, s. 21<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>11.</B> Paragraph 515(6)(<I>d</I>) of the <I>Criminal Code</I> is replaced by the following:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>d</I>) with having committed an offence punishable by imprisonment for life under any of sections 5 to 7 of the <I>Controlled Drugs and Substances Act</I> or the offence of conspiring to commit such an offence.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:National Defence Act--><MarginalNote>R.S., c. N-5<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="10" Bold="Yes" SmallCaps="Yes" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">National Defence Act</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>1998, c. 35, s. 40<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>12.</B> Subparagraph (<I>a</I>)(ii) of the definition “designated offence” in section 153 of the English version of the <I>National Defence Act</I> is replaced by the following:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="4" FirstLineIndent="0">(ii) an offence punishable by imprisonment for life under subsection 5(3), 6(3) or 7(2) of the <I>Controlled Drugs and Substances Act</I>, or</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:CONSEQUENTIAL AMENDMENTS--><Para TopMargin="10" Bold="Yes" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">CONSEQUENTIAL AMENDMENTS</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:Criminal Code--><MarginalNote>R.S., c. C-46<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" Bold="Yes" SmallCaps="Yes" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">Criminal Code</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>2001, c. 41, s. 133(15)<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>13.</B> Paragraph 515(4.1)(<I>c</I>) of the <I>Criminal Code</I> is replaced by the following:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>c</I>) an offence relating to the contravention of any of sections 5 to 7 of the <I>Controlled Drugs and Substances Act</I>,</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>1996, c. 19, s. 72<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>14.</B> Subparagraph 553(<I>c</I>)(xi) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="4" FirstLineIndent="0">(xi) paragraph 5(3)(<I>a.1</I>) of the <I>Controlled Drugs and Substances Act.</I></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:National Defence Act--><MarginalNote>R.S., c. N-5<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="10" Bold="Yes" SmallCaps="Yes" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">National Defence Act</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>1996, c. 19, s. 83.1<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>15.</B> Paragraph 147.1(1)(<I>c</I>) of the <I>National Defence Act</I> is replaced by the following:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>c</I>) relating to the contravention of any of sections 5 to 7 of the <I>Controlled Drugs and Substances Act</I>, or</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:COMING INTO FORCE--><Para TopMargin="10" Bold="Yes" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">COMING INTO FORCE</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Order in council<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>16.</B> The provisions of this Act, other than sections 11 and 12, come into force on a day or days to be fixed by order of the Governor in Council.</Para></Block><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="BPT_ImprintE">Published under authority of the Senate of Canada<br/>Available from:<br/>Publishing and Depository Services<br/>Public Works and Government Services Canada<br/>Ottawa, Ontario K1A 0S5<br/>Telephone: 613-941-5995 or 1-800-635-7943<br/>Fax: 613-954-5779 or 1-800-565-7757<br/>publications@tpsgc-pwgsc.gc.ca<br/>http://publications.gc.ca</Para></Block><Block Align="Yes" LineCnt="N"><Para NoLineBreak="Yes" NoHtml="Yes" Leading="0" Size="0" TopMargin="0" BottomMargin="0"></Para></Block></Bill_Part></Bill>
