<?xml version="1.0"?>
<Bill RHead_reign="59 Eliz. II" RHead_ParlYear="2010" DocumentTitle="BILL S-217" Bill_No="S-217" Document_No="3810432" xml:lang="EN" Bill_Type="Non-amending" Stage_Name="First-Reading-Senate" Reprint="No" xml:space="preserve" ChapterNo_E="C. " ChapterNo_F="ch. " Bill-Origin="senate"><Bill_Part Part_Type="Cover" CountLines="No"><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="CovBillNo">S-217</Para></Block><Block><Para TopMargin="24" Size="9" Leading="10" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0" TextAlign="Center">Third Session, Fortieth Parliament,</Para></Block><Block><Para Size="9" Leading="10" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0" TextAlign="Center">59 Elizabeth II, 2010</Para></Block><Block><Para TopMargin="48" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0" Bold="Yes" TextAlign="Center">SENATE OF CANADA</Para></Block><Block><Para TopMargin="42" Size="18" Leading="20" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0" Bold="Yes" TextAlign="Center">BILL S-217</Para></Block><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="CovLongTitle">An Act to establish and maintain a national registry of medical devices</Para></Block><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="COV_StageLine"></Para></Block><Block><Para Size="9" AllCaps="Yes" Hyphenate="OFF">first reading, April 14, 2010</Para></Block><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="COV_StageLine"></Para></Block><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="Cover_Sponsors">THE HONOURABLE SENATOR HARB</Para></Block><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="Cover_DocNo">3810432</Para></Block></Bill_Part><Bill_Part CountLines="No" Part_Type="InsideCover"><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="BPT_InsideCoverE">Available on the Parliament of Canada Web Site at the following address:<br/><B>http://www.parl.gc.ca</B></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><Para TopMargin="108" BottomMargin="4" Size="10" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">SUMMARY</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" Size="8" Leading="9" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">This enactment requires the Registrar of Medical Devices, designated by the Minister of Health, to establish and maintain a Medical Devices Registry. The Registry will contain, with their consent, the names and addresses of persons who use implantable medical devices or prescribed home-use medical devices, a description of the medical devices and other information. Personal information in the Registry may not be disclosed for any purpose without the person’s written and informed consent.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" Size="8" Leading="9" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">The enactment requires the manufacturers, importers and distributors of these medical devices to notify the Registrar if they become aware that a medical device may pose a risk to the health or safety of the user.  The Registrar is required to notify registered users if a medical device may pose a risk to their health or safety.</Para></Block></Bill_Part><Bill_Part Part_Type="MainText" CountLines="Yes" RunningHead_E="Medical Devices Registry"><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="MainText_DocNo">3810432</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes"><Para Style="Session_Reign">3rd Session, 40th Parliament,</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes"><Para Style="Session_Reign">59 Elizabeth II, 2010</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes"><Para Style="MainBillOrigin">senate of canada</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes"><Para Bold="Yes" Style="MAIN@BillNo_Title">BILL S-217</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes"><Para Style="MAIN@ti;04">An Act to establish and maintain a national registry of medical devices</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Preamble<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">Whereas medical device problem reporting is an essential element in the continued efforts of the Health Products and Food Branch Inspectorate of the Department of Health to protect the health and safety of Canadians;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">And whereas, although manufacturers and importers are required to report certain medical device problems, the Parliament of Canada acknowledges that a complementary medical device problem notification system should be maintained by the Department of Health;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">Now, therefore, Her Majesty, by and with the advice and consent of the Senate and House of Commons of Canada, enacts as follows:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:SHORT TITLE--><Para TopMargin="10" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">SHORT TITLE</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Short title<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>1.</B> This Act may be cited as the <I>Medical Devices Registry Act</I>.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:INTERPRETATION--><Para TopMargin="10" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">INTERPRETATION</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Definitions<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>2.</B> The following definitions apply in this Act.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><MarginalNote>“home-use medical device”<br/>« <I>instrument médical pour usage à domicile</I> »<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0">“home-use medical device” means a medical device</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>a</I>) intended to be used by a person in a home environment for purposes related to their health care; and</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>b</I>) of a kind prescribed by the regulations.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><MarginalNote>“implantable medical device”<br/>« <I>instrument médical implantable</I> »<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0">“implantable medical device” means a medical device that</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>a</I>) is partly or totally inserted into the human body or a natural orifice by means of a surgical or medical procedure;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>b</I>) is expected to stay there for 30 days or more; and</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>c</I>) would require a surgical or medical procedure to remove it.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><MarginalNote>“manufacturer”<br/>« <I>fabricant</I> »<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0">“manufacturer” means a person who sells a medical device under their own name, or under a trade-mark, design, trade name or other name or mark owned or controlled by the person, and who is responsible for designing, manufacturing, assembling, processing, labelling, packaging, refurbishing or modifying the device, or for assigning to it a purpose, whether those tasks are performed by that person or on their behalf.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><MarginalNote>“medical device”<br/>« <I>instrument médical</I> »<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0">“medical device” means a device within the meaning of the <I>Food and Drugs Act</I>.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><MarginalNote>“medical practitioner”<br/>« <I>médecin</I> »<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0">“medical practitioner” means a person lawfully entitled to practise medicine in the place in which the practice is carried on by that person.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><MarginalNote>“Minister”<br/>« <I>ministre</I> »<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0">“Minister” means the Minister of Health.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><MarginalNote>“Registrar”<br/>« <I>directeur</I> »<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0">“Registrar” means the Registrar of Medical Devices designated under section 3.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><MarginalNote>“Registry”<br/>« <I>Registre</I> »<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0">“Registry” means the Medical Devices Registry established under subsection 4(1).</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><MarginalNote>“supply”<br/>« <I>fournir</I> »<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0">“supply”, in relation to a medical device, includes to issue a prescription that authorizes a person to obtain a medical device.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><MarginalNote>“user”<br/>« <I>utilisateur</I> »<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0">“user” means a person who has had an implantable medical device inserted into their body or who uses a home-use medical device supplied to them by a medical practitioner.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:MEDICAL DEVICES REGISTRATION SYSTEM--><Para TopMargin="10" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">MEDICAL DEVICES REGISTRATION SYSTEM</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:Registrar of Medical Devices--><Para TopMargin="5" SmallCaps="Yes" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">Registrar of Medical Devices</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Designation of Registrar of Medical Devices<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>3.</B> The Minister shall designate a person, from among persons employed in the Department of Health, as the Registrar of Medical Devices.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Medical Devices Registry<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>4.</B> (1) The Registrar shall establish and maintain, within the Department of Health, a registry, to be called the Medical Devices Registry, containing</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>a</I>) the information submitted by medical practitioners under subsection 5(1);</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>b</I>) a record of any information provided by the manufacturer, importer or distributor of a medical device that identifies any risk to the health or safety of the user; and</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>c</I>) any other information prescribed by the regulations.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Operation<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(2) The Registrar is responsible for the day-to-day operation of the Registry.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Destruction of information<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(3) The Registrar may destroy information kept in the Registry at the times and in the circumstances that may be prescribed by the regulations.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:Reporting and Notification--><Para TopMargin="10" SmallCaps="Yes" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">Reporting and Notification</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Submission of information by medical practitioner<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>5.</B> (1) A medical practitioner who inserts an implantable medical device into a person’s body or who supplies a home-use medical device to a person shall, as soon as possible after doing so, submit to the Registrar, in the form prescribed by the regulations, the following information:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>a</I>) the name, date of birth and address of the person, if the person consents to the disclosure of the information;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>b</I>) the medical practitioner’s name;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>c</I>) the date on which, and the health care facility at which, the device was inserted or supplied;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>d</I>) the name and address of the manufacturer of the device;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>e</I>) the model designation of the device, if applicable;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>f</I>) the lot or serial number of the device; and</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>g</I>) any other information prescribed by the regulations.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Information and consent<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(2) A medical practitioner who inserts an implantable medical device into a person’s body or who supplies a home-use medical device to a person shall</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>a</I>) inform the person of the nature and purpose of the Registry and the requirement to submit information to the Registrar; and</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>b</I>) seek the consent of the person to the disclosure to the Registrar of the information referred to in paragraph (1)(<I>a</I>).</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Change of address<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>6.</B> The Registrar shall, on receipt of information submitted under subsection 5(1) that includes the name and address of the person in respect of whom the information is submitted, provide to the person a copy of the information and a statement advising the person to notify the Registrar of any change in the person’s permanent address.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Duty of manufacturers, distributors and importers<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>7.</B> A manufacturer, importer or distributor of an implantable medical device or a home-use medical device shall notify the Registrar immediately after becoming aware that the device may pose a risk to the health or safety of the user, and shall provide the Registrar with the information prescribed by the regulations.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Duty to notify users of risk<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>8.</B> (1) When the Registrar receives a notification under section 7 or otherwise has reasonable grounds to believe that an implantable medical device or a home-use medical device may pose a risk to the health or safety of the user, the Registrar shall contact without delay</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>a</I>) each user of the device whose name and address is listed in the Registry; or</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>b</I>) in respect of each device for which the name and address of the user was not submitted to the Registrar, the medical practitioner who registered the device.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Information to be provided<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(2) When the Registrar contacts a person under subsection (1), the Registrar shall provide to the person any information that the Registrar considers necessary to assist the person in assessing the risk to the health or safety of the user.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:Electronic Filing--><Para TopMargin="10" SmallCaps="Yes" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">Electronic Filing</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Electronic filing<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>9.</B> Subject to the regulations, any notices and documents that are sent to or issued by the Registrar under this or any other Act of Parliament may be sent or issued in electronic or other form in any manner specified by the Registrar.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Organization of Registry<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>10.</B> (1) The Registry shall be organized in the manner and kept in the form determined by the Registrar.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Probative value<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(2) Where the Registrar maintains a record of a document otherwise than in written or printed form, an extract from that record that is certified by the Registrar has the same probative value as the document would have had if it had been proved in the ordinary way.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:Confidentiality--><Para TopMargin="10" SmallCaps="Yes" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">Confidentiality</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Prohibited disclosure of name and address of user<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>11.</B> Information described in paragraph 5(1)(<I>a</I>) that is contained in the Registry is confidential, and the Registrar shall not disclose the information to anyone, including an agency of the Crown, without the written consent of the person to whom the information relates, given after the person has been informed of the purpose for which the consent is sought.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:REGULATIONS--><Para TopMargin="10" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">REGULATIONS</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Regulations<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>12.</B> The Governor in Council may, on the recommendation of the Minister, make regulations for carrying out the purposes and provisions of this Act, including regulations</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>a</I>) for the purposes of the definition “home-use medical device”, prescribing any kind of medical device intended to be used by a person in a home environment for purposes related to their health care;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>b</I>) prescribing information to be contained in the Registry for the purposes of paragraph 4(1)(<I>c</I>);</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>c</I>) respecting the destruction of information kept in the Registry for the purposes of subsection 4(3);</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>d</I>) respecting information to be submitted by a medical practitioner for the purposes of subsection 5(1);</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>e</I>) respecting information to be provided by manufacturers, importers and distributors for the purposes of section 7; and</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>f</I>) exempting any medical device, or type of medical device, from the application of this Act if the Minister is of the opinion that the exemption is in the public interest and consistent with public health and safety.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:COMING INTO FORCE--><Para TopMargin="10" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">COMING INTO FORCE</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Coming into force<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>13.</B> This Act comes into force on a day, not later than two years after the day on which it receives royal assent,  to be fixed by order of the Governor in Council.</Para></Block><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="BPT_ImprintE">Published under authority of the Senate of Canada<br/>Available from:<br/>Publishing and Depository Services<br/>Public Works and Government Services Canada<br/>Ottawa, Ontario K1A 0S5<br/>Telephone: 613-941-5995 or 1-800-635-7943<br/>Fax: 613-954-5779 or 1-800-565-7757<br/>publications@tpsgc-pwgsc.gc.ca<br/>http://publications.gc.ca</Para></Block><Block Align="Yes" LineCnt="N"><Para NoLineBreak="Yes" NoHtml="Yes" Leading="0" Size="0" TopMargin="0" BottomMargin="0"></Para></Block></Bill_Part></Bill>
