<?xml version="1.0"?>
<Bill RHead_reign="59 Eliz. II" RHead_ParlYear="2010" DocumentTitle="BILL S-220" Bill_No="S-220" Document_No="4031006" xml:lang="EN" Bill_Type="Amending" Stage_Name="First-Reading-Senate" Reprint="No" xml:space="preserve" ChapterNo_E="C. " ChapterNo_F="ch. " Bill-Origin="senate"><Bill_Part Part_Type="Cover" CountLines="No"><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="CovBillNo">S-220</Para></Block><Block><Para TopMargin="24" Size="9" Leading="10" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0" TextAlign="Center">Third Session, Fortieth Parliament,</Para></Block><Block><Para Size="9" Leading="10" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0" TextAlign="Center">59 Elizabeth II, 2010</Para></Block><Block><Para TopMargin="48" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0" Bold="Yes" TextAlign="Center">SENATE OF CANADA</Para></Block><Block><Para TopMargin="42" Size="18" Leading="20" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0" Bold="Yes" TextAlign="Center">BILL S-220</Para></Block><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="CovLongTitle">An Act to amend the Official Languages Act (communications with and services to the public)</Para></Block><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="COV_StageLine"></Para></Block><Block><Para Size="9" AllCaps="Yes" Hyphenate="OFF">first reading, June 9, 2010</Para></Block><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="COV_StageLine"></Para></Block><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="Cover_Sponsors">THE HONOURABLE SENATOR CHAPUT</Para></Block><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="Cover_DocNo">4031006</Para></Block></Bill_Part><Bill_Part CountLines="No" Part_Type="InsideCover"><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="BPT_InsideCoverE">Available on the Parliament of Canada Web Site at the following address:<br/><B>http://www.parl.gc.ca</B></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><Para TopMargin="108" BottomMargin="4" Size="10" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">SUMMARY</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" Size="8" Leading="9" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">This enactment amends the <I>Official Languages Act</I>. The concept of equal quality of communications and services in each official language is introduced. The enactment modifies the criteria used to determine when there is a significant demand for communications and services in one of the official languages.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" Size="8" Leading="9" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">This enactment specifies the locations where federal institutions have a duty to provide communications and services in both official languages. That duty is applied to cases where an official language minority is located in a specific geographic region or faces linguistic assimilation. Many of the duties of the federal institutions to provide communications and services in both official languages are extended to the carriers designated by regulation of the Governor in Council.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" Size="8" Leading="9" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">The provisions on prior consultation are applied more specifically to amendments to regulations that provide for exceptions to the application of Part IV of the Act in certain circumstances or to certain bodies.</Para></Block></Bill_Part><Bill_Part Part_Type="MainText" CountLines="Yes" RunningHead_E="Official Languages (communications with and services to the public)"><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="MainText_DocNo">4031006</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes"><Para Style="Session_Reign">3rd Session, 40th Parliament,</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes"><Para Style="Session_Reign">59 Elizabeth II, 2010</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes"><Para Style="MainBillOrigin">senate of canada</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes"><Para Bold="Yes" Style="MAIN@BillNo_Title">BILL S-220</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes"><Para Style="MAIN@ti;04">An Act to amend the Official Languages Act (communications with and services to the public)</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>1985, c. 31 (4th Supp.)<br/></MarginalNote><Para LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">Her Majesty, by and with the advice and consent of the Senate and House of Commons of Canada, enacts as follows:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>1.</B> Subsection 3(1) of the <I>Official Languages Act</I> is amended by adding the following in alphabetical order:</Para><ExplNote><Para Align="Yes" TopMargin="10" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0" Italic="Yes" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">Official Languages Act</Para><Para Align="Yes" TopMargin="10" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><I>Clause 1</I>: New.</Para></ExplNote></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>“designated carrier”<br/>« <I>transporteur désigné</I> »<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0"><change>“designated carrier” means a business or undertaking, and any subsidiary thereof, incorporated pursuant to an Act of Parliament or of the legislature of a province or territory and designated by regulation, that provides rail, maritime or air transportation services and related services prescribed by regulation of the Governor in Council;</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><MarginalNote>“metropolitan area”<br/>« <I>région métropolitaine</I> »<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0"><change>“metropolitan area” means any area that is classified by Statistics Canada in its most recent census of Canada as a census metropolitan area;</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><MarginalNote>“provincial or territorial institution”<br/>« <I>institutions provinciales ou territoriales</I> »<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0"><change>“provincial or territorial institution” includes any of the following institutions of the legislature or government of a province or territory:</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0"><change>(<I>a</I>) any provincial or territorial court,</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0"><change>(<I>b</I>) any board, commission, council, office, municipal institution or other body established to perform a governmental function by or pursuant to an Act of the legislature of a province or territory or by or under the authority of the lieutenant governor in council of a province or commissioner in council of a territory,</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0"><change>(<I>c</I>) a department of the Government of a province or territory,</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0"><change>(<I>d</I>) a Crown corporation established by or pursuant to an Act of the legislature of a province or territory, and</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0"><change>(<I>e</I>) any other body that is specified by an Act of the legislature of a province or territory to be an agent of Her Majesty in right of the province or territory or to be subject to the direction of the lieutenant governor in council of the province or commissioner in council of the territory or a provincial or territorial minister of the Crown;</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>2.</B> Sections 21 to 23 of the Act are replaced by the following:</Para><ExplNote><Para Align="Yes" TopMargin="10" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><I>Clause 2</I>: Text of sections 21 to 23:</Para><Para Align="Yes" TopMargin="5" Size="8" Leading="9" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>21.</B> Any member of the public in Canada has the right to communicate with and to receive available services from federal institutions in accordance with this Part.</Para><Para Align="Yes" TopMargin="5" Size="8" Leading="9" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>22.</B> Every federal institution has the duty to ensure that any member of the public can communicate with and obtain available services from its head or central office in either official language, and has the same duty with respect to any of its other offices or facilities</Para><Para Align="No" TopMargin="5" Size="8" Leading="9" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>a</I>) within the National Capital Region; or</Para><Para Align="No" TopMargin="5" Size="8" Leading="9" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>b</I>) in Canada or elsewhere, where there is significant demand for communications with and services from that office or facility in that language.</Para><Para Align="Yes" TopMargin="5" Size="8" Leading="9" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>23.</B> (1) For greater certainty, every federal institution that provides services or makes them available to the travelling public has the duty to ensure that any member of the travelling public can communicate with and obtain those services in either official language from any office or facility of the institution in Canada or elsewhere where there is significant demand for those services in that language.</Para><Para Align="Yes" TopMargin="5" Size="8" Leading="9" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(2) Every federal institution has the duty to ensure that such services to the travelling public as may be prescribed by regulation of the Governor in Council that are provided or made available by another person or organization pursuant to a contract with the federal institution for the provision of those services at an office or facility referred to in subsection (1) are provided or made available, in both official languages, in the manner prescribed by regulation of the Governor in Council.</Para></ExplNote></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Rights relating to language of communication<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>21.</B> Any member of the public in Canada has the right to communicate with and to receive available services from federal institutions <change>and designated carriers</change> in accordance with this Part.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Where communications and services must be in both official languages: federal institutions<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>22.</B> <change>(1)</change> Every federal institution has the duty to ensure that any member of the public can communicate with and obtain available services from its head or central office in either official language, and has the same duty with respect to any of its other offices or facilities</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>a</I>) within the National Capital Region;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0"><change>(<I>b</I>) in a region where provincial or territorial institutions have a legal or administrative duty to communicate with and offer services to members of the public in both official languages; or</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0"><change>(<I>c</I>)</change> in Canada or elsewhere, where there is significant demand for communications with and services from that office or facility in that language.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Trans-Canada Highway<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><change>(2) The Royal Canadian Mounted Police is required to communicate with and provide services to the public in either official language on those portions of the Trans-Canada Highway served by its detachments.</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Where communications and services must be in both official languages: designated carriers<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>23.</B> (1) Every <change>designated carrier</change> has the duty to ensure that any member of the public can communicate with and obtain <change>available</change> services from its head or central office in either official language<change>, and has the same duty with respect to any of its other offices or facilities</change> in Canada or elsewhere where there is significant demand for <change>communications and</change> services in that language.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Application in certain locations<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><change>(1.1) Federal institutions and designated carriers are required to communicate with and provide services to the public in either official language in the following locations:</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0"><change>(<I>a</I>) railway stations and airports serving a metropolitan area;</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0"><change>(<I>b</I>) railway stations and airports serving the national capital or the capital of a province or territory;</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0"><change>(<I>c</I>) ferry terminals serving at least one hundred thousand persons annually; and</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0"><change>(<I>d</I>) railway stations, airports, ferry terminals, public ports and public port facilities prescribed by regulation of the Governor in Council.</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Services provided pursuant to a contract<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(2) Every federal institution <change>and designated carrier</change> has the duty to ensure that such services to the public as may be prescribed by regulation of the Governor in Council that are provided or made available by another person or organization pursuant to a contract with the federal institution <change>or designated carrier</change> for the provision of those services at an office or facility referred to in <change>section 22 or this section</change> are provided or made available, in both official languages, in the manner prescribed by regulation of the Governor in Council.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Equal quality<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><change><B>23.1</B> (1) Every federal institution and designated carrier has the duty to take every reasonable measure to ensure that communications with and services to members of the public are of equal quality in both official languages.</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Consultation<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><change>(2) Every federal institution and designated carrier shall, in the manner prescribed by regulation of the Governor in Council, consult the English and French linguistic minority communities and, where appropriate, members of the public generally on the quality of the communications and services that they offer to the public in each of the official languages.</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>3.</B> The portion of subsection 24(1) before paragraph (<I>a</I>) and paragraph 24(1)(<I>a</I>) of the Act are replaced by the following:</Para><ExplNote><Para Align="Yes" TopMargin="10" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><I>Clause 3</I>: Relevant portion of subsection 24(1):</Para><Para Align="Yes" TopMargin="5" Size="8" Leading="9" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>24.</B> (1) Every federal institution has the duty to ensure that any member of the public can communicate in either official language with, and obtain available services in either official language from, any of its offices or facilities in Canada or elsewhere</Para><Para Align="No" TopMargin="5" Size="8" Leading="9" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>a</I>) in any circumstances prescribed by regulation of the Governor in Council that relate to any of the following:</Para><Para Align="No" TopMargin="5" Size="8" Leading="9" LeftMargin="4" FirstLineIndent="0">(i) the health, safety or security of members of the public,</Para><Para Align="No" TopMargin="5" Size="8" Leading="9" LeftMargin="4" FirstLineIndent="0">(ii) the location of the office or facility, or</Para><Para Align="No" TopMargin="5" Size="8" Leading="9" LeftMargin="4" FirstLineIndent="0">(iii) the national or international mandate of the office; or</Para></ExplNote></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Nature of the office<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>24.</B> (1) Every federal institution <change>or designated carrier</change> has the duty to ensure that any member of the public can communicate in either official language with, and obtain available services in either official language from, any of its offices or facilities in Canada or elsewhere</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>a</I>) in any circumstances prescribed by regulation of the Governor in Council that relate to any of the following:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="4" FirstLineIndent="0">(i) the health, safety or security of members of the public,</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="4" FirstLineIndent="0">(ii) the location of the office or facility, or</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="4" FirstLineIndent="0">(iii) the national or international mandate <change>or services</change> of the office;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0"><change>(<I>a.1</I>) in any circumstances prescribed by regulation of the Governor in Council where the services in question significantly affect or benefit the English or French linguistic minority population in a given geographic area;</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0"><change>(<I>a.2</I>) in any circumstances prescribed by regulation of the Governor in Council, relating to the loss of the language or linguistic assimilation, where the application of this subsection is likely to lead to the revitalization or advancement of the use of the language of the English or French linguistic minority population; or</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>4.</B> Section 25 of the Act is replaced by the following:</Para><ExplNote><Para Align="Yes" TopMargin="10" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><I>Clause 4</I>: Text of section 25:</Para><Para Align="Yes" TopMargin="5" Size="8" Leading="9" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>25.</B> Every federal institution has the duty to ensure that, where services are provided or made available by another person or organization on its behalf, any member of the public in Canada or elsewhere can communicate with and obtain those services from that person or organization in either official language in any case where those services, if provided by the institution, would be required under this Part to be provided in either official language.</Para></ExplNote></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Where services provided on behalf of federal institutions and designated carriers<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>25.</B> Every federal institution <change>and designated carrier</change> has the duty to ensure that, where services are provided or made available by another person or organization on its behalf, any member of the public in Canada or elsewhere can communicate with and obtain those services from that person or organization in either official language in any case where those services, if provided by the institution <change>or carrier</change>, would be required under this Part to be provided in either official language.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>5.</B> Sections 28 to 30 of the Act are replaced by the following:</Para><ExplNote><Para Align="Yes" TopMargin="10" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><I>Clause 5</I>: Text of sections 28 to 30:</Para><Para Align="Yes" TopMargin="5" Size="8" Leading="9" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>28.</B> Every federal institution that is required under this Part to ensure that any member of the public can communicate with and obtain available services from an office or facility of that institution, or of another person or organization on behalf of that institution, in either official language shall ensure that appropriate measures are taken, including the provision of signs, notices and other information on services and the initiation of communication with the public, to make it known to members of the public that those services are available in either official language at the choice of any member of the public.</Para><Para Align="Yes" TopMargin="5" Size="8" Leading="9" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>29.</B> Where a federal institution identifies any of its offices or facilities with signs, each sign shall include both official languages or be placed together with a similar sign of equal prominence in the other official language.</Para><Para Align="Yes" TopMargin="5" Size="8" Leading="9" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>30.</B> Subject to Part II, where a federal institution is engaged in communications with members of the public in both official languages as required in this Part, it shall communicate by using such media of communication as will reach members of the public in the official language of their choice in an effective and efficient manner that is consistent with the purposes of this Act.</Para></ExplNote></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Active offer<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>28.</B> Every federal institution <change>and designated carrier</change> that is required under this Part to ensure that any member of the public can communicate with and obtain available services from an office or facility of that institution <change>or carrier</change>, or of another person or organization on behalf of that institution <change>or carrier</change>, in either official language shall ensure that appropriate measures are taken, including the provision of signs, notices and other information on services and the initiation of communication with the public, to make it known to members of the public that those services are available in either official language at the choice of any member of the public.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Signs identifying offices<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>29.</B> Where a federal institution <change>or designated carrier</change> identifies any of its offices or facilities with signs, each sign shall include both official languages or be placed together with a similar sign of equal prominence in the other official language.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Manner of communicating<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>30.</B> Subject to Part II, where a federal institution <change>or designated carrier</change> is engaged in communications with members of the public in both official languages as required in this Part, it shall communicate by using such media of communication as will reach members of the public in the official language of their choice in an effective and efficient manner that is consistent with the purposes of this Act.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>6.</B> (1) Paragraphs 32(1)(<I>a</I>) and (<I>b</I>) of the Act are replaced by the following:</Para><ExplNote><Para Align="Yes" TopMargin="10" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><I>Clause 6</I>: Relevant portions of section 32:</Para><Para Align="Yes" TopMargin="5" Size="8" Leading="9" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>32.</B> (1) The Governor in Council may make regulations</Para><Para Align="No" TopMargin="5" Size="8" Leading="9" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>a</I>) prescribing the circumstances in which there is significant demand for the purpose of paragraph 22(<I>b</I>) or subsection 23(1);</Para><Para Align="No" TopMargin="5" Size="8" Leading="9" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>b</I>) prescribing circumstances not otherwise provided for under this Part in which federal institutions have the duty to ensure that any member of the public can communicate with and obtain available services from offices of the institution in either official language;</Para><Para Align="No" TopMargin="5" Size="8" Leading="9" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">. . . </Para><Para Align="No" TopMargin="5" Size="8" Leading="9" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>d</I>) prescribing circumstances, in relation to the public or the travelling public, for the purpose of paragraph 24(1)(<I>a</I>) or (<I>b</I>); and</Para><Para Align="No" TopMargin="5" Size="8" Leading="9" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>e</I>) defining the expression “English or French linguistic minority population” for the purpose of paragraph (2)(<I>a</I>).</Para><Para Align="Yes" TopMargin="5" Size="8" Leading="9" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(2) In prescribing circumstances under paragraph (1)(<I>a</I>) or (<I>b</I>), the Governor in Council may have regard to</Para><Para Align="No" TopMargin="5" Size="8" Leading="9" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>a</I>) the number of persons composing the English or French linguistic minority population of the area served by an office or facility, the particular characteristics of that population and the proportion of that population to the total population of that area;</Para><Para Align="No" TopMargin="5" Size="8" Leading="9" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>b</I>) the volume of communications or services between an office or facility and members of the public using each official language; and</Para></ExplNote></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>a</I>) prescribing the circumstances in which there is significant demand for the purpose of <change>paragraph 22(1)(<I>c</I>)</change> or subsection 23(1);</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>b</I>) prescribing circumstances not otherwise provided for under this Part in which federal institutions <change>or designated carriers</change> have the duty to ensure that any member of the public can communicate with and obtain available services from offices of the institution in either official language;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes">(2) Paragraphs 32(1)(<I>d</I>) and (<I>e</I>) of the Act are replaced by the following:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0"><change>(<I>d</I>) designating carriers and their subsidiaries for the purpose of the definition “designated carrier” in subsection 3(1);</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0"><change>(<I>e</I>) prescribing transportation services and related services for the purpose of the definition “designated carrier” in subsection 3(1);</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0"><change>(<I>f</I>) designating railway stations, ferry terminals, public ports, public port facilities and airports for the purpose of paragraph 23(1.1)(<I>d</I>);</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0"><change>(<I>g</I>) establishing the manner in which the consultations referred to in subsection 23.1(2) are to be carried out;</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0"><change>(<I>h</I>) prescribing circumstances, in relation to the public, for the purpose of paragraphs 24(1)(<I>a</I>), (<I>a.1</I>) and (<I>a.2</I>) or (<I>b</I>); and</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0"><change>(<I>i</I>) establishing the manner in which the review referred to in section 32.1 is to be carried out.</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes">(3) The portion of subsection 32(2) before paragraph (<I>a</I>) and paragraphs 32(2)(<I>a</I>) and (<I>b</I>) of the Act are replaced by the following:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Where circumstances prescribed under paragraph 1(<I>a</I>) or (<I>b</I>)<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(2) In prescribing circumstances under paragraph (1)(<I>a</I>) or (<I>b</I>), the Governor in Council <change>shall</change> have regard to</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>a</I>) the number of <change>people who can communicate in the language of</change> the English or French linguistic minority population of the area served by an office or facility;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>b</I>) the particular characteristics<change>, including the institutional vitality,</change> of the English or French linguistic minority population of the area served by an office or facility; and</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>7.</B> The Act is amended by adding the following after section 32:</Para><ExplNote><Para Align="Yes" TopMargin="10" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><I>Clause 7</I>: New.</Para></ExplNote></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Decennial review<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><change><B>32.1</B> (1) In the sixty days following the publication of each decennial census, the President of the Treasury Board, or such other minister of the Crown as may be designated by the Governor in Council, shall undertake a review of regulations made under this Part and shall complete it within one year from the time when the review was undertaken.</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Manner<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><change>(2) The review provided for in subsection (1) shall be carried out in the manner prescribed by regulation of the Governor in Council.</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>8.</B> Section 33 of the Act is replaced by the following:</Para><ExplNote><Para Align="Yes" TopMargin="10" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><I>Clause 8</I>: Text of section 33:</Para><Para Align="Yes" TopMargin="5" Size="8" Leading="9" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>33.</B> The Governor in Council may make any regulations that the Governor in Council deems necessary to foster actively communications with and services from offices or facilities of federal institutions — other than the Senate, House of Commons, Library of Parliament, office of the Senate Ethics Officer or office of the Conflict of Interest and Ethics Commissioner — in both official languages, if those communications and services are required under this Part to be provided in both official languages.</Para></ExplNote></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Regulations<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>33.</B> The Governor in Council may make any regulations that the Governor in Council deems necessary to foster actively communications with and services from offices or facilities of <change>designated carriers and</change> federal institutions — other than the Senate, House of Commons, Library of Parliament, office of the Senate Ethics Officer or office of the Conflict of Interest and Ethics Commissioner — in both official languages, if those communications and services are required under this Part to be provided in both official languages.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>9.</B> The Act is amended by adding the following after section 86:</Para><ExplNote><Para Align="Yes" TopMargin="10" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><I>Clause 9</I>: New.</Para></ExplNote></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Definition of “regulation”<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><change><B>86.1</B> (1) In this section and section 86.2, “regulation” means any regulation that relates to the application of Part IV relating to one of the following areas:</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0"><change>(<I>a</I>) exempting from the application of that Part certain communications or services offered to the public in either official language by a federal institution or designated carrier; and</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0"><change>(<I>b</I>) relieving a federal institution or designated carrier of the duty, under that Part, to communicate with or offer services to the public in either official language.</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Publication of proposed regulation<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><change>(2) The President of the Treasury Board, or such other minister of the Crown as may be designated by the Governor in Council, shall, where the Governor in Council intends to make a regulation, lay a draft of the proposed regulation before each House of Parliament at least thirty days before a copy of the proposed regulation is published in the <I>Canada Gazette</I> under section 86.2.</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Calculation of  thirty day period<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><change>(3) In calculating the thirty day period referred to in subsection (2), there shall not be counted any day on which neither House of Parliament sits.</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Publication of proposed regulation<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><change><B>86.2</B> (1) A proposed regulation shall be published in the <I>Canada Gazette</I> and, wherever possible, be printed in one of the official languages in at least one publication in general circulation within each region where the matter applies that appears wholly or mainly in that language and in the other official language in at least one publication in general circulation within each region where the matter applies that appears wholly or mainly in that other language at least thirty days before the proposed effective date thereof, and a reasonable opportunity shall be afforded to interested persons to make representations to the President of the Treasury Board with respect thereto.</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Exception<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><change>(2) No proposed regulation need be published under subsection (1) if it has previously been published pursuant to that subsection, whether or not it has been amended as a result of representations made pursuant to that subsection.</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Calculation of thirty day period<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><change>(3) In calculating the thirty day period referred to in subsection (1), there shall not be counted any day on which neither House of Parliament sits.</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Coming into force<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>10.</B> This Act comes into force one hundred and eighty days after the day on which it receives royal assent.</Para></Block><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="BPT_ImprintE">Published under authority of the Senate of Canada<br/>Available from:<br/>Publishing and Depository Services<br/>Public Works and Government Services Canada<br/>Ottawa, Ontario K1A 0S5<br/>Telephone: 613-941-5995 or 1-800-635-7943<br/>Fax: 613-954-5779 or 1-800-565-7757<br/>publications@tpsgc-pwgsc.gc.ca<br/>http://publications.gc.ca</Para></Block><Block Align="Yes" LineCnt="N"><Para NoLineBreak="Yes" NoHtml="Yes" Leading="0" Size="0" TopMargin="0" BottomMargin="0"></Para></Block></Bill_Part></Bill>
