<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><Bill bill-origin="commons" bill-type="private-public" xml:lang="en" date-time="2015-05-25 08:27:24"><Identification><BillNumber>C-216</BillNumber><Parliament><Session>1</Session><Number>42</Number><RegnalYear><Year-s>64</Year-s><Monarch>Elizabeth II</Monarch></RegnalYear><Year-s>2015-2016</Year-s></Parliament><LongTitle>An Act to establish National Perinatal Bereavement Awareness Day</LongTitle><ShortTitle status="unofficial" /><RunningHead>An Act to establish National Perinatal Bereavement Awareness Day</RunningHead><BillHistory><Stages stage="first-reading-house"><Date><YYYY>2016</YYYY><MM>2</MM><DD>3</DD></Date></Stages></BillHistory><BillSponsor><Emphasis style="smallcaps">Ms. Moore</Emphasis></BillSponsor><BillRefNumber date-time="2015-05-25">421008</BillRefNumber></Identification><Introduction><Summary><TitleText>SUMMARY</TitleText><Provision><Text>This enactment designates October 15 in each and every year as “National Perinatal Bereavement Awareness Day”.</Text></Provision></Summary><Preamble><Provision><MarginalNote>Preamble</MarginalNote><Text>Whereas each year in Canada, thousands of families are affected by perinatal bereavement;</Text></Provision><Provision><Text>Whereas perinatal death, considered one of the most stressful events that can occur in life, has a significant impact on the parents’ psychological and physical health and can even lead to the breakup of their relationship;</Text></Provision><Provision><Text>Whereas those close to the bereaved parents often do not know what to say or do and feel powerless in the face of the parents’ distress, which can contribute to the latter’s isolation;</Text></Provision><Provision><Text>Whereas it is important that the Parliament of Canada make the Canadian public aware of perinatal bereavement in order to help those affected by it;</Text></Provision><Provision language-align="yes"><Text>Now, therefore, Her Majesty, by and with the advice and consent of the Senate and House of Commons of Canada, enacts as follows:</Text></Provision></Preamble></Introduction><Body><Heading level="1"><TitleText>Short Title</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Short title</MarginalNote><Label>1</Label><Text>This Act may be cited as the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">National Perinatal Bereavement Awareness Day Act</XRefExternal>.</Text></Section><Heading level="1"><TitleText>National Perinatal Bereavement Awareness Day</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>National Perinatal Bereavement Awareness Day</MarginalNote><Label>2</Label><Text>Throughout Canada, in each and every year, October 15 is to be known as “National Perinatal Bereavement Awareness Day.”</Text></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Not a legal holiday</MarginalNote><Label>3</Label><Text>For greater certainty, National Perinatal Bereavement Awareness Day is not a legal holiday or a non-juridical day.</Text></Section></Body></Bill>