<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><Bill bill-origin="commons" bill-type="private-public" xml:lang="en" date-time="2014-11-05 13:13:39"><Identification><BillNumber>C-219</BillNumber><Parliament><Session>1</Session><Number>42</Number><RegnalYear><Year-s>64</Year-s><Monarch>Elizabeth II</Monarch></RegnalYear><Year-s>2015-2016</Year-s></Parliament><LongTitle>An Act to amend the Canada Shipping Act, 2001 (wreck)</LongTitle><ShortTitle status="unofficial" /><RunningHead>An Act to amend the Canada Shipping Act, 2001 (wreck)</RunningHead><BillHistory><Stages stage="first-reading-house"><Date><YYYY>2016</YYYY><MM>2</MM><DD>4</DD></Date></Stages></BillHistory><BillSponsor><Emphasis style="smallcaps">Ms. Malcolmson</Emphasis></BillSponsor><BillRefNumber date-time="2014-11-05">421102</BillRefNumber></Identification><Introduction><Summary><TitleText>SUMMARY</TitleText><Provision first-line-indent="0" subsequent-line-indent="0"><Text>This enactment amends the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Canada Shipping Act, 2001</XRefExternal> to strengthen the requirements relating to wreck by ensuring that regulations are made to establish measures to be taken for their removal, disposition or destruction. It designates the Canadian Coast Guard as a receiver of wreck for the purposes of Part 7 of the Act and requires receivers of wreck to take reasonable steps to determine and locate the owner of the wreck.</Text></Provision></Summary><Enacts><Provision first-line-indent="0" subsequent-line-indent="0"><MarginalNote><HistoricalNote>2001, c. 26</HistoricalNote></MarginalNote><Text>Her Majesty, by and with the advice and consent of the Senate and House of Commons of Canada, <Keep>enacts</Keep> as follows:</Text></Provision></Enacts></Introduction><Body><Section type="amending"><Label>1</Label><Text>Subsection 154(1) of the <Emphasis style="italic">Canada Shipping Act, 2001</Emphasis> is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><Section change="ins"><MarginalNote>Canadian Coast Guard designated</MarginalNote><Label>154</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The Canadian Coast Guard is designated as a receiver of wreck for the purposes of this Part.</Text></Subsection><Subsection change="off"><MarginalNote>Designation</MarginalNote><Label>(1.1)</Label><Text>The Minister may designate <Ins>any other</Ins> persons or classes of persons as receivers of wreck.</Text></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>2</Label><Text>Subsections 155(2) and (3) of the Act are replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><Subsection><MarginalNote>Locating owner</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>If wreck has been reported <Ins>to or observed by a receiver of wreck, the</Ins> receiver <Ins>shall</Ins> take reasonable <Ins>steps</Ins> to determine and <Ins>locate</Ins> the owner of the wreck, including <Ins>by</Ins> giving notice of the wreck in the manner that the receiver considers <Ins>most effective and</Ins> appropriate.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Taking measures</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text><Ins>Except in the circumstances described in regulations made under subsection 163(1.1),</Ins> a receiver of wreck <Ins>shall</Ins> take measures, or direct that measures be taken, <Ins>in accordance with those regulations in order to remove, dispose of or destroy wreck</Ins>.</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>3</Label><Text>Section 163 of the Act is amended by adding the following after subsection (1):</Text><AmendedText><Subsection change="ins"><MarginalNote>Regulations — Minister and Minister of Fisheries and Oceans
</MarginalNote><Label>(1.1)</Label><Text>The Governor in Council may, on the recommendation of the Minister and the Minister of Fisheries and Oceans, make regulations respecting</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>the appropriate measures that receivers of wreck are to take, or direct to be taken, to remove, dispose of or destroy wreck; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>the circumstances in which the obligation to take measures under subsection 155(3) does not apply.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>4</Label><Text>The Act is amended by adding the following after section 164:</Text><AmendedText><Heading level="2" change="ins"><TitleText>Report to Parliament</TitleText></Heading><Section change="ins"><MarginalNote>Review and report by Minister</MarginalNote><Label>164.1</Label><Text>Every five years, the Minister must review the operation of this Part and cause to be laid before each House of Parliament a report setting out the results of the review.</Text></Section></AmendedText></Section></Body></Bill>