<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><Bill bill-origin="commons" bill-type="private-public" xml:lang="en" date-time="2016-02-11 15:33:56"><Identification><BillNumber>C-227</BillNumber><Parliament><Session>1</Session><Number>42</Number><RegnalYear><Year-s>64-65</Year-s><Monarch>Elizabeth II</Monarch></RegnalYear><Year-s>2015-2016</Year-s></Parliament><LongTitle>An Act to amend the Department of Public Works and Government Services Act (community benefit)</LongTitle><ShortTitle status="unofficial" /><RunningHead>An Act to amend the Department of Public Works and Government Services Act (community benefit)</RunningHead><BillHistory><Stages stage="report-house"><Date><YYYY>2016</YYYY><MM>12</MM><DD>5</DD></Date><StageText>Reprinted as amended by the Standing Committee on Transport, Infrastructure and Communities as a working copy for the use of the House of Commons at Report Stage and as reported to the House on December 5, 2016</StageText></Stages></BillHistory><BillSponsor><Emphasis style="smallcaps">Mr. Hussen</Emphasis></BillSponsor><BillRefNumber date-time="2016-02-11">421153</BillRefNumber></Identification><Introduction><Summary><TitleText>SUMMARY</TitleText><Provision><Text>This enactment amends the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Department of Public Works and Government Services Act</XRefExternal> to provide the Minister with the authority to require an assessment of the benefits that a community derives from a construction, maintenance or repair project.</Text></Provision></Summary><Enacts><Provision><MarginalNote><HistoricalNote>1996, c. 16</HistoricalNote></MarginalNote><Text>Her Majesty, by and with the advice and consent <Keep>of the</Keep> Senate and House of Commons of Canada, <Keep>enacts</Keep> as follows:</Text></Provision></Enacts></Introduction><Body><Section type="amending"><Label>1</Label><Text>The <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Department of Public Works and Government Services Act</XRefExternal> is amended by adding the following after section 20:</Text><AmendedText><Section><MarginalNote>Definition of <DefinedTermEn>community benefit</DefinedTermEn></MarginalNote><Label>20.1</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>For the purpose of this section, <DefinedTermEn><Emphasis style="bold">community benefit</Emphasis></DefinedTermEn> means a social<Ins>,</Ins> economic or <Ins>environmental</Ins> benefit that a community derives from a construction, maintenance or repair project, and includes local job creation and training opportunities, improvement of public space within the community and any other specific benefit identified by the community.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Community benefit — requirement</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The Minister may, before awarding a contract for the construction, maintenance or repair of public works, federal real property or federal immovables, require bidders on the proposal to provide information on the community benefits that the project will provide.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Report to Minister</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>A contracting party shall, upon request by the Minister, provide the Minister with an assessment as to whether the project has provided community benefits.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Report to Parliament</MarginalNote><Label>(4)</Label><Text>The Minister shall cause to be tabled before each House of Parliament, within <Ins>90</Ins> days after the end of each fiscal  year  or,  if  Parliament  is not then sitting, on any of<PageBreak />the first <Ins>90</Ins> days next thereafter that Parliament is sitting, a report <Ins>on</Ins> community benefits provided <Ins>by</Ins> construction, maintenance or repair projects.</Text></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Section></Body></Bill>