<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><Bill bill-origin="commons" bill-type="private-public" xml:lang="en" date-time="2016-02-17 10:26:21"><Identification><BillNumber>C-231</BillNumber><Parliament><Session>1</Session><Number>42</Number><RegnalYear><Year-s>64-65</Year-s><Monarch>Elizabeth II</Monarch></RegnalYear><Year-s>2015-2016</Year-s></Parliament><LongTitle>An Act to establish National Food Waste Awareness Day and to provide for the development of a national strategy to reduce food waste in Canada</LongTitle><ShortTitle status="unofficial" /><RunningHead>An Act to establish National Food Waste Awareness Day and to provide for the development of a national strategy to reduce ...</RunningHead><BillHistory><Stages stage="first-reading-house"><Date><YYYY>2016</YYYY><MM>2</MM><DD>24</DD></Date></Stages></BillHistory><BillSponsor><Emphasis style="smallcaps">Ms. Brosseau</Emphasis></BillSponsor><BillRefNumber date-time="2016-02-17">421158</BillRefNumber></Identification><Introduction><Summary><TitleText>SUMMARY</TitleText><Provision first-line-indent="0" subsequent-line-indent="0"><Text>This enactment designates the 16th day of October in each and every year as “National Food Waste Awareness Day” and provides for the development and implementation of a national strategy to reduce food waste in Canada. </Text></Provision></Summary><Preamble><Provision first-line-indent="0" subsequent-line-indent="0"><MarginalNote>Preamble</MarginalNote><Text>Whereas food waste is a scourge in Canada, which caused some $107 billion in economic losses in 2014;</Text></Provision><Provision first-line-indent="0" subsequent-line-indent="0"><Text>Whereas Canadians annually confine some $31 billion in food to the landfill or compost heap;</Text></Provision><Provision first-line-indent="0" subsequent-line-indent="0"><Text>Whereas over 6.3 million tonnes of foodstuffs are wasted in Canada each year, which represents 183 kg per inhabitant;</Text></Provision><Provision first-line-indent="0" subsequent-line-indent="0"><Text>Whereas food waste occurs primarily among manufacturers of processed foods, retailers and consumers; </Text></Provision><Provision first-line-indent="0" subsequent-line-indent="0"><Text>And whereas over 850,000 Canadians, 36% of them young people and children, visited food banks each month in 2015;</Text></Provision></Preamble><Enacts><Provision first-line-indent="0" subsequent-line-indent="0"><Text>Now, therefore, Her Majesty, by and with the advice and consent of the Senate and House of Commons of Canada, enacts as follows:</Text></Provision></Enacts></Introduction><Body><Heading level="1"><TitleText>Short Title</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Short title</MarginalNote><Label>1</Label><Text>This Act may be cited as the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Fight Against Food Waste Act</XRefExternal>.</Text></Section><Heading level="1"><TitleText>National Day</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>National Food Waste Awareness Day</MarginalNote><Label>2</Label><Text>Throughout Canada, in each and every year, the 16th day of October is to be known as “National Food Waste Awareness Day”.</Text></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Not a legal holiday</MarginalNote><Label>3</Label><Text>For greater certainty, National Food Waste Awareness Day is not a legal holiday or a non-juridical day.</Text></Section><Heading level="1"><TitleText>National Strategy</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Development and implementation</MarginalNote><Label>4</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The Minister of Agriculture and Agri-Food, in consultation with representatives of the provincial and territorial governments responsible for agriculture and agri-food and stakeholders in the agriculture and agri-food industry, must develop and implement a national strategy to reduce food waste in Canada that includes measures to</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>raise public awareness of food waste through a national campaign;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>put in place the tools needed to allow consumers to reduce food waste;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(c)</Label><Text>facilitate the donation, by the private sector, of blemished but edible food products to community organizations and food banks;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(d)</Label><Text>study various ways of reducing the environmental impact of the production of unused food resources; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(e)</Label><Text>establish food waste reduction targets.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Conference</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Within six months after the day on which this Act comes into force, the Minister must convene a conference with representatives of the provincial and territorial governments responsible for agriculture and agri-food and stakeholders from the agriculture and agri-food industries in order to develop the national strategy.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Report to Parliament</MarginalNote><Label>5</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The Minister of Agriculture and Agri-Food must prepare a report setting out the national strategy and cause the report to be laid before each House of Parliament in the year following the day on which this Act comes into force.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Publication of report</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The Minister must post the report on the departmental website within 10 days after the day on which the report is tabled in Parliament.</Text></Subsection></Section><Heading level="1"><TitleText>Review and Report</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Review and report</MarginalNote><Label>6</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Within five years of the tabling of the report referred to in section 5, and every five years after that, the Minister of Agriculture and Agri-Food must prepare a report on the effectiveness of the national strategy, setting out his or her conclusions and recommendations regarding the strategy, and cause the report to be laid before each House of Parliament on any of the first 15 days on which that House is sitting after the report is completed.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Publication of report</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The Minister must post the report on the departmental website within 10 days after the day on which the report is tabled in Parliament.</Text></Subsection></Section></Body></Bill>