<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><Bill bill-origin="commons" bill-type="private-public" xml:lang="en" date-time="2016-02-18 13:29:45"><Identification><BillNumber>C-247</BillNumber><Parliament><Session>1</Session><Number>42</Number><RegnalYear><Year-s>64-65</Year-s><Monarch>Elizabeth II</Monarch></RegnalYear><Year-s>2015-2016</Year-s></Parliament><LongTitle>An Act to amend the Criminal Code (passive detection device)</LongTitle><ShortTitle status="unofficial" /><RunningHead>An Act to amend the Criminal Code (passive detection device)</RunningHead><BillHistory><Stages stage="first-reading-house"><Date><YYYY>2016</YYYY><MM>2</MM><DD>26</DD></Date></Stages></BillHistory><BillSponsor><Emphasis style="smallcaps">Mr. Sikand</Emphasis></BillSponsor><BillRefNumber date-time="2016-02-18">421150</BillRefNumber></Identification><Introduction><Summary><TitleText>SUMMARY</TitleText><Provision><Text>This enactment amends the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Criminal Code</XRefExternal> to authorize the use by a peace officer of a passive detection device to detect the presence of alcohol in the immediate vicinity of a person whom the officer has reasonable grounds to believe was, within the preceeding three hours, operating a motor vehicle or having the care or control of a motor vehicle.  The enactment also provides that if such a device indicates the presence of alcohol, it establishes reasonable grounds to suspect that the person has alcohol in their body.</Text></Provision></Summary><Enacts><Provision><MarginalNote><HistoricalNote>R.S., c. C-46</HistoricalNote></MarginalNote><Text>Her Majesty, by and with the advice and consent <Keep>of the</Keep> Senate and House of Commons of Canada, <Keep>enacts</Keep> as follows:</Text></Provision></Enacts></Introduction><Body><Section type="amending"><Label>1</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Subsection 254(1) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Criminal Code</XRefExternal> is amended by adding the following in alphabetical order:</Text><AmendedText><SectionPiece><Definition change="ins"><Text><DefinedTermEn>approved passive detection device</DefinedTermEn> means a device of a kind that is designed to detect the presence of alcohol in the ambient air and that is approved for the purposes of this section by order of the Attorney General of Canada. (<DefinedTermFr><Emphasis style="regular">détecteur passif approuvé</Emphasis></DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Definition></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Section 254 of the Act is amended by adding the following after subsection (1):</Text><AmendedText><Subsection change="ins"><MarginalNote>Passive detection device</MarginalNote><Label>(1.1)</Label><Text>A peace officer may use an approved passive detection device to collect a sample of ambient air from the immediate vicinity of a person whom the officer has reasonable grounds to believe was, within the preceeding three hours, operating a motor vehicle or having the care or control of a motor vehicle, whether it was in motion or not. </Text></Subsection><Subsection change="ins"><MarginalNote>Presence of alcohol</MarginalNote><Label>(1.2)</Label><Text>If an approved passive detection device indicates the presence of alcohol in a sample collected by a peace officer, it establishes reasonable grounds to suspect that the person has alcohol in their body.</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Subsection></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>2</Label><Text>Subsection 254.1(1) of the Act is amended by striking out “and” at the end of paragraph (b), by adding “and’’ at the end of paragraph (c) and by adding the following after paragraph (c):</Text><AmendedText><SectionPiece><Paragraph change="ins"><Label>(d)</Label><Text>prescribing any matter related to the approval, use or maintenance of approved passive detection devices.</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>3</Label><Text>Subsections 255(3) and (3.1) of the Act are replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><Subsection><MarginalNote>Impaired driving causing death</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>Everyone who commits an offence under paragraph 253(1)(a) and causes the death of another person as a result is guilty of <Ins>the</Ins> indictable offence <Ins>of vehicular homicide as a result of impairment</Ins> and is liable to imprisonment for life.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Blood alcohol level over legal limit — death</MarginalNote><Label>(3.1)</Label><Text>Everyone who, while committing an offence under paragraph 253(1)(b), causes an accident resulting in the death of another person is guilty of <Ins>the</Ins> indictable offence of  <Ins>vehicular homicide as a result of impairment</Ins> and liable to imprisonment for life. </Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Section></Body></Bill>