<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>


<Bill bill-origin="commons" bill-type="private-public" xml:lang="en" date-time="2008-04-09 11:37:58"><Identification><BillNumber>C-244</BillNumber><Parliament><Session>1</Session><Number>42</Number><RegnalYear><Year-s>64-65</Year-s><Monarch>Elizabeth II</Monarch></RegnalYear><Year-s>2015-2016</Year-s></Parliament><LongTitle>An Act to establish Leif Erikson Day</LongTitle><ShortTitle status="unofficial" /><RunningHead>Leif Erikson Day Act</RunningHead><BillHistory><Stages stage="first-reading-house"><Date><YYYY>2016</YYYY><MM>2</MM><DD>26</DD></Date></Stages></BillHistory><BillSponsor><Emphasis style="smallcaps">Mr. Julian</Emphasis></BillSponsor><BillRefNumber date-time="2008-04-09">421065</BillRefNumber></Identification><Introduction><Summary><TitleText>SUMMARY</TitleText><Provision first-line-indent="0" subsequent-line-indent="0"><Text>This enactment designates the ninth day of October in each and every year as “Leif Erikson Day”.</Text></Provision></Summary><Enacts><Provision first-line-indent="0" subsequent-line-indent="0" language-align="yes"><MarginalNote>Preamble</MarginalNote><Text>Whereas Leif Erikson is believed to have been the first European to land in North America, around the year 1000, making him the forerunner of the well-known European explorers that followed and, therefore, the first to  open the European exploration of North America;</Text><Provision first-line-indent="0" subsequent-line-indent="0"><Text>Whereas there is historical and archaeological evidence to suggest that Leif Erikson established the oldest known Norse settlement in North America, in what is today L’Anse aux Meadows National Historic Site of Canada in the province of Newfoundland and Labrador;</Text><Provision first-line-indent="0" subsequent-line-indent="0"><Text>Whereas the people of Canada wish to honour and recognize the significant historical voyage of Leif Erikson, which included landing on the North American continent;</Text><Provision first-line-indent="0" subsequent-line-indent="0"><Text>And whereas the people of Canada also wish to honour the valuable contributions of the Scandinavian peoples of Norway, Sweden, Denmark, Finland and Iceland to Canada;</Text><Provision first-line-indent="0" subsequent-line-indent="0" language-align="yes"><Text>Now, therefore, Her Majesty, by and with the advice and consent of the Senate and House of Commons of Canada, enacts as follows:</Text></Provision></Provision></Provision></Provision></Provision></Enacts></Introduction><Body><Heading level="1"><TitleText>Short Title</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Short title</MarginalNote><Label>1</Label><Text>This Act may be cited as the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Leif Erikson Day Act</XRefExternal>.</Text></Section><Heading level="1"><TitleText>Leif Erikson Day</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Leif Erikson Day</MarginalNote><Label>2</Label><Text>Throughout Canada, in each and every year, the ninth day of October is to be known as “Leif Erikson Day”.</Text></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Not a legal holiday</MarginalNote><Label>3</Label><Text>For greater certainty, Leif Erikson Day is not a legal holiday or a non-juridical day.</Text></Section></Body></Bill>