<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>


<Bill bill-origin="commons" bill-type="private-public" xml:lang="en" date-time="2010-06-18 08:45:13"><Identification><BillNumber>C-255</BillNumber><Parliament><Session>1</Session><Number>42</Number><RegnalYear><Year-s>64-65</Year-s><Monarch>Elizabeth II</Monarch></RegnalYear><Year-s>2015-2016</Year-s></Parliament><LongTitle>An Act to amend the Immigration and Refugee Protection Act (appeal process for <Keep>temporary</Keep> resident visa applicants)</LongTitle><ShortTitle status="unofficial" /><RunningHead>An Act to amend the Immigration and Refugee Protection Act (appeal process for <Keep>temporary</Keep> resident visa applicants)</RunningHead><BillHistory><Stages stage="first-reading-house"><Date><YYYY>2016</YYYY><MM>3</MM><DD>24</DD></Date></Stages></BillHistory><BillSponsor><Emphasis style="smallcaps">Mr. Davies</Emphasis></BillSponsor><BillRefNumber date-time="2010-06-18">421024</BillRefNumber></Identification><Introduction><Summary><TitleText>SUMMARY</TitleText><Provision first-line-indent="0" subsequent-line-indent="0"><Text>This enactment establishes an appeal process for foreign nationals who apply for temporary resident visas under the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Immigration and Refugee Protection Act</XRefExternal>. It extends the jurisdiction of the Immigration Appeal Division of the Immigration and Refugee Board for that purpose, by expanding its mandate to include appeals from foreign nationals who have been refused a temporary resident visa or an extension of an authorization to remain in Canada.</Text></Provision></Summary><Enacts><Provision first-line-indent="0" subsequent-line-indent="0"><Text>Her Majesty, by and with the advice and consent of the Senate and House of Commons of Canada, <Keep>enacts</Keep> as follows:</Text></Provision></Enacts></Introduction><Body><Heading level="1" type="amending"><MarginalNote><HistoricalNote>2001, c. 27</HistoricalNote></MarginalNote><TitleText>Immigration and Refugee Protection Act</TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><Label>1</Label><Text>Section 63 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Immigration and Refugee Protection Act</XRefExternal> is amended by adding the following after subsection (1):</Text><AmendedText><Subsection change="ins"><MarginalNote>Right to appeal — temporary resident visa</MarginalNote><Label>(1.1)</Label><Text>A foreign national who has made in the prescribed manner an application for a tempo­rary resident visa or for an extension of an authorization to remain in Canada as a tempo­rary resident may appeal to the Immigration Appeal Division against a decision not to issue the foreign national a temporary resident visa or not to extend an authorization.</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>2</Label><Text>Subsection  64(1) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><Section><MarginalNote>No appeal for
inadmissibility
</MarginalNote><Label>64</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>No appeal may be made to the Immigration Appeal Division by a foreign national or their sponsor<Ins>,</Ins> by a permanent resident or <Ins>by a temporary resident</Ins> if the foreign national<Ins>,</Ins> permanent resident <Ins>or temporary resident</Ins> has been found to be inadmissible on grounds of security, violating human or international rights, serious criminality or organized criminality.
</Text></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>3</Label><Text>Subsection 69(2) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><Subsection><MarginalNote>Minister’s appeal </MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>In the case of an appeal by the Minister respecting a permanent resident<Ins>, a temporary resident</Ins> or a protected person, other than a person referred to in subsection 64(1), if the Immigration Appeal Division is satisfied that, taking into account the best interests of a child directly affected by the decision, sufficient humanitarian and compassionate considerations warrant special relief in light of all the circumstances of the case, it may make and may stay the applicable removal order, or dismiss the appeal, despite being satisfied of a matter set out in paragraph 67(1)(a) or (b).</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Section><Heading level="1" type="amending"><TitleText>Coming Into Force</TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote>Coming into force</MarginalNote><Label>4</Label><Text>This Act comes into force 30 days after the day on which it receives royal assent.</Text></Section></Body></Bill>