<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><Bill bill-origin="commons" bill-type="private-public" xml:lang="en" date-time="2013-10-01 09:43:07"><Identification><BillNumber>C-259</BillNumber><Parliament><Session>1</Session><Number>42</Number><RegnalYear><Year-s>64-65</Year-s><Monarch>Elizabeth II</Monarch></RegnalYear><Year-s>2015-2016</Year-s></Parliament><LongTitle>An Act to amend the Access to Information Act (scientific research)</LongTitle><ShortTitle status="unofficial" /><RunningHead>An Act to amend the Access to Information Act (scientific research)</RunningHead><BillHistory><Stages stage="first-reading-house"><Date><YYYY>2016</YYYY><MM>4</MM><DD>14</DD></Date></Stages></BillHistory><BillSponsor><Emphasis style="smallcaps">Ms. May</Emphasis></BillSponsor><BillRefNumber date-time="2013-10-01">421011</BillRefNumber></Identification><Introduction><Summary><TitleText>SUMMARY</TitleText><Provision first-line-indent="0" subsequent-line-indent="0"><Text>This enactment amends the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Access to Information Act</XRefExternal> to require each government institution to post on its website, or make accessible through it, all records composed in whole or in part of scientific research as soon as practicable following the conclusion of the research.</Text></Provision></Summary><Preamble><Provision subsequent-line-indent="0" first-line-indent="0"><MarginalNote>Preamble</MarginalNote><Text>Whereas the free pursuit of scientific knowledge is ГўВЂВ‰a central pillar of a healthy democracy and a prosperous 21st-century society;</Text></Provision><Provision subsequent-line-indent="0" first-line-indent="0"><Text>Whereas the dissemination of scientific researchГўВЂВ‰ГўВЂВ”ГўВЂВ‰a fundamental public goodГўВЂВ‰ГўВЂВ”ГўВЂВ‰is critical both for popular education and the furthering of knowledge;</Text></Provision><Provision subsequent-line-indent="0" first-line-indent="0"><Text>Whereas there is no legitimate reason that research conducted by scientists of the Government of Canada should be withheld from the Canadian public;</Text></Provision><Provision subsequent-line-indent="0" first-line-indent="0"><Text>Whereas the government of the day should not be allowed to dictate, based on partisan political considerations, which publicly funded science belongs in the public domain and which should be withheld; </Text></Provision><Provision subsequent-line-indent="0" first-line-indent="0"><Text>And whereas the proactive, transparent and timely disclosure of  research findings produced by Government of Canada scientists is best ensured through the enactment of a legal obligation; </Text></Provision><Provision first-line-indent="0" language-align="yes" subsequent-line-indent="0"><Text>Now, therefore, Her Majesty, by and with the advice and consent <Keep>of the</Keep> Senate and House of Commons of Canada, <Keep>enacts</Keep> as follows: </Text></Provision></Preamble></Introduction><Body><Heading level="1"><TitleText>Short Title</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Short title</MarginalNote><Label>1</Label><Text>This Act may be cited as the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Open Science Act</XRefExternal>.</Text></Section><Heading level="1" type="amending"><MarginalNote><HistoricalNote>R.S., c. A-1</HistoricalNote></MarginalNote><TitleText>Access to Information Act</TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><Label>2</Label><Text>The <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Access to Information Act</XRefExternal> is amended by adding the following after section 5:</Text><AmendedText><Section change="ins"><MarginalNote>Access to scientific research</MarginalNote><Label>5.1</Label><Text>Subject to this Act, each government institution shall cause all records composed in whole or in part of scientific research, including any paper, report or analysis prepared by, or in collaboration with, the government institution, to be posted on its website, or made accessible through it, as soon as practicable following the conclusion of the research.</Text></Section></AmendedText></Section></Body></Bill>