<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><Bill bill-origin="commons" bill-type="private-public" xml:lang="en" date-time="2014-10-08 12:06:02"><Identification><BillNumber>C-253</BillNumber><Parliament><Session>1</Session><Number>42</Number><RegnalYear><Year-s>64-65</Year-s><Monarch>Elizabeth II</Monarch></RegnalYear><Year-s>2015-2016</Year-s></Parliament><LongTitle>An Act to Recognize Charlottetown as the Birthplace of Confederation</LongTitle><ShortTitle status="unofficial" /><RunningHead>Recognition of Charlottetown as the Birthplace of Confederation Act</RunningHead><BillHistory><Stages stage="first-reading-house"><Date><YYYY>2016</YYYY><MM>3</MM><DD>24</DD></Date></Stages></BillHistory><BillSponsor><Emphasis style="smallcaps">Mr. Easter</Emphasis></BillSponsor><BillRefNumber date-time="2014-10-08">421194</BillRefNumber></Identification><Introduction><Summary><TitleText>SUMMARY</TitleText><Provision><Text>This enactment recognizes Charlottetown as the birthplace of Confederation.</Text></Provision></Summary><Preamble><Provision><MarginalNote>Preamble</MarginalNote><Text>Whereas on September 1, 1864, leaders of the governments and legislatures of Prince Edward Island, Nova Scotia, New Brunswick and the Province of Canada met in Charlottetown, Prince Edward Island, and created a shared vision of a union of the British North American colonies and the creation of a new country;</Text></Provision><Provision><Text>Whereas the ambitions and ideals that flourished at, and grew out of, the Charlottetown Conference are the basis of the nation of Canada;</Text></Provision><Provision><Text>Whereas the rich heritage of Charlottetown is reflec-<Keep>ted in</Keep> the recognition of Province House, where the discussions took place, as a national historic site and the recognition of other national historic sites in Charlottetown in view of their strong associations with the birth of this country;</Text></Provision><Provision><Text>Whereas, by Proclamation of the Prime Minister of Canada, on September 1, 1996, the role of Charlottetown was recognized and affirmed as the birthplace of Confederation and an integral part of our Canadian heritage;</Text></Provision><Provision><Text>And whereas September 1, 2014, marked the 150th anniversary of the Charlottetown Conference and the birth of Confederation;</Text></Provision><Provision language-align="yes"><Text>Now, therefore, Her Majesty, by and with the advice and consent of the Senate and House of Commons of Canada, enacts as follows:</Text></Provision></Preamble></Introduction><Body><Section><MarginalNote>Short title</MarginalNote><Label>1</Label><Text>This Act may be cited as the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Recognition of Charlottetown as the Birthplace of Confederation Act</XRefExternal>. </Text></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Birthplace of Confederation</MarginalNote><Label>2</Label><Text>Charlottetown, Prince Edward Island, is recognized as and declared to be the birthplace of Confederation.</Text></Section></Body></Bill>