<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>


<Bill bill-origin="commons" bill-type="private-public" xml:lang="en" date-time="2010-04-13 16:52:28"><Identification><BillNumber>C-256</BillNumber><Parliament><Session>1</Session><Number>42</Number><RegnalYear><Year-s>64-65</Year-s><Monarch>Elizabeth II</Monarch></RegnalYear><Year-s>2015-2016</Year-s></Parliament><LongTitle>An Act to amend the Income Tax Act (tax credit for dues paid to veterans’ organizations)</LongTitle><ShortTitle status="unofficial" /><RunningHead>An Act to amend the Income Tax Act (tax credit for dues paid to veterans’ organizations)</RunningHead><BillHistory><Stages stage="first-reading-house"><Date><YYYY>2016</YYYY><MM>3</MM><DD>24</DD></Date></Stages></BillHistory><BillSponsor><Emphasis style="smallcaps">Mr. Davies</Emphasis></BillSponsor><BillRefNumber date-time="2010-04-13">421027</BillRefNumber></Identification><Introduction><Summary><TitleText>SUMMARY</TitleText><Provision first-line-indent="0" subsequent-line-indent="0"><Text>This enactment amends the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Income Tax Act</XRefExternal> to provide a refundable tax credit to an individual in respect of membership dues paid to a branch of the Royal Canadian Legion or Army, Navy and Air Force Veterans in Canada Association or to a prescribed veterans’ organization.</Text></Provision></Summary><Enacts><Provision first-line-indent="0" subsequent-line-indent="0"><MarginalNote><HistoricalNote>R.S., c. 1 (5th Supp.)</HistoricalNote></MarginalNote><Text>Her Majesty, by and with the advice and consent of the Senate and the House of Commons of Canada, <Keep>enacts</Keep> as follows:</Text></Provision></Enacts></Introduction><Body><Section type="amending"><Label>1</Label><Text>The <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Income Tax Act</XRefExternal> is amended by adding the following after section 122.51:</Text></Section><Section change="ins"><MarginalNote>Deemed payment on account of tax — membership dues</MarginalNote><Label>122.52</Label><Text>Where a return of income is filed in respect of an eligible individual described in section 122.51 for a particular taxation year that ends at the end of a calendar year, there is deemed to be paid at the end of the particular year on account of the individual’s tax payable under this Part for the particular year an amount equal to the amount that the individual paid during the year as membership dues to a branch of the Royal Canadian Legion or Army, Navy and Air Force Veterans in Canada Association or to a prescribed veterans’ organization.</Text></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>2</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Paragraph 152(1)(b) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>the amount of tax, if any, deemed by subsection 120(2) or (2.2), 122.5(3) <Ins>or</Ins> 122.51(2), <Ins>section 122.52 or subsection</Ins> 122.7(2) or (3), 125.4(3), 125.5(3), 127.1(1), 127.41(3) or 210.2(3) or (4) to be paid on account of the taxpayer’s tax payable under this Part for the year.</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Paragraph 152(4.2)(b) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>redetermine the amount, if any, deemed by subsection 120(2) or (2.2), 122.5(3) <Ins>or</Ins> 122.51(2), <Ins>section 122.52 or subsection</Ins> 122.7(2) or (3), 122.8(2) or (3), 127.1(1), 127.41(3) or 210.2(3) or (4) to be paid on account of the taxpayer’s tax payable under this Part for the year or deemed by subsection 122.61(1) to be an overpayment on account of the taxpayer’s liability under this Part for the year.</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection></Section></Body></Bill>