<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>


<Bill bill-origin="commons" bill-type="private-public" xml:lang="en" date-time="2006-10-13 10:55:38"><Identification><BillNumber>C-261</BillNumber><Parliament><Session>1</Session><Number>42</Number><RegnalYear><Year-s>64-65</Year-s><Monarch>Elizabeth II</Monarch></RegnalYear><Year-s>2015-2016</Year-s></Parliament><LongTitle>An Act to amend the Canadian Forces Super-<Keep>annuation</Keep> Act and the Royal Canadian Mounted Police Superannuation Act  (increase of allowance for survivors and children)</LongTitle><ShortTitle status="unofficial" /><RunningHead> An Act to amend the Canadian Forces Superannuation Act and the Royal Canadian Mounted Police Superannuation Act  ...</RunningHead><BillHistory><Stages stage="first-reading-house"><Date><YYYY>2016</YYYY><MM>4</MM><DD>14</DD></Date></Stages></BillHistory><BillSponsor><Emphasis style="smallcaps">Ms. Mathyssen</Emphasis></BillSponsor><BillRefNumber date-time="2006-10-13">421128</BillRefNumber></Identification><Introduction><Summary><TitleText>SUMMARY</TitleText><Provision first-line-indent="0" subsequent-line-indent="0"><Text>The purpose of this enactment is to increase the allowance given to the  survivors and children of Canadian Forces or Royal Canadian Mounted Police contributors from 50% to 70% of the contributor’s annuity or allowance.</Text></Provision></Summary><Enacts><Provision first-line-indent="0" subsequent-line-indent="0"><Text>Her Majesty, by and with the advice and consent <Keep>of the</Keep> Senate and House of Commons of Canada, <Keep>enacts</Keep> as follows:</Text></Provision></Enacts></Introduction><Body><Heading level="1" type="amending"><MarginalNote><HistoricalNote>R.S., c. C-17</HistoricalNote></MarginalNote><TitleText>Canadian Forces Superannuation Act</TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><Label>1</Label><Text>The portion of subsection 25(1) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Canadian Forces Superannuation Act</XRefExternal> before paragraph (a) is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><Section><MarginalNote>Benefits payable on death of retired member</MarginalNote><Label>25</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>On the death of a contributor who, at the time of <Ins>the contributor’s</Ins> death, was entitled under this Part to an annuity or an annual allowance, the survivor and children of the contributor are entitled to the following allowances, computed on the basis of the product obtained by multiplying the average annual pay received by the contributor during the period specified in subparagraph 15(1)(a)(ii) by the number of years of pensionable service to the contributor’s credit, one <Ins>seventieth</Ins> of the product so obtained being referred to in this section as the “basic allowance”:</Text></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Section><Heading level="1" type="amending"><MarginalNote><HistoricalNote>R.S., c. R-11</HistoricalNote></MarginalNote><TitleText>Royal Canadian Mounted Police Superannuation Act</TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><Label>2</Label><Text>The portion of subsection 13(1) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Royal Canadian Mounted Police Superannuation Act</XRefExternal> before paragraph (a) is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><Section><MarginalNote>Benefits payable on death</MarginalNote><Label>13</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>On the death of a contributor who, at the time of the contributor’s death, was entitled under this Part to an annuity or annual allowance, the survivor and children of the contributor are entitled to the following allowances, computed on the basis of the product obtained by multiplying the average annual pay received by the contributor during the period specified in subparagraph 10(1)(a)(ii), by the number of years of pensionable service to the contributor’s credit, one <Ins>seventieth</Ins> of the product so obtained being hereinafter referred to as the “basic allowance”:</Text></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Section></Body></Bill>