<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><Bill bill-origin="commons" bill-type="private-public" xml:lang="en" date-time="2014-06-02 13:16:44"><Identification><BillNumber>C-278</BillNumber><Parliament><Session>1</Session><Number>42</Number><RegnalYear><Year-s>64-65</Year-s><Monarch>Elizabeth II</Monarch></RegnalYear><Year-s>2015-2016</Year-s></Parliament><LongTitle>An Act to amend the Lobbying Act (reporting obligations)</LongTitle><ShortTitle status="unofficial" /><RunningHead>An Act to amend the Lobbying Act (reporting obligations)</RunningHead><BillHistory><Stages stage="first-reading-house"><Date><YYYY>2016</YYYY><MM>5</MM><DD>30</DD></Date></Stages></BillHistory><BillSponsor><Emphasis style="smallcaps">Mrs. Gallant</Emphasis></BillSponsor><BillRefNumber date-time="2014-06-02">421092</BillRefNumber></Identification><Introduction><Summary><TitleText>SUMMARY</TitleText><Provision first-line-indent="0" subsequent-line-indent="0"><Text>This enactment amends the <Emphasis style="italic">Lobbying Act</Emphasis> to require lobbyists to disclose</Text></Provision><Provision first-line-indent="1" subsequent-line-indent="1"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>whether they are funded by a foreign national, a non-<Keep>resident</Keep> corporation or a non-resident organization; and</Text></Provision><Provision first-line-indent="1" subsequent-line-indent="1"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>whether they use, or expect to use, grass-roots communication to seek to persuade organizations or members of the public to take measures to obstruct, delay or otherwise negatively affect any process that requires the Government of Canada to consult with the public before embarking on a specific course of action, in an attempt to place pressure on a public office holder to endorse a particular opinion.</Text></Provision><Provision first-line-indent="0" subsequent-line-indent="0"><Text>It also makes a housekeeping amendment to the English version of paragraph 5(2)(e.1) of the Act.</Text></Provision></Summary><Enacts><Provision first-line-indent="0" subsequent-line-indent="0"><Text>Her Majesty, by and with the advice and consent of the Senate and House of Commons of Canada, <Keep>enacts</Keep> as follows:</Text></Provision></Enacts></Introduction><Body><Heading level="1"><TitleText>Short Title</TitleText></Heading><Section type="normal"><Label>1</Label><Text>This Act may be cited as the <Emphasis style="italic">Foreign Lobbyist Transparency Act</Emphasis>.</Text></Section><Heading level="1" type="amending"><MarginalNote><HistoricalNote>R.S., c. 44 (4th Supp.); 2006, c. 9, s. 66</HistoricalNote></MarginalNote><TitleText>Lobbying Act</TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><Label>2</Label><Text>Subsection 2(1) of the <Emphasis style="italic">Lobbying Act</Emphasis> is amended by adding the following in alphabetical order:</Text><AmendedText><SectionPiece><Definition change="ins"><Text><DefinedTermEn>foreign national</DefinedTermEn> has the meaning assigned by subsection 2(1) of the <Emphasis style="italic">Immigration and Refugee Protection Act</Emphasis>. (<DefinedTermFr><Emphasis style="regular">étranger</Emphasis></DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Definition><Definition change="ins"><Text><DefinedTermEn>grass-roots communication</DefinedTermEn> means the appeals, directions and other communications described in subparagraphs 5(2)(j)(i) and (ii). (<DefinedTermFr><Emphasis style="regular">appel au grand public</Emphasis></DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Definition><Definition change="ins"><Text><DefinedTermEn>non-resident</DefinedTermEn> means not resident in Canada. (<DefinedTermFr><Emphasis style="regular">non-<Keep>résident</Keep></Emphasis></DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Definition></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>3</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Paragraph 5(2)(e.1) of the English version of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(e.1)</Label><Text><Ins>if</Ins> the client is funded in whole or in part by a government or government agency, the name of the government or agency, as the case may be, and the amount of funding received;</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Subsection 5(2) of the Act is amended by adding the following after paragraph (e.1):</Text><AmendedText><SectionPiece><Paragraph change="ins"><Label>(e.2)</Label><Text>if the client is directly or indirectly funded, in whole or in part, by a foreign national, a non-resident corporation or a non-resident organization, the name of the foreign national, non-resident corporation or non-resident organization, as the case may be, including the direct funder, the ultimate funder and any intermediaries, and the amount of funding received;</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection><Label>(3)</Label><Text>Paragraphs 5(2)(j) and (k) of the Act are replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(j)</Label><Text>if the individual undertakes to communicate with a public office holder in respect of any matter described in subparagraphs (1)(a)(i) to (vi), particulars to identify any communication technique that the individual uses or expects to use in connection with the communication with the public office holder, including</Text><Subparagraph><Label><Ins>(i)</Ins></Label><Text>any appeals to members of the public through the mass media or by direct communication that seek to persuade those members of the public to communicate directly with <Ins>the</Ins> public office holder in an attempt to place pressure on the public office holder to endorse a particular opinion, and</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph change="ins"><Label>(ii)</Label><Text>any appeals, directions or other communications to organizations or members of the public through the mass media or by direct communication that seek to persuade those organizations or members of the public to take measures to obstruct, delay or otherwise negatively affect any Government of Canada policy-making process, including any process that requires the Government of Canada to consult with the public before embarking on a specific course of action, in an attempt to place pressure on the public office holder to endorse a particular opinion; and</Text></Subparagraph></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(k)</Label><Text><Ins>any</Ins> other information <Ins>that is prescribed</Ins> relating to the identity of the individual, the client, any person or organization referred to in paragraph (b), any subsidiary referred to in paragraph (c), the other corporation referred to in paragraph (d), any member of a coalition referred to in paragraph (e), <Ins>any foreign national, non-resident corporation or non-resident or- ganization referred to in paragraph (e.2)</Ins> or any department or institution referred to in paragraph (i).</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>4</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Subsection 7(3) of the Act is amended by adding the following after paragraph (e):</Text><AmendedText><SectionPiece><Paragraph change="ins"><Label>(e.1)</Label><Text>if the employer is directly or indirectly funded, in whole or in part, by a foreign national, a non-<Keep>resident</Keep> corporation or a non-resident organization, the name of the foreign national, non-resident corporation or non-resident organization, as the case may be, including the direct funder, the ultimate funder and any intermediaries, and the amount of funding received;</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Paragraph 7(3)(k) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(k)</Label><Text>particulars to identify any communication technique, including grass-roots communication, that any employee named in the return uses or is expected to use in connection with any communication in respect of any matter described in subparagraphs (1)(a)(i) to (v); and</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection></Section></Body></Bill>