<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>


<Bill bill-origin="commons" bill-type="private-public" xml:lang="en" date-time="2011-10-05 13:03:04"><Identification><BillNumber>C-284</BillNumber><Parliament><Session>1</Session><Number>42</Number><RegnalYear><Year-s>64-65</Year-s><Monarch>Elizabeth II</Monarch></RegnalYear><Year-s>2015-2016</Year-s></Parliament><LongTitle>An Act respecting a national strategy for the development of renewable energy sources</LongTitle><ShortTitle status="unofficial" /><RunningHead>National Renewable Energy Strategy Act</RunningHead><BillHistory><Stages stage="first-reading-house"><Date><YYYY>2016</YYYY><MM>6</MM><DD>3</DD></Date></Stages></BillHistory><BillSponsor><Emphasis style="smallcaps">Mr. Davies</Emphasis></BillSponsor><BillRefNumber date-time="2011-10-05">421110</BillRefNumber></Identification><Introduction><Summary><TitleText>SUMMARY</TitleText><Provision first-line-indent="0" subsequent-line-indent="0"><Text>This enactment requires the Minister of Natural Resources, in consultation with provincial and territorial government represent­atives responsible for energy matters, to develop and implement a national strategy for increasing the proportion of electricity generated from renewable energy sources in Canada to 90% as soon as possible, but no later than December 31, 2030.</Text></Provision></Summary><Enacts><Provision first-line-indent="0" subsequent-line-indent="0"><Text>Her Majesty, by and with the advice and consent <Keep>of the</Keep> Senate and House of Commons of Canada, <Keep>enacts</Keep> as follows:</Text></Provision></Enacts></Introduction><Body><Heading level="1"><TitleText>Short Title</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Short title</MarginalNote><Label>1</Label><Text>This Act may be cited as the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">National Renewable Energy Strategy Act</XRefExternal>.</Text></Section><Heading level="1"><TitleText>Interpretation</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Definitions</MarginalNote><Label>2</Label><Text>The following definitions apply in this Act.</Text><Definition><Text><DefinedTermEn>Minister</DefinedTermEn> means the Minister of Natural Resources. (<DefinedTermFr><Emphasis style="regular">mi­nistre</Emphasis></DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Definition><Definition><Text><DefinedTermEn>renewable energy source</DefinedTermEn> means an energy source that can be naturally replenished or renewed within a human lifespan. (<DefinedTermFr><Emphasis style="regular">source d’énergie renouvelable</Emphasis></DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Definition></Section><Heading level="1"><TitleText>National Strategy</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Development of national strategy</MarginalNote><Label>3</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The Minister must, in consultation with provincial and territorial government representatives responsible for energy matters, develop and implement a national strategy for increasing the proportion of electricity generated from renewable energy sources in Canada to 90% as soon as possible, but no later than December 31, 2030.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Posting of national strategy</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The Minister must post the national strategy on the departmental website within one year after the day on which this Act comes into force.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Objectives of national strategy</MarginalNote><Label>4</Label><Text>The national strategy referred to in section 3 must include the following objectives:</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>the initiation in each calendar year of twice as many renewable energy production projects as non-renewable energy production projects;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>an increase in federal investment in the research and development of renewable energy technologies;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(c)</Label><Text>cooperation between the federal government and provincial and territorial governments in the establishment of new large-scale, public producers of electricity; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(d)</Label><Text>the creation of a green energy economy and the creation of green jobs.</Text></Paragraph></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Tax incentives</MarginalNote><Label>5</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Within one year after the day on which this Act comes into force, the Minister must work with the Minister of Finance to develop and implement tax incentives to</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>encourage the development of, and investment in, renewable energy projects related to solar, wind, tidal and biomass electricity generation; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>encourage homeowners and businesses to retrofit their properties with new or more efficient renewable energy technologies to increase the proportion of electricity used by these properties that is derived from renewable energy sources.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Clarification</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The tax incentives described in paragraph (1)(a) apply solely to the start-up costs of new projects and not to ongoing costs.</Text></Subsection></Section><Heading level="1"><TitleText>Report</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Report</MarginalNote><Label>6</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Within three years after the day on which this Act comes into force and every three years after that, the Minister must prepare a report on the effectiveness of the national strategy referred to in section 3, and cause a copy of the report to be laid before each House of Parliament on any of the first 15 days on which that House is sitting after the report is completed.
</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Publication of report</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The Minister must post the report on the departmental Web site within 30 days after the day on which the report is tabled in Parliament.</Text></Subsection></Section></Body></Bill>