<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><Bill bill-origin="commons" bill-type="private-public" xml:lang="en" date-time="2016-04-04 08:24:08"><Identification><BillNumber>C-286</BillNumber><Parliament><Session>1</Session><Number>42</Number><RegnalYear><Year-s>64-65</Year-s><Monarch>Elizabeth II</Monarch></RegnalYear><Year-s>2015-2016</Year-s></Parliament><LongTitle>An Act respecting the establishment of  a framework to promote the development of co-operatives in Canada and amending the Department of Industry Act and other Acts</LongTitle><ShortTitle status="unofficial" /><RunningHead>Framework on Co-operatives Act</RunningHead><BillHistory><Stages stage="first-reading-house"><Date><YYYY>2016</YYYY><MM>6</MM><DD>8</DD></Date></Stages></BillHistory><BillSponsor><Emphasis style="smallcaps">Mrs. Mendès</Emphasis></BillSponsor><BillRefNumber date-time="2016-04-04">421135</BillRefNumber></Identification><Introduction><Summary><TitleText>SUMMARY</TitleText><Provision><Text>The purpose of this enactment is to provide for the establishment and implementation of a framework to promote the development of co-operatives in Canada and to amend the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Department of Industry Act</XRefExternal> and other acts to specify that, within their mandates, federal ministers and agencies are to develop and promote the co-operative model in Canada.</Text></Provision></Summary><Enacts><Provision><Text>Her Majesty, by and with the advice and consent <Keep>of the</Keep> Senate and House of Commons of Canada, <Keep>enacts</Keep> as follows:</Text></Provision></Enacts></Introduction><Body><Heading level="1"><TitleText>Framework on <Keep>Co-operatives</Keep></TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Short title</MarginalNote><Label>1</Label><Text>This Act may be cited as the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Framework on Co-operatives Act</XRefExternal>.</Text></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Framework on co-operatives</MarginalNote><Label>2</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The Minister of Industry must, in collaboration with the other federal ministers and heads of federal agencies concerned and with representatives of the provincial and territorial governments and the co-<Keep>operative</Keep> sector, establish and implement a framework on co-operatives that, among other things,</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>establishes the definition and principles applicable to the co-operative model in Canada;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>creates a plan to promote and support the co-<Keep>operative</Keep> model as a lever for economic development;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(c)</Label><Text>develops information programs to foster public understanding of the co-operative model and awareness of co-operative initiatives carried out in Canada; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(d)</Label><Text>develops policies and programs to foster access to cross-government networks and programs for the co-operative sector.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Consultations</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The Minister of Industry must, in collaboration with the other federal ministers and heads of federal agencies concerned and within six months after the day on which this Act comes into force, hold consultations with representatives of the provincial and territorial governments and the co-operative sector on the establishment of the framework.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Report to Parliament</MarginalNote><Label>3</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The Minister of Industry must cause a report setting out the conclusions of the consultations referred to in subsection 2(2) to be laid before each House of Parliament within one year after the day on which this Act comes into force.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Publication of report</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The Minister of Industry must post the report on the departmental Web site within 30 days after the day on which it is tabled in Parliament.</Text></Subsection></Section><Heading level="2"><TitleText>Review and Report</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Review and report</MarginalNote><Label>4</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Within four years of the tabling of the report referred to in section 3, and every five years after that, the Minister of Industry must prepare a report setting out his or her recommendations regarding the framework on co-operatives as well as the actions taken by the federal government to support the framework, and cause the report to be laid before each House of Parliament on any of the first 15 days on which that House is sitting after it is completed.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Publication of report</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The Minister of Industry must post the report on the departmental Web site within 30 days after the day on which it is tabled in Parliament.</Text></Subsection></Section><Heading level="1" type="amending"><MarginalNote><HistoricalNote>1995, c. 1</HistoricalNote></MarginalNote><TitleText>Department of Industry Act</TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><Label>5</Label><Text>Section 5 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Department of Industry Act</XRefExternal> is amended by adding the following after paragraph (a):</Text><AmendedText><SectionPiece><Paragraph change="ins"><Label>(a.1)</Label><Text>develop and promote the co-operative model in Canada;</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>6</Label><Text>Paragraph 9(2)(a) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>provide and, where appropriate, coordinate serv­ices promoting regional economic development in Ontario<Ins>,</Ins> including services to develop entrepreneurial talent, support local business associations, stimulate investment and support small- and medium-sized enterprises<Ins>, and more particularly co-operatives,</Ins> in that province or any part of that province; and</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Section><Heading level="1" type="amending"><MarginalNote><HistoricalNote>R.S.,  c. 11 (4th Supp.)</HistoricalNote></MarginalNote><TitleText>Western Economic Diversification Act</TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><Label>7</Label><Text>Subparagraph 6(1)(c)(i) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Western Economic Diversification Act</XRefExternal> is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><SectionPiece><Subparagraph><Label>(i)</Label><Text>the establishment, development, support and promotion of enterprises, and more particularly <Ins>co-operatives and</Ins> small and medium-sized enterprises, in Western Canada, and</Text></Subparagraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Section><Heading level="1" type="amending"><MarginalNote><HistoricalNote>R.S., c. 41 (4th Supp.)</HistoricalNote></MarginalNote><TitleText>Atlantic Canada Opportunities Agency Act</TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><Label>8</Label><Text>Subparagraph 13(b)(i) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Atlantic Canada Opportunities Agency Act</XRefExternal> is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><SectionPiece><Subparagraph><Label>(i)</Label><Text>the establishment, development, support and promotion of enterprises, and more particularly <Ins>co-operatives and</Ins> small and medium-sized enterprises, in Atlantic Canada,</Text></Subparagraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Section><Heading level="1" type="amending"><MarginalNote><HistoricalNote>2005, c. 26</HistoricalNote></MarginalNote><TitleText>Economic Development Agency of Canada for the Regions of Quebec Act</TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><Label>9</Label><Text>Subparagraph 11(1)(b)(i) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Economic Development Agency of Canada for the Regions of Quebec Act</XRefExternal> is replaced by the following:<PageBreak /></Text><AmendedText><SectionPiece><Subparagraph><Label>(i)</Label><Text>to the establishment, development, support and promotion of enterprises, and more particularly <Ins>co-operatives and</Ins> small- and medium-sized enterprises, in Quebec,</Text></Subparagraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Section></Body></Bill>