<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><Bill bill-origin="commons" bill-type="private-public" xml:lang="en" date-time="2014-11-27 11:28:01"><Identification><BillNumber>C-289</BillNumber><Parliament><Session>1</Session><Number>42</Number><RegnalYear><Year-s>64-65</Year-s><Monarch>Elizabeth II</Monarch></RegnalYear><Year-s>2015-2016</Year-s></Parliament><LongTitle>An Act to establish Canadian Optimist Movement Awareness Day</LongTitle><ShortTitle status="unofficial" /><RunningHead>Canadian Optimist Movement Awareness Day Act</RunningHead><BillHistory><Stages stage="first-reading-house"><Date><YYYY>2016</YYYY><MM>6</MM><DD>9</DD></Date></Stages></BillHistory><BillSponsor><Emphasis style="smallcaps">Ms. Quach</Emphasis></BillSponsor><BillRefNumber date-time="2014-11-27">421142</BillRefNumber></Identification><Introduction><Summary><TitleText>SUMMARY</TitleText><Provision><Text>This enactment designates the first Thursday in February in each and every year as “Canadian Optimist Movement Awareness Day”.</Text></Provision></Summary><Preamble><Provision><MarginalNote>Preamble</MarginalNote><Text>Whereas Optimist clubs have existed throughout Canada since 1924 and have played an important role in the country’s social history;</Text></Provision><Provision><Text>Whereas Canada today has over 600 Optimist clubs whose members take part in activities that allow them to help an average of 80 young people in each locality;</Text></Provision><Provision><Text>Whereas it is important to support young people, and Optimist clubs have a positive social, economic and cultural effect on their life;</Text></Provision><Provision><Text>Whereas the Optimist movement allows young Canadians to flourish and reach their full potential by adopting optimism as a philosophy of life;</Text></Provision><Provision><Text>And whereas it is important to make Canadians aware of the Optimist movement so that they become a part of it and so that all Canadian communities can benefit from the advantages it offers;</Text></Provision></Preamble><Enacts><Provision><Text>Now, therefore, Her Majesty, with the advice and consent <Keep>of the</Keep> Senate and House of Commons of Canada, <Keep>enacts</Keep> as follows:</Text></Provision></Enacts></Introduction><Body><Heading level="1"><TitleText>Short Title</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Short title</MarginalNote><Label>1</Label><Text>This Act may be cited as the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Canadian Optimist Movement Awareness Day Act</XRefExternal>.</Text></Section><Heading level="1"><TitleText>Canadian Optimist Movement Awareness Day</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Canadian Optimist Movement Awareness Day</MarginalNote><Label>2</Label><Text>Throughout Canada, in each and every year, the first Thursday in February is to be known as “Canadian Optimist Movement Awareness Day”.</Text></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Not a legal holiday</MarginalNote><Label>3</Label><Text>For greater certainty, Canadian Optimist Movement Awareness Day is not a legal holiday or a non-juridical day.</Text></Section></Body></Bill>