<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><Bill bill-origin="commons" bill-type="private-public" xml:lang="en" date-time="2016-05-18 16:14:33"><Identification><BillNumber>C-285</BillNumber><Parliament><Session>1</Session><Number>42</Number><RegnalYear><Year-s>64-65</Year-s><Monarch>Elizabeth II</Monarch></RegnalYear><Year-s>2015-2016</Year-s></Parliament><LongTitle>An Act to provide for the development of national standards for the transport of currency and valuables by armoured car</LongTitle><ShortTitle status="unofficial" /><RunningHead>National Standards for the Armoured Transport of Currency and Valuables Act</RunningHead><BillHistory><Stages stage="first-reading-house"><Date><YYYY>2016</YYYY><MM>6</MM><DD>3</DD></Date></Stages></BillHistory><BillSponsor><Emphasis style="smallcaps">Mr. Julian</Emphasis></BillSponsor><BillRefNumber date-time="2016-05-18">421198</BillRefNumber></Identification><Introduction><Summary><TitleText>SUMMARY</TitleText><Provision><Text>This enactment provides for the development of national stand­ards with respect to the transport of currency and valuables by armoured car.</Text></Provision></Summary><Preamble salutation="no"><Provision><MarginalNote>Preamble</MarginalNote><Text>Whereas standards regarding employee training, equipment requirements and crew sizes in the armoured car industry vary across Canada and may be inadequate or non-existent;</Text></Provision><Provision language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text>Whereas employees in the armoured car industry are at risk of being victims of armed robbery and gun crime, and cost-cutting measures in the industry may increase the risk of harm to employees and the public;</Text></Provision><Provision language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text>Whereas the Parliament of Canada is concerned about the health and safety of those employed in the armoured car industry as well as the public with which they interact;</Text></Provision><Provision language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text>Whereas the Parliament of Canada has an interest in ensuring that employee training, vehicle and crew specifications, and equipment in the armoured car industry respect consistent nationwide standards;</Text></Provision><Provision><Text>Whereas it is desirable to develop consistent <Keep>stand­</Keep>ards for the armoured car industry across Canada, while respecting provincial jurisdiction over various related matters;</Text></Provision><Provision><Text>And whereas the development of nationwide <Keep>stand­</Keep>ards promotes responsible business practices as well as employee health and safety;</Text></Provision></Preamble><Enacts><Provision><Text>Now, therefore, Her Majesty, by and with the advice and consent of the Senate and the House of <Keep>Commons of</Keep> Canada, enacts as follows:</Text></Provision></Enacts></Introduction><Body><Heading level="1"><TitleText>Short Title</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Short title</MarginalNote><Label>1</Label><Text>This Act may be cited as the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">National Standards for the Armoured Transport of Currency and Valuables Act</XRefExternal>.</Text></Section><Heading level="1"><TitleText>National Standards</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Development of standards</MarginalNote><Label>2</Label><Text>For the purpose of harmonizing and standardizing federal and provincial practices, the Minister of Labour must, in collaboration with other federal ministers, with representatives of the provincial and territorial governments responsible for employment, and with other relevant stakeholders, conduct consultations to develop national standards for the transport of currency and valuables by armoured car that include standards regarding</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>employee training;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>equipment and equipment safety;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(c)</Label><Text>workplace and off-site safety;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(d)</Label><Text>crew sizes;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(e)</Label><Text>labour conditions;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(f)</Label><Text>licensing regimes in respect of industry operations; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(g)</Label><Text>the operation of armoured cars used to transport currency and valuables.</Text></Paragraph></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Report to Parliament</MarginalNote><Label>3</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Within two years after the day on which this Act comes into force, the Minister of Labour must prepare a report that includes the details of the consultations held and national standards developed under section 2 as well as any recommendations, and cause it to be laid before each House of Parliament.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Publication of report</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The Minister must post the report on the departmental Web site within 30 days after the day on which the report is tabled in Parliament.</Text></Subsection></Section><Heading level="1"><TitleText>Review and Report</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Review and report</MarginalNote><Label>4</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Within three years after the tabling of the report referred to in section 3, and every three years after that, the Minister of Labour must prepare a report setting out his or her assessment of and recommendations regarding the national standards for the transport of currency and valuables by armoured car and cause a copy of the report to be laid before each House of Parliament on any of the first 15 days on which that House is sitting after the report is completed.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Publication of report</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The Minister must post the report on the departmental Web site within 30 days after the day on which the report is tabled in Parliament.</Text></Subsection></Section></Body></Bill>