<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>


<Bill bill-origin="commons" bill-type="private-public" xml:lang="en" date-time="2008-05-21 08:43:15"><Identification><BillNumber>C-292</BillNumber><Parliament><Session>1</Session><Number>42</Number><RegnalYear><Year-s>64-65</Year-s><Monarch>Elizabeth II</Monarch></RegnalYear><Year-s>2015-2016</Year-s></Parliament><LongTitle>An Act to amend the Canada Labour Code (occupational disease and accident registry)</LongTitle><ShortTitle status="unofficial" /><RunningHead>An Act to amend the Canada Labour Code (occupational disease and accident registry)</RunningHead><BillHistory><Stages stage="first-reading-house"><Date><YYYY>2016</YYYY><MM>6</MM><DD>14</DD></Date></Stages></BillHistory><BillSponsor><Emphasis style="smallcaps">Ms. Benson</Emphasis></BillSponsor><BillRefNumber date-time="2008-05-21">421217</BillRefNumber></Identification><Introduction><Summary><TitleText>SUMMARY</TitleText><Provision><Text>This enactment amends the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Canada Labour Code</XRefExternal> to require the Minister of Labour to maintain a registry containing information reported by employers about accidents, occupational diseases and other hazardous occurrences and to make such information available for examination to past, present and potential employees.</Text></Provision></Summary><Enacts><Provision><MarginalNote><HistoricalNote>R.S., c. L-2</HistoricalNote></MarginalNote><Text>Her Majesty, by and with the advice and consent <Keep>of the</Keep> Senate and House of Commons of Canada, <Keep>enacts</Keep> as follows:</Text></Provision></Enacts></Introduction><Body><Section type="amending"><Label>1</Label><Text>Subsection 125(1) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Canada Labour Code</XRefExternal> is amended by adding the following after paragraph (c):</Text><AmendedText><SectionPiece><Paragraph change="ins"><Label>(c.1)</Label><Text>report to the Minister, for the purposes of the occupational disease and accident registry referred to in section 125.4, all accidents, occupational diseases and other hazardous occurrences, including exposure to a hazardous substance, known to the employer;</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>2</Label><Text>The Act is amended by adding the following after section 125.3:</Text><AmendedText><Heading level="2" change="ins"><TitleText>Occupational Disease and Accident Registry</TitleText></Heading><Section change="ins"><MarginalNote>Occupational disease and accident registry</MarginalNote><Label>125.4</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The Minister shall maintain an occupational disease and accident registry containing information about all accidents, occupational diseases and other hazardous occurrences, including exposure to a hazardous substance, reported under paragraph 125(1)(c.1).</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Information to be made available</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The Minister shall, for the purpose of allowing hazards to health and safety associated with a work place to be identified, make information contained in the registry that relates to a work place readily available, in printed or electronic form, for examination by persons </Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>who are employed or have been employed at that work place; or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>who have received a written offer of employment from an employer that could involve employment at that work place.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Limitation on disclosure</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>No information that could be used to identify any person other than the employer may be made available under subsection (2).</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Information for research or statistical purposes</MarginalNote><Label>(4)</Label><Text>The Minister may make information contained in the registry available to an individual or organization for scientific research or statistical purposes, other than information that could be used to identify any person.</Text></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Section></Body></Bill>