<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><Bill bill-origin="commons" bill-type="private-public" xml:lang="en" date-time="2016-06-06 13:57:25"><Identification><BillNumber>C-293</BillNumber><Parliament><Session>1</Session><Number>42</Number><RegnalYear><Year-s>64-65</Year-s><Monarch>Elizabeth II</Monarch></RegnalYear><Year-s>2015-2016</Year-s></Parliament><LongTitle>An Act to amend the Department of Health Act (Advisory Committee)</LongTitle><ShortTitle status="unofficial" /><RunningHead>An Act to amend the Department of Health Act (Advisory Committee)</RunningHead><BillHistory><Stages stage="first-reading-house"><Date><YYYY>2016</YYYY><MM>6</MM><DD>14</DD></Date></Stages></BillHistory><BillSponsor><Emphasis style="smallcaps">Mr. Davies</Emphasis></BillSponsor><BillRefNumber date-time="2016-06-06">421235</BillRefNumber></Identification><Introduction><Summary><TitleText>SUMMARY</TitleText><Provision><Text>This enactment amends the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Department of Health Act</XRefExternal> in order to establish an advisory committee charged with gathering and making public information on the establishment of universal public coverage for prescription medication.</Text></Provision></Summary><Enacts><Provision><MarginalNote><HistoricalNote>1996, c. 8</HistoricalNote></MarginalNote><Text>Her Majesty, by and with the advice and consent <Keep>of the</Keep> Senate and House of Commons of Canada, <Keep>enacts</Keep> as follows:</Text></Provision></Enacts></Introduction><Body><Section type="amending"><Label>1</Label><Text>The <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Department of Health Act</XRefExternal> is amended by adding the following after section 5:</Text><AmendedText><Heading level="1" change="ins"><TitleText>Advisory Committee</TitleText></Heading><Section change="ins"><MarginalNote>Advisory Committee established</MarginalNote><Label>5.1</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>There is established a committee, to be known as the Advisory Committee on Public Coverage for Prescription Medication, consisting of five members appointed by the Governor in Council for a term not exceeding five years, which term may be renewed for one or more further terms.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Mandate</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The mandate of the Advisory Committee is to advise and assist the Minister with respect to public coverage for prescription medication and to gather and make public information on the establishment of universal public coverage for prescription medication by</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>collecting and analyzing leading, independent and peer-reviewed research on public coverage for prescription medication and commissioning research, where needed, to acquire relevant knowledge;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>consulting with relevant stakeholders in Canada and abroad regarding the establishment of universal public coverage for prescription medication;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(c)</Label><Text>studying existing and proposed models of public coverage for prescription medication in other jurisdictions to determine best practices;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(d)</Label><Text>meeting with representatives of the federal, provincial and territorial governments and of First Nations to discuss models of universal public coverage for prescription medication and to determine the most suitable model for Canada, taking into account relevant legal and cultural considerations; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(e)</Label><Text>making recommendations to the Minister regarding the establishment of universal public coverage for prescription medication.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Chair</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>The Minister must appoint one of the members as Chair of the Advisory Committee.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Remuneration of Chair</MarginalNote><Label>(4)</Label><Text>The Chair of the Advisory Committee is to be paid the remuneration fixed by the Governor in Council.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Travel, living and other expenses</MarginalNote><Label>(5)</Label><Text>The members of the Advisory Committee are entitled to be reimbursed, in accordance with Treasury Board directives, for travel, living and other expenses incurred in connection with their work for the committee while absent from their ordinary place or residence.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Meetings</MarginalNote><Label>(6)</Label><Text>The Chair may determine the times and places at which the Advisory Committee will meet, but it must meet at least four times a year.</Text></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Section></Body></Bill>