<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><Bill bill-origin="commons" bill-type="private-public" xml:lang="en" date-time="2016-06-08 12:06:42"><Identification><BillNumber>C-303</BillNumber><Parliament><Session>1</Session><Number>42</Number><RegnalYear><Year-s>64-65</Year-s><Monarch>Elizabeth II</Monarch></RegnalYear><Year-s>2015-2016</Year-s></Parliament><LongTitle>An Act respecting the repeal of the Acts enacted by the Anti-terrorism Act, 2015 and amending or repealing certain provisions enacted by that Act</LongTitle><ShortTitle status="unofficial" /><RunningHead>An Act respecting the repeal of the Acts enacted by the Anti-terrorism Act, 2015 and amending or repealing certain provisions enacted by that Act</RunningHead><BillHistory><Stages stage="first-reading-house"><Date><YYYY>2016</YYYY><MM>9</MM><DD>26</DD></Date></Stages></BillHistory><BillSponsor><Emphasis style="smallcaps">Mr. Garrison</Emphasis></BillSponsor><BillRefNumber date-time="2016-06-08">421224</BillRefNumber></Identification><Introduction><Summary><TitleText>SUMMARY</TitleText><Provision><Text>This enactment repeals the Acts enacted by the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Anti-terrorism Act, 2015</XRefExternal> as well as the amendments made to other Acts by that Act.</Text></Provision></Summary><Enacts><Provision><Text>Her Majesty, by and with the advice and consent <Keep>of the</Keep> Senate and House of Commons of Canada, <Keep>enacts</Keep> as follows:</Text></Provision></Enacts></Introduction><Body><Heading level="1" type="amending"><MarginalNote><HistoricalNote>2015, c. 20, s. 2</HistoricalNote></MarginalNote><TitleText>Security of Canada Information Sharing Act</TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><Label>1</Label><Text>The <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Security of Canada Information Sharing Act</XRefExternal> is repealed.</Text></Section><Heading level="1" type="amending"><MarginalNote><HistoricalNote>2015, c. 20, s. 11</HistoricalNote></MarginalNote><TitleText>Secure Air Travel Act</TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><Label>2</Label><Text>The <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Secure Air Travel Act</XRefExternal> is repealed. </Text></Section><Heading level="1" type="amending"><MarginalNote><HistoricalNote>R.S., c. C-46</HistoricalNote></MarginalNote><TitleText>Criminal Code</TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><Label>3</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Paragraph (f) of the definition <DefinedTermEn>Attorney General</DefinedTermEn> in section 2 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Criminal Code</XRefExternal> is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(f)</Label><Text>with respect to proceedings under section 83.13, 83.14, 83.28, 83.29 or 83.3, means either the Attorney General of Canada or the Attorney General or Solicitor General of the province in which those proceedings are taken and includes the lawful deputy of any of them, and</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The definition <DefinedTermEn>justice system participant</DefinedTermEn> in section 2 of the Act is amended by adding “and” at the end of paragraph (a), by striking out “and” at the end of paragraph (b) and by repealing paragraph (c).</Text></Subsection></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>4</Label><Text>Sections 83.221 to 83.223 of the Act are repealed. </Text></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>5</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Paragraphs 83.3(2)(a) and (b) of the Act are replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>believes on reasonable grounds that a terrorist activity <Ins>will</Ins> be carried out; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>suspects on reasonable grounds that the imposition of a recognizance with conditions on a person, or the arrest of a person, is <Ins>necessary</Ins> to prevent the carrying out of the terrorist activity.</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The portion of subsection 83.3(4) of the French version of the Act before paragraph (a) is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><Subsection><MarginalNote>Arrestation sans mandat</MarginalNote><Label>(4)</Label><Text><Language xml:lang="fr">Par dérogation aux paragraphes (2) et (3), l’agent de la paix, s’il a des motifs raisonnables de soupçonner que la mise sous garde de la personne <Ins>est nécessaire afin</Ins> de l’empêcher de se livrer à une activité terroriste, peut, sans mandat, arrêter la personne et la faire mettre sous garde en vue de la conduire devant un juge de la cour provinciale en conformité avec le paragraphe (6) dans l’un ou l’autre des cas suivants :</Language></Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(3)</Label><Text>Paragraph 83.3(4)(b) of the English version of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>the peace officer suspects on reasonable grounds that the detention of the person in custody is <Ins>necessary in order</Ins> to prevent a terrorist activity.</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(4)</Label><Text>Subsections 83.3(7.1) and (7.2) of the Act are repealed.</Text></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(5)</Label><Text>Paragraphs 83.3(8)(a) and (b) of the Act are replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>may, if satisfied by the evidence adduced that the peace officer has reasonable grounds for the suspicion, order that the person enter into a recognizance to keep the peace and be of good behaviour for <Ins>any</Ins> period <Ins>that does not exceed</Ins> 12 months and to comply with any other reasonable conditions prescribed in the recognizance, including the conditions set out in <Ins>subsection</Ins> (10), that the judge considers desirable for preventing the carrying out of a terrorist activity; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>if the person was not released under subparagraph (7)(b)(i), shall order that the person be released, <Keep>subject</Keep> to the recognizance, if any, ordered under paragraph (a).</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(6)</Label><Text>Subsection 83.3(8.1) of the Act is repealed. </Text></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(7)</Label><Text>Subsections 83.3(11.1) to (12) of the Act are replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><Subsection type="normal"><MarginalNote>Reasons</MarginalNote><Label>(12)</Label><Text>If the judge does not add <Ins>the</Ins> condition to a recognizance, <Ins>they</Ins> shall include in the record a statement of the reasons for not adding it.</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Subsection></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>6</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Paragraph 83.31(2)(c) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(c)</Label><Text>the number of cases in which a person was not released under subsection 83.3(7) pending a hearing;</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Subparagraph 83.31(3)(b)(ii) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><SectionPiece><Subparagraph><Label>(ii)</Label><Text>by a judge under paragraph 83.3(7)(a).</Text></Subparagraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>7</Label><Text>Subparagraph (xii. 81) of the definition <DefinedTermEn>offence</DefinedTermEn> in section 183 of the Act is repealed.</Text></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>8</Label><Text>Paragraphs 195(1)(a) and (b) of the Act are replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>authorizations for which that Minister and agents <Ins>to be named in the report who were</Ins> specially designated in writing by that Minister for the purposes of section 185 applied and <Ins>to</Ins> the interceptions made under those authorizations in the immediately preceding year;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>authorizations given under section 188 for which peace officers <Ins>to be named in the report who were</Ins> specially designated by that Minister for the purposes of that section applied and <Ins>to</Ins> the interceptions made under those authorizations in the immediately preceding year; and</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>9</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Subsections 486(1) and (1.1) of the Act are replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><Section><MarginalNote>Exclusion of public in certain cases</MarginalNote><Label>486</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Any proceedings against an accused shall be held in open court, but the presiding judge or justice may order the exclusion of all or any members of the public from the court room for all or part of the proceedings if the judge or justice is of the opinion that such an order is in the interest of public morals, the maintenance of order or the proper administration of justice or is necessary to prevent injury to international relations or national defence or national security.</Text></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Subsection 486(4) of the Act is repealed.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>10</Label><Text>Paragraph 486.2(3)(f.1) of the Act is repealed. </Text></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>11</Label><Text>Paragraph 486.31(3)(e.1) of the Act is repealed.</Text></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>12</Label><Text>Section 486.7 of the Act is repealed. </Text></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>13</Label><Text>Subparagraph (i.091) of the definition <DefinedTermEn>primary designated offence</DefinedTermEn> in section 487.04 of the Act is repealed. </Text></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>14</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Subsection 810.01(1) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><Section><MarginalNote>Fear of certain offences</MarginalNote><Label>810.01</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>A person who fears on reasonable grounds that another person will commit an offence under section 423.1<Ins>,</Ins> a criminal organization offence or <Ins>a terrorism offence</Ins> may, with <Ins>the</Ins> consent <Ins>of</Ins> the Attorney <Ins>General</Ins>, lay an information before a provincial court judge.</Text></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Subsection 810.01(8) of the Act is repealed.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>15</Label><Text>Section 810.011 of the Act is repealed. </Text></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>16</Label><Text>Sections 810.21 and 810.22 of the Act are repealed. </Text></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>17</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The portion of subsection 810.3(1) of the Act before paragraph (a) is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><Section><MarginalNote>Samples — designations and specifications</MarginalNote><Label>810.3</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>For the purposes of sections 810, 810.01, 810.1 and 810.2 and subject to the regulations, the Attorney General of a province or the minister of justice of a territory shall, with respect to the province or territory,</Text></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Paragraphs 810.3(2)(a) and (b) of the Act are replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>to make a demand for a sample of a bodily substance for the purposes of paragraphs 810(3.02)(b), 810.01(4.1)(f), 810.1(3.02)(h) and 810.2(4.1)(f); and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>to specify the regular intervals at which a <Keep>defend­</Keep>ant must provide a sample of a bodily substance for the purposes of paragraphs 810(3.02)(c), 810.01(4.1)(g), 810.1(3.02)(i) and 810.2(4.1)(g).</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(3)</Label><Text>Subsections 810.3(3) and (4) of the Act are replaced by the following:

</Text><AmendedText><Subsection><MarginalNote>Restriction</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>Samples of bodily substances referred to in sections 810, 810.01, 810.1 and 810.2 may not be taken, analyzed, stored, handled or destroyed, and the records of the results of the analysis of the samples may not be protected or destroyed, except in accordance with the designations and specifications made under subsection (1).</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Destruction of samples</MarginalNote><Label>(4)</Label><Text>The Attorney General of a province or the minister of justice of a territory, or a person authorized by the Attorney General or minister, shall cause all samples of bodily substances provided under a recognizance under section 810, 810.01, 810.1 or 810.2 to be destroyed within the period prescribed by regulation unless the samples are reasonably expected to be used as evidence in a proceeding for an offence under section 811.</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(4)</Label><Text>Paragraph 810.3(5)(a) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>prescribing bodily substances for the purposes of sections 810, 810.01, 810.1 and 810.2; </Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(5)</Label><Text>Subsection 810.3(6) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><Subsection><MarginalNote>Notice — samples at regular intervals</MarginalNote><Label>(6)</Label><Text>The notice referred to in paragraph 810(3.02)(c), 810.01(4.1)(g), 810.1(3.02)(i) or 810.2(4.1)(g) must specify the places and times at which and the days on which the defendant must provide samples of a bodily substance under a condition described in that paragraph. The first sample may not be taken earlier than 24 hours after the defendant is served with the notice, and subsequent samples must be taken at regular intervals of at least seven days. </Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Subsection></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>18</Label><Text>Subsections 810.4(1) to (3) of the Act are replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><Section><MarginalNote>Prohibition on use of bodily substance</MarginalNote><Label>810.4</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>No person shall use a bodily substance provided under a recognizance under section 810, 810.01, 810.1 or 810.2 except for the purpose of determining whether a defendant is complying with a condition in the recognizance that they abstain from the consumption of drugs, alcohol or any other intoxicating substance.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote> 	Prohibition on use or disclosure of result</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Subject to subsection (3), no person shall use, disclose or allow the disclosure of the results of the analysis of a bodily substance provided under a recognizance under section 810, 810.01, 810.1 or 810.2.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote> 	Exception</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>The results of the analysis of a bodily substance provided under a recognizance under section 810, 810.01, 810.1 or 810.2 may be disclosed to the defendant to whom they relate, and may also be used or disclosed in the course of an investigation of, or in a proceeding for, an offence under section 811 or, if the results are made anonymous, for statistical or other research purposes.</Text></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>19</Label><Text>The portion of section 811 of the Act before paragraph (a) is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><Section><MarginalNote>Breach of recognizance</MarginalNote><Label>811</Label><Text>A person bound by a recognizance under <Ins>section</Ins> 83.3, 810<Ins>, 810.01, 810.02, 810.1 or</Ins> 810.2 who commits a breach of the recognizance is guilty of</Text></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>20</Label><Text>Subsection 811.1(1) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><Section><MarginalNote>Proof of certificate of analyst — bodily substance</MarginalNote><Label>811.1</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>In a prosecution for breach of a condition in a recognizance under section 810, 810.01, 810.1 or 810.2 that a defendant not consume drugs, alcohol or any other intoxicating substance, a certificate purporting to be signed by an analyst that states that the analyst has analyzed a sample of a bodily substance and that states the result of the analysis is admissible in evidence and, in the absence of evidence to the contrary, is proof of the statements contained in the certificate without proof of the signature or official character of the person who appears to have signed the certificate. </Text></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>21</Label><Text>The section references after the heading “FORM 51” in Form 51 in Part XXVIII of the Act are replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><ScheduleFormHeading><Label /><OriginatingRef>(Paragraphs 732.1(3)(c.2), 742.3(2)(a.2), 810(3.02)(c), 810.01(4.1)(g), 810.1(3.02)(i) and 810.2(4.1)(g)) </OriginatingRef></ScheduleFormHeading></AmendedText></Section><Heading level="1" type="amending"><MarginalNote><HistoricalNote>R.S., c. C-23</HistoricalNote></MarginalNote><TitleText>Canadian Security Intelligence Service Act</TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><Label>22</Label><Text>Subsection 6(5) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Canadian Security Intelligence Service Act</XRefExternal> is repealed.</Text></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>23</Label><Text>Subsection 7(2) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><Subsection><MarginalNote>Consultation with Deputy Minister — warrant</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The Director or any employee designated by the Minister for the purpose of applying for a warrant under section 21 or 23 shall consult the Deputy Minister before applying for the warrant or the renewal of the warrant.</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>24</Label><Text>Sections 12.1 and 12.2 of the Act are repealed. </Text></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>25</Label><Text>Paragraph 21(2)(h) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(h)</Label><Text>any previous application made in relation to a person identified in the affidavit <Ins>pursuant to</Ins> paragraph (d), the date on which the application was made, the name of the judge to whom <Ins>each application</Ins> was made and the decision <Ins>of the</Ins> judge <Ins>in respect of each application</Ins>.</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>26</Label><Text>Section 21.1 of the Act is repealed. </Text></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>27</Label><Text>Sections 22.1 to 23 of the Act are replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><Section><MarginalNote>Warrant authorizing removal</MarginalNote><Label>23</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>On application in writing by the Director or any employee designated by the Minister for the purpose, a judge may, if the judge thinks fit, issue a warrant <Keep>authoriz­</Keep>ing the persons to whom the warrant is directed to remove from any place any thing installed <Ins>pursuant to</Ins> a warrant issued under subsection 21(3) and, for that purpose, to enter any place or open or obtain access to any thing.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Matters to be specified in warrants</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>There shall be specified in a warrant issued under subsection (1) the matters referred to in paragraphs 21(4)(c) to (f).</Text></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>28</Label><Text>Section 24.1 of the Act is repealed.</Text></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>29</Label><Text>Paragraph 25(a) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>the use or disclosure <Ins>pursuant to</Ins> this Act of any communication intercepted under the authority of a warrant issued under section 21; or</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>30</Label><Text>Sections 26 and 27 of the Act are replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><Section><MarginalNote>Exclusion of Part VI of <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Criminal Code</XRefExternal></MarginalNote><Label>26</Label><Text>Part VI of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Criminal Code</XRefExternal> does not apply in relation to any interception of a communication under the authority of a warrant issued under section 21 or in relation to any communication so intercepted.</Text></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Hearing of applications</MarginalNote><Label>27</Label><Text>An application under section 21, 22 or 23 <Ins>to a judge</Ins> for a warrant or the renewal of a warrant shall be heard in private in accordance with regulations made under section 28.</Text></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>31</Label><Text>Paragraphs 28(a) and (b) of the Act are replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>prescribing the forms of warrants that may be issued under section 21 or 23;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>governing the practice and procedure of, and security requirements applicable to, hearings of applications for those warrants and for renewals of those warrants; and</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>32</Label><Text>Subsection 38(1.1) of the Act is repealed. </Text></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>33</Label><Text>Subsection 53(2) of the Act is repealed.</Text></Section><Heading level="1" type="amending"><MarginalNote><HistoricalNote>2001, c. 27</HistoricalNote></MarginalNote><TitleText>Immigration and Refugee Protection Act</TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><Label>34</Label><Text>Subsection 72(1) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Immigration and Refugee Protection Act</XRefExternal> is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><Section><MarginalNote>Application for judicial review</MarginalNote><Label>72</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Judicial review by the Federal Court with respect to any matter — a decision, determination or order made, a measure taken or a question raised — under this Act is commenced by making an application for leave to the Court.</Text></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>35</Label><Text>Paragraph 74(d) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(d)</Label><Text>an appeal to the Federal Court of Appeal may be made only if, in rendering judgment, the judge certifies that a serious question of general importance is involved and states the question.</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>36</Label><Text>Subsections 77(2) and (3) of the Act are replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><Subsection><MarginalNote>Filing of evidence and summary</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>When the certificate is referred, the Minister shall file with the Court the information and other evidence on which the certificate is based, <Ins>and</Ins> a summary of information and other evidence that enables the person <Ins>who is</Ins> named in the certificate to be reasonably informed of the case made by the Minister but that does not include anything that, in the Minister’s opinion, would be injurious to national security or endanger the safety of any person if disclosed.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Effect of referral</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>Once the certificate is referred, no proceeding under this Act respecting the person who is named in the certificate — other than proceedings relating to sections 82 to <Ins>82.3</Ins>, 112 and 115 — may be commenced or continued until the judge determines whether the certificate is reasonable.</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>37</Label><Text>Section 79.1 of the Act is repealed. </Text></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>38</Label><Text>Section 82.31 of the Act is repealed. </Text></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>39</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Paragraphs 83(1)(c.1) and (c.2) of the Act are repealed.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Subsection 83(1) of the Act is amended by adding “and” at the end of paragraph (i), by striking out “and” at the end of paragraph (j) and by repealing paragraph (k).</Text></Subsection></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>40</Label><Text>Section 84 of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><Section><MarginalNote>Protection of information on appeal</MarginalNote><Label>84</Label><Text>Section 83 — other than the obligation to provide a summary — and sections 85.1 to 85.5 apply <Ins>to</Ins> an appeal under section 79 or 82.3<Ins>,</Ins> and <Ins>to</Ins> any further appeal, with any necessary modifications.</Text></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>41</Label><Text>Subsection 85.4(1) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><Section><MarginalNote>Obligation to provide information</MarginalNote><Label>85.4</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The Minister shall, within a period set by the judge, provide the special advocate with a copy of all information and other evidence that is <Ins>provided to the judge</Ins> but that is not disclosed to the permanent resident or foreign national and their counsel.</Text></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>42</Label><Text>Section 86.1 of the Act is repealed.</Text></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>43</Label><Text>Sections 87 and 87.01 of the Act are replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><Section><MarginalNote>Application for non-disclosure — judicial review</MarginalNote><Label>87</Label><Text>The Minister may, during a judicial review, apply for the non-disclosure of information or other evidence. Section 83 — other than the obligations to appoint a special advocate and to provide a summary — applies <Ins>to</Ins> the proceeding with any necessary modifications.</Text></Section></AmendedText></Section><Heading level="1" type="amending"><TitleText>Transitional Provision</TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote>Cases excluded from application of sections 35 to 43</MarginalNote><Label>44</Label><Text>The amendments made by sections 35 to 43 do not apply in respect of an application, proceeding or matter that is pending or in progress under Division 9 of Part 1 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Immigration and Refugee Protection Act</XRefExternal> immediately before the coming into force of this Act, or in respect of any appeal or judicial review, commenced on or after that coming into force, of a decision made in such an application, proceeding or matter.</Text></Section><Heading level="1" type="amending"><TitleText>Consequential Amendments</TitleText></Heading><Heading level="2" type="amending"><MarginalNote><HistoricalNote>R.S., c. A-2</HistoricalNote></MarginalNote><TitleText>Aeronautics Act</TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><Label>45</Label><Text>Paragraph 7.6(1)(a) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Aeronautics Act</XRefExternal> is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>designate any provision of this Part or of any regulation, notice, order or security measure made under this Part, in this section and in sections 7.7 to 8.2 referred to as a “designated provision”, as a provision the contravention of which may be dealt with under and in accordance with the procedure set out in sections 7.7 to 8.2;</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Section><Heading level="2" type="amending"><MarginalNote><HistoricalNote>R.S., c. C-5</HistoricalNote></MarginalNote><TitleText>Canada Evidence Act</TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><Label>46</Label><Text>Item 4 of the schedule to the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Canada Evidence Act</XRefExternal> is repealed.</Text></Section><Heading level="2" type="amending"><MarginalNote><HistoricalNote>R.S., c. E-15</HistoricalNote></MarginalNote><TitleText>Excise Tax Act</TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><Label>47</Label><Text>Subsection 295(5.05) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Excise Tax Act</XRefExternal> is repealed. </Text></Section><Heading level="2" type="amending"><MarginalNote><HistoricalNote>R.S., c. F-15</HistoricalNote></MarginalNote><TitleText>Department of Fisheries and Oceans Act</TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><Label>48</Label><Text>Subsection 4(3) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Department of Fisheries and Oceans Act</XRefExternal> is repealed. </Text></Section><Heading level="2" type="amending"><MarginalNote><HistoricalNote>R.S., c. P-20</HistoricalNote></MarginalNote><TitleText>Prisons and Reformatories Act</TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><Label>49</Label><Text>The portion of the definition <DefinedTermEn>prisoner</DefinedTermEn> in subsection 2(1) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Prisons and Reformatories Act</XRefExternal> after paragraph (b) is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><SectionPiece><ContinuedDefinition><Text>who is confined in a prison pursuant to a sentence for an offence under an Act of Parliament or any of its  regulations, or pursuant to a committal for failure or refusal to enter into a recognizance under sections 810<Ins>, 810.1 or</Ins> 810.2 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Criminal Code</XRefExternal>; (<DefinedTermFr>prisonnier</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></ContinuedDefinition></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Section><Heading level="2" type="amending"><MarginalNote><HistoricalNote>R.S., c. 1 (2nd Supp.)</HistoricalNote></MarginalNote><TitleText>Customs Act</TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><Label>50</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Subsection 107(4) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Customs Act</XRefExternal> is amended by adding “or” at the end of paragraph (g), by striking out “or” at the end of paragraph (h) and by repealing paragraph (i).</Text></Subsection><Subsection><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Paragraph 107(5)(j) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(j)</Label><Text>an official of the Department of Citizenship and Immigration solely for the purpose of administering or enforcing the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Immigration and Refugee Protection Act</XRefExternal>, if the information relates to the movement of people into and out of Canada;</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection></Section><Heading level="2" type="amending"><MarginalNote><HistoricalNote>R.S., c. 1 (5th Supp.)</HistoricalNote></MarginalNote><TitleText>Income Tax Act</TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><Label>51</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The portion of subsection 241(9) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Income Tax Act</XRefExternal> before paragraph (c) is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><Subsection><MarginalNote>Threats to security</MarginalNote><Label>(9)</Label><Text>An official may provide, to <Ins>an official of the Canadian Security Intelligence Service, of the Royal Canadian Mounted Police or of the Financial Transactions and Reports Analysis Centre of Canada,</Ins></Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>publicly accessible charity information;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text><Ins>designated</Ins> taxpayer information, if there are reasonable grounds to suspect that the information would be relevant to</Text><Subparagraph><Label>(i)</Label><Text>an investigation <Ins>by the Canadian Security Intelligence Service</Ins> of whether the activity of any person may constitute threats to the security of Canada, as defined in section 2 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Canadian Security Intelligence Service Act</XRefExternal>,</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph><Label>(ii)</Label><Text>an investigation of whether <Ins>an offence</Ins> may have been committed <Ins>under</Ins></Text><Clause><Label>(A)</Label><Text><Ins>Part II.1</Ins> of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Criminal Code</XRefExternal>, <Ins>or</Ins></Text></Clause><Clause><Label>(B)</Label><Text>section 462.31 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Criminal Code</XRefExternal>, if that investigation is related to <Ins>an</Ins> offence <Ins>under Part II.1</Ins> of that Act<Ins>, or</Ins></Text></Clause></Subparagraph><Subparagraph change="ins"><Label>(iii)</Label><Text>the prosecution of an offence referred to in subparagraph (ii); and</Text></Subparagraph></Paragraph></Subsection></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Subsection 241(10) of the Act is amended by adding the following in alphabetical order:</Text><AmendedText><SectionPiece><Definition change="ins"><Text><DefinedTermEn>designated taxpayer information</DefinedTermEn> means taxpayer information — other than designated donor information — of a registered charity, or of a person who has at any time made an application for registration as a registered charity, that is</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>in respect of a financial transaction</Text><Subparagraph><Label>(i)</Label><Text>relating to the importation or exportation of currency or monetary instruments by the charity or applicant, or</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph><Label>(ii)</Label><Text>in which the charity or applicant has engaged a person to whom section 5 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Proceeds of Crime (Money Laundering) and Terrorist Financing Act</XRefExternal> applies,</Text></Subparagraph></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>information provided to the Minister by the Canadian Security Intelligence Service, the Royal Canadian Mounted Police or the Financial Transactions and Reports Analysis Centre of Canada,</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(c)</Label><Text>the name, address, date of birth and citizenship of any current or former director, trustee or like official, or of any agent, mandatary or employee, of the charity or applicant,</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(d)</Label><Text>information submitted by the charity or applicant in support of an application for registration as a registered charity that is not publicly accessible charity information,</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(e)</Label><Text>publicly available, including commercially available databases, or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(f)</Label><Text>information prepared from publicly accessible charity information and information 	referred to in paragraphs (a) to (e); (<DefinedTermFr>renseignement confidentiel désigné</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Paragraph></Definition></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection></Section><Heading level="2" type="amending"><MarginalNote><HistoricalNote> 1992, c. 20</HistoricalNote></MarginalNote><TitleText>Corrections and Conditional Release Act</TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><Label>52</Label><Text>Paragraph (a.92) in section 1 of Schedule I to the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Corrections and Conditional Release Act</XRefExternal> is repealed.</Text></Section><Heading level="2" type="amending"><MarginalNote><HistoricalNote>1995, c. 25</HistoricalNote></MarginalNote><TitleText>Chemical Weapons Convention Implementation Act</TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><Label>53</Label><Text>Subsection 17(3) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Chemical Weapons Convention Implementation Act</XRefExternal> is amended <Keep>by adding</Keep> “or” at the end of paragraph (a), by <Keep>striking out</Keep> “or” at the end of paragraph (b) and by repealing paragraph (c).</Text></Section><Heading level="2" type="amending"><MarginalNote><HistoricalNote>1997, c. 36</HistoricalNote></MarginalNote><TitleText>Customs Tariff</TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><Label>54</Label><Text>The Description of Goods of tariff item No. 9899.00.00 in the List of Tariff Provisions set out in the schedule to the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Customs Tariff</XRefExternal> is amended by striking out the reference to “Writings, signs, visible representations or audio recordings that constitute terrorist propaganda within the meaning of subsection 83.222(8) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Criminal Code</XRefExternal>;”.</Text></Section><Heading level="2" type="amending"><MarginalNote><HistoricalNote>2002, c. 1</HistoricalNote></MarginalNote><TitleText>Youth Criminal Justice Act</TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><Label>55</Label><Text>Subsection 14(2) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Youth Criminal Justice Act</XRefExternal> is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><Subsection><MarginalNote>Orders</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>A youth justice court has jurisdiction to make orders against a young person under sections 810 (recognizance — fear of injury or damage), 810.01 (recognizance — fear of <Ins>criminal organization offence</Ins>), 810.02 (recognizance — fear of forced marriage or marriage under age of 16 years) and 810.2 (recognizance — fear of serious personal injury offence) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Criminal Code</XRefExternal>. If the young person fails or refuses to enter into a recognizance referred to in any of those sections, the court may impose any one of the sanctions set out in subsection 42(2) (youth <Ins>sentence</Ins>) except that, in the case of an order under paragraph 42(2)(n) (custody and supervision order), it shall not exceed 30 days.</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>56</Label><Text>Paragraph 142(1)(a) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>in respect of an order under section 810 (recognizance — fear of injury or damage), 810.01 (recognizance — fear of <Ins>criminal organization offence</Ins>), 810.02 (recognizance — fear of forced marriage or marriage under age of 16 years) or 810.2 (recognizance — fear of serious personal injury offence) of that Act or an offence under section 811 (breach of recognizance) of that Act;</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Section><Heading level="2" type="amending"><MarginalNote><HistoricalNote>2002, c. 22</HistoricalNote></MarginalNote><TitleText>Excise Act, 2001</TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><Label>57</Label><Text>Subsection 211(6.5) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Excise Act, 2001</XRefExternal> is repealed.</Text></Section></Body></Bill>