<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><Bill bill-origin="commons" bill-type="private-public" xml:lang="en" date-time="2016-09-22 16:49:21"><Identification><BillNumber>C-307</BillNumber><Parliament><Session>1</Session><Number>42</Number><RegnalYear><Year-s>64-65</Year-s><Monarch>Elizabeth II</Monarch></RegnalYear><Year-s>2015-2016</Year-s></Parliament><LongTitle>An Act to amend the Controlled Drugs and Substances Act (tamper resistance and abuse deterrence)</LongTitle><ShortTitle status="unofficial" /><RunningHead>An Act to amend the Controlled Drugs and Substances Act (tamper resistance and abuse deterrence)</RunningHead><BillHistory><Stages stage="first-reading-house"><Date><YYYY>2016</YYYY><MM>9</MM><DD>28</DD></Date></Stages></BillHistory><BillSponsor><Emphasis style="smallcaps">Mr. Sorenson</Emphasis></BillSponsor><BillRefNumber date-time="2016-09-22">421295</BillRefNumber></Identification><Introduction><Summary><TitleText>Summary</TitleText><Provision><Text>This enactment amends the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Controlled Drugs and Substances Act</XRefExternal> to provide for regulations regarding tamper-resistant properties and abuse-deterrent formulations of controlled substances.</Text></Provision></Summary><Enacts><Provision><MarginalNote><HistoricalNote>1996, c. 19</HistoricalNote></MarginalNote><Text>Her Majesty, by and with the advice and consent of the Senate and House of Commons of Canada, <Keep>enacts</Keep> as follows:</Text></Provision></Enacts></Introduction><Body><Section type="amending"><Label>1</Label><Text>Subsection 55(1) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Controlled Drugs and Substances Act</XRefExternal> is amended by adding the following after paragraph (i):</Text><AmendedText><SectionPiece><Subparagraph change="ins"><Label>(i.1)</Label><Text>specifying controlled substances or classes of controlled substances that must have tamper-<Keep>resistant properties</Keep> or abuse-deterrent formulations;</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph change="ins"><Label>(i.2)</Label><Text>providing that the Minister may authorize any person to conduct any of the activities referred to in paragraph (a) in relation to a controlled substance or a class of controlled substances that is specified under paragraph (i.1) if the Minister is satisfied, on the basis of scientific evidence, that the substance or the substances in the class have tamper-resistant properties or abuse-deterrent formulations;</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph change="ins"><Label>(i.3)</Label><Text>respecting the issuance, suspension, cancellation, duration and terms and conditions of any authorization referred to in paragraph (i.2);</Text></Subparagraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>2</Label><Text>The Act is amended by adding the following after section 55:</Text><AmendedText><Heading level="1" change="ins"><TitleText>Reports to Parliament</TitleText></Heading><Section change="ins"><MarginalNote>Absence of regulations</MarginalNote><Label>55.1</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>If no regulations are made under paragraph 55(1)(i.1) within 12 months after the day on which this section comes into force, the Minister must cause a report stating the reasons no regulations have been made and establishing a schedule for the making of such regulations to be laid before each House of Parliament on any of the first 10 days on which that House is sitting after the expiry of that 12-month period.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Subsequent reports</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>If no regulations are made within 12 months after the tabling of the report referred to in subsection (1), the Minister must cause a report stating the reasons no regulations have been made and establishing a schedule for the making of such regulations to be laid before each House of Parliament on any of the first 10 days on which that House is sitting after the expiry of that 12-month period, and at least once every subsequent 12-month period as long as no regulations have been made.</Text></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Section></Body></Bill>