<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><Bill bill-origin="commons" bill-type="private-public" xml:lang="en" date-time="2016-01-14 15:05:37"><Identification><BillNumber>C-315</BillNumber><Parliament><Session>1</Session><Number>42</Number><RegnalYear><Year-s>64-65</Year-s><Monarch>Elizabeth II</Monarch></RegnalYear><Year-s>2015-2016</Year-s></Parliament><LongTitle>An Act to amend the Parks Canada Agency Act (Conservation of National Historic Sites Account)</LongTitle><ShortTitle status="unofficial" /><RunningHead>An Act to amend the Parks Canada Agency Act (Conservation of National Historic Sites Account)</RunningHead><BillHistory><Stages stage="first-reading-house"><Date><YYYY>2016</YYYY><MM>10</MM><DD>18</DD></Date></Stages></BillHistory><BillSponsor><Emphasis style="smallcaps">Mr. Brown</Emphasis></BillSponsor><BillRefNumber date-time="2016-01-14">421104</BillRefNumber></Identification><Introduction><Summary><TitleText>SUMMARY</TitleText><Provision><Text>This enactment establishes the Conservation of National Historic Sites Account and sets out the rules in respect of donations made for the conservation of national historic sites.</Text></Provision></Summary><Enacts><Provision><MarginalNote><HistoricalNote>1998, c. 31</HistoricalNote></MarginalNote><Text>Her Majesty, by and with the advice and consent of the Senate and House of Commons of Canada, <Keep>enacts as</Keep> follows:</Text></Provision></Enacts></Introduction><Body><Section type="amending"><Label>1</Label><Text>The <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Parks Canada Agency Act</XRefExternal> is amended by adding the following after section 22: </Text><AmendedText><Section change="ins"><MarginalNote>Conservation of National Historic Sites Account </MarginalNote><Label>22.1</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>There is established an account in the accounts of Canada to be called the Conservation of National Historic Sites Account.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Credit</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>There shall be credited to that account</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>all proceeds from a gift, bequest or other form of donation if, when making the donation, the donor indicates in writing that it is to be used for the conservation of a particular national historic site; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>an amount representing interest on the balance from time to time to the credit of the account, calculated at the rates and in the manner that the Governor in Council, on the recommendation of the Minister of Finance, prescribes.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Limit</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>No donation in respect of a particular national historic site shall be accepted if the total of the existing donations received for that site exceeds the total cost of rebuilding the site if it were completely destroyed.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Charges</MarginalNote><Label>(4)</Label><Text>There may be paid out of the account any amount paid in accordance with subsection (5).</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Amounts for conservation</MarginalNote><Label>(5)</Label><Text>Amounts that correspond to the interest credited to the Conservation of National Historic Sites Account in respect of all amounts donated for a particular national historic site, as determined by the Minister of Finance, may be used to fund the cost of conservation of that site, including</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>preservation, designed to protect, maintain or stabilize existing materials and the form and integrity of the site or of a component of the site;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>rehabilitation, designed to make possible a contemporary use of the site or of a component of the site; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(c)</Label><Text>restoration, designed to accurately reveal, recover or represent the state of the site, or of a component of the site, as it appeared at a particular period in its history.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Qualified donee</MarginalNote><Label>(6)</Label><Text>For greater certainty, with respect to all donations made under this section, the Agency is a <DefinedTermEn>qualified donee</DefinedTermEn> within the meaning of subsection 149.1(1) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Income Tax Act</XRefExternal>.</Text></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Section></Body></Bill>