<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><Bill bill-origin="commons" bill-type="private-public" xml:lang="en" date-time="2016-12-06 11:00:25"><Identification><BillNumber>C-335</BillNumber><Parliament><Session>1</Session><Number>42</Number><RegnalYear><Year-s>64-65</Year-s><Monarch>Elizabeth II</Monarch></RegnalYear><Year-s>2015-2016-2017</Year-s></Parliament><LongTitle>An Act to amend the Conflict of Interest Act (gift or other advantage)</LongTitle><ShortTitle status="unofficial" /><RunningHead>An Act to amend the Conflict of Interest Act (gift or other advantage)</RunningHead><BillHistory><Stages stage="first-reading-house"><Date><YYYY>2017</YYYY><MM>2</MM><DD>1</DD></Date></Stages></BillHistory><BillSponsor><Emphasis style="smallcaps">Mr. Boulerice</Emphasis></BillSponsor><BillRefNumber date-time="2016-12-06">421322</BillRefNumber></Identification><Introduction><Summary><TitleText>SUMMARY</TitleText><Provision><Text>This enactment amends the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Conflict of Interest Act</XRefExternal> to specify that certain contributions are gifts or other advantages and to prohibit public office holders from giving preferential treatment to a person or organization in exchange for a gift or other advantage or from accepting a gift or other advantage in exchange for a face-to-face meeting. It also prohibits public office holders from soliciting funds indirectly from a person or organization in certain circumstances.</Text></Provision></Summary><Enacts><Provision><MarginalNote><HistoricalNote>2006, c. 9, s. 2</HistoricalNote></MarginalNote><Text>Her Majesty, by and with the advice and consent <Keep>of the</Keep> Senate and House of Commons of Canada, <Keep>enacts</Keep> as follows:</Text></Provision></Enacts></Introduction><Body><Section type="amending"><Label>1</Label><Text>Paragraph (a) of the definition <DefinedTermEn>gift or other advantage</DefinedTermEn> in subsection 2(1) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Conflict of Interest Act</XRefExternal> is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>an amount of money if there is no obligation to repay it<Ins>, including a monetary contribution to a registered party or to a registered association made under the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Canada Elections Act</XRefExternal></Ins>; and</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>2</Label><Text>Section 7 of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><Section><MarginalNote>Preferential treatment</MarginalNote><Label>7</Label><Text>No public office holder shall, in the exercise of an official power, duty or function, give preferential treatment to any person or organization</Text><Paragraph><Label><Ins>(a)</Ins></Label><Text>based on the identity of <Ins>another</Ins> person or organization that represents the person or organization; or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph change="ins"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>in exchange for a gift or other advantage received from the person or organization.</Text></Paragraph></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>3</Label><Text>Section 16 of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><Section><MarginalNote>Fundraising</MarginalNote><Label>16</Label><Subsection><Label><Ins>(1)</Ins></Label><Text>No public office holder shall solicit funds<Ins>, directly or indirectly,</Ins> from any person or organization if it would place the public office holder in a <Ins>real or potential</Ins> conflict of interest.</Text></Subsection><Subsection change="ins"><MarginalNote>Meeting with public office holder</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>No public office holder shall accept a gift or other advantage from a person or organization in exchange for a face-to-face meeting with the person or a representative of the organization.</Text></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Section></Body></Bill>