<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><Bill bill-origin="commons" bill-type="private-public" xml:lang="en" date-time="2016-11-30 12:49:42"><Identification><BillNumber>C-332</BillNumber><Parliament><Session>1</Session><Number>42</Number><RegnalYear><Year-s>64-65</Year-s><Monarch>Elizabeth II</Monarch></RegnalYear><Year-s>2015-2016</Year-s></Parliament><LongTitle>An Act to provide for reporting on compliance with the United Nations Declaration on the Rights of Indigenous Peoples</LongTitle><ShortTitle status="unofficial" /><RunningHead>An Act to provide for reporting on compliance with the United Nations Declaration on the Rights of Indigenous Peoples</RunningHead><BillHistory><Stages stage="first-reading-house"><Date><YYYY>2016</YYYY><MM>12</MM><DD>14</DD></Date></Stages></BillHistory><BillSponsor><Emphasis style="smallcaps">Mr. Ouellette</Emphasis></BillSponsor><BillRefNumber date-time="2016-11-30">421324</BillRefNumber></Identification><Introduction><Summary><TitleText>SUMMARY</TitleText><Provision><Text>This enactment requires the Minister of Indian Affairs and Northern Development to table an annual report in Parliament on Canada’s compliance with the United Nations Declaration on the Rights of Indigenous Peoples.</Text></Provision></Summary><Enacts><Provision><Text>Her Majesty, by and with the advice and consent <Keep>of the</Keep> Senate and House of Commons of Canada, <Keep>enacts</Keep> as follows:</Text></Provision></Enacts></Introduction><Body><Section><MarginalNote>Short title</MarginalNote><Label>1</Label><Text>This Act may be cited as the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">United Nations Declaration on the Rights of Indigenous Peoples Reporting Act</XRefExternal>.</Text></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Report</MarginalNote><Label>2</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The Minister of Indian Affairs and Northern Development, in consultation with representatives of provincial and territorial governments and of First Nations, Métis and Inuit peoples, must prepare an annual report on Canada’s compliance, during the preceding year, with its obligations under the United Nations Declaration on the Rights of Indigenous Peoples adopted by the General Assembly of the United Nations on September 13, 2007.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Report to Parliament</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The Minister must cause the report to be tabled before each House of Parliament within the first 15 sitting days following the second of June in each year.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Coming into force</MarginalNote><Label>3</Label><Text>This Act comes into force on January 1 of the year after the year in which this Act receives royal assent.</Text></Section></Body></Bill>