<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><Bill bill-origin="commons" bill-type="private-public" xml:lang="en" date-time="2016-10-21 11:50:40"><Identification><BillNumber>C-330</BillNumber><Parliament><Session>1</Session><Number>42</Number><RegnalYear><Year-s>64-65</Year-s><Monarch>Elizabeth II</Monarch></RegnalYear><Year-s>2015-2016</Year-s></Parliament><LongTitle>An Act to amend the Controlled Drugs and Substances Act (landlord consent)</LongTitle><ShortTitle status="unofficial" /><RunningHead>An Act to amend the Controlled Drugs and Substances Act (landlord consent)</RunningHead><BillHistory><Stages stage="first-reading-house"><Date><YYYY>2016</YYYY><MM>12</MM><DD>14</DD></Date></Stages></BillHistory><BillSponsor><Emphasis style="smallcaps">Mrs. McLeod</Emphasis></BillSponsor><BillRefNumber date-time="2016-10-21">421286</BillRefNumber></Identification><Introduction><Summary><TitleText>SUMMARY</TitleText><Provision><Text>This enactment amends the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Controlled Drugs and Substances Act</XRefExternal> to provide for regulations requiring the consent of landlords to activities in leased premises in respect of controlled drugs and substances.</Text></Provision></Summary><Enacts><Provision><Text>Her Majesty, by and with the advice and consent <Keep>of the</Keep> Senate and House of Commons of Canada, <Keep>enacts</Keep> as follows:</Text></Provision></Enacts></Introduction><Body><Heading level="1"><TitleText>Controlled Drugs and Substances Act</TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote><HistoricalNote>1996, c. 19</HistoricalNote></MarginalNote><Label>1</Label><Text>Subsection 55(1) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Controlled Drugs and Substances Act</XRefExternal> is amended by adding the following after paragraph (g): </Text><AmendedText><SectionPiece><Paragraph change="ins"><Label>(g.1)</Label><Text>requiring that persons or classes of persons who intend to produce or sell any controlled substance or any class of controlled substances in leased premises obtain the written consent of the landlord, and prescribing the manner and form in which that consent is to be obtained and the conditions under which it must be renewed;</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Section><Heading level="1"><TitleText>Reports to Parliament</TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote>Absence of regulations</MarginalNote><Label>2</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>If no regulations are made under paragraph 55(1)(g.1) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Controlled Drugs and Substances Act</XRefExternal>, as enacted by section 1 of this Act, within 12 months after the day on which this section comes into force, the Minister must cause a report to be laid before each House of Parliament on any of the first 10 days on which that House is sitting after the expiry of the 12-month period, and at least once every subsequent 12-month period as long as no regulations have been made.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Content of reports</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The reports must state the reasons no regulations have been made and establish a schedule for the making of such regulations.</Text></Subsection></Section></Body></Bill>