<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><Bill bill-origin="commons" bill-type="private-public" xml:lang="en" date-time="2016-11-01 15:41:39"><Identification><BillNumber>C-339</BillNumber><Parliament><Session>1</Session><Number>42</Number><RegnalYear><Year-s>64-65-66</Year-s><Monarch>Elizabeth II</Monarch></RegnalYear><Year-s>2015-2016-2017</Year-s></Parliament><LongTitle>An Act to amend the Canadian Forces Members and Veterans Re-establishment and Compensation Act (death benefit)</LongTitle><ShortTitle status="unofficial" /><RunningHead>An Act to amend the Canadian Forces Members and Veterans Re-establishment and Compensation Act (death benefit)</RunningHead><BillHistory><Stages stage="first-reading-house"><Date><YYYY>2017</YYYY><MM>2</MM><DD>24</DD></Date></Stages></BillHistory><BillSponsor><Emphasis style="smallcaps">Ms. Mathyssen</Emphasis></BillSponsor><BillRefNumber date-time="2016-11-01">421319</BillRefNumber></Identification><Introduction><Summary><TitleText>SUMMARY</TitleText><Provision><Text>This enactment amends the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Canadian Forces Members and Veterans Re-establishment and Compensation Act</XRefExternal> to provide that the death benefit be payable to a designated family member if there are no survivors or dependent children at the time of a memberГўВҖВҷs death.</Text></Provision></Summary><Enacts><Provision><MarginalNote><HistoricalNote>2005, c. 21</HistoricalNote></MarginalNote><Text>Her Majesty, by and with the advice and consent <Keep>of the</Keep> Senate and House of Commons of Canada, <Keep>enacts</Keep> as follows:</Text></Provision></Enacts></Introduction><Body><Section type="amending"><Label>1</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The portion of subsection 57(1) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Canadian Forces Members and Veterans Re-establishment and Compensation Act</XRefExternal> before paragraph (a) is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><Section><MarginalNote>EligibilityГўВҖВүГўВҖВ”ГўВҖВүservice-related injury or disease</MarginalNote><Label>57</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The Minister may, on application <Ins>and</Ins> in <Keep>accord-</Keep>ance with section 59, pay a death benefit to a memberГўВҖВҷs survivor or a person who was, at the time of the memberГўВҖВҷs death, a dependent child <Ins>or, if there is no survivor and no such dependent child, to a designated family member,</Ins> if</Text></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The portion of subsection 57(2) of the English version of the Act before paragraph (a) is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><Subsection><MarginalNote>EligibilityГўВҖВүГўВҖВ”ГўВҖВүinjury or disease aggravated by service</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The Minister may, on application <Ins>and</Ins> in accordance with section 59, pay a death benefit to a memberГўВҖВҷs survivor or a person who was, at the time of the memberГўВҖВҷs death, a dependent child <Ins>or, if there is no survivor and no such dependent child, to a designated family member,</Ins> if</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Subsection></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>2</Label><Text>Section 59 of the Act is renumbered as subsection 59(1) and is amended by adding the following:</Text><AmendedText><Subsection change="ins"><MarginalNote>Designated family member</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>If there is no survivor and no person who was, at the time of a memberГўВҖВҷs death, a dependent child, the death benefit is payable to the family member designated by the member.</Text></Subsection><Subsection change="ins"><MarginalNote>Division of benefitГўВҖВүГўВҖВ”ГўВҖВүdesignated family member</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>If there is more than one designated family member, each designated family member is entitled to the amount obtained by dividing the death benefit by the number of designated family members.</Text></Subsection><Subsection change="ins"><MarginalNote>Regulations</MarginalNote><Label>(4)</Label><Text>For the purposes of subsection (2), the Governor in Council may make regulations</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>defining the expression ГўВҖВңfamily memberГўВҖВқ; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>prescribing the form and manner in which the designation must be made.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection></AmendedText></Section></Body></Bill>