<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><Bill bill-origin="commons" bill-type="private-public" xml:lang="en" date-time="2016-09-20 15:50:08"><Identification><BillNumber>C-347</BillNumber><Parliament><Session>1</Session><Number>42</Number><RegnalYear><Year-s>64-65-66</Year-s><Monarch>Elizabeth II</Monarch></RegnalYear><Year-s>2015-2016-2017</Year-s></Parliament><LongTitle>An Act providing for the award of a Canadian Search and Rescue Voluntary Service Medal</LongTitle><ShortTitle status="unofficial" /><RunningHead>Canadian Search and Rescue Voluntary Service Medal Act</RunningHead><BillHistory><Stages stage="first-reading-house"><Date><YYYY>2017</YYYY><MM>4</MM><DD>10</DD></Date></Stages></BillHistory><BillSponsor><Emphasis style="smallcaps">Mr. Arnold</Emphasis></BillSponsor><BillRefNumber date-time="2016-09-20">421383</BillRefNumber></Identification><Introduction><Summary><TitleText>SUMMARY</TitleText><Provision><Text>This enactment provides for the award of a medal to persons who have volunteered with a search and rescue team.</Text></Provision></Summary><Preamble><Provision><MarginalNote>Preamble</MarginalNote><Text>Whereas there are over 300 search and rescue teams with over 12,000 trained volunteers throughout Canada;

</Text></Provision><Provision><Text>And whereas it is important to recognize the work, dedication and bravery of those men and women who voluntarily spend endless hours training for and executing search and rescue missions throughout the country;</Text></Provision></Preamble><Enacts><Provision><Text>Now, therefore, Her Majesty, by and with the advice and consent <Keep>of the</Keep> Senate and House of Commons of Canada, <Keep>enacts</Keep> as follows:</Text></Provision></Enacts></Introduction><Body><Heading level="1"><TitleText>Short Title</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Short title</MarginalNote><Label>1</Label><Text>This Act may be cited as the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Canadian Search and Rescue Voluntary Service Medal Act</XRefExternal>.</Text></Section><Heading level="1"><TitleText>Medal</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Purpose of Medal</MarginalNote><Label>2</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The purpose of the Canadian Search and Rescue Voluntary Service Medal is to recognize the service of volunteers on search and rescue teams across the country.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Award of Medal</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The Governor in Council may award the Medal to any person who has volunteered with a search and rescue team and meets the qualifications set out in the regulations.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Single award</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>The Medal is not to be awarded twice to the same person.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Posthumous award</MarginalNote><Label>(4)</Label><Text>The Medal may be awarded posthumously.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Next of kin</MarginalNote><Label>(5)</Label><Text>If the Medal is awarded posthumously, it is to be presented to the next of kin of the person in whose name it is awarded or, if there is no next of kin or they cannot be readily located, to the person who is the most appropriate in the opinion of the Governor in Council.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Design of Medal</MarginalNote><Label>3</Label><Text>The Governor in Council may determine the design of the Canadian Search and Rescue Voluntary Service Medal and its associated ribbon.</Text></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Wearing of Medal</MarginalNote><Label>4</Label><Text>The Canadian Search and Rescue Voluntary Service Medal is to be worn in accordance with the applicable order of precedence of orders, decorations and medals.</Text></Section><Heading level="1"><TitleText>Regulations</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Regulations</MarginalNote><Label>5</Label><Text>The Governor in Council may make regulations</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>setting the qualifications of persons or classes of persons who may be awarded the Canadian Search and Rescue Voluntary Service Medal; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>prescribing classes of persons who are excluded from entitlement to the Medal.</Text></Paragraph></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Prerogative not affected</MarginalNote><Label>6</Label><Text>Nothing in this Act limits the right of the Governor General to exercise all powers and authorities of Her Majesty in respect of the Canadian Search and Rescue Voluntary Service Medal.</Text></Section></Body></Bill>