<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><Bill bill-type="private-public" bill-origin="commons" xml:lang="en" date-time="2016-09-14 14:32:23"><Identification><BillNumber>C-341</BillNumber><Parliament><Session>1</Session><Number>42</Number><RegnalYear><Year-s>64-65-66</Year-s><Monarch>Elizabeth II</Monarch></RegnalYear><Year-s>2015-2016-2017</Year-s></Parliament><LongTitle>An Act to amend the Aeronautics Act (aerodromes)</LongTitle><ShortTitle status="unofficial" /><RunningHead>An Act to amend the Aeronautics Act (aerodromes)</RunningHead><BillHistory><Stages stage="first-reading-house"><Date><YYYY>2017</YYYY><MM>3</MM><DD>8</DD></Date></Stages></BillHistory><BillSponsor><Emphasis style="smallcaps">Ms. Brosseau</Emphasis></BillSponsor><BillRefNumber date-time="2016-09-14">421250</BillRefNumber></Identification><Introduction><Summary><TitleText>SUMMARY</TitleText><Provision subsequent-line-indent="0"><Text>This enactment amends the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Aeronautics Act</XRefExternal> to provide for the holding of consultations before the development or expansion of an aerodrome or before any change is made to its operation.</Text></Provision></Summary><Enacts><Provision><MarginalNote><HistoricalNote>R.S., c. A-2</HistoricalNote></MarginalNote><Text>Her Majesty, by and with the advice and consent <Keep>of the</Keep> Senate and House of Commons of Canada, <Keep>enacts</Keep> as follows:</Text></Provision></Enacts></Introduction><Body><Section type="amending"><Label>1</Label><Text>The <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Aeronautics Act</XRefExternal> is amended by adding the following after section 4.87:</Text><AmendedText><Heading level="1" change="ins"><TitleText>Aerodrome Requirements</TitleText></Heading><Section change="ins"><MarginalNote>Notice</MarginalNote><Label>4.88</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>A promoter who intends to develop an aerodrome or the operator of an aerodrome who intends to expand it or to make any changes to its operation must advise the Minister and any interested parties.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Interested parties</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>For the purposes of subsection (1), the following are interested parties:</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>suppliers of air navigation services;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>local and municipal governments any part of whose territory is within 4 km of the aerodrome;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(c)</Label><Text>owners of buildings located within 4 km of the aerodrome;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(d)</Label><Text>persons likely to be directly affected by the project; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(e)</Label><Text>any other person that the Governor in Council may prescribe by regulation.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Project description</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>The promoter or operator, as the case may be, must provide the Minister and interested parties with a <Keep svc="1">description</Keep> of the project that contains the information that the Governor in Council may prescribe by regulation.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Additional information</MarginalNote><Label>(4)</Label><Text>If the Minister deems the description incomplete or imprecise, he or she may, within 10 days of its receipt, require the promoter or operator, as the case may be, to provide an amended version containing the information and specifications that the Minister requests.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Consultation</MarginalNote><Label>(5)</Label><Text>When, in the opinion of the Minister, the project description contains all the requested information, the Minister must then appoint a disinterested person to hold public consultations on the project.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Consultation fees</MarginalNote><Label>(6)</Label><Text>The promoter or operator, as the case may be, must pay the fees of the person holding the consultations and any expenses related to those consultations.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Invitation</MarginalNote><Label>(7)</Label><Text>To initiate consultations, the person holding the consultations must publish the project description and invite interested parties to submit their observations within the period and in the form set out in the invitation.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Report</MarginalNote><Label>(8)</Label><Text>The person holding the consultations must submit to the Minister and the promoter or operator, as the case may be, a report on the results of the consultations that includes specifications regarding</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>the interested parties that participated in the consultations;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>the extent to which the project respects the development plans and rules established by the province or the local, municipal or regional governments; and </Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(c)</Label><Text>the observations, in summarized form, and any measures provided for in response to those observations.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Publication of report</MarginalNote><Label>(9)</Label><Text>The Minister must post the report on the Internet site of the Department of Transportation for a minimum period of five years.</Text></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>2</Label><Text>Paragraph 4.9(k.2) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(k.2)</Label><Text>the <Ins>terms and conditions</Ins> of the consultations <Ins>provided for in section 4.88, including the applicable time periods;</Ins></Text></Paragraph><Paragraph change="ins"><Label>(k.3)</Label><Text>the aerodromes excluded from the application of section 4.88;</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Section></Body></Bill>