<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><Bill bill-origin="commons" bill-type="private-public" xml:lang="en" date-time="2017-02-13 10:18:58"><Identification><BillNumber>C-345</BillNumber><Parliament><Session>1</Session><Number>42</Number><RegnalYear><Year-s>64-65-66</Year-s><Monarch>Elizabeth II</Monarch></RegnalYear><Year-s>2015-2016-2017</Year-s></Parliament><LongTitle>An Act to amend the Canada Labour Code (pregnant and nursing employees)</LongTitle><ShortTitle status="unofficial" /><RunningHead>An Act to amend the Canada Labour Code (pregnant and nursing employees)</RunningHead><BillHistory><Stages stage="first-reading-house"><Date><YYYY>2017</YYYY><MM>4</MM><DD>6</DD></Date></Stages></BillHistory><BillSponsor><Emphasis style="smallcaps">Ms. Moore</Emphasis></BillSponsor><BillRefNumber date-time="2017-02-13">421297</BillRefNumber></Identification><Introduction><Summary><TitleText>SUMMARY</TitleText><Provision><Text>This enactment amends the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Canada Labour Code</XRefExternal> to authorize the Minister of Labour to enter into an agreement with the government of a province that provides for the application, to pregnant or nursing employees, of certain provisions of the  provincial legislation concerning occupational health and safety.</Text></Provision><Provision><Text>It also requires the Minister to prepare a report on the agreements and to cause the report to be laid before each House of Parliament.</Text></Provision></Summary><Enacts><Provision><MarginalNote><HistoricalNote>R.S., c. L-2</HistoricalNote></MarginalNote><Text>Her Majesty, by and with the advice and consent <Keep>of the</Keep> Senate and House of Commons of Canada, <Keep>enacts</Keep> as follows:</Text></Provision></Enacts></Introduction><Body><Section type="amending"><Label>1</Label><Text>The <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Canada Labour Code</XRefExternal> is amended by adding the following after section 132:</Text><AmendedText><Section change="ins"><MarginalNote>Agreement – application of provincial legislation</MarginalNote><Label>132.1</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The Minister may, with the approval of the Governor in Council, enter into an agreement with the government of a province that provides for the application, to the employees referred to in section 132, of certain provisions of the provincial legislation concerning occupational health and safety  if the Minister is of the opinion that the provincial legislation is at least as favourable to the employees as the federal legislation.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Provision not applicable</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Without prejudice to any other right conferred by this Act, by a collective agreement or other agreement, or by any terms and conditions of employment, the employee may no longer cease to perform her job under section 132 while the agreement is in force.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section change="ins"><MarginalNote>Report</MarginalNote><Label>132.2</Label><Text>Within one year after the day on which section 132.1 comes into force, and every five years after that, the Minister shall prepare a report on any agreements that are in force, under negotiation or expired, and cause it to be laid before each House of Parliament on any of the first 15 days on which that House is sitting after the report is completed.  </Text></Section></AmendedText></Section></Body></Bill>