<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><Bill bill-origin="commons" bill-type="private-public" xml:lang="en" date-time="2017-03-23 15:09:06"><Identification><BillNumber>C-348</BillNumber><Parliament><Session>1</Session><Number>42</Number><RegnalYear><Year-s>64-65-66</Year-s><Monarch>Elizabeth II</Monarch></RegnalYear><Year-s>2015-2016-2017</Year-s></Parliament><LongTitle>An Act to amend the Department of Employment and Social Development Act (persons with disabilities)</LongTitle><ShortTitle status="unofficial" /><RunningHead>An Act to amend the Department of Employment and Social Development Act (persons with disabilities)</RunningHead><BillHistory><Stages stage="first-reading-house"><Date><YYYY>2017</YYYY><MM>4</MM><DD>10</DD></Date></Stages></BillHistory><BillSponsor><Emphasis style="smallcaps">Ms. Hardcastle</Emphasis></BillSponsor><BillRefNumber date-time="2017-03-23">421381</BillRefNumber></Identification><Introduction><Summary><TitleText>SUMMARY</TitleText><Provision><Text>This enactment amends the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Department of Employment and Social Development Act</XRefExternal> to require the Minister to provide information and guidance on applications for programs and services for which persons with disabilities may be eligible and to implement a streamlined application process that, among other things, reduces the administrative burden on applicants. It also provides for reporting requirements in relation to the application process.</Text></Provision></Summary><Enacts><Provision><MarginalNote><HistoricalNote>2005, c. 34; 2013, c. 40, s. 205</HistoricalNote></MarginalNote><Text>Her Majesty, by and with the advice and consent <Keep>of the</Keep> Senate and House of Commons of Canada, <Keep>enacts</Keep> as follows:</Text></Provision></Enacts></Introduction><Body><Section type="amending"><Label>1</Label><Text>The <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Department of Employment and Social Development Act</XRefExternal> is amended by adding the following after section 7: </Text><AmendedText><Section change="ins"><MarginalNote>Persons with disabilities</MarginalNote><Label>8</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The Minister is the primary point of contact with the Government of Canada for persons with disabilities seeking access to programs and services related to disability assistance.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Access to programs and services related to disability assistance</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The Minister shall</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>provide information and guidance on applications for grants, benefits, compensation and any other programs and services for which persons with disabilities may be eligible; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>through coordination with other departments that administer programs and services for persons with disabilities, establish and implement an effective and comprehensive application process that reduces the administrative burden on applicants and prevents unnecessary overlap and duplication of effort.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection></Section><Section change="ins"><MarginalNote>Review and report</MarginalNote><Label>8.1</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Within 18 months after the day on which this section comes into force and every two years after that, the Minister shall undertake a review of the  effectiveness of the application process provided for under paragraph 8(2)(b) and prepare a report setting out his or her findings and recommendations. </Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Tabling of report</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The Minister shall cause the report to be laid before each House of Parliament on any of the first 15 days on which that House is sitting after the report is completed.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Publication</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>The Minister shall publish the report on the Department’s website within 30 days after the report has been laid before both Houses of Parliament. </Text></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Section></Body></Bill>