<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><Bill bill-origin="commons" bill-type="private-public" xml:lang="en" date-time="2017-02-10 10:34:12"><Identification><BillNumber>C-351</BillNumber><Parliament><Session>1</Session><Number>42</Number><RegnalYear><Year-s>64-65-66</Year-s><Monarch>Elizabeth II</Monarch></RegnalYear><Year-s>2015-2016-2017</Year-s></Parliament><LongTitle>An Act to amend the Importation of Intoxicating Liquors Act and the Excise Act, 2001 (importation)</LongTitle><ShortTitle status="unofficial" /><RunningHead>An Act to amend the Importation of Intoxicating Liquors Act and the Excise Act, 2001 (importation)</RunningHead><BillHistory><Stages stage="first-reading-house"><Date><YYYY>2017</YYYY><MM>4</MM><DD>11</DD></Date></Stages></BillHistory><BillSponsor><Emphasis style="smallcaps">Mr. Barlow</Emphasis></BillSponsor><BillRefNumber date-time="2017-02-10">421351</BillRefNumber></Identification><Introduction><Summary><TitleText>SUMMARY</TitleText><Provision><Text>This enactment amends the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Importation of Intoxicating Liquors Act</XRefExternal> to limit the application of its prohibitions to intoxicating liquors imported into Canada. It also makes a related amendment to the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Excise Act, 2001</XRefExternal>.</Text></Provision></Summary><Enacts><Provision><Text>Her Majesty, by and with the advice and consent <Keep>of the</Keep> Senate and House of Commons of Canada, <Keep>enacts</Keep> as follows:</Text></Provision></Enacts></Introduction><Body><Heading level="1" type="amending"><MarginalNote><HistoricalNote>R.S., c. I-3</HistoricalNote></MarginalNote><TitleText>Importation of Intoxicating Liquors Act</TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><Label>1</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Subsection 3(1) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Importation of Intoxicating Liquors Act</XRefExternal> is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><Section><MarginalNote>Prohibitions</MarginalNote><Label>3</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text><Ins>Despite</Ins> any other Act, no person shall import or cause to be imported into Canada any intoxicating liquor <Ins>unless it</Ins> has been purchased by or on behalf of, and is consigned to Her Majesty or the executive government of, the province into which it is being imported, or any board, commission, officer or other governmental agency that, by the law of the province, is vested with the right of selling intoxicating liquor.</Text></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Paragraph 3(2)(a) of the Act is repealed.</Text></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(3)</Label><Text>Subsection 3(2) of the Act is amended by striking out “and” at the end of paragraph (g) and by repealing paragraph (h).</Text></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Subsection></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>2</Label><Text>Section 4 of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><Section><MarginalNote>Burden of proof</MarginalNote><Label>4</Label><Text>The burden of proving the right to import, or to cause to be imported, any intoxicating liquor into <Ins>Canada</Ins> is on the person accused.</Text></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>3</Label><Text>Section 6 of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><Section><MarginalNote>Prosecution in place where liquor imported</MarginalNote><Label>6</Label><Text>A prosecution for any offence under this Act may be brought and carried on, and a conviction had, in the city, town or place into which any intoxicating liquor is unlawfully imported or in the place where the accused resides, but no prosecution shall be brought in any province against a person not within or residing in that province without the written approval of the attorney general of that province.</Text></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>4</Label><Text>Section 8 of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><Section><MarginalNote>Sacramental, medicinal and other purposes exempted</MarginalNote><Label>8</Label><Text>Nothing in this Act shall be deemed to forbid importing, or causing to be imported, into Canada intoxicating liquor for sacramental or medicinal purposes or for manufacturing or commercial purposes other than for the manufacture or use <Ins>of the intoxicating liquor</Ins> as a beverage.</Text></Section></AmendedText></Section><Heading level="1" type="amending"><MarginalNote><HistoricalNote>2002, c. 22</HistoricalNote></MarginalNote><TitleText>Related Amendment to the Excise Act, 2001</TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><Label>5</Label><Text>Section 59 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Excise Act, 2001</XRefExternal> is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><Section><MarginalNote>Application — <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Importation of Intoxicating Liquors Act</XRefExternal></MarginalNote><Label>59</Label><Text>For greater certainty, the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Importation of Intoxicating Liquors Act</XRefExternal> continues to apply to the importation of intoxicating liquor into <Ins>Canada</Ins>.</Text></Section></AmendedText></Section></Body></Bill>