<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><Bill bill-origin="commons" bill-type="private-public" xml:lang="en" date-time="2017-10-04 15:15:44"><Identification><BillNumber>C-374</BillNumber><Parliament><Session>1</Session><Number>42</Number><RegnalYear><Year-s>64-65-66</Year-s><Monarch>Elizabeth II</Monarch></RegnalYear><Year-s>2015-2016-2017</Year-s></Parliament><LongTitle>An Act to amend the Historic Sites and Monuments Act (composition of the Board)</LongTitle><ShortTitle status="unofficial" /><RunningHead>An Act to amend the Historic Sites and Monuments Act (composition of the Board)</RunningHead><BillHistory><Stages stage="first-reading-house"><Date><YYYY>2017</YYYY><MM>10</MM><DD>18</DD></Date></Stages></BillHistory><BillSponsor><Emphasis style="smallcaps">Mr. Aldag</Emphasis></BillSponsor><BillRefNumber date-time="2017-10-04">421440</BillRefNumber></Identification><Introduction><Summary><TitleText>SUMMARY</TitleText><Provision><Text>This enactment amends the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Historic Sites and Monuments Act</XRefExternal> to increase the number of members of the Historic Sites and Monuments Board of Canada and to provide for First Nations, Inuit and Métis representation on the Board. It also modifies the en­titlements of Board members. </Text></Provision></Summary><Enacts><Provision><MarginalNote><HistoricalNote>R.S., c. H-4</HistoricalNote></MarginalNote><Text>Her Majesty, by and with the advice and consent <Keep>of the</Keep> Senate and House of Commons of Canada, <Keep>enacts</Keep> as follows:</Text></Provision></Enacts></Introduction><Body><Section type="amending"><Label>1</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The portion of subsection 4(1) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Historic Sites and Monuments Act</XRefExternal> before paragraph (a) is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><Section><Label>4</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>There is established a Board, to be called the Historic Sites and Monuments Board of Canada, consisting of <Ins>19</Ins> members as follows:</Text></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Subsection 4(1) of the Act is amended by striking out “and” at the end of paragraph (c), by adding “and’’ at the end of paragraph (d) and by adding the following after paragraph (d):</Text><AmendedText><SectionPiece><Paragraph change="ins"><Label>(e)</Label><Text>a First Nation member, an Inuk and a Métis person, to be appointed by the Governor in Council.</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Subsection></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>2</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Subsections 5(1) and (2) of the English version of the Act are replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><Section><MarginalNote>Designation of Chair</MarginalNote><Label>5</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The Governor in Council shall designate one of the members of the Board to be its <Ins>Chair</Ins>.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Meetings</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The Board shall meet at least once in every calendar year at the call of the <Ins>Chair</Ins>, but the time and place of each meeting is subject to the approval of the Minister.</Text></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Subsection 5(4) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><Subsection><MarginalNote>Quorum</MarginalNote><Label>(4)</Label><Text><Ins>Ten</Ins> members of the Board constitute a quorum.</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Subsection></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>3</Label><Text>Section 8 of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><Section><MarginalNote>Remuneration </MarginalNote><Label>8</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Each member of the Board appointed by the Governor in Council <Ins>is to</Ins> be paid <Ins>the remuneration that</Ins> is fixed by the Governor in Council.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Travel and living expenses</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Members of the Board are entitled to be paid, <Ins>in accordance with Treasury Board directives, reasonable</Ins> travel and living expenses incurred <Ins>in the course of performing their duties under this Act while absent from their ordinary place of residence</Ins>.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Administrative costs</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text><Ins>The Chair</Ins> of the Board <Ins>and each member</Ins> of the Board appointed by the Governor in Council <Ins>is entitled to an annual allowance to be fixed by the Governor in Council in respect of administrative costs that are incurred in the course of performing their duties</Ins>.</Text></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Section></Body></Bill>