<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><Bill bill-origin="commons" bill-type="private-public" xml:lang="en" date-time="2017-09-21 11:34:11"><Identification><BillNumber>C-373</BillNumber><Parliament><Session>1</Session><Number>42</Number><RegnalYear><Year-s>64-65-66</Year-s><Monarch>Elizabeth II</Monarch></RegnalYear><Year-s>2015-2016-2017</Year-s></Parliament><LongTitle>An Act respecting a federal framework on distracted driving</LongTitle><ShortTitle status="unofficial" /><RunningHead>Federal Framework on Distracted Driving Act</RunningHead><BillHistory><Stages stage="first-reading-house"><Date><YYYY>2017</YYYY><MM>10</MM><DD>18</DD></Date></Stages></BillHistory><BillSponsor><Emphasis style="smallcaps">Mr. Eyolfson</Emphasis></BillSponsor><BillRefNumber date-time="2017-09-21">421436</BillRefNumber></Identification><Introduction><Summary><TitleText>SUMMARY</TitleText><Provision><Text>This enactment provides for the development of a federal framework to deter and prevent distracted driving. It also sets out consultation, review and reporting requirements in relation to the framework.</Text></Provision></Summary><Enacts><Provision><Text>Her Majesty, by and with the advice and consent <Keep>of the</Keep> Senate and House of Commons of Canada, <Keep>enacts</Keep> as follows:</Text></Provision></Enacts></Introduction><Body><Heading level="1"><TitleText>Short Title</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Short title</MarginalNote><Label>1</Label><Text>This Act may be cited as the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Federal Framework on Distracted Driving Act</XRefExternal>.</Text></Section><Heading level="1"><TitleText>Interpretation</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Definition of <DefinedTermEn>Minister</DefinedTermEn></MarginalNote><Label>2</Label><Text>In this Act, <DefinedTermEn>Minister</DefinedTermEn> means the Minister of Justice.</Text></Section><Heading level="1"><TitleText>Federal Framework on Distracted Driving</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Federal framework</MarginalNote><Label>3</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The Minister must, in collaboration with the Minister of Transport and the provincial governments, develop a federal framework to coordinate and promote efforts in the provinces to deter and prevent distracted driving involving the use of hand-held electronic devices, including communication devices and navigation devices. </Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Mandatory contents</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The framework must cover all of the following elements:</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>the collection of information and statistics relating to incidents that occur as a result of distracted driving involving the use of hand-held electronic devices;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>the administration and enforcement of laws respecting such distracted driving;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(c)</Label><Text>the creation and implementation of public education programs to deter distracted driving; </Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(d)</Label><Text>the role of driver-assistance technology in reducing the number of incidents that occur as a result of distracted driving;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(e)</Label><Text>the sharing among the provinces of best practices regarding deterrence and prevention;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(f)</Label><Text>recommendations regarding possible amendments to federal laws, policies and programs.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Consultation</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>In developing the federal framework, the Minister must consult with stakeholders and other interested parties, including representatives of police services, automobile associations, vehicle manufacturers and insurance companies.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Report — federal framework</MarginalNote><Label>4</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Within 18 months after the day on which this Act comes into force, the Minister must prepare a report setting out the federal framework and cause it to be tabled in each House of Parliament on any of the first 15 days on which that House is sitting after it is completed.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Publication</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The Minister must publish the report on the Department of Justice’s website within 30 days after it has been tabled in both Houses of Parliament.</Text></Subsection></Section><Heading level="1"><TitleText>Review and Report</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Review by Minister</MarginalNote><Label>5</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Within three years after the report referred to in section 4 has been tabled in both Houses of Parliament, the Minister must, in consultation with the provincial governments and the parties referred to in subsection 3(3), undertake a comprehensive review of the implementation and effectiveness of the federal framework in each province, and prepare a report setting out his or her findings and recommendations.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Tabling of report</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The Minister must cause the report of the review to be tabled in each House of Parliament on any of the first 15 days on which that House is sitting after it is completed.</Text></Subsection></Section></Body></Bill>