<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><Bill bill-origin="commons" bill-type="private-public" xml:lang="en" date-time="2017-10-16 16:03:45"><Identification><BillNumber>C-378</BillNumber><Parliament><Session>1</Session><Number>42</Number><RegnalYear><Year-s>64-65-66</Year-s><Monarch>Elizabeth II</Monarch></RegnalYear><Year-s>2015-2016-2017</Year-s></Parliament><LongTitle>An Act to amend the Department of Veterans Affairs Act (fairness principles)</LongTitle><ShortTitle status="unofficial" /><RunningHead>An Act to amend the Department of Veterans Affairs Act (principles)</RunningHead><BillHistory><Stages stage="first-reading-house"><Date><YYYY>2017</YYYY><MM>10</MM><DD>23</DD></Date></Stages></BillHistory><BillSponsor><Emphasis style="smallcaps">Mr. Brassard</Emphasis></BillSponsor><BillRefNumber date-time="2017-10-16">421452</BillRefNumber></Identification><Introduction><Summary><TitleText>SUMMARY</TitleText><Provision><Text>This enactment amends the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Department of Veterans Affairs Act</XRefExternal> to require that, in exercising his or her powers and in performing his or her duties and functions, the Minister of Veterans Affairs take into account certain principles in relation to, among others,  persons who have served in the Canadian Forces or merchant navy or in the naval, army or air forces or merchant navies of Her Majesty as well as in relation to their dependants or survivors.</Text></Provision></Summary><Enacts><Provision><Text>Her Majesty, by and with the advice and consent <Keep>of the</Keep> Senate and House of Commons of Canada, <Keep>enacts</Keep> as follows:</Text></Provision></Enacts></Introduction><Body><Heading level="1"><MarginalNote><HistoricalNote>R.S., c.V-1</HistoricalNote></MarginalNote><TitleText>Department of Veterans Affairs Act</TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><Label>1</Label><Text>Section 4 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Department of Veterans Affairs Act</XRefExternal> is renumbered as subsection 4(1) and is amended by adding the following:</Text><AmendedText><Subsection change="ins"><MarginalNote>Principles</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>In exercising his or her powers and in performing his or her duties and functions in respect of any person referred to in subparagraph (1)(a)(i), the Minister shall take into account the following principles:</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>that the person, as well as their dependants or survivors, is to be treated with dignity, respect and fairness;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>that the uniqueness of the person’s profession and of the obligations and sacrifices such a profession demands also impacts the experiences of their family; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(c)</Label><Text>that any decision regarding the care, treatment or re-establishment in civil life of the person and the benefits to be provided to them be made in a timely manner.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection></AmendedText></Section></Body></Bill>