<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><Bill bill-origin="commons" bill-type="private-public" xml:lang="en" date-time="2017-10-02 17:26:21"><Identification><BillNumber>C-380</BillNumber><Parliament><Session>1</Session><Number>42</Number><RegnalYear><Year-s>64-65-66</Year-s><Monarch>Elizabeth II</Monarch></RegnalYear><Year-s>2015-2016-2017</Year-s></Parliament><LongTitle>An Act to promote local foods</LongTitle><ShortTitle status="unofficial" /><RunningHead>Promotion of Local Foods Act</RunningHead><BillHistory><Stages stage="first-reading-house"><Date><YYYY>2017</YYYY><MM>10</MM><DD>24</DD></Date></Stages></BillHistory><BillSponsor><Emphasis style="smallcaps">Ms. Quach</Emphasis></BillSponsor><BillRefNumber date-time="2017-10-02">421411</BillRefNumber></Identification><Introduction><Summary><TitleText>SUMMARY</TitleText><Provision><Text>This enactment provides for the development of a pan-Canadian local foods strategy. It also amends the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Department of Public Works and Government Services Act</XRefExternal> to provide that, in the awarding of certain contracts, preference may be given to suppliers offering local foods.</Text></Provision></Summary><Enacts><Provision><Text>Her Majesty, by and with the advice and consent <Keep>of the</Keep> Senate and House of Commons of Canada, <Keep>enacts</Keep> as follows:</Text></Provision></Enacts></Introduction><Body><Heading level="1"><TitleText>Short Title</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Short title</MarginalNote><Label>1</Label><Text>This Act may be cited as the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Promotion of Local Foods Act</XRefExternal>.</Text></Section><Heading level="1"><TitleText>Interpretation</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Definition of <DefinedTermEn>Minister</DefinedTermEn></MarginalNote><Label>2</Label><Text>In this Act, <DefinedTermEn>Minister</DefinedTermEn> means the Minister of Agriculture and Agri-Food.</Text></Section><Heading level="1"><TitleText>Pan-Canadian Local Foods Strategy </TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Pan-Canadian strategy</MarginalNote><Label>3</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The Minister must, in collaboration with the provincial ministers responsible for agriculture and agri-food, develop a pan-Canadian local foods strategy that, among other things, provides for</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>a definition of what constitutes a local food for the purposes of the strategy;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>the creation of a forum for sharing information on best practices regarding the procurement of local foods and on the results of initiatives implemented by the provinces;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(c)</Label><Text>measures to raise public awareness of the <Keep>import­</Keep>ance of purchasing local foods; </Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(d)</Label><Text>the coordination of efforts made by producers and distributors to promote the purchase of local foods; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(e)</Label><Text>recommendations regarding possible amendments to federal laws, policies and programs.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Consultation</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>In developing the strategy, the Minister must consult with interested parties, including food producers and distributors, representatives of consumers and of farmers’ markets as well as of community groups that promote healthy living.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Report</MarginalNote><Label>4</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Within 18 months after the day on which this Act comes into force, the Minister must prepare a report setting out the pan-Canadian strategy and cause it to be tabled before each House of Parliament on any of the first 15 days on which that House is sitting after it is completed.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Publication</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The Minister must publish the report on the Department of Agriculture and Agri-Food’s website within 30 days after it has been tabled before both Houses of Parliament.</Text></Subsection></Section><Heading level="1"><TitleText>Review and Report</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Review by Minister</MarginalNote><Label>5</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Within three years after the report prepared under section 4 has been tabled in both Houses of Parliament, the Minister must, in consultation with the provincial ministers responsible for agriculture and agri-food and the parties referred to in subsection 3(2), undertake a comprehensive review of the implementation and ef­<Keep>fectiveness</Keep> of the strategy in each province, and prepare a report setting out his or her findings and recommendations.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Tabling of report</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The Minister must cause the report of the review to be tabled in each House of Parliament on any of the first 15 days on which that House is sitting after it is completed.</Text></Subsection></Section><Heading level="1" type="amending"><MarginalNote><HistoricalNote>1996, c. 16</HistoricalNote></MarginalNote><TitleText>Department of Public Works and Government Services Act </TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><Label>6</Label><Text>Section 7 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Department of Public Works and Government Services Act</XRefExternal> is amended by adding the following after subsection (2): </Text><AmendedText><Subsection change="ins"><MarginalNote>Provision of foods</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>In awarding contracts for the provision of foods, the Minister may, if appropriate, give preference to suppliers offering local foods.</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Section></Body></Bill>