<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><Bill bill-origin="commons" bill-type="private-public" xml:lang="en" date-time="2018-05-26 12:05:43"><Identification><BillNumber>C-406</BillNumber><Parliament><Session>1</Session><Number>42</Number><RegnalYear><Year-s>64-65-66-67</Year-s><Monarch>Elizabeth II</Monarch></RegnalYear><Year-s>2015-2016-2017-2018</Year-s></Parliament><LongTitle>An Act to amend the Canada Elections Act (foreign contributions)</LongTitle><ShortTitle status="unofficial" /><RunningHead>An Act to amend the Canada Elections Act (foreign contributions)</RunningHead><BillHistory><Stages stage="first-reading-house"><Date><YYYY>2018</YYYY><MM>6</MM><DD>4</DD></Date></Stages></BillHistory><BillSponsor><Emphasis style="smallcaps">Mr. Calkins</Emphasis></BillSponsor><BillRefNumber date-time="2018-05-26">421527</BillRefNumber></Identification><Introduction><Summary><TitleText>SUMMARY</TitleText><Provision><Text>This enactment amends the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Canada Elections Act</XRefExternal> to prohibit foreign contributions to third parties for election advertising purposes.</Text></Provision></Summary><Enacts><Provision><Text>Her Majesty, by and with the advice and consent <Keep>of the</Keep> Senate and House of Commons of Canada, <Keep>enacts</Keep> as follows:</Text></Provision></Enacts></Introduction><Body><Heading level="1"><MarginalNote><HistoricalNote>2000, c. 9</HistoricalNote></MarginalNote><TitleText>Canada Elections Act</TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><Label>1</Label><Text>Subsection 363(2) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Canada Elections Act</XRefExternal> is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><Subsection change="ins"><MarginalNote>ProhibitionГўВЂВЇГўВЂВ”ГўВЂВЇthird party </MarginalNote><Label>(1.1)</Label><Text>No person or entity referred to in paragraphs 358(a) to (e) shall make a contribution to a third party for election advertising purposes.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Return of contributions</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>If a registered party, a registered association, <Keep>a nomГ‚В­</Keep>ination contestant, a candidate, a leadership contestant <Ins>or a third party</Ins> receives a contribution from an ineligible contributor, the chief agent of the registered party, the financial agent of the registered association, the official agent of the candidate, the financial agent of the nomination contestant or leadership contestant or <Ins>the official representative of the third party</Ins>, as the case may be, shall, within 30 days after becoming aware of the ineligibility, return the contribution unused to the contributor or, if that is not possible, pay the amount of itГўВЂВЇГўВЂВ”ГўВЂВЇor, in the case of a non-monetary contribution, an amount of <Keep>money</Keep> equal to its commercial valueГўВЂВЇГўВЂВ”ГўВЂВЇto the Chief Electoral Officer, who shall forward that amount to the Receiver General.

</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>2</Label><Text>Section 370 of the Act is amended by adding the following after subsection (1):</Text><AmendedText><Subsection change="ins"><MarginalNote>ProhibitionГўВЂВЇГўВЂВ”ГўВЂВЇthird party </MarginalNote><Label>(1.1)</Label><Text>No person or entity referred to in paragraphs 358(a) to (e) shall make a contribution to a third party for election advertising purposes that comes from money, property or the services of another person or entity that was provided to that person or entity for that purpose.</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Section><Heading level="1"><TitleText>Coordinating Amendment</TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote><HistoricalNote>Bill C-76</HistoricalNote></MarginalNote><Label>3</Label><Text>If Bill C-76, introduced in the 1st session of the 42nd Parliament and entitled <XRefExternal reference-type="standard">An Act to amend the Canada Elections Act and other Acts and to make certain consequential amendments</XRefExternal>, receives royal assent, then, on the first day on which both section 231 of that Act and section 1 of this Act are in force, </Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>subsection 363(1.1) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Canada Elections Act</XRefExternal> is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><Subsection><MarginalNote>ProhibitionГўВЂВЇГўВЂВ”ГўВЂВЇthird party</MarginalNote><Label>(1.1)</Label><Text>No foreign entity referred to in paragraphs 358(a) to (e) shall make a contribution to a third party for the purpose of an election advertising message.</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Paragraph><Paragraph type="amending"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>subsection 370(1.1) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><Subsection><MarginalNote>ProhibitionГўВЂВЇГўВЂВ”ГўВЂВЇthird party</MarginalNote><Label>(1.1)</Label><Text>No foreign entity referred to in paragraphs 358(a) to (e) shall make a contribution to a third party for an election advertising message that comes from money, property or the services of another person or entity that was provided to that person or entity for that purpose.</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Paragraph></Section></Body></Bill>