<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><Bill bill-origin="commons" bill-type="private-public" xml:lang="en" date-time="2018-10-23 10:09:03"><Identification><BillNumber>C-419</BillNumber><Parliament><Session>1</Session><Number>42</Number><RegnalYear><Year-s>64-65-66-67</Year-s><Monarch>Elizabeth II</Monarch></RegnalYear><Year-s>2015-2016-2017-2018</Year-s></Parliament><LongTitle>An Act to amend the Bank Act, the Trust and Loan <Keep>Companies</Keep> Act, the Insurance Companies Act and the <Keep>Cooperative</Keep> Credit Associations Act (credit cards)</LongTitle><ShortTitle status="unofficial" /><RunningHead>An Act to amend the Bank Act, the Trust and Loan Companies Act, the Insurance Companies Act and the Cooperative Credit Associations Act ...</RunningHead><BillHistory><Stages stage="first-reading-house"><Date><YYYY>2018</YYYY><MM>10</MM><DD>31</DD></Date></Stages></BillHistory><BillSponsor><Emphasis style="smallcaps">Ms. Harder</Emphasis></BillSponsor><BillRefNumber date-time="2018-10-23">421546</BillRefNumber></Identification><Introduction><Summary><TitleText>SUMMARY</TitleText><Provision><Text>This enactment amends the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Bank Act</XRefExternal>, the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Trust and Loan Companies Act</XRefExternal>, the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Insurance Companies Act</XRefExternal> and the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Cooperative Credit Associations Act</XRefExternal> to implement a number of measures respecting credit card accounts.</Text></Provision></Summary><Enacts><Provision><Text>Her Majesty, by and with the advice and consent <Keep>of the</Keep> Senate and House of Commons of Canada, <Keep>enacts</Keep> as follows:</Text></Provision></Enacts></Introduction><Body><Heading level="1"><TitleText>Short Title</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Short title</MarginalNote><Label>1</Label><Text>This Act may be cited as the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Credit Card Fairness Act</XRefExternal>.</Text></Section><Heading level="1"><MarginalNote><HistoricalNote>1991, c. 46</HistoricalNote></MarginalNote><TitleText>Bank Act</TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><Label>2</Label><Text>The <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Bank Act</XRefExternal> is amended by adding the following after section 451:</Text><AmendedText change="ins"><Section><MarginalNote>Calculating interest re credit card</MarginalNote><Label>451.1</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>If, in respect of purchases of goods or services made on a credit card during a particular billing cycle, the borrower pays at least 95% of the outstanding balance owing on the credit card account on or before the due date for that cycle, the bank may only charge interest on the difference between the outstanding balance on the due date and the amount of all payments made on or before that due date.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Different interest rates</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>If different interest rates apply to different amounts owing for a particular billing cycle on a credit card account, the bank shall apply, in respect of each of those amounts, the lesser of the interest rate applicable during that billing cycle and the interest rate applicable at the time of the purchase of the goods or services.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Credit card statement</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>If a bank has issued a credit card to a natural person, the bank shall set out in the statement of account for that card, in a clear and prominent manner, the total of all amounts of interest paid by the person for the previous 12 billing cycles.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Allocation of payments</MarginalNote><Label>451.2</Label><Text>If different interest rates apply to different amounts owing for a particular billing cycle on a credit card account, the bank shall first allocate any payment made by the borrower that is greater than the minimum payment required for that billing cycle to the amount in respect of which the interest rate is highest and then allocate any remaining portion of the payment to the other amounts in descending order, based on their applicable interest rates.</Text></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Consent for increase in credit limit</MarginalNote><Label>451.3</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>A bank may not increase the credit limit on a borrower’s credit card account without first obtaining the borrower’s express consent.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Confirmation in writing</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>If the borrower’s consent to the increase is given verbally, the bank shall, not later than the date of the first statement of account that is provided after the day on which verbal consent is obtained, provide confirmation of that consent to the borrower in writing, in paper or electronic form.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Online banking – changes to account</MarginalNote><Label>451.4</Label><Text>If a bank provides online banking, it shall make available to a borrower an electronic means to decrease the credit limit on their credit card account or to close their account.</Text></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Confirmation in writing</MarginalNote><Label>451.5</Label><Text>If a borrower requests that the credit limit on their credit card account be decreased or that their account be closed, the bank shall provide the borrower with <Keep>confirm­</Keep>ation in writing – in paper or electronic form – of the decrease or closure, as the case may be.</Text></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>3</Label><Text>Section 453 of the Act is renumbered as subsection 453(1) and is amended by adding the following:

</Text><AmendedText change="ins"><Subsection><MarginalNote>Advertising re credit card</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>If the advertisement relates to a credit card, the following information shall be clearly and prominently displayed, easily legible and in distinct contrast to any other information shown on the advertisement:</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>the annual interest rate;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>the annual fees charged in connection with the credit card; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(c)</Label><Text>if there is a discount on the annual interest rate that is applicable to the credit card account, its <Keep>dur­</Keep>ation and the interest rate that is applicable once the discount ceases to apply.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>4</Label><Text>The Act is amended by adding the following after section 569:</Text><AmendedText change="ins"><Section><MarginalNote>Calculating interest re credit card</MarginalNote><Label>569.1</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>If, in respect of purchases of goods or services made on a credit card during a particular billing cycle, the borrower pays at least 95% of the outstanding balance owing on the credit card account on or before the due date for that cycle, the authorized foreign bank may only charge interest on the difference between the outstanding balance on the due date and the amount of all payments made on or before that due date.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Different interest rates</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>If different interest rates apply to different amounts owing for a particular billing cycle on a credit card account, the authorized foreign bank shall apply, in respect of each of those amounts, the lesser of the interest rate applicable during that billing cycle and the interest rate applicable at the time of the purchase of the goods or services.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Credit card statement</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>If an authorized foreign bank has issued a credit card to a natural person, the authorized foreign bank shall set out in the statement of account for that card, in a clear and prominent manner, the total of all amounts of interest paid by the person for the previous 12 billing cycles.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Allocation of payments</MarginalNote><Label>569.2</Label><Text>If different interest rates apply to different amounts owing for a particular billing cycle on a credit card account, the authorized foreign bank shall first allocate any payment made by the borrower that is greater than the minimum payment required for that billing <Keep>cycle</Keep> to the amount in respect of which the interest rate is highest and then allocate any remaining portion of the payment to the other amounts in descending order, based on their applicable interest rates.</Text></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Consent for increase in credit limit</MarginalNote><Label>569.3</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>An authorized foreign bank may not increase the credit limit on a borrower’s credit card account without first obtaining the borrower’s express consent.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Confirmation in writing</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>If the borrower’s consent to the increase is given verbally, the authorized foreign bank shall, not later than the date of the first statement of account that is provided after the day on which verbal consent is obtained, provide confirmation of that consent to the borrower in writing, in paper or electronic form.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Online banking – changes to account</MarginalNote><Label>569.4</Label><Text>If an authorized bank provides online banking, it shall make available to a borrower an electronic means to decrease the credit limit on their credit card account or to close their account.</Text></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Confirmation in writing</MarginalNote><Label>569.5</Label><Text>If a borrower requests that the credit limit on their credit card account be decreased or that their account be closed, the authorized foreign bank shall provide the borrower with confirmation in writing – in <Keep>paper</Keep> or electronic form – of the decrease or closure, as the case may be.</Text></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>5</Label><Text>Section 571 of the Act is renumbered as subsection 571(1) and is amended by adding the following:</Text><AmendedText change="ins"><Subsection><MarginalNote>Advertising re credit card</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>If the advertisement relates to a credit card, the following information shall be clearly and prominently displayed, easily legible and in distinct contrast to any other information shown on the advertisement:</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>the annual interest rate;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>the annual fees charged in connection with the credit card; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(c)</Label><Text>if there is a discount on the annual interest rate that is applicable to the credit card account, its <Keep>dur­</Keep>ation and the interest rate that is applicable once the discount ceases to apply.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection></AmendedText></Section><Heading level="1"><MarginalNote><HistoricalNote>1991, c. 45</HistoricalNote></MarginalNote><TitleText>Trust and Loan Companies Act</TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><Label>6</Label><Text>The <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Trust and Loan Companies Act</XRefExternal> is amended by adding the following after section 437:</Text><AmendedText change="ins"><Section><MarginalNote>Calculating interest re credit card</MarginalNote><Label>437.1</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>If, in respect of purchases of goods or services made on a credit card during a particular billing cycle, the borrower pays at least 95% of the outstanding balance owing on the credit card account on or before the due date for that cycle, the company may only charge interest on the difference between the outstanding balance on the due date and the amount of all payments made on or before that due date.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Different interest rates</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>If different interest rates apply to different amounts owing for a particular billing cycle on a credit card account, the company shall apply, in respect of each of those amounts, the lesser of the interest rate applicable during that billing cycle and the interest rate applicable at the time of the purchase of the goods or services.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Credit card statement</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>If a company has issued a credit card to a natural person, the company shall set out in the statement of account for that card, in a clear and prominent manner, the total of all amounts of interest paid by the person for the previous 12 billing cycles.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Allocation of payments</MarginalNote><Label>437.2</Label><Text>If different interest rates apply to different amounts owing for a particular billing cycle on a credit card account, the company shall first allocate any payment made by the borrower that is greater than the <Keep>min­</Keep>imum payment required for that billing cycle to the amount in respect of which the interest rate is highest and then allocate any remaining portion of the payment to the other amounts in descending order, based on their applicable interest rates.</Text></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Consent for increase in credit limit</MarginalNote><Label>437.3</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>A company may not increase the credit limit on a borrower’s credit card account without first obtaining the borrower’s express consent.

</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Confirmation in writing</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>If the borrower’s consent to the increase is given verbally, the company shall, not later than the date of the first statement of account that is provided after the day on which verbal consent is obtained, provide confirmation of that consent to the borrower in writing, in paper or electronic form.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Online banking – changes to account</MarginalNote><Label>437.4</Label><Text>If a company provides online banking, it shall make available to a borrower an electronic means to <Keep svc="1">decrease</Keep> the credit limit on their credit card account or to close their account.</Text></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Confirmation in writing</MarginalNote><Label>437.5</Label><Text>If a borrower requests that the credit limit on their credit card account be decreased or that their account be closed, the company shall provide the borrower with confirmation in writing – in paper or electronic form – of the decrease or closure, as the case may be.</Text></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>7</Label><Text>Section 439 of the Act is renumbered as subsection 439(1) and is amended by adding the following:</Text><AmendedText change="ins"><Subsection><MarginalNote>Advertising re credit card</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>If the advertisement relates to a credit card, the following information shall be clearly and prominently displayed, easily legible and in distinct contrast to any other information shown on the advertisement:</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>the annual interest rate;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>the annual fees charged in connection with the credit card; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(c)</Label><Text>if there is a discount on the annual interest rate that is applicable to the credit card account, its <Keep>dur­</Keep>ation and the interest rate that is applicable once the discount ceases to apply.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection></AmendedText></Section><Heading level="1"><MarginalNote><HistoricalNote>1991, c. 47</HistoricalNote></MarginalNote><TitleText>Insurance Companies Act</TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><Label>8</Label><Text>The <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Insurance Companies Act</XRefExternal> is amended by adding the following after section 481:</Text><AmendedText change="ins"><Section><MarginalNote>Calculating interest re credit card</MarginalNote><Label>481.1</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>If, in respect of purchases of goods or services made on a credit card during a particular billing cycle, the borrower pays at least 95% of the outstanding balance owing on the credit card account on or before the due date for that cycle, the company may only charge interest on the difference between the outstanding balance on the due date and the amount of all payments made on or before that due date.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Different interest rates</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>If different interest rates apply to different amounts owing for a particular billing cycle on a credit card account, the company shall apply, in respect of each of those amounts, the lesser of the interest rate applicable during that billing cycle and the interest rate applicable at the time of the purchase of the goods or services.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Credit card statement</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>If a company has issued a credit card to a natural person, the company shall set out in the statement of account for that card, in a clear and prominent manner, the total of all amounts of interest paid by the person for the previous 12 billing cycles.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Allocation of payments</MarginalNote><Label>481.2</Label><Text>If different interest rates apply to different amounts owing for a particular billing cycle on a credit card account, the company shall first allocate any payment made by the borrower that is greater than the <Keep>min­</Keep>imum payment required for that billing cycle to the amount in respect of which the interest rate is highest and then allocate any remaining portion of the payment to the other amounts in descending order, based on their applicable interest rates.</Text></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Consent for increase in credit limit</MarginalNote><Label>481.3</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>A company may not increase the credit limit on a borrower’s credit card account without first obtaining the borrower’s express consent.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Confirmation in writing</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>If the borrower’s consent to the increase is given verbally, the company shall, not later than the date of the first statement of account that is provided after the day on which verbal consent is obtained, provide confirmation of that consent to the borrower in writing, in paper or electronic form.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Online banking – changes to account</MarginalNote><Label>481.4</Label><Text>If a company provides online banking, it shall make available to a borrower an electronic means to decrease the credit limit on their credit card account or to close their account.</Text></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Confirmation in writing</MarginalNote><Label>481.5</Label><Text>If a borrower requests that the credit limit on their credit card account be decreased or that their account be closed, the company shall provide the borrower with confirmation in writing – in paper or electronic form – of the decrease or closure, as the case may be.</Text></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>9</Label><Text>Section 483 of the Act is renumbered as subsection 483(1) and is amended by adding the following:</Text><AmendedText change="ins"><Subsection><MarginalNote>Advertising re credit card</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>If the advertisement relates to a credit card, the following information shall be clearly and prominently displayed, easily legible and in distinct contrast to any other information shown on the advertisement:</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>the annual interest rate;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>the annual fees charged in connection with the credit card; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(c)</Label><Text>if there is a discount on the annual interest rate that is applicable to the credit card account, its <Keep>dur­</Keep>ation and the interest rate that is applicable once the discount ceases to apply.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>10</Label><Text>The Act is amended by adding the following <Keep>after</Keep> section 600:</Text><AmendedText change="ins"><Section><MarginalNote>Calculating interest re credit card</MarginalNote><Label>600.1</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>If, in respect of purchases of goods or services made on a credit card during a particular billing cycle, the borrower pays at least 95% of the outstanding balance owing on the credit card account on or before the due date for that cycle, the foreign company may only charge interest on the difference between the outstanding balance on the due date and the amount of all payments made on or before that due date.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Different interest rates</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>If different interest rates apply to different amounts owing for a particular billing cycle on a credit card account, the foreign company shall apply, in respect of each of those amounts, the lesser of the interest rate <Keep>applic­</Keep>able during that billing cycle and the interest rate <Keep>applic­</Keep>able at the time of the purchase of the goods or services.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Credit card statement</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>If a foreign company has issued a credit card to a natural person, the foreign company shall set out in the statement of account for that card, in a clear and promin­ent manner, the total of all amounts of interest paid by the person for the previous 12 billing cycles.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Allocation of payments</MarginalNote><Label>600.2</Label><Text>If different interest rates apply to different amounts owing for a particular billing cycle on a credit card account, the foreign company shall first allocate any payment made by the borrower that is greater than the minimum payment required for that billing cycle to the amount in respect of which the interest rate is highest and then allocate any remaining portion of the payment to the other amounts in descending order, based on their applicable interest rates.</Text></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Consent for increase in credit limit</MarginalNote><Label>600.3</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>A foreign company may not increase the credit limit on a borrower’s credit card account without first obtaining the borrower’s express consent.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Confirmation in writing</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>If the borrower’s consent to the increase is given verbally, the foreign company shall, not later than the date of the first statement of account that is provided after the day on which verbal consent is obtained, provide <Keep>con­</Keep><Keep>firmation</Keep> of that consent to the borrower in writing, in paper or electronic form.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Online banking – changes to account</MarginalNote><Label>600.4</Label><Text>If a foreign company provides online banking, it shall make available to a borrower an electronic means to decrease the credit limit on their credit card account or to close their account.</Text></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Confirmation in writing</MarginalNote><Label>600.5</Label><Text>If a borrower requests that the credit limit on their credit card account be decreased or that their account be closed, the foreign company shall provide the borrower with confirmation in writing – in paper or electronic form – of the decrease or closure, as the case may be.</Text></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>11</Label><Text>Section 601.2 of the Act is renumbered as subsection 601.2(1) and is amended by adding the following:</Text><AmendedText change="ins"><Subsection><MarginalNote>Advertising re credit card</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>If the advertisement relates to a credit card, the following information shall be clearly and prominently displayed, easily legible and in distinct contrast to any other information shown on the advertisement:</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>the annual interest rate;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>the annual fees charged in connection with the credit card; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(c)</Label><Text>if there is a discount on the annual interest rate that is applicable to the credit card account, its dur­ation and the interest rate that is applicable once the discount ceases to apply.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection></AmendedText></Section><Heading level="1"><MarginalNote><HistoricalNote>1991, c. 48</HistoricalNote></MarginalNote><TitleText>Cooperative Credit Associations Act</TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><Label>12</Label><Text>The <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Cooperative Credit Associations Act</XRefExternal> is amended by adding the following after section 385.17:</Text><AmendedText change="ins"><Section><MarginalNote>Calculating interest re credit card</MarginalNote><Label>385.171</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>If, in respect of purchases of goods or services made on a credit card during a particular billing <Keep>cycle</Keep>, the borrower pays at least 95% of the outstanding balance owing on the credit card account on or before the due date for that cycle, the retail association may only charge interest on the difference between the outstanding balance on the due date and the amount of all payments made on or before that due date.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Different interest rates</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>If different interest rates apply to different amounts owing for a particular billing cycle on a credit card account, the retail association shall apply, in respect of each of those amounts, the lesser of the interest rate <Keep>applic­</Keep>able during that billing cycle and the interest rate <Keep>applic­</Keep>able at the time of the purchase of the goods or services.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Credit card statement</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>If a retail association has issued a credit card to a natural person, the retail association shall set out in the statement of account for that card, in a clear and promin­ent manner, the total of all amounts of interest paid by the person for the previous 12 billing cycles.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Allocation of payments</MarginalNote><Label>385.172</Label><Text>If different interest rates apply to different amounts owing for a particular billing cycle on a credit card account, the retail association shall first allocate any payment made by the borrower that is greater than the minimum payment required for that billing cycle to the amount in respect of which the interest rate is highest and then allocate any remaining portion of the payment to the other amounts in descending order, based on their applicable interest rates.</Text></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Consent for increase in credit limit</MarginalNote><Label>385.173</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>A retail association may not increase the credit limit on a borrower’s credit card account without first obtaining the borrower’s express consent.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Confirmation in writing</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>If the borrower’s consent to the increase is given verbally, the retail association shall, not later than the date of the first statement of account that is provided after the day on which verbal consent is obtained, provide <Keep>con­</Keep><Keep>firmation</Keep> of that consent to the borrower in writing, in <Keep>paper</Keep> or electronic form.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Online banking – changes to account</MarginalNote><Label>385.174</Label><Text>If a retail association provides online banking, it shall make available to a borrower an electronic means to decrease the credit limit on their credit card account or to close their account.</Text></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Confirmation in writing</MarginalNote><Label>385.175</Label><Text>If a borrower requests that the credit limit on their credit card account be decreased or that their account be closed, the retail association shall provide the borrower with confirmation in writing – in paper or electronic form – of the decrease or closure, as the case may be.</Text></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>13</Label><Text>Section 385.2 of the Act is renumbered as subsection 385.2(1) and is amended by adding the following:</Text><AmendedText change="ins"><Subsection><MarginalNote>Advertising re credit card</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>If the advertisement relates to a credit card, the following information shall be clearly and prominently displayed, easily legible and in distinct contrast to any other information shown on the advertisement:</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>the annual interest rate;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>the annual fees charged in connection with the credit card; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(c)</Label><Text>if there is a discount on the annual interest rate that is applicable to the credit card account, its <Keep>dur­</Keep>ation and the interest rate that is applicable once the discount ceases to apply.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection></AmendedText></Section><Heading level="1"><TitleText>Coming into Force</TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote>Six months after royal assent</MarginalNote><Label>14</Label><Text>This Act comes into force on the day that, in the sixth month after the month in which it receives royal assent, has the same calendar number as the day on which it receives royal assent or, if that sixth month has no day with that number, the last day of that sixth month.</Text></Section></Body></Bill>