<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><Bill bill-origin="commons" bill-type="private-public" xml:lang="en" date-time="2018-06-11 08:51:04"><Identification><BillNumber>C-413</BillNumber><Parliament><Session>1</Session><Number>42</Number><RegnalYear><Year-s>64-65-66-67</Year-s><Monarch>Elizabeth II</Monarch></RegnalYear><Year-s>2015-2016-2017-2018</Year-s></Parliament><LongTitle>An Act to amend the Personal Information Protection and Electronic Documents Act (compliance with obligations)</LongTitle><ShortTitle status="unofficial" /><RunningHead>An Act to amend the Personal Information Protection and Electronic Documents Act (compliance with obligations)</RunningHead><BillHistory><Stages stage="first-reading-house"><Date><YYYY>2018</YYYY><MM>6</MM><DD>20</DD></Date></Stages></BillHistory><BillSponsor><Emphasis style="smallcaps">Mr. Erskine-Smith</Emphasis></BillSponsor><BillRefNumber date-time="2018-06-11">421526</BillRefNumber></Identification><Introduction><Summary><TitleText>SUMMARY</TitleText><Provision><Text>This enactment amends the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Personal Information Protection and Electronic Documents Act</XRefExternal> to expand the grounds on which the Privacy Commissioner may decide not to investigate a complaint. It also authorizes the Privacy Commissioner to make orders directing an organization to take any action that, in the Commissioner芒聙聶s opinion, is reasonable to ensure compliance with the organization芒聙聶s obligations under the Act. Finally, this enactment provides that an organization that is found to have failed to comply with certain obligations under the Act is liable to a fine.</Text></Provision></Summary><Enacts><Provision><Text>Her Majesty, by and with the advice and consent <Keep>of the</Keep> Senate and House of Commons of Canada, <Keep>enacts</Keep> as follows:</Text></Provision></Enacts></Introduction><Body><Heading level="1"><MarginalNote><HistoricalNote>2000, c. 5</HistoricalNote></MarginalNote><TitleText>Personal Information Protection and Electronic Documents Act </TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><Label>1</Label><Text>Subsection 12(1) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Personal Information Protection and Electronic Documents Act</XRefExternal> is amended by striking out 芒聙聹or芒聙聺 at the end of paragraph (b), by adding 芒聙聹or芒聙聺 at the end of paragraph (c) and by adding the following after paragraph (c):</Text><AmendedText><SectionPiece><Paragraph change="ins"><Label>(d)</Label><Text>having regard to all the circumstances, an investigation is not necessary or reasonably practicable.</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>2</Label><Text>Paragraph 12.2(1)(f) is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(f)</Label><Text>any of the circumstances mentioned in paragraphs 12(1)(a) to (<Ins>d</Ins>) apply; or</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>3</Label><Text>The Act is amended by adding the following after section 12.2:</Text><AmendedText><Heading level="1" change="ins"><TitleText>Compliance Orders</TitleText></Heading><Section change="ins"><MarginalNote>Compliance orders</MarginalNote><Label>12.3</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>On completing an investigation, if the Commissioner is of the opinion that the organization that is the object of the investigation has contravened a provision of Division 1 or 1.1 or has not followed a recommendation set out in Schedule 1, he or she may, by order, direct the organization to do, or to refrain from doing, anything that, in the Commissioner芒聙聶s opinion, is reasonable and necessary in order to ensure compliance with Division 1 or 1.1 or Schedule 1.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Conditions</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The Commissioner may specify any conditions in the order that he or she considers appropriate.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Copy of order</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>The Commissioner shall give a copy of the order to the organization concerned and, if the investigation was conducted in respect of a complaint filed by an individual, to that individual.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Compliance</MarginalNote><Label>(4)</Label><Text>The organization shall comply with the order within the period specified by the Commissioner in the order or, on written application by the organization within the specified period, within any longer period that the Commissioner considers reasonable in the circumstances.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Effect of filing</MarginalNote><Label>(5)</Label><Text>An order of the Commissioner under subsection (1) becomes an order of the Court when a certified copy of it is filed in that court, and it may subsequently be enforced as such.</Text></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>4</Label><Text>The portion of subsection 13(1) of the Act before paragraph (a) is replaced by the following: </Text><AmendedText><Section><MarginalNote>Contents</MarginalNote><Label>13</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text><Ins>If</Ins> the Commissioner <Ins>decides not to make an order under subsection 12.3(1) in respect of a matter that is the object of an investigation, he or she</Ins> shall, within one year after the day on which a complaint is filed or is initiated by the Commissioner, prepare a report that contains </Text></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>5</Label><Text>Subsection 14(1) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><Section><MarginalNote>Application</MarginalNote><Label>14</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>A complainant may, after receiving the Commissioner芒聙聶s report, <Ins>being notified under subsection 12(3) of a decision under paragraph 12(1)(d) that the complaint will not be investigated</Ins> or being notified under subsection 12.2(3) that the investigation of the complaint has been discontinued, apply to the Court for a hearing in respect of any matter in respect of which the complaint was made, or that is referred to in the Commissioner芒聙聶s report, and that is referred to in clause 4.1.3, 4.2, 4.3.3, 4.4, 4.6, 4.7 or 4.8 of Schedule 1, in clause 4.3, 4.5 or 4.9 of that Schedule as modified or clarified by Division 1 or 1.1, in subsection 5(3) or 8(6) or (7), in section 10 or in Division 1.1.</Text></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>6</Label><Text>The portion of subsection 18(1) of the Act before paragraph (a) is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><Section><MarginalNote>Compliance</MarginalNote><Label>18</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The Commissioner may, on reasonable notice and at any reasonable time, audit the personal information management practices of an organization <Ins>to verify compliance or prevent non-compliance with the provisions</Ins> of Division 1 or 1.1 <Ins>or the recommendations</Ins> set out in Schedule 1, and for that purpose may</Text></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>7</Label><Text>The Act is amended by adding the following after section 28:</Text><AmendedText><Section change="ins"><MarginalNote>Offence and punishment芒聙炉芒聙聰芒聙炉organization</MarginalNote><Label>28.1</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Every organization that knowingly or recklessly contravenes section 5 is guilty of</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>an offence punishable on summary conviction and liable to a fine not exceeding 
$15 million; or
</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>an indictable offence and liable to a fine not exceeding $30 million.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Aggravating or mitigating factors</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>In determining the amount of a fine to be imposed under subsection (1), the court shall consider the following:</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>the size, resources and capacity of the organization;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>the nature, gravity and duration of the contravention, taking into account the nature, scope or purpose of the organization芒聙聶s activities as well as the number of individuals affected and any loss or damage suffered by them as a result of the contravention;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(c)</Label><Text>any measures taken by the organization to mitigate the loss or damage suffered by the individuals;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(d)</Label><Text>the history of compliance with this Act by the organization; </Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(e)</Label><Text>the extent to which the organization has cooperated with the Commissioner to remedy the contravention and mitigate its adverse effects;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(f)</Label><Text>the nature of the personal information in relation to which the offence was committed; and </Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(g)</Label><Text>any other relevant factor.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Section></Body></Bill>