<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><Bill bill-origin="commons" bill-type="private-public" xml:lang="en" date-time="2018-05-02 16:49:05"><Identification><BillNumber>C-412</BillNumber><Parliament><Session>1</Session><Number>42</Number><RegnalYear><Year-s>64-65-66-67</Year-s><Monarch>Elizabeth II</Monarch></RegnalYear><Year-s>2015-2016-2017-2018</Year-s></Parliament><LongTitle>An Act to amend the Canada Shipping Act, 2001 (Compensation for Damage Due to Navigation and Shipping Activities Fund)</LongTitle><ShortTitle status="unofficial" /><RunningHead>An Act to amend the Canada Shipping Act, 2001 (Compensation for Damage Due to Navigation...</RunningHead><BillHistory><Stages stage="first-reading-house"><Date><YYYY>2018</YYYY><MM>6</MM><DD>19</DD></Date></Stages></BillHistory><BillSponsor><Emphasis style="smallcaps">Mr. Aubin</Emphasis></BillSponsor><BillRefNumber date-time="2018-05-02">421460</BillRefNumber></Identification><Introduction><Summary><TitleText>SUMMARY</TitleText><Provision><Text>This enactment amends the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Canada Shipping Act, 2001</XRefExternal> to create the Compensation for Damage Due to Navigation and Shipping Activities Fund and to authorize payments to that Fund out of the Consolidated Revenue Fund.</Text></Provision></Summary><Enacts><Provision><Text>Her Majesty, by and with the advice and consent <Keep>of the</Keep> Senate and House of Commons of Canada, <Keep>enacts</Keep> as follows:</Text></Provision></Enacts></Introduction><Body><Heading level="1"><MarginalNote><HistoricalNote>2001, c. 26</HistoricalNote></MarginalNote><TitleText>Canada Shipping Act, 2001</TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><Label>1</Label><Text>The <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Canada Shipping Act, 2001</XRefExternal> is amended by adding the following after section 268:</Text><AmendedText><Heading level="2" change="ins"><TitleText>Compensation for Damage Due to Navigation and Shipping Activities Fund</TitleText></Heading><Section change="ins"><MarginalNote>Account established</MarginalNote><Label>268.01</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>There is established in the accounts of Canada an account to be known as the Compensation for Damage Due to Navigation and Shipping Activities Fund.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Compensation</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The Minister of Transport may pay full or partial compensation to any person for loss or damage that they suffered as the result of the commission of a violation. The amount of the compensation must not exceed the <Keep>total</Keep> of the amount standing to the credit of the Fund.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Credits</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>The amounts referred to in any of paragraphs 234(1)(a) to (c) received by the Receiver General in <Keep svc="1">respect</Keep> of the commission of a violation set out in Schedule 4 are to be credited to the Fund.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Interest to be credited to Fund</MarginalNote><Label>(4)</Label><Text>The Minister of Finance must, from the Consolidated Revenue Fund, credit to the Fund interestГўВЂВЇГўВЂВ”ГўВЂВЇcalculated in the manner and at the rate determined by the Governor in CouncilГўВЂВЇГўВЂВ”ГўВЂВЇon the balance of that Fund.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Charges</MarginalNote><Label>(5)</Label><Text>On the requisition of the Minister of Transport, there is to be paid out of the Consolidated Revenue Fund and charged to the Fund the amounts required for the payment of compensation under subsection (2) and the administration of the Fund.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Amendment of Schedule 4</MarginalNote><Label>(6)</Label><Text>The Governor in Council may, by regulation made on the recommendation of the Minister of Transport, add to Schedule 4 any <DefinitionRef>violation</DefinitionRef> within the meaning of section 228 for which, as required by subsection (3), an amount must be credited to the Fund.</Text></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>2</Label><Text>The Act is amended by adding, after Schedule 3, the Schedule 4 set out in the schedule to this Act.</Text></Section><Heading level="1" type="amending"><TitleText>Compensation for Damage Due to Navigation and Shipping Activities Fund</TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote>Payments out of C.R.F</MarginalNote><Label>3</Label><Text>From the Consolidated Revenue Fund, there may, on the requisition of the Minister of Finance made on the recommendation of the Minister of Transport, be credited to the Compensation for Damage Due to Navigation and Shipping Activities Fund payments not greater than, in the aggregate, two hundred thousand dollars.</Text></Section></Body><Schedule><ScheduleFormHeading type="amending"><Label>SCHEDULE</Label><OriginatingRef>(section 2)</OriginatingRef></ScheduleFormHeading><Schedule type="normal"><ScheduleFormHeading type="normal"><Label>SCHEDULE 4</Label><OriginatingRef>(section 268.01)</OriginatingRef><TitleText>ViolationsГўВЂВЇГўВЂВ”ГўВЂВЇCompensation for Damage Due to Navigation and Shipping Activities Fund</TitleText></ScheduleFormHeading></Schedule><Provision language-align="yes"><Label>1</Label><Text>ГўВЂВѓГўВЂВ‚Section 7 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="regulation">Collision Regulations</XRefExternal>.</Text></Provision></Schedule></Bill>