<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><Bill bill-origin="commons" bill-type="private-public" xml:lang="en" date-time="2018-10-02 13:21:34"><Identification><BillNumber>C-416</BillNumber><Parliament><Session>1</Session><Number>42</Number><RegnalYear><Year-s>64-65-66-67</Year-s><Monarch>Elizabeth II</Monarch></RegnalYear><Year-s>2015-2016-2017-2018</Year-s></Parliament><LongTitle>An Act to designate the month of October as Hindu Heritage Month</LongTitle><ShortTitle status="unofficial" /><RunningHead>Hindu Heritage Month Act</RunningHead><BillHistory><Stages stage="first-reading-house"><Date><YYYY>2018</YYYY><MM>10</MM><DD>4</DD></Date></Stages></BillHistory><BillSponsor><Emphasis style="smallcaps">Mr. Obhrai</Emphasis></BillSponsor><BillRefNumber date-time="2018-10-02">421540</BillRefNumber></Identification><Introduction><Summary><TitleText>SUMMARY</TitleText><Provision><Text>This enactment designates the month of October as “Hindu <Keep>Heritage</Keep> Month”.</Text></Provision></Summary><Preamble><Provision><MarginalNote>Preamble</MarginalNote><Text>Whereas Canada is home to a large and vibrant Hindu community numbering approximately 500,000 Canadians;</Text></Provision><Provision><Text>Whereas Hindu Canadians, since the first Hindu immigrants to Canada arrived in the early 1900s, have made and continue to make significant contributions to Canada’s economic growth and social development;</Text></Provision><Provision><Text>Whereas Hindu Canadians are a peaceful and religious people whose festivals, such as Diwali, Navratri and Durga Puja, are celebrated across Canada and include, since 1998,  an annual celebration of Diwali on Parliament Hill, the first Diwali celebration to take place at a national legislature in the West;</Text></Provision><Provision><Text>And whereas designating the month of October as Hindu Heritage Month recognizes the important role played by Hindu Canadians from coast to coast while providing an opportunity for all Canadians to reflect on, celebrate and educate others about the role that Hindu Canadians play in communities across the country;

</Text></Provision></Preamble><Enacts><Provision><Text>Now, therefore, Her Majesty, by and with the advice and consent of the Senate and House of Commons of Canada, enacts as follows:</Text></Provision></Enacts></Introduction><Body><Heading level="1"><TitleText>Short Title</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Short title</MarginalNote><Label>1</Label><Text>This Act may be cited as the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Hindu Heritage Month Act</XRefExternal>.</Text></Section><Heading level="1"><TitleText>Hindu Heritage Month</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Designation</MarginalNote><Label>2</Label><Text>Throughout Canada, in each and every year, the month of October is to be known as “Hindu Heritage Month”.</Text></Section></Body></Bill>