<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><Bill bill-origin="commons" bill-type="private-public" xml:lang="en" date-time="2019-02-04 15:59:10"><Identification><BillNumber>C-429</BillNumber><Parliament><Session>1</Session><Number>42</Number><RegnalYear><Year-s>64-65-66-67-68</Year-s><Monarch>Elizabeth II</Monarch></RegnalYear><Year-s>2015-2016-2017-2018-2019</Year-s></Parliament><LongTitle>An Act to amend the Canadian Environmental Protection Act, 1999 (packaging)</LongTitle><ShortTitle status="unofficial" /><RunningHead>Zero Waste Packaging Act</RunningHead><BillHistory><Stages stage="first-reading-house"><Date><YYYY>2019</YYYY><MM>2</MM><DD>20</DD></Date></Stages></BillHistory><BillSponsor><Emphasis style="smallcaps">Mr. Cullen</Emphasis></BillSponsor><BillRefNumber date-time="2019-02-04">421574</BillRefNumber></Identification><Introduction><Summary><TitleText>SUMMARY</TitleText><Provision><Text>This enactment amends the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Canadian Environmental Protection Act, 1999</XRefExternal>, to prohibit the use of consumer product packaging unless it is made of a material that is recyclable or compostable.</Text></Provision></Summary><Preamble><Provision><MarginalNote>Preamble</MarginalNote><Text>Whereas severe environmental and ecological damage is caused by the 8 million tonnes of plastic waste that enters the oceans every year;</Text></Provision><Provision><Text>Whereas 40% of all plastics are produced for packaging and account for 50% of all plastic in landfills worldwide;</Text></Provision><Provision><Text>Whereas it is estimated that less than 11% of the plastics used in Canada are recycled;</Text></Provision><Provision><Text>Whereas the United Nations’ Sustainable Development Goals call on all countries to achieve a substantial reduction in waste generation by 2030 through the promotion of sustainable consumption and production;</Text></Provision><Provision><Text>Whereas, as part of the G7’s Ocean Plastics Charter, the Government of Canada committed to reducing plastic waste by ensuring that all plastics used in Canada are designed for reuse and recycling and to working with industry towards a goal of 100% recyc­lable, reusable or recoverable plastics by 2030;</Text></Provision><Provision><Text>Whereas the excessive use of non-recyclable and non-compostable materials for packaging consumer products makes it increasingly difficult for consumers, municipalities and recycling agencies to reduce waste;</Text></Provision><Provision><Text>Whereas the annual cost of waste management to municipalities in Canada amounts to over $3 billion;</Text></Provision><Provision><Text>And whereas the principle of extended producer responsibility has been identified by provinces and the federal government as an important tool to reduce waste and ensure a focus on recycling throughout all stages in the lifecycle of a product;</Text></Provision><Provision language-align="yes"><Text>Now, therefore, Her Majesty, by and with the advice and consent of the Senate and House of Commons of Canada, enacts as follows:</Text></Provision></Preamble></Introduction><Body><Heading level="1"><TitleText>Short Title</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Short title</MarginalNote><Label>1</Label><Text>This Act may be cited as the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Zero Waste Packaging Act</XRefExternal>.</Text></Section><Heading level="1"><MarginalNote><HistoricalNote>1999, c. 33</HistoricalNote></MarginalNote><TitleText>Canadian Environmental Protection Act, 1999</TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><Label>2</Label><Text>Section 3 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Canadian Environmental Protection Act, 1999</XRefExternal> is amended by adding the following in alphabetical order: </Text><AmendedText><SectionPiece><Definition change="ins"><Text><DefinedTermEn>consumer product</DefinedTermEn> means a product, including its components, parts or accessories, that may reasonably be expected to be obtained by an individual to be used for non-commercial purposes, including for domestic, recrea­tional and sports purposes. (<DefinedTermFr>produit de consommation</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Definition><Definition change="ins"><Text><DefinedTermEn>packaging material</DefinedTermEn> means, in relation to a consumer product, the material used to contain, identify and protect it, or to facilitate its use. It includes inner and outer containers and coverings, but does not include packaging used solely for the safe transportation of the product from the manufacturer to the seller. (<DefinedTermFr>matériel d’emballage</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Definition></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>3</Label><Text>The Act is amended by adding the following <Keep>after</Keep> section 137:</Text></Section><Heading level="1" change="ins"><Label>DIVISION 3.1</Label><TitleText>Non-recyclable and Non-compostable Packaging</TitleText></Heading><Heading level="2" change="ins"><TitleText>Packaging Material</TitleText></Heading><Section change="ins"><MarginalNote>Prohibition</MarginalNote><Label>137.1</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>No person shall sell, or offer for sale, a packaged consumer product unless its packaging material is</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>set out in Schedule 7; or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>the subject of an exemption granted under subsection 137.1(2).</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Exemption</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>On application, the Minister may, in respect of a particular consumer product, exempt any of its packaging material from the application of this Act, if the Minister is of the opinion that</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>the consumer product is used for medical pur­<Keep>poses</Keep> and no suitable alternative packaging material exists;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>the packaging material is essential to the proper delivery or functioning of the consumer product; or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(c)</Label><Text>no recyclable or compostable alternative packaging material could be used without compromising the integrity or quality of the consumer product.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection></Section><Section change="ins"><MarginalNote>Schedule of materials</MarginalNote><Label>137.2</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The Governor in Council may, on the recommendation of the Minister made under subsection (2), by regulation, add a packaging material other than a non-biodegradable plastic, to Schedule 7. </Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Consultation</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>After consulting with the provincial and municipal governments and stakeholders in the recycling industry, if the Minister is of the opinion that a sufficient number of communities and municipalities have access to facilities capable of recycling or composting a particular packaging material, he or she may recommend that it be added to Schedule 7.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>4</Label><Text>The Act is amended by adding, after Schedule 6, the Schedule 7 set out in the schedule to this Act.</Text></Section><Heading level="1"><TitleText>Coming into Force</TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote>Fixed date</MarginalNote><Label>5</Label><Text>This Act comes into force on the first anniversary of the day on which it receives royal assent.</Text></Section></Body><Schedule type="normal"><ScheduleFormHeading type="normal"><Label>SCHEDULE</Label><OriginatingRef>(Section 4)</OriginatingRef></ScheduleFormHeading><Schedule bilingual="no"><ScheduleFormHeading><Label>SCHEDULE 7</Label><OriginatingRef>(Sections 137.1 and 137.2)</OriginatingRef><TitleText>Recyclable and Compostable Materials</TitleText></ScheduleFormHeading><List><Item><Text>Paper</Text></Item></List><List><Item><Text>Glass</Text></Item></List><List><Item><Text>Corrugated fiberboard</Text></Item></List><List><Item><Text>Paperboard</Text></Item></List><List><Item><Text>Aluminum</Text></Item></List><List><Item><Text>Steel</Text></Item></List><List><Item><Text>Polyethylene Terephthalate</Text></Item></List><List><Item><Text>High-density Polyethylene</Text></Item></List></Schedule></Schedule></Bill>