<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><Bill bill-origin="commons" bill-type="private-public" xml:lang="en" date-time="2018-08-16 08:08:26"><Identification><BillNumber>C-428</BillNumber><Parliament><Session>1</Session><Number>42</Number><RegnalYear><Year-s>64-65-66-67-68</Year-s><Monarch>Elizabeth II</Monarch></RegnalYear><Year-s>2015-2016-2017-2018-2019</Year-s></Parliament><LongTitle>An Act to amend the Income Tax Act (child fitness tax credit)</LongTitle><ShortTitle status="unofficial" /><RunningHead>An Act to amend the Income Tax Act (child fitness tax credit)</RunningHead><BillHistory><Stages stage="first-reading-house"><Date><YYYY>2019</YYYY><MM>2</MM><DD>6</DD></Date></Stages></BillHistory><BillSponsor><Emphasis style="smallcaps">Ms. Leitch</Emphasis></BillSponsor><BillRefNumber date-time="2018-08-16">421535</BillRefNumber></Identification><Introduction><Summary><TitleText>SUMMARY</TitleText><Provision><Text>This enactment amends the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Income Tax Act</XRefExternal> in order to establish the child fitness tax credit.</Text></Provision></Summary><Enacts><Provision><Text>Her Majesty, by and with the advice and consent <Keep>of the</Keep> Senate and House of Commons of Canada, <Keep>enacts</Keep> as follows:</Text></Provision></Enacts></Introduction><Body><Heading level="1"><MarginalNote><HistoricalNote>R.S., c. 1 (5th Supp.)</HistoricalNote></MarginalNote><TitleText>Income Tax Act</TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><Label>1</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Income Tax Act</XRefExternal> is amended by adding the following after section 118.01:</Text><AmendedText change="ins"><Section><MarginalNote>Definitions</MarginalNote><Label>118.02</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The following definitions apply in this section.</Text><Definition change="ins"><Text><DefinedTermEn>eligible fitness expense</DefinedTermEn>, in respect of a qualifying child of an individual for a taxation year, means the amount of a fee paid to a qualifying entity (other than an amount paid to a person that is, at the time the amount is paid, the individual芒聙聶s spouse or common-law partner or an脗颅<Keep>other</Keep> individual who is under 18 years of age), to the extent that the fee is attributable to the cost of registration or membership of the qualifying child in a prescribed program of physical activity and, for the purposes of this section, that cost</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>includes the cost to the qualifying entity of the program in respect of its administration, instruction, rental of required facilities, and uniforms and equipment that cannot be acquired by a participant in the program for an amount less than their fair market <Keep>value</Keep> at the time, if any, they are so acquired; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>does not include</Text><Subparagraph><Label>(i)</Label><Text>the cost of accommodation, travel, food or beverages, or</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph><Label>(ii)</Label><Text>any amount deductible under section 63 in computing any person芒聙聶s income for any taxation year. (<DefinedTermFr>d脙漏pense admissible pour activit脙漏s physiques</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Subparagraph></Paragraph></Definition><Definition change="ins"><Text><DefinedTermEn>qualifying child</DefinedTermEn>芒聙聜of an individual for a taxation year means a child of the individual who is, at the beginning of the taxation year,</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>under 18 years of age; or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>under 21 years of age, if the child is a person in respect of whom an amount is deductible under section 118.3 in computing any person芒聙聶s tax payable under this Part for the taxation year. (<DefinedTermFr>enfant admissible</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Paragraph></Definition><Definition change="ins"><Text><DefinedTermEn>qualifying entity</DefinedTermEn>芒聙聜means a person or partnership that offers one or more prescribed programs of physical activity. (<DefinedTermFr>entit脙漏 admissible</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Definition></Subsection><Subsection change="ins"><MarginalNote>Child fitness tax credit</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>For the purpose of computing the tax payable under this Part by an individual for a taxation year, there may be deducted the amount determined by the formula</Text><FormulaGroup><Formula><FormulaText>A 脙聴 B</FormulaText></Formula><FormulaConnector>where</FormulaConnector></FormulaGroup><FormulaDefinition><FormulaTerm>A</FormulaTerm><Text>is the appropriate percentage for the taxation year; and</Text></FormulaDefinition><FormulaDefinition><FormulaTerm>B</FormulaTerm><Text>is the total of all amounts each of which is, in respect of a qualifying child of the individual for the taxation year, the lesser of $500 and the amount determined by the formula</Text><FormulaGroup><Formula><FormulaText>C 芒聙聯 D</FormulaText></Formula><FormulaConnector>where</FormulaConnector></FormulaGroup></FormulaDefinition><FormulaDefinition indent-level="1.5"><FormulaTerm>C</FormulaTerm><Text>is the total of all amounts each of which is an amount paid in the taxation year by the individ脗颅ual, or by the individual芒聙聶s spouse or common law partner, that is an eligible fitness expense in respect of the qualifying child of the individual, and</Text></FormulaDefinition><FormulaDefinition indent-level="1.5"><FormulaTerm>D</FormulaTerm><Text>is the total of all amounts that any person is or was entitled to receive, each of which relates to an amount included in computing the value of C in respect of the qualifying child that is the amount of a reimbursement, allowance or any other form of assistance (other than an amount that is included in computing the income for any taxation year of that person and that is not deductible in computing the taxable income of that person).</Text></FormulaDefinition></Subsection><Subsection change="ins"><MarginalNote>Child fitness tax credit芒聙炉芒聙聰芒聙炉child with disability</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>For the purpose of computing the tax payable under this Part by an individual for a taxation year there may be deducted in respect of a qualifying child of the individual an amount equal to $1000 multiplied by the appropriate percentage for the taxation year if</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>the amount referred to in the description of B in subsection (2) is $100 or more; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>an amount is deductible in respect of the qualifying child under section 118.3 in computing any person芒聙聶s tax payable under this Part for the taxation year.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection change="ins"><MarginalNote>Apportionment of credit</MarginalNote><Label>(4)</Label><Text>If more than one individual is entitled to a deduction under this section for a taxation year in respect of a qualifying child, the total of all amounts so deductible shall not exceed the maximum amount that would be so deductible for the year by any one of those individuals in respect of that qualifying child if that individual were the only individual entitled to deduct an amount for the year under this section in respect of that qualifying child, and if the individuals cannot agree as to what portion of the amount each can so deduct, the Minister may fix the portions.</Text></Subsection><Subsection type="amending" change="off"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Subsection (1) applies to the 2019 and subsequent taxation years.</Text></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Subsection></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>2</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Section 118.92 of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><Section><MarginalNote>Ordering of credits</MarginalNote><Label>118.92</Label><Text>In computing an individual芒聙聶s tax payable under this Part, the following provisions shall be applied in the following order: subsections 118(1) and (2), section 118.7, subsections 118(3) and (10) and sections 118.01, <Ins>118.02</Ins>, 118.04, 118.041, 118.05, 118.06, 118.07, 118.3, 118.61, 118.5, 118.9, 118.8, 118.2, 118.1, 118.62 and 121.</Text></Section></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Subsection (1) applies to the 2019 and subsequent taxation years.</Text></Subsection></Section></Body></Bill>