<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><Bill bill-origin="commons" bill-type="private-public" xml:lang="en" date-time="2018-12-11 09:19:55"><Identification><BillNumber>C-436</BillNumber><Parliament><Session>1</Session><Number>42</Number><RegnalYear><Year-s>64-65-66-67-68</Year-s><Monarch>Elizabeth II</Monarch></RegnalYear><Year-s>2015-2016-2017-2018-2019</Year-s></Parliament><LongTitle>An Act to establish Acromegaly Awareness Day</LongTitle><ShortTitle status="unofficial" /><RunningHead>Acromegaly Awareness Day Act</RunningHead><BillHistory><Stages stage="first-reading-house"><Date><YYYY>2019</YYYY><MM>2</MM><DD>28</DD></Date></Stages></BillHistory><BillSponsor><Emphasis style="smallcaps">Mr. Strahl</Emphasis></BillSponsor><BillRefNumber date-time="2018-12-11">421479</BillRefNumber></Identification><Introduction><Summary><TitleText>SUMMARY</TitleText><Provision><Text>This enactment establishes the first day of November, in each year, as “Acromegaly Awareness Day”.</Text></Provision></Summary><Preamble><Provision><MarginalNote>Preamble</MarginalNote><Text>Whereas acromegaly is a rare condition resulting from excessive production of growth hormone, most commonly caused by a benign tumour in the pituitary gland;</Text></Provision><Provision><Text>Whereas the condition causes abnormal growth of bones, characterized by enlargement of a person’s hands and feet, and changes in facial features;</Text></Provision><Provision><Text>Whereas because acromegaly is uncommon and physical changes occur gradually, the condition is difficult to diagnose and may not be recognized for years;</Text></Provision><Provision><Text>Whereas a failure to promptly diagnose and treat acromegaly can lead to serious illnesses that can become life-threatening;</Text></Provision><Provision><Text>And whereas the Parliament of Canada wishes to increase awareness among Canadians of acromegaly and the key role that early diagnosis and treatment of the condition plays in reducing the risk of complications for affected individuals and in improving their symptoms, as well as in helping them to obtain the support they and their families need;</Text></Provision><Provision language-align="yes"><Text>Now, therefore, Her Majesty, by and with the advice and consent of the Senate and House of Commons of Canada, enacts as follows:</Text></Provision></Preamble></Introduction><Body><Heading level="1"><TitleText>Short Title</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Short title</MarginalNote><Label>1</Label><Text>This Act may be cited as the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Acromegaly Awareness Day Act</XRefExternal>.</Text></Section><Heading level="1"><TitleText>Acromegaly Awareness Day </TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Designation</MarginalNote><Label>2</Label><Text>Throughout Canada, in each year, the first day of November is to be known as “Acromegaly Awareness Day”.</Text></Section></Body></Bill>