<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><Bill bill-origin="commons" bill-type="private-public" xml:lang="en" date-time="2019-01-28 12:11:03"><Identification><BillNumber>C-435</BillNumber><Parliament><Session>1</Session><Number>42</Number><RegnalYear><Year-s>64-65-66-67-68</Year-s><Monarch>Elizabeth II</Monarch></RegnalYear><Year-s>2015-2016-2017-2018-2019</Year-s></Parliament><LongTitle>An Act to establish Rare Disease Day</LongTitle><ShortTitle status="unofficial" /><RunningHead>Rare Disease Day Act</RunningHead><BillHistory><Stages stage="first-reading-house"><Date><YYYY>2019</YYYY><MM>2</MM><DD>28</DD></Date></Stages></BillHistory><BillSponsor><Emphasis style="smallcaps">Mr. Kmiec</Emphasis></BillSponsor><BillRefNumber date-time="2019-01-28">421576</BillRefNumber></Identification><Introduction><Summary><TitleText>SUMMARY</TitleText><Provision><Text>This enactment designates the last day in February in each year as Rare Disease Day.</Text></Provision></Summary><Preamble><Provision><MarginalNote>Preamble</MarginalNote><Text>Whereas millions of Canadians, two thirds of them children, are affected by one of over 7,000 rare diseases; </Text></Provision><Provision><Text>Whereas Canadians living with a rare disease often face lengthy delays and barriers in the approval process for rare disease treatments or orphan drugs and only one in every three Canadians living with a rare disease is able to access the treatments that they need;</Text></Provision><Provision><Text>Whereas a national Rare Disease Day would mobilize governments, as well as health and research commun­ities, to continue to fund new research into rare diseases and to develop new treatments and ther­apies for Canadians living with a rare disease;</Text></Provision><Provision><Text>And whereas increased awareness about rare diseases would strengthen community support and mobilize resources for Canadians living with a rare disease;</Text></Provision></Preamble><Enacts><Provision><Text>Now, therefore, Her Majesty, by and with the advice and consent of the Senate and House of Commons of Canada, enacts as follows:</Text></Provision></Enacts></Introduction><Body><Heading level="1"><TitleText>Short Title</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Short title</MarginalNote><Label>1</Label><Text>This Act may be cited as the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Rare Disease Day Act</XRefExternal>.</Text></Section><Heading level="1"><TitleText>Rare Disease Day</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Designation</MarginalNote><Label>2</Label><Text>Throughout Canada, in each year, the last day in February is to be known as Rare Disease Day.</Text></Section></Body></Bill>