<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><Bill bill-origin="commons" bill-type="private-public" xml:lang="en" date-time="2019-04-04 15:03:03"><Identification><BillNumber>C-445</BillNumber><Parliament><Session>1</Session><Number>42</Number><RegnalYear><Year-s>64-65-66-67-68</Year-s><Monarch>Elizabeth II</Monarch></RegnalYear><Year-s>2015-2016-2017-2018-2019</Year-s></Parliament><LongTitle>An Act to amend the Parliament of Canada Act (management and direction of the Parliamentary Protect­ive Service)</LongTitle><ShortTitle status="unofficial" /><RunningHead>An Act to amend the Parliament of Canada Act (management and direction of the Parliamentary Protective Service)</RunningHead><BillHistory><Stages stage="first-reading-house"><Date><YYYY>2019</YYYY><MM>5</MM><DD>3</DD></Date></Stages></BillHistory><BillSponsor><Emphasis style="smallcaps">Mr. Graham</Emphasis></BillSponsor><BillRefNumber date-time="2019-04-04">421584</BillRefNumber></Identification><Introduction><Summary><TitleText>SUMMARY</TitleText><Provision><Text>This enactment amends the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Parliament of Canada Act</XRefExternal> to update the framework for the exercise of the power of the Speaker of the Senate and the Speaker of the House of Commons to ensure the physical security services throughout the parliamentary precinct and Parliament Hill and to add a restriction on who may be appointed as Director of the Parliamentary Protective Service.</Text></Provision></Summary><Enacts><Provision><Text>Her Majesty, by and with the advice and consent <Keep>of the</Keep> Senate and House of Commons of Canada, <Keep>enacts</Keep> as follows:</Text></Provision></Enacts></Introduction><Body><Heading level="1"><MarginalNote><HistoricalNote>1985, c. P-1</HistoricalNote></MarginalNote><TitleText>Parliament of Canada Act</TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><Label>1</Label><Text>Sections 79.54 to 79.56 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Parliament of Canada Act</XRefExternal> are replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><Section><MarginalNote>Director</MarginalNote><Label>79.54</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>There shall be a Director of the Parliamentary Protective Service who shall lead the integrated security operations throughout the parliamentary precinct and Parliament Hill under the joint general policy direction of the Speaker of the Senate and the Speaker of the House of Commons.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Control and management of Service</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The Director has the control and management of the Service.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Appointment</MarginalNote><Label>79.55</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text><Ins>The Speaker of the Senate and the Speaker of the House of Commons shall jointly appoint</Ins> a person to act as the Director of the Parliamentary Protective Service. <Ins>They</Ins> shall also <Ins>designate</Ins> a person — identified by name or position — to act as the Director on an interim basis if the Director is absent or incapacitated or if the office of Dir­ector is vacant and <Ins>specify</Ins> the maximum per­<Keep>iod</Keep> that the person may act as the Director on an interim basis.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Restriction</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The Director, or the person acting as the Director on an interim basis, must <Ins>not</Ins> be a <DefinitionRef>member</DefinitionRef> as that term is defined in subsection 2(1) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Royal Canadian Mounted Police Act</XRefExternal>.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section change="ins"><MarginalNote>Remuneration</MarginalNote><Label>79.56</Label><Text>The Director shall be paid the remuneration and expenses fixed by the Speaker of the Senate and the Speaker of the House of Commons.</Text></Section></AmendedText></Section><Heading level="1" type="amending"><TitleText>Coming into Force</TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote>Earlier of the days</MarginalNote><Label>2</Label><Text>This Act comes into force on the third anniversary of the day on which it receives royal assent or on any earlier day that may be fixed by order of the Governor in Council.</Text></Section></Body></Bill>