<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><Bill bill-origin="commons" bill-type="private-public" xml:lang="en" date-time="2018-12-05 15:28:37"><Identification><BillNumber>C-449</BillNumber><Parliament><Session>1</Session><Number>42</Number><RegnalYear><Year-s>64-65-66-67-68</Year-s><Monarch>Elizabeth II</Monarch></RegnalYear><Year-s>2015-2016-2017-2018-2019</Year-s></Parliament><LongTitle>An Act to amend the Old Age Security Act (monthly guaranteed income supplement)</LongTitle><ShortTitle status="unofficial" /><RunningHead>An Act to amend the Old Age Security Act (monthly guaranteed income supplement)</RunningHead><BillHistory><Stages stage="first-reading-house"><Date><YYYY>2019</YYYY><MM>5</MM><DD>16</DD></Date></Stages></BillHistory><BillSponsor><Emphasis style="smallcaps">Ms. Blaney</Emphasis></BillSponsor><BillRefNumber date-time="2018-12-05">421563</BillRefNumber></Identification><Introduction><Summary><TitleText>SUMMARY</TitleText><Provision><Text>This enactment amends the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Old Age Security Act</XRefExternal> to require the Minister of Employment and Social Development to estimate, for the purposes of the monthly guaranteed income supplement payable to a pensioner, the income for the applicable calendar year of a pensioner who does not comply with the requirement to make a statement of their income for that year. The enactment also requires the Minister to provide the information and resources necessary to reduce the administrative burden on the person in relation to the requirement to make the statement.</Text></Provision></Summary><Enacts><Provision><Text>Her Majesty, by and with the advice and consent <Keep>of the</Keep> Senate and House of Commons of Canada, <Keep>enacts</Keep> as follows:</Text></Provision></Enacts></Introduction><Body><Heading level="1"><MarginalNote><HistoricalNote>R.S., c. O-9</HistoricalNote></MarginalNote><TitleText>Old Age Security Act</TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><Label>1</Label><Text>Section 14 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Old Age Security Act</XRefExternal> is amended by adding the following after subsection (1.01):</Text><AmendedText><Subsection change="ins"><MarginalNote>Estimate of person’s income</MarginalNote><Label>(1.02)</Label><Text>If a person who received a supplement in respect of the previous base calendar year does not make the statement required under subsection (1) and no information has been made available to the Minister under subsection (1.01) in respect of that person, the Minister shall estimate the person’s income for the base calendar year using the person’s income for that previous base calendar year.</Text></Subsection><Subsection change="ins"><MarginalNote>Previous payment period</MarginalNote><Label>(1.03)</Label><Text>Subsection (1.02) does not apply if the person did not make the statement in respect of the previous payment period.</Text></Subsection><Subsection change="ins"><MarginalNote>Notice</MarginalNote><Label>(1.04)</Label><Text>If an estimate is made for a person in accordance with subsection (1.02), the Minister shall advise the Canada Revenue Agency.</Text></Subsection><Subsection change="ins"><MarginalNote>Reduction of administrative burden</MarginalNote><Label>(1.05)</Label><Text>The Minister shall provide, to the person whose income has been estimated, the information and resources necessary to reduce their administrative burden in relation to the requirement to make a statement of their income. </Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>2</Label><Text>Section 34 of the Act is amended by adding the following after paragraph (c):</Text><AmendedText><SectionPiece><Paragraph change="ins"><Label>(c.1)</Label><Text>prescribing, for the purposes of subsection 14(1.05), the information and resources that must be made available to a person described in subsection 14(1.02);</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Section></Body></Bill>