<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><Bill bill-origin="commons" bill-type="private-public" xml:lang="en" date-time="2018-03-29 10:15:41"><Identification><BillNumber>C-444</BillNumber><Parliament><Session>1</Session><Number>42</Number><RegnalYear><Year-s>64-65-66-67-68</Year-s><Monarch>Elizabeth II</Monarch></RegnalYear><Year-s>2015-2016-2017-2018-2019</Year-s></Parliament><LongTitle>An Act to amend the International Boundary Waters Treaty Act (water quality)</LongTitle><ShortTitle status="unofficial" /><RunningHead>An Act to amend the International Boundary Waters Treaty Act (water quality)</RunningHead><BillHistory><Stages stage="first-reading-house"><Date><YYYY>2019</YYYY><MM>5</MM><DD>1</DD></Date></Stages></BillHistory><BillSponsor><Emphasis style="smallcaps">Mr. Paradis</Emphasis></BillSponsor><BillRefNumber date-time="2018-03-29">421433</BillRefNumber></Identification><Introduction><Summary><TitleText>SUMMARY</TitleText><Provision><Text>This enactment requires the Minister of Foreign Affairs to undertake steps toward the possible amendment of the International Boundary Waters Treaty in order that not only the natural level and flow of boundary waters are taken into account, but also their quality.</Text></Provision></Summary><Enacts><Provision><Text>Her Majesty, by and with the advice and consent <Keep>of the</Keep> Senate and House of Commons of Canada, <Keep>enacts</Keep> as follows:</Text></Provision></Enacts></Introduction><Body><Heading level="1"><MarginalNote><HistoricalNote>R.S., c. I-17</HistoricalNote></MarginalNote><TitleText>International Boundary Waters Treaty Act</TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><Label>1</Label><Text>The <XRefExternal reference-type="act">International Boundary Waters Treaty Act</XRefExternal> is amended by adding the following after section 42:</Text><AmendedText><Heading level="1" change="ins"><TitleText>Quality of Boundary Waters</TitleText></Heading><Section change="ins"><MarginalNote>Boundary waters treaty</MarginalNote><Label>42.1</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The Minister shall undertake steps toward the possible amendment of the treaty in order that the qual­ity of boundary waters is taken into account.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Consultation and measures — water quality</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The Minister shall also consult the International Joint Commission, representatives of the provinces responsible for the environment and environmental experts or specialists concerning the measures that should be taken to ensure the quality of boundary waters, including measures to establish buffer zones and prohibit the construction of infrastructures likely to affect the quality of waters bordering them without the agreement of the parties to the treaty.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Annual report</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>Within two years after the day on which this section comes into force, and every year after that, the Minister shall prepare a report indicating the steps undertaken under this section during the period covered by the report, and the Minister shall cause the report to be laid before each House of Parliament on any of the first 15 days on which that House is sitting after the report is prepared.</Text></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Section></Body></Bill>