<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><Bill bill-origin="commons" bill-type="private-public" xml:lang="en" date-time="2019-01-15 12:37:49"><Identification><BillNumber>C-450</BillNumber><Parliament><Session>1</Session><Number>42</Number><RegnalYear><Year-s>64-65-66-67-68</Year-s><Monarch>Elizabeth II</Monarch></RegnalYear><Year-s>2015-2016-2017-2018-2019</Year-s></Parliament><LongTitle>An Act to amend the Canada Health Act</LongTitle><ShortTitle status="unofficial" /><RunningHead>An Act to amend the Canada Health Act</RunningHead><BillHistory><Stages stage="first-reading-house"><Date><YYYY>2019</YYYY><MM>5</MM><DD>16</DD></Date></Stages></BillHistory><BillSponsor><Emphasis style="smallcaps">Ms. Leitch</Emphasis></BillSponsor><BillRefNumber date-time="2019-01-15">421498</BillRefNumber></Identification><Introduction><Summary><TitleText>SUMMARY</TitleText><Provision><Text>This enactment amends the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Canada Health Act</XRefExternal> to add to the requirements that a province must meet in order to qualify for a full cash contribution the criterion of accountability in relation to the timely delivery of health  services. It also provides for the referral of certain defaults to arbitration for determination. </Text></Provision></Summary><Enacts><Provision><Text>Her Majesty, by and with the advice and consent <Keep>of the</Keep> Senate and House of Commons of Canada, <Keep>enacts</Keep> as follows:</Text></Provision></Enacts></Introduction><Body><Heading level="1"><MarginalNote><HistoricalNote>R.S., c. C-6</HistoricalNote></MarginalNote><TitleText>Canada Health Act</TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><Label>1</Label><Text>The <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Canada Health Act</XRefExternal> is amended by adding the following after section 7:</Text><AmendedText><Section change="ins"><MarginalNote>Additional criterion 芒聙聰 accountability</MarginalNote><Label>7.1</Label><Text>In addition to meeting the other requirements of this Act, in order that a province may qualify for a full cash contribution referred to in section 5 for a fiscal year, the law of the province must, throughout the fiscal year, satis脗颅fy the criterion described in section 12.1 respecting accountability.</Text></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>2</Label><Text>The Act is amended by adding the following <Keep>after</Keep> section 12:</Text><AmendedText><Section change="ins"><MarginalNote>Accountability</MarginalNote><Label>12.1</Label><Text>In order to satisfy the criterion respecting accountability, the law of a province</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>must provide for measures to ensure that insured health services are delivered in a timely manner that meets reasonable standards of care;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>must provide that legal proceedings may be brought against the government of the province in respect of insured health services that are not delivered in a timely manner; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(c)</Label><Text>must permit an insured person to receive hospital services, physician services or surgical-dental services that are provided outside the health care insurance plan of the province if there is no reasonable access to care under the plan.</Text></Paragraph></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>3</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Subsection 14(1) of the Act is replaced by the following:  </Text><AmendedText><Section><MarginalNote>Referral to arbitration</MarginalNote><Label>14</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Subject to subsection (3), the Minister shall refer a matter to <Ins>arbitration if</Ins> the Minister, after consultation in accordance with subsection (2) with the minister responsible for health care in a province, is of the opinion that <Ins>a default described in any of paragraphs (a) to (c) is occurring in the province</Ins> and the province has not given an undertaking satisfactory to the Minister to remedy the default within a period that the Minister considers reasonable:</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>the health care insurance plan of the province does not or has ceased to satisfy any one of the criteria described in sections 8 to 12; </Text></Paragraph><Paragraph change="ins"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>the law of a province does not or has ceased to satis脗颅fy the criterion described in section 12.1; or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label><Ins>(c)</Ins></Label><Text>the province has failed to comply with any condition set out in section 13.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The portion of subsection 14(2) of the Act before paragraph (a) is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><Subsection><MarginalNote>Consultation process</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Before referring a matter to <Ins>arbitration</Ins> under subsection (1) in respect of a province, the Minister shall</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(3)</Label><Text>Subsection 14(3) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><Subsection><MarginalNote>When no consultation can be achieved</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>The Minister may act without consultation under subsection (1) if the Minister is of the opinion that a sufficient time has expired after reasonable efforts to achieve consultation and that consultation will not be achieved. <Ins>However, the Minister shall first notify in writing the minister responsible for health care in the province that the matter is to be referred to arbitration</Ins>.</Text></Subsection><Subsection change="ins"><MarginalNote>Request</MarginalNote><Label>(4)</Label><Text>On referring a matter to arbitration, the Minister shall make a written request to the chief justice of the superior court of the province in which the matter arises to appoint a judge of that court to act as arbitrator.</Text></Subsection><Subsection change="ins"><MarginalNote>Appointment of arbitrator </MarginalNote><Label>(5)</Label><Text>Within a reasonable period after receipt of a request referred to in subsection (4), the chief justice shall, after any inquiry that  he or she considers necessary, appoint a judge as arbitrator.</Text></Subsection><Subsection change="ins"><MarginalNote>Joint statement</MarginalNote><Label>(6)</Label><Text>On the appointment of an arbitrator, the parties shall prepare a joint statement of the issues in dispute and shall submit that statement to the arbitrator.</Text></Subsection><Subsection change="ins"><MarginalNote>Hearing</MarginalNote><Label>(7)</Label><Text>Within 21 days after being appointed, the arbitrator shall hold a hearing.</Text></Subsection><Subsection change="ins"><MarginalNote>Determination</MarginalNote><Label>(8)</Label><Text>Within 60 days after being appointed, the arbitrator shall determine whether a default described in any of paragraphs (1)(a) to (c) is occurring in the province and advise the Minister of his or her determination.</Text></Subsection><Subsection change="ins"><MarginalNote><XRefExternal reference-type="act">Judges Act</XRefExternal></MarginalNote><Label>(9)</Label><Text>Subsection 57(3) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Judges Act</XRefExternal> does not apply in respect of a judge acting as an arbitrator under this Act.</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Subsection></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>4</Label><Text>The portion of subsection 15(1) of the Act before paragraph (a) is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><Section><MarginalNote>Order reducing or withholding contribution</MarginalNote><Label>15</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text><Ins>If</Ins>, on the referral of a matter under section 14, <Ins>the arbitrator芒聙聶s determination is</Ins> that the health care insurance plan of a province does not or has ceased to satisfy any one of the criteria described in sections 8 to 12, <Ins> that the law of a province does not or has ceased to satisfy the criterion described in section 12.1</Ins> or that a province has failed to comply with any condition set out in section 13, <Ins>the Minister shall so inform</Ins> the Governor in Council <Ins>who</Ins> may, by order,</Text></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>5</Label><Text>Section 16 of the Act is replaced by the following: </Text><AmendedText><Section><MarginalNote>Reimposition of reductions or withholdings</MarginalNote><Label>16</Label><Text>In the case of a continuing failure to satisfy any of the criteria described in sections 8 to <Ins>12.1</Ins> or to comply with any condition set out in section 13, any reduction or withholding under section 15 of a cash contribution to a province for a fiscal year shall be reimposed for each succeeding fiscal year as long as the Minister is satisfied, <Keep>after</Keep> consultation with the minister responsible for health care in the province, that the default is continuing.</Text></Section></AmendedText></Section><Heading level="1"><TitleText>Coming into Force</TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote>One year after royal assent</MarginalNote><Label>6</Label><Text>This Act comes into force on the first anniversary of the day on which it receives royal assent.</Text></Section></Body></Bill>