<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><Bill bill-origin="commons" bill-type="private-public" xml:lang="en" date-time="2019-05-28 13:04:06"><Identification><BillNumber>C-457</BillNumber><Parliament><Session>1</Session><Number>42</Number><RegnalYear><Year-s>64-65-66-67-68</Year-s><Monarch>Elizabeth II</Monarch></RegnalYear><Year-s>2015-2016-2017-2018-2019</Year-s></Parliament><LongTitle>An Act to amend the Employment Equity Act</LongTitle><ShortTitle status="unofficial" /><RunningHead>An Act to amend the Employment Equity Act</RunningHead><BillHistory><Stages stage="first-reading-house"><Date><YYYY>2019</YYYY><MM>6</MM><DD>12</DD></Date></Stages></BillHistory><BillSponsor><Emphasis style="smallcaps">Mr. Garrison</Emphasis></BillSponsor><BillRefNumber date-time="2019-05-28">421600</BillRefNumber></Identification><Introduction><Summary><TitleText>SUMMARY</TitleText><Provision><Text>This enactment amends the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Employment Equity Act</XRefExternal> to provide that the lesbian, gay, bisexual, transgender, queer and two-spirit communities are included in the designated groups for the purposes of the Act.</Text></Provision></Summary><Enacts><Provision><Text>Her Majesty, by and with the advice and consent <Keep>of the</Keep> Senate and House of Commons of Canada, <Keep>enacts</Keep> as follows:</Text></Provision></Enacts></Introduction><Body><Heading level="1"><MarginalNote><HistoricalNote>1995, c. 44</HistoricalNote></MarginalNote><TitleText>Employment Equity Act</TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><Label>1</Label><Text>Section 2 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Employment Equity Act</XRefExternal> is replaced by the following:

</Text><AmendedText><Section><MarginalNote>Purpose of Act</MarginalNote><Label>2</Label><Text>The purpose of this Act is to achieve equality in the workplace so that no person shall be denied employment opportunities or benefits for reasons unrelated to ability and, in the fulfilment of that goal, to correct the conditions of disadvantage in employment experienced by women, Aboriginal peoples, persons with disabilities, members of visible minorities and <Ins>members of the lesbian, gay, bisexual, transgender, queer and two-spirit communities</Ins> by giving effect to the principle that employment equity means more than treating persons in the same way but also requires special measures and the accommodation of differences.</Text></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>2</Label><Text>The definition <DefinitionRef>designated groups</DefinitionRef> in section 3 of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><SectionPiece><Definition><Text><DefinedTermEn>designated groups</DefinedTermEn> means women, Aboriginal peoples, persons with disabilities, members of visible minorities and <Ins>members of the lesbian, gay, bisexual, transgender, queer and two-spirit communities</Ins>; (<DefinedTermFr>groupes désignés</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Definition></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>3</Label><Text>Subsection 9(2) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><Subsection><MarginalNote>Self-identification</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Only those employees who identify themselves to an employer, or agree to be identified by an employer, as Aboriginal peoples, members of visible minorities, persons with disabilities or <Ins>members of the lesbian, gay, bisexual, transgender, queer and two-spirit communities</Ins> are to be counted as members of those designated groups for the purposes of implementing employment equity.</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>4</Label><Text>Subsection 18(4) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><Subsection><MarginalNote>Self-identification</MarginalNote><Label>(4)</Label><Text>Only those employees who identify themselves to their employer, or agree to be identified by their employer, as Aboriginal peoples, members of visible minorities, persons with disabilities and <Ins>members of the lesbian, gay, bisexual, transgender, queer and two-spirit communities</Ins> are to be counted as members of those designated groups for the purposes of the report.</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>5</Label><Text>Paragraph 25(1.1)(a) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><SectionPiece><Paragraph><MarginalNote> </MarginalNote><Label>(a)</Label><Text>an employer has been informed of a non-compliance by a compliance officer under subsection (1) and the finding of non-compliance is based, in whole or in part, on the apparent underrepresentation of Aboriginal peoples, members of visible minorities, persons with disabilities or <Ins>members of the lesbian, gay, bisexual, transgender, queer and two-spirit communities</Ins> in the employer’s work force, as reflected in the employer’s work force analysis conducted <Ins>under</Ins> paragraph 9(1)(a), and</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Section></Body></Bill>