<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><Bill bill-origin="commons" bill-type="private-public" xml:lang="en" date-time="2019-06-11 13:51:27"><Identification><BillNumber>C-462</BillNumber><Parliament><Session>1</Session><Number>42</Number><RegnalYear><Year-s>64-65-66-67-68</Year-s><Monarch>Elizabeth II</Monarch></RegnalYear><Year-s>2015-2016-2017-2018-2019</Year-s></Parliament><LongTitle>An Act to amend the Department of the Environment Act (greenhouse gas reduction action plan)</LongTitle><ShortTitle status="unofficial" /><RunningHead>An Act to amend the Department of the Environment Act (greenhouse gas reduction action plan)</RunningHead><BillHistory><Stages stage="first-reading-house"><Date><YYYY>2019</YYYY><MM>6</MM><DD>18</DD></Date></Stages></BillHistory><BillSponsor><Emphasis style="smallcaps">Mr. Boulerice</Emphasis></BillSponsor><BillRefNumber date-time="2019-06-11">421603</BillRefNumber></Identification><Introduction><Summary><TitleText>SUMMARY</TitleText><Provision><Text>This enactment amends the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Department of the Environment Act</XRefExternal> to provide for the establishment by the Minister of a greenhouse gas emissions reduction plan and the independent review of the effectiveness of this plan.</Text></Provision></Summary><Enacts><Provision><Text>Her Majesty, by and with the advice and consent <Keep>of the</Keep> Senate and House of Commons of Canada, <Keep>enacts</Keep> as follows:</Text></Provision></Enacts></Introduction><Body><Heading level="1"><MarginalNote><HistoricalNote>R.S., c. E-10</HistoricalNote></MarginalNote><TitleText>Department of the Environment Act</TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><Label>1</Label><Text>The <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Department of the Environment Act</XRefExternal> is amended by adding the following after section 5:</Text><AmendedText><Section change="ins"><MarginalNote>Greenhouse gas emissions reduction action plan</MarginalNote><Label>5.1</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The Minister shall establish a greenhouse gas emissions reduction action plan that sets out greenhouse gas emissions reduction targets and the measures to be taken to attain those targets, and that takes into con­sideration Canada’s international commitments in that regard.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Independent review</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Each year, the Minister shall cause to be conducted an independent review of the effectiveness of the action plan and the progress made in reducing greenhouse gas emissions.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Revision</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>The Minister shall review the action plan following each independent review conducted under subsection (2).</Text></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>2</Label><Text>Section 8 of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><Section><MarginalNote>Annual report</MarginalNote><Label>8</Label><Text>The Minister shall <Ins>cause to be laid before each House of</Ins> Parliament, on or before January 31 next following the end of each fiscal year or, if <Ins>that House</Ins> is not then sitting, on any of the first <Ins>15</Ins> days <Ins>on which that</Ins> House is sitting <Ins>after that date</Ins>, a report showing the operations of the Department for that fiscal year, <Ins>along with the report of the independent review provided for in subsection 5.1(2)</Ins>.</Text></Section></AmendedText></Section></Body></Bill>