<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><Bill bill-origin="commons" bill-type="private-public" xml:lang="en" date-time="2019-06-17 14:22:23"><Identification><BillNumber>C-469</BillNumber><Parliament><Session>1</Session><Number>42</Number><RegnalYear><Year-s>64-65-66-67-68</Year-s><Monarch>Elizabeth II</Monarch></RegnalYear><Year-s>2015-2016-2017-2018-2019</Year-s></Parliament><LongTitle>An Act to amend the Parks Canada Agency Act (Canada’s tentative list for world heritage protection)</LongTitle><ShortTitle status="unofficial" /><RunningHead>An Act to amend the Parks Canada Agency Act (Canada’s tentative list for world heritage protection)</RunningHead><BillHistory><Stages stage="first-reading-house"><Date><YYYY>2019</YYYY><MM>6</MM><DD>20</DD></Date></Stages></BillHistory><BillSponsor><Emphasis style="smallcaps">Ms. Trudel</Emphasis></BillSponsor><BillRefNumber date-time="2019-06-17">421613</BillRefNumber></Identification><Introduction><Summary><TitleText>SUMMARY</TitleText><Provision><Text>This enactment amends the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Parks Canada Agency Act</XRefExternal> in order to require the Agency to update Canada’s tentative list for world heritage protection every four years.</Text></Provision></Summary><Enacts><Provision><Text>Her Majesty, by and with the advice and consent <Keep>of the</Keep> Senate and House of Commons of Canada, <Keep>enacts</Keep> as follows:</Text></Provision></Enacts></Introduction><Body><Heading level="1"><MarginalNote><HistoricalNote>1998, c. 31</HistoricalNote></MarginalNote><TitleText>Parks Canada Agency Act</TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><Label>1</Label><Text>The <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Parks Canada Agency Act</XRefExternal> is amended by adding the following after section 6:</Text><AmendedText><Section change="ins"><MarginalNote>Definitions </MarginalNote><Label>6.01</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The definitions in this subsection apply in this section.</Text><Definition><Text><DefinedTermEn>Convention</DefinedTermEn> means the Convention concerning the Protection of the World Cultural and Natural Heritage, adopted by the General Conference of the United Nations Educational, Scientific and Cultural Organization on November 16, 1972. (<DefinedTermFr>Convention</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Definition><Definition><Text><DefinedTermEn>tentative list</DefinedTermEn> means the list prepared in accordance with Article 11 of the Convention. (<DefinedTermFr>liste indicative</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Definition></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Advisory committee</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The Minister, in cooperation with the Minister of Canadian Heritage, shall establish an advisory committee to review proposals for inclusion on the tentative list and to recommend to the Agency the sites that, in its opinion, should be included on the list.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Composition</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>The advisory committee shall consist of seven members who have extensive knowledge of natural and cultural heritage conservation and commemoration in Canada.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Protection of world heritage</MarginalNote><Label>(4)</Label><Text>The Agency, as representative of Canada as a State Party to the Convention, shall update Canada’s tentative list every four years, subject to the approval of the Minister and the Minister of Canadian Heritage.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Number of sites</MarginalNote><Label>(5)</Label><Text>The list shall include at least 15 sites that reflect the desired balance between natural and cultural sites, are considered to be significant natural or cultural properties and satisfy the selection criteria provided for in the Convention.</Text></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Section></Body></Bill>