<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!--Arbortext, Inc., 1988-2010, v.4002--><Bill bill-origin="commons" bill-type="govt-public" xml:lang="en"><Identification><BillNumber>C-87</BillNumber><Parliament><Session>1</Session><Number>42</Number><RegnalYear><Year-s>64-65-66-67</Year-s><Monarch>Elizabeth II</Monarch></RegnalYear><Year-s>2015-2016-2017-2018</Year-s></Parliament><LongTitle>An Act respecting the reduction of poverty</LongTitle><ShortTitle status="official">Poverty Reduction Act</ShortTitle><RunningHead>Poverty Reduction Act</RunningHead><BillHistory><Stages stage="first-reading-house"><Date><YYYY>2018</YYYY><MM>11</MM><DD>6</DD></Date></Stages></BillHistory><BillSponsor>MINISTER OF FAMILIES, CHILDREN AND SOCIAL DEVELOPMENT</BillSponsor><BillRefNumber date-time="2018-11-6">90888</BillRefNumber></Identification><Introduction><Recommendation><TitleText>RECOMMENDATION</TitleText><Provision format-ref="section"><Text>Her Excellency the Governor General recommends to the House of Commons the appropriation of public revenue under the circumstances, in the manner and for the purposes set out in a measure entitled “<Emphasis style="italic">An Act respecting the reduction of poverty</Emphasis>”.</Text></Provision></Recommendation><Summary><TitleText>SUMMARY</TitleText><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Text>This enactment enacts the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Poverty Reduction Act</XRefExternal>, which provides for an official metric and other metrics to measure the level of poverty in Canada, sets out two poverty reduction targets in Canada and establishes the National Advisory Council on Poverty.</Text></Provision></Summary><Preamble><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="no"><MarginalNote>Preamble</MarginalNote><Text>Whereas Canada aspires to be a world leader in the eradication of poverty;</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="no"><Text>And whereas the progress made by Canada in the reduction of poverty contributes to meeting the Sustainable Development Goals of the United Nations;</Text></Provision></Preamble><Enacts><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Text>Now, therefore, Her Majesty, by and with the advice and consent <Keep>of the </Keep>Senate and House of Commons of Canada, <Keep>enacts</Keep> as follows:</Text></Provision></Enacts></Introduction><Body><Heading level="1"><TitleText>Short Title</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Short title</MarginalNote><Label>1</Label><Text>This Act may be cited as the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Poverty Reduction Act</XRefExternal>.</Text></Section><Heading level="1"><TitleText>Interpretation</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Definitions</MarginalNote><Label>2</Label><Text>The following definitions apply in this Act.</Text><Definition><Text><DefinedTermEn>Council</DefinedTermEn> means the National Advisory Council on Poverty established under section <XRefInternal>9</XRefInternal>. (<DefinedTermFr>Conseil</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Definition><Definition><Text><DefinedTermEn>Minister</DefinedTermEn> means the member of the Queen’s Privy Council for Canada designated under section <XRefInternal>4</XRefInternal>. (<DefinedTermFr>ministre</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Definition><Definition><Text><DefinedTermEn>Official Poverty Line</DefinedTermEn> means the Market Basket Measure, as published by Statistics Canada under the authority of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Statistics Act</XRefExternal>. (<DefinedTermFr>seuil officiel de la pauvreté</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Definition></Section><Heading level="1"><TitleText>Purpose</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Purpose</MarginalNote><Label>3</Label><Text>The purpose of the Act is to support continuous efforts in, and continuous monitoring of, poverty reduction in Canada.</Text></Section><Heading level="1"><TitleText>Designation of Minister</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Order in council</MarginalNote><Label>4</Label><Text>The Governor in Council may, by order, designate a member of the Queen’s Privy Council for Canada to be the Minister for the purposes of this Act.</Text></Section><Heading level="1"><TitleText>Poverty Reduction Strategy</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Strategy development and implementation</MarginalNote><Label>5</Label><Text>The Minister must develop and implement a poverty reduction strategy.</Text></Section><Heading level="1"><TitleText>Targets</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Poverty reduction targets</MarginalNote><Label>6</Label><Text>The targets for poverty reduction in Canada to which the Government of Canada aspires are the following:</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>20% below the level of poverty in 2015 by 2020; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>50% below the level of poverty in 2015 by 2030.</Text></Paragraph></Section><Heading level="1"><TitleText>Official Poverty Line and Other Metrics</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Official metric</MarginalNote><Label>7</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The Official Poverty Line is Canada’s official metric to measure the level of poverty in Canada and to assess progress in meeting the targets set out in section <XRefInternal>6</XRefInternal>.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Review</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The Official Poverty Line is to be reviewed, on a regular basis as determined by Statistics Canada, to ensure that it reflects the up-to-date cost of a basket of goods and services representing a modest, basic standard of living in Canada.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Other metrics</MarginalNote><Label>8</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The metrics set out in the schedule are to be used, in addition to the Official Poverty Line, to measure the level of poverty in Canada.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Amendment of schedule</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The Governor in Council may, by order, amend the schedule by adding or deleting a metric.</Text></Subsection></Section><Heading level="1"><TitleText>National Advisory Council on Poverty</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Establishment</MarginalNote><Label>9</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>A council is established, to be known as the National Advisory Council on Poverty, consisting of eight to ten members, including a Chairperson and a member with particular responsibilities for children’s issues.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Deputy Minister — <Language xml:lang="la">ex officio</Language> member</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The Deputy Minister of the department for which the Minister is responsible is <Language xml:lang="la">ex officio</Language> a member of the Council.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Appointment of other members</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>The members of the Council, other than the <Language xml:lang="la">ex officio</Language> member, are to be appointed by the Governor in Council to hold office during pleasure for a term not exceeding three years and are eligible for reappointment on the expiry of a first or subsequent term of office.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Full-time or part-time membership</MarginalNote><Label>(4)</Label><Text>The Chairperson is to be appointed as a full-time member and the other members are to be appointed as either full-time members or part-time members.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Chairperson’s role</MarginalNote><Label>(5)</Label><Text>The Chairperson has supervision over and direction of the work of the Council.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Chairperson absent or unable to act</MarginalNote><Label>(6)</Label><Text>If the Chairperson is absent or unable to act or if the office of Chairperson is vacant, the Minister may designate another member of the Council to act as Chairperson, but that member may act as Chairperson for a period of more than 90 days only with the approval of the Governor in Council.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Remuneration</MarginalNote><Label>(7)</Label><Text>The members of the Council, other than the <Language xml:lang="la">ex officio</Language> member, are to be paid, in connection with their work for the Council, the remuneration that may be fixed by the Governor in Council.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Travel and living expenses</MarginalNote><Label>(8)</Label><Text>The members of the Council are entitled to be reimbursed for the travel, living and other expenses incurred, in connection with their work for the Council, while absent from, in the case of full-time members, their ordinary place of work or, in the case of part-time members, their ordinary place of residence.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Deemed employment</MarginalNote><Label>(9)</Label><Text>The members of the Council are deemed to be employees for the purposes of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Government Employees Compensation Act</XRefExternal> and to be employed in the federal public administration for the purposes of any regulations made under section 9 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Aeronautics Act</XRefExternal>. Full-time members are also deemed to be employed in the public service for the purposes of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Public Service Superannuation Act</XRefExternal>.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Functions</MarginalNote><Label>10</Label><Text>The Council must</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>provide advice to the Minister on poverty reduction in Canada, including with respect to programs, funding and activities that support poverty reduction;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>undertake consultations with the public, including the academic community and other experts, Indigenous persons and persons with lived experience in poverty;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(c)</Label><Text>within six months after the end of each fiscal year, submit a report to the Minister</Text><Subparagraph><Label>(i)</Label><Text>on the progress being made in meeting the targets referred to in section <XRefInternal>6</XRefInternal> and the progress being made in poverty reduction measured by, among other things, the metrics set out in the schedule, and</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph><Label>(ii)</Label><Text>on the advice that the Council provided to the Minister under paragraph (a) during the fiscal year; and</Text></Subparagraph></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(d)</Label><Text>undertake any activity specified by the Minister.</Text></Paragraph></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Dissolution of Council</MarginalNote><Label>11</Label><Text>The Governor in Council may, by order, dissolve the Council, on the recommendation of the Minister made after the Minister is of the opinion that the level of <Keep svc="1">poverty</Keep> in Canada has been reduced by 50% below the level of poverty in 2015.</Text></Section><Heading level="1"><TitleText>Tabling of Report in Parliament</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Minister’s duty</MarginalNote><Label>12</Label><Text>The Minister must cause the report referred to in paragraph <XRefInternal>10</XRefInternal>(c) to be tabled in each House of Parliament on any of the first 15 days on which that House is sitting after the Minister receives the report.</Text></Section><Heading level="1"><TitleText>Coordinating Amendments</TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote><HistoricalNote>Bill C-86</HistoricalNote></MarginalNote><Label>13</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Subsections (2) to (4) apply if Bill C-86, introduced in the 1st session of the 42nd Parliament and entitled <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Budget Implementation Act, 2018, No. 2</XRefExternal>, (in this section referred to as the “other Act”), receives royal assent.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><Label>(2)</Label><Text>If section 687 of the other Act comes into force before section <XRefInternal>1</XRefInternal> of this Act, then the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Poverty Reduction Act</XRefExternal>, as enacted by that section 687, is repealed.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><Label>(3)</Label><Text>If section <XRefInternal>1</XRefInternal> of this Act comes into force before section 687 of the other Act, then that section 687 is deemed never to have come into force and is repealed.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><Label>(4)</Label><Text>If section 687 of the other Act comes into force on the same day as section <XRefInternal>1</XRefInternal> of this Act, then that section <XRefInternal>1</XRefInternal> is deemed to have come into force before that section 687 and subsection (3) applies as a consequence.</Text></Subsection></Section><Heading level="1"><TitleText>Coming into Force</TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote>Order in council</MarginalNote><Label>14</Label><Text>Sections <XRefInternal>9</XRefInternal> to <XRefInternal>12</XRefInternal> come into force on a day to be fixed by order of the Governor in Council.</Text></Section></Body><Schedule><ScheduleFormHeading><Label>SCHEDULE</Label><OriginatingRef>(Section 8 and subparagraph 10(c)(i))</OriginatingRef><TitleText>Metrics</TitleText></ScheduleFormHeading></Schedule></Bill>