<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!--Arbortext, Inc., 1988-2010, v.4002--><Bill bill-origin="commons" bill-type="govt-public" xml:lang="en"><!--Authoring to Exchange Transform created with auth2exch.xsl--><Identification><BillNumber>C-94</BillNumber><Parliament><Session>1</Session><Number>42</Number><RegnalYear><Year-s>64-65-66-67-68</Year-s><Monarch>Elizabeth II</Monarch></RegnalYear><Year-s>2015-2016-2017-2018-2019</Year-s></Parliament><LongTitle>An Act respecting certain payments to be made out of the Consolidated Revenue Fund</LongTitle><ShortTitle status="official">Consolidated Revenue Fund, An Act respecting certain payments to be made out of the</ShortTitle><RunningHead>An Act respecting certain payments to be made out of the Consolidated Revenue Fund</RunningHead><BillHistory><Stages stage="first-reading-house"><Date><YYYY>2019</YYYY><MM>3</MM><DD>20</DD></Date></Stages></BillHistory><BillSponsor>MINISTER OF FINANCE</BillSponsor><BillRefNumber date-time="2019-3-20">90898</BillRefNumber></Identification><Introduction><Recommendation><TitleText>RECOMMENDATION</TitleText><Provision format-ref="section"><Text>Her Excellency the Governor General recommends to the House of Commons the appropriation of public revenue under the circumstances, in the manner and for the purposes set out in a measure entitled “<Emphasis style="italic">An Act respecting certain payments to be made out of the Consolidated Revenue Fund</Emphasis>”.</Text></Provision></Recommendation><Summary><TitleText>SUMMARY</TitleText><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Text>This enactment authorizes payments to be made out of the Consolidated Revenue Fund in relation to infrastructure as well as to the Federation of Canadian Municipalities and to the Shock Trauma Air Rescue Service.</Text></Provision></Summary><Enacts><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Text>Her Majesty, by and with the advice and consent of the Senate and House of Commons of Canada, <Keep>enacts</Keep> as follows:</Text></Provision></Enacts></Introduction><Body><Heading level="1"><TitleText>Payment in Relation to Infrastructure</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Maximum payment of $2,200,000,000</MarginalNote><Label>1</Label><Text>Despite section 161 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Keeping Canada’s Economy and Jobs Growing Act</XRefExternal>, as amended by section 233 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Economic Action Plan 2013 Act, No.1</XRefExternal>, there may be paid out of the Consolidated Revenue Fund, on the requisition of the Minister of Infrastructure and Communities or the Minister of State (Indigenous Services), in accordance with terms and conditions approved by the Treasury Board, in addition to the sum referred to in that section 161, a sum not exceeding $2,200,000,000 to provinces, territories, municipalities, municipal associations, provincial, territorial and municipal entities and First Nations for the purpose of municipal, regional and First Nations infrastructure.</Text></Section><Heading level="1"><TitleText>Payment to Federation of Canadian Municipalities</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Maximum payment of $950,000,000</MarginalNote><Label>2</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>There may be paid out of the Consolidated Revenue Fund, on the requisition of the Minister of Natural Resources, in accordance with the terms and conditions provided for in the agreement referred to in subsection (2), a sum not exceeding $950,000,000 to the Federation of Canadian Municipalities for the purpose of providing funding to the Green Municipal Fund.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Terms and conditions</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The Minister of Natural Resources may, with the approval of the Treasury Board, at any time, including before this section comes into force, enter into an agreement with the Federation of Canadian Municipalities respecting the terms and conditions applicable to the making of the payment referred to in subsection (1) and its use.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Maximum payment of $60,000,000</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>There may be paid out of the Consolidated Revenue Fund, on the requisition of the Minister of Infrastructure and Communities, in accordance with the terms and conditions provided for in the agreement referred to in subsection (4), a sum not exceeding $60,000,000 to the Federation of Canadian Municipalities for the purpose of providing funding to the Asset Management Fund.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Terms and conditions</MarginalNote><Label>(4)</Label><Text>The Minister of Infrastructure and Communities may, with the approval of the Treasury Board, at any time, including before this section comes into force, enter into an agreement with the Federation of Canadian Municipalities respecting the terms and conditions applicable to the making of the payment referred to in subsection (3) and its use.</Text></Subsection></Section><Heading level="1"><TitleText>Payment to Shock Trauma Air Rescue Service</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Maximum payment of $65,000,000</MarginalNote><Label>3</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>There may be paid out of the Consolidated Revenue Fund, on the requisition of the Minister of Public Safety and Emergency Preparedness, in accordance with the terms and conditions provided for in the agreement referred to in subsection (2), a sum not exceeding $65,000,000 to the Shock Trauma Air Rescue Service for the acquisition of new emergency ambulance helicopters.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Terms and conditions</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The Minister of Public Safety and Emergency Preparedness may, with the approval of the Treasury Board, at any time, including before this section comes into force, enter into an agreement with the Shock Trauma Air Rescue Service respecting the terms and conditions applicable to the making of the payment referred to in subsection (1) and its use.</Text></Subsection></Section></Body></Bill>