<Bill bill-origin="senate" bill-type="private-public" xml:lang="en" date-time="2018-02-23 10:59:49"><Identification><BillNumber>S-1003</BillNumber><Parliament><Session>1</Session><Number>42</Number><RegnalYear><Year-s>64-65-66-67-68</Year-s><Monarch>Elizabeth II</Monarch></RegnalYear><Year-s>2015-2016-2017-2018-2019</Year-s></Parliament><LongTitle>An Act to amend The United Church of Canada Act</LongTitle><ShortTitle status="unofficial" /><RunningHead>An Act to amend The United Church of Canada Act</RunningHead><BillHistory><Stages stage="assented-to"><Date><YYYY>2019</YYYY><MM>4</MM><DD>11</DD></Date></Stages></BillHistory><Chapter><ConsolidatedNumber /><AnnualStatuteId><AnnualStatuteNumber>31</AnnualStatuteNumber><YYYY>2019</YYYY></AnnualStatuteId></Chapter><BillRefNumber date-time="">4211720</BillRefNumber></Identification><Introduction><Summary><TitleText>SUMMARY</TitleText><Provision><Text>This enactment amends the statute governing the corporation known as The United Church of Canada, <XRefExternal reference-type="act">The United Church of Canada Act</XRefExternal>, by amending a definition and by adding provisions necessary to effect a new governance structure.</Text></Provision></Summary><Preamble><Provision pointsize="6" topmarginspacing="-12" language-align="yes"><Text><?xm-replace_text Text?></Text></Provision><Provision pointsize="10" topmarginspacing="-6" language-align="yes"><MarginalNote>Preamble</MarginalNote><Text>Whereas the corporation known as The United Church of Canada has, by its petition, represented that</Text></Provision><Provision first-line-indent="1" subsequent-line-indent="1"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>the corporation, having its head office in the City of Toronto, in the Province of Ontario, was incorporated by an Act of the Parliament of Canada, being chapter 100 of the Statutes of Canada, 1924, entitled <XRefExternal reference-type="act">An Act incorporating The United Church of Canada</XRefExternal> under the name The United Church of Canada;</Text></Provision><Provision first-line-indent="1" subsequent-line-indent="1"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>the Act of incorporation has since been amended from time to time; and</Text></Provision><Provision first-line-indent="1" subsequent-line-indent="1"><Label>(c)</Label><Text>the corporation wishes that <XRefExternal reference-type="act">The United Church of Canada Act</XRefExternal> be amended so that it may change its governance structure in accordance with the restructuring motion adopted by The United Church of Canada芒聙聶s 42nd General Council on August 14, 2015, and the results of the remit process undertaken thereafter, as confirmed by The United Church of Canada芒聙聶s 43rd General Council on July 22, 2018;</Text></Provision><Provision><Text>And whereas the petitioner has, by its petition, prayed that it be enacted as hereinafter set forth, and it is expedient to grant the prayer of the petition;</Text></Provision></Preamble><Enacts><Provision language-align="yes"><MarginalNote><HistoricalNote>1924, c. 100; 1939, c. 65</HistoricalNote></MarginalNote><Text>Now, therefore, Her Majesty, by and with the advice and consent of the Senate and House of Commons of Canada, enacts as follows:</Text></Provision></Enacts></Introduction><Body><Section type="amending"><Label>1</Label><Text>Paragraph 3(b) of <XRefExternal reference-type="act">The United Church of Canada Act</XRefExternal> is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><SectionPiece><Paragraph><MarginalNote>芒聙聹The Basis of Union.芒聙聺</MarginalNote><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>芒聙聹The Basis of Union芒聙聺 means the Basis of Union set forth in Schedule A to this Act, as amended from time to time under paragraph 28(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>) by The United Church of Canada; </Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>2</Label><Text>The Act is amended by adding the following after section 30:</Text><AmendedText><Section><MarginalNote>Denominational Council of The United Church of Canada</MarginalNote><Label>31</Label><Text>Any reference to the 芒聙聹General Council of The United Church of Canada芒聙聺 in this Act is also to be read, if the context requires, as a reference to the 芒聙聹Denominational Council of The United Church of Canada芒聙聺 or to any successor to that Council that is established in accordance with the process set out in the Basis of Union.</Text></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Regional Council</MarginalNote><Label>32</Label><Text>Any reference to the 芒聙聹Conference芒聙聺 or 芒聙聹Presbytery芒聙聺 in this Act is also to be read, if the context requires, as a reference to the 芒聙聹Regional Council芒聙聺 or to any successor to those entities that is established in accordance with the process set out in the Basis of Union.</Text></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Community of Faith</MarginalNote><Label>33</Label><Text>Any reference to 芒聙聹congregation芒聙聺 in this Act is also to be read, if the context requires, as a reference to 芒聙聹community of faith芒聙聺 or to any successor to those entities that is established in accordance with the process set out in the Basis of Union.</Text></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>3</Label><Text>Schedule B to the Act, 芒聙聹<Emphasis style="smallcaps">Trusts of Model Deed</Emphasis>芒聙聺, is amended, in Column Two, by replacing item 6 with the following:</Text><AmendedText><Provision first-line-indent="1"><Text>6. The Trustees or a majority of them may, but only with the consent in writing of the Regional Council within the bounds of which the lands are situate (such consent to be under the hand of the presiding officer or secretary or clerk thereof), sell the said lands or any part thereof either by public sale or private contract, either for cash or upon credit, upon such terms as to price and for such price and upon such terms as to payment or otherwise as they may deem expedient;  mortgage, hypothecate or exchange the said lands or any part thereof; let any church, chapel or meeting-house upon the same for such rent and upon such terms as they may deem expedient; and make all such conveyances, mortgages, leases and assurances as may be required to complete any such sale, mortgage, hypothecation, exchange or lease. The said Trustees after first paying or otherwise providing for all indebtedness of the Trustees shall apply the moneys arising from such sale, mortgage, hypothecation, lease or exchange for the purposes of such congregation as the Official Board thereof shall direct, but should such congregation cease to exist as an organized body, such proceeds, less any expense incurred in the execution of these trusts, shall be paid to The United Church of Canada to be <Keep svc="1">applied</Keep> for such purposes for the benefit of The United Church of Canada as the Regional Council within the bounds of which the said lands are situate may determine under the by-laws, rules and regulations of the Denominational Council. Every application by Trustees for the consent of a Regional Council as aforesaid shall be in writing and shall state the purpose for which the moneys arising from such intended sale, mortgage, hypothecation, lease or exchange will be applied. Any decision of a Regional Council with regard to the sale, mortgage, hypothecation, lease or exchange of the said lands or any part thereof shall be subject to appeal to the Denominational Council at the instance of not fewer than any five members of the congregation affected thereby. In every case where the consent of such Regional Council or the Denominational Council has been obtained as aforesaid it shall not be incumbent upon the purchaser, mortgagee or lessee of the said lands or of any part thereof to enquire into the necessity, expediency or propriety of any such sale, mortgage, hypothecation, lease or exchange, or to see to the application of the moneys paid to the Trustees. A certificate of the secretary or clerk of any Regional Council or the Denominational Council that any such consent has been given shall be sufficient and conclusive evidence of such consent.</Text></Provision></AmendedText></Section></Body></Bill>