<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet href='BillExchange.css' type='text/css'?><Bill bill-origin="senate" bill-type="private-public" xml:lang="en" date-time="2014-03-03 11:56:36"><Identification><BillNumber>S-205</BillNumber><Parliament><Session>1</Session><Number>42</Number><RegnalYear><Year-s>64-65</Year-s><Monarch>Elizabeth II</Monarch></RegnalYear><Year-s>2015-2016</Year-s></Parliament><LongTitle>An Act to amend the Canada Border Services Agency Act (Inspector General of the Canada Border Services Agency) and to make consequential amendments to other Acts</LongTitle><ShortTitle status="unofficial" /><RunningHead>An Act to amend the Canada Border Services Agency Act (Inspector General of the Canada Border Services Agency) ...</RunningHead><BillHistory><Stages stage="third-reading-senate"><Date><YYYY>2016</YYYY><MM>10</MM><DD>25</DD></Date></Stages></BillHistory><BillRefNumber date-time="2014-03-03">4211124</BillRefNumber></Identification><Introduction><Summary><TitleText>SUMMARY</TitleText><Provision language-align="yes"><Text>This enactment provides for the appointment of an Inspector General of the Canada Border Services Agency whose mandate is to receive and consider complaints about the Agency.</Text></Provision></Summary><TableOfProvisions><Heading level="1"><TitleText>TABLE OF PROVISIONS</TitleText></Heading><Heading level="1"><TitleText>An Act to amend the Canada Border Services Agency Act (Inspector General of the Canada Border Services Agency) and to make consequential amendments to other Acts</TitleText></Heading><Heading level="1"><TitleText><XRefExternal reference-type="act">Canada Border Services Agency Act</XRefExternal></TitleText></Heading><Label><Emphasis style="bold">1</Emphasis></Label><Text>Amendments</Text><Heading level="1"><TitleText>Consequential Amendments</TitleText></Heading><Label><Emphasis style="bold">3</Emphasis></Label><Text><XRefExternal reference-type="act">Access to Information Act</XRefExternal></Text><Label><Emphasis style="bold">5</Emphasis></Label><Text><XRefExternal reference-type="act">Canada Evidence Act</XRefExternal></Text><Label><Emphasis style="bold">6</Emphasis></Label><Text><XRefExternal reference-type="act">Financial Administration Act</XRefExternal></Text><Label><Emphasis style="bold">8</Emphasis></Label><Text><XRefExternal reference-type="act">Privacy Act</XRefExternal></Text><Label><Emphasis style="bold">9</Emphasis></Label><Text><XRefExternal reference-type="act">Official Languages Act</XRefExternal></Text><Label><Emphasis style="bold">10</Emphasis></Label><Text><XRefExternal reference-type="act">Public Sector Compensation Act</XRefExternal></Text><Label><Emphasis style="bold">11</Emphasis></Label><Text><XRefExternal reference-type="act">Public Servants Disclosure Protection Act</XRefExternal></Text><Heading level="1"><TitleText>Coming into Force</TitleText></Heading><Label><Emphasis style="bold">12</Emphasis></Label><Text>Coming into force</Text></TableOfProvisions><Enacts><Provision language-align="yes"><Text>Her Majesty, by and with the advice and consent of the Senate and House of Commons of Canada, <Keep>enacts</Keep> as follows:</Text></Provision></Enacts></Introduction><Body><Heading level="1"><MarginalNote><HistoricalNote>2005, c. 38</HistoricalNote></MarginalNote><TitleText><XRefExternal reference-type="act">Canada Border Services Agency Act</XRefExternal></TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><Label>1</Label><Text>Section 2 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Canada Border Services Agency Act</XRefExternal> is amended by adding the following in alphabetical order:</Text><AmendedText><SectionPiece><Definition><MarginalNote><DefinedTermEn>Inspector General</DefinedTermEn></MarginalNote><MarginalNote><DefinedTermFr>inspecteur général</DefinedTermFr></MarginalNote><Text><DefinedTermEn>Inspector General</DefinedTermEn> means the Inspector General of the Agency appointed under subsection 15.11(1).</Text></Definition></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>2</Label><Text>The Act is amended by adding the following after section 15.1:</Text><AmendedText><Heading level="1"><TitleText>Inspector General</TitleText></Heading><Heading level="2"><TitleText>Appointment and Powers</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Appointment</MarginalNote><Label>15.11</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The Governor in Council shall appoint an Inspector General of the Agency after consultation with the leader of every recognized party in the Senate and House of Commons and approval of the appointment by resolution of the Senate and House of Commons.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Tenure</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The Inspector General holds office during good behaviour for a term of seven years, but may be removed for cause by the Governor in Council at any time on address of the Senate and House of Commons.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Further terms</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>The Inspector General is eligible to be reappointed for one or more further terms of not more than seven years each.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Interim appointment</MarginalNote><Label>(4)</Label><Text>In the event of the absence or incapacity of the Inspector General, or if that office is vacant, the Governor in Council may appoint any qualified person to hold that office in the interim for a term not exceeding six months, and that person shall, while holding office, be paid the salary or other remuneration and expenses that may be fixed by the Governor in Council.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Rank and powers</MarginalNote><Label>15.12</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The Inspector General has the rank and all the powers of a deputy head of a department.  </Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Duties</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The Inspector General shall engage exclusively in the duties of the office of Inspector General under this Act and shall not hold any other office or engage in any other employment for reward.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Salary and expenses</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>The Inspector General shall be paid the remuneration that is fixed by the Governor in Council, and is entitled to be paid reasonable travel and living expenses incurred in the performance of his or her duties while absent from his or her ordinary place of work.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Pension benefits</MarginalNote><Label>(4)</Label><Text>The Inspector General is deemed to be employed in the public service for the purposes of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Public Service Superannuation Act</XRefExternal>.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Other benefits</MarginalNote><Label>(5)</Label><Text>The Inspector General is deemed to be employed in the federal public administration for the purposes of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Government Employees Compensation Act</XRefExternal> and regulations made under section 9 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Aeronautics Act</XRefExternal>.</Text></Subsection></Section><Heading level="2"><TitleText>Staff</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Staff of the Inspector General</MarginalNote><Label>15.13</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The officers and employees necessary to enable the Inspector General to perform his or her powers, duties and functions under this Act shall be appointed in accordance with the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Public Service Employment Act</XRefExternal>.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Technical assistance</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The Inspector General may engage, on a temporary basis, the services of persons having technical or specialized knowledge of any matter relating to the work of the Inspector General to advise and assist the Inspector General in the performance of his or her powers, duties and functions and, with the approval of the Treasury Board, may fix and pay the remuneration and expenses of those persons.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Delegation</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>The Inspector General may authorize any person employed in his or her office to exercise and perform, in any manner and subject to any terms and conditions that he or she directs, any of the powers, duties and functions of the Inspector General. </Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Subdelegation</MarginalNote><Label>(4)</Label><Text>Any person authorized under subsection (3) may, subject to and in accordance with the authorization, authorize one or more persons under that person’s jurisdiction to exercise any power or perform any function to which the authorization relates.</Text></Subsection></Section><Heading level="2"><TitleText>Mandate</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Mandate</MarginalNote><Label>15.14</Label><Text>The mandate of the Inspector General is to consider any complaint made under subsection 15.15(1).</Text></Section><Heading level="2"><TitleText>Investigations</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Investigation of complaints</MarginalNote><Label>15.15</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Any person who claims to be aggrieved by any act or thing done by the Agency may make a complaint to the Inspector General and, subject to this section, the Inspector General shall investigate the complaint.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Written complaint</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>A complaint shall be in writing unless the Inspector General authorizes otherwise.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Procedure</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>Subject to this Act, the Inspector General may determine the procedure to be followed in carrying out an investigation under this Act.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Discontinuance of investigation</MarginalNote><Label>(4)</Label><Text>If, in the course of investigating any complaint, the Inspector General is of the opinion that, having regard to all the circumstances of the case, any further investigation is unnecessary, the Inspector General may refuse to investigate the matter further.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Refuse or cease investigation</MarginalNote><Label>(5)</Label><Text>The Inspector General may refuse to investigate or cease to investigate any complaint if, in the opinion of the Inspector General,</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>the complaint is trivial, frivolous, vexatious or made in bad faith; or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>the subject-matter of the complaint does not come within the authority of the Inspector General under this Act.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Complainant to be notified</MarginalNote><Label>(6)</Label><Text>If the Inspector General decides to refuse to investigate or cease to investigate a complaint under subsection (4) or (5), the Inspector General shall inform the complainant of that decision and the reasons for it.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Notice of intention to investigate</MarginalNote><Label>15.16</Label><Text>Before commencing an investigation of a complaint, the Inspector General shall inform the complainant and shall notify the Minister and the President of his or her intention to carry out the investigation and inform them of the subject-matter of the complaint.</Text></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Investigations in private</MarginalNote><Label>15.17</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Every investigation of a complaint under this Act by the Inspector General shall be conducted in private.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Right to make representations</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>In the course of an investigation of a complaint by the Inspector General, the complainant and the President shall be given an opportunity to make representations to the Inspector General, to present evidence and to be heard personally, by counsel or by any other representative, but no one is entitled as of right to be present during, to have access to or to comment on representations made to the Inspector General by any other person.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Powers of Inspector General</MarginalNote><Label>15.18</Label><Text>The Inspector General has, in relation to the investigation of any complaint under this Act, power</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>to summon and enforce the appearance of persons before the Inspector General  and to compel them to give oral or written evidence on oath and to produce any documents or things that the Inspector General considers necessary for the full investigation and consideration of the complaint in the same manner and to the same extent as a superior court of record;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>to administer oaths; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(c)</Label><Text>to receive and accept any evidence and other information, on oath or by affidavit or otherwise, that the Inspector General sees fit, whether or not that evidence or information is or would be admissible in a court of law.</Text></Paragraph></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Evidence in other proceedings</MarginalNote><Label>15.19</Label><Text>Except in a prosecution of a person for an offence under section 131 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Criminal Code</XRefExternal> (perjury) in respect of a statement made under this Act, evidence given by a person in proceedings under this Act and evidence of the existence of the proceedings are inadmissible against that person in a court or in any other proceedings.</Text></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Findings and recommendations of Inspector General</MarginalNote><Label>15.2</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>If, on investigating a complaint under this Act, the Inspector General finds that the complaint is well-founded, the Inspector General shall provide the Minister and the President with a report containing</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>the findings of the investigation and any recommendations that the Inspector General considers appropriate; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>where appropriate, a request that, within a specified time, notice be given to the Inspector General of any action taken or proposed to be taken to implement the recommendations contained in the report or reasons why no such action has been or is proposed to be taken.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Report to complainant</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The Inspector General shall, after investigating a complaint under this Act, report to the complainant the results of the investigation, but where a notice has been requested under paragraph (1)(b) no report shall be made under this subsection until the expiration of the time within which the notice is to be given to the Inspector General.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Matter to be included in report to complainant</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>Where a notice has been requested under paragraph (1)(b) but no such notice is received by the Inspector General within the time specified for such notice or the action described in the notice is, in the opinion of the Inspector General, inadequate or inappropriate or will not be taken within a reasonable time, the Inspector General shall so advise the complainant in the report under subsection (2) and may include in the report any comments on the matter that he or she considers appropriate.</Text></Subsection></Section><Heading level="2"><TitleText>Reports to Parliament</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Inspector General’s report</MarginalNote><Label>15.21</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Within three months after the end of each fiscal year, the Inspector General shall submit to the Minister a report on the Inspector General’s activities for that fiscal year.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Special report</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The Inspector General may, at any time, submit to the Minister a special report referring to and commenting on any matter within the scope of the powers, duties and functions of the Inspector General where, in his or her opinion, the matter is of such urgency or importance that a report on it should not be deferred until the next annual report.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Submission and tabling of report</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>The Minister shall cause a copy of a report received under subsection (1) or (2) to be laid before each House of Parliament on any of the first 15 days on which that House is sitting after the Minister receives the report.</Text></Subsection></Section><Heading level="2"><TitleText>General Provisions</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Access to information</MarginalNote><Label>15.22</Label><Text>Despite any other Act of Parliament, the Inspector General is entitled to have access to any information under the control of the Agency that relates to the performance of the powers, duties and functions of the Inspector General and to receive from the Agency any information, reports and explanations that the Inspector General considers necessary for the performance of those duties and functions.</Text></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Security requirements</MarginalNote><Label>15.23</Label><Text>The Inspector General and every person acting on behalf or under the direction of the Inspector General who receives or obtains information under this Act shall, with respect to access to and the use of that information, satisfy any security requirements applicable to, and take any oath of secrecy required to be taken by, persons who normally have access to and use of that information.</Text></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Confidentiality</MarginalNote><Label>15.24</Label><Text>Unless the disclosure is required by law or permitted by this Act, the Inspector General and every person acting on behalf or under the direction of the Inspector General shall not disclose any information that comes to their knowledge in the performance of their powers, duties and functions under this Act.</Text></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Disclosure not waiver</MarginalNote><Label>15.25</Label><Text>The disclosure of information to the Inspector General under this Act does not, by itself, constitute a waiver of any privilege that may exist with respect to the information.</Text></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Protection of confidential information</MarginalNote><Label>15.26</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The Inspector General shall consult with the Minister in order to ensure compliance with section 15.23 in preparing any report made under this Act.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Information not to be disclosed</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Subject to subsection (3), the Inspector General and any person acting on behalf or under the direction of the Inspector General shall not disclose any information that the Agency or the Government of Canada or any portion of the public sector is taking measures to protect, including, but not limited to, information that</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>is a confidence of the Queen’s Privy Council for Canada in respect of which subsection 39(1) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Canada Evidence Act</XRefExternal> applies;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>is subject to solicitor-client privilege;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(c)</Label><Text>is special operational information within the meaning of subsection 8(1) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Security of Information Act</XRefExternal>;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(d)</Label><Text>is subject to any restriction on disclosure created by or under any other Act of Parliament;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(e)</Label><Text>could reasonably be expected to cause injury to international relations, national defence or national security, or to the detection, prevention or suppression of criminal, subversive or hostile activities;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(f)</Label><Text>could reasonably be expected to cause injury to the privacy interests of an individual; or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(g)</Label><Text>could reasonably be expected to cause injury to commercial interests.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Exception – previously disclosed information or consent</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>The Inspector General may disclose any information referred to in subsection (2) if it has already been disclosed following a request under the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Access to Information Act</XRefExternal> or with the consent of the relevant individual or an authorized person in the organization that has a primary interest in the information.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section><MarginalNote>No summons</MarginalNote><Label>15.27</Label><Text>In respect of any matter coming to the knowledge of the Inspector General or any person acting on behalf or under the direction of the Inspector General as a result of performing any powers, duties or functions conferred on them under this Act, neither the Inspector General nor that person is a competent or compellable witness in any proceedings other than a prosecution for an offence under this Act or an offence under section 131 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Criminal Code</XRefExternal> (perjury) in respect of a statement made under this Act.</Text></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Protection of  Inspector General</MarginalNote><Label>15.28</Label><Text>No criminal or civil proceedings lie against the Inspector General, or against any person acting on behalf or under the direction of the Inspector General, for anything done — or omitted to be done — or reported or said in good faith in the course of the actual or purported exercise or performance of any power, duty or function of the Inspector General.</Text></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Decisions of Inspector General final </MarginalNote><Label>15.29</Label><Text>The Inspector General’s decisions in respect of a complaint or an investigation under this Act, and the findings and recommendations contained in the Inspector General’s report referred to in subsection 15.2(1), are final and are not subject to appeal or to review by any court.</Text></Section><Heading level="2"><TitleText>Offences</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Obstruction</MarginalNote><Label>15.3</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>No person shall obstruct the Inspector General or any person acting on behalf or under the direction of the Inspector General in the performance of the Inspector General’s powers, duties and functions.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Offence and punishment</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Every person who contravenes subsection (1) is guilty of an offence and liable on summary conviction to a fine not exceeding $5,000.</Text></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Section><Heading level="1"><TitleText>Consequential Amendments</TitleText></Heading><Heading level="2"><MarginalNote><HistoricalNote>R.S., c. A-1</HistoricalNote></MarginalNote><TitleText><XRefExternal reference-type="act">Access to Information Act</XRefExternal></TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><Label>3</Label><Text>Subsection 16.1(1) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Access to Information Act</XRefExternal> is amended by adding the following after paragraph (b):</Text><AmendedText><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(b.1)</Label><Text>the Inspector General of the Canada Border Services Agency;</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>4</Label><Text>Schedule I to the Act is amended by adding the following in alphabetical order under the heading “Other Government Institutions”:</Text><AmendedText><BilingualGroup><BilingualItemEn>Office of the Inspector General of the Canada Border Services Agency</BilingualItemEn><BilingualItemFr>Bureau de l’inspecteur général de l’Agence des services frontaliers du Canada</BilingualItemFr></BilingualGroup></AmendedText></Section><Heading level="2"><MarginalNote><HistoricalNote>R.S., c. C-5</HistoricalNote></MarginalNote><TitleText><XRefExternal reference-type="act">Canada Evidence Act</XRefExternal></TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><Label>5</Label><Text>The schedule to the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Canada Evidence Act</XRefExternal> is amended by adding the following after item 22 under the heading “Designated Entities”:</Text><AmendedText><Section><Label>23</Label><Text>The Inspector General of the Canada Border Services Agency, for the purposes of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Canada Border Services Agency Act</XRefExternal>.</Text></Section></AmendedText></Section><Heading level="2"><MarginalNote><HistoricalNote>R.S., c. F-11</HistoricalNote></MarginalNote><TitleText><XRefExternal reference-type="act">Financial Administration Act</XRefExternal></TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><Label>6</Label><Text>Schedule I.1 to the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Financial Administration Act</XRefExternal> is amended by adding, in alphabetical order in column I, a reference to</Text><AmendedText><BilingualGroup><BilingualItemEn>Office of the Inspector General of the Canada Border Services Agency</BilingualItemEn><BilingualItemFr>Bureau de l’inspecteur général de l’Agence des services frontaliers du Canada</BilingualItemFr></BilingualGroup></AmendedText><ContinuedSectionSubsection type="amending"><Text><Emphasis style="bold">and a corresponding reference in column II to the “Minister of Public Safety and Emergency Preparedness”.</Emphasis></Text></ContinuedSectionSubsection></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>7</Label><Text>Schedule IV to the Act is amended by adding the following in alphabetical order:</Text><AmendedText><BilingualGroup><BilingualItemEn>Office of the Inspector General of the Canada Border Services Agency</BilingualItemEn><BilingualItemFr>Bureau de l’inspecteur général de l’Agence des services frontaliers du Canada</BilingualItemFr></BilingualGroup></AmendedText></Section><Heading level="2"><MarginalNote><HistoricalNote>R.S., c. P-21</HistoricalNote></MarginalNote><TitleText><XRefExternal reference-type="act">Privacy Act</XRefExternal></TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><Label>8</Label><Text>The schedule to the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Privacy Act</XRefExternal> is amended by adding the following in alphabetical order under the heading “Other Government Institutions”:</Text><AmendedText><BilingualGroup><BilingualItemEn>Office of the Inspector General of the Canada Border Services Agency</BilingualItemEn><BilingualItemFr>Bureau de l’inspecteur général de l’Agence des services frontaliers du Canada</BilingualItemFr></BilingualGroup></AmendedText></Section><Heading level="2"><MarginalNote><HistoricalNote>R.S., c. 31 (4th supp.)</HistoricalNote></MarginalNote><TitleText><XRefExternal reference-type="act">Official Languages Act</XRefExternal></TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><Label>9</Label><Text>Subsection 24(3) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Official Languages Act</XRefExternal> is amended by striking out “and” at the end of paragraph (e), by adding “and” at the end of paragraph (f) and by adding the following after paragraph (f):</Text><AmendedText><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(g)</Label><Text>the Office of the Inspector General of the Canada Border Services Agency.</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Section><Heading level="2"><MarginalNote><HistoricalNote>1991, c. 30</HistoricalNote></MarginalNote><TitleText><XRefExternal reference-type="act">Public Sector Compensation Act</XRefExternal></TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><Label>10</Label><Text>Schedule I to the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Public Sector Compensation Act</XRefExternal> is amended by adding the following in alphabetical order under the heading “<Emphasis style="italic">Other Portions of the Public Service</Emphasis>”:</Text><AmendedText><BilingualGroup><BilingualItemEn>Office of the Inspector General of the Canada Border Services Agency</BilingualItemEn><BilingualItemFr>Bureau de l’inspecteur général de l’Agence des services frontaliers du Canada</BilingualItemFr></BilingualGroup></AmendedText></Section><Heading level="2"><MarginalNote><HistoricalNote>2005, c. 46</HistoricalNote></MarginalNote><TitleText><XRefExternal reference-type="act">Public Servants Disclosure Protection Act</XRefExternal></TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><Label>11</Label><Text>Schedule 2 to the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Public Servants Disclosure Protection Act</XRefExternal> is amended by adding the following in alphabetical order:</Text><AmendedText><BilingualGroup><BilingualItemEn>Office of the Inspector General of the Canada Border Services Agency</BilingualItemEn><BilingualItemFr>Bureau de l’inspecteur général de l’Agence des services frontaliers du Canada</BilingualItemFr></BilingualGroup></AmendedText></Section><Heading level="1" type="amending"><TitleText>Coming into Force</TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote>Coming into force</MarginalNote><Label>12</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Subject to subsection (2), this Act comes into force on a day to be fixed by order of the Governor in Council.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Royal recommendation</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>No order may be made under subsection (1) unless the appropriation of moneys for the purposes of this Act has been recommended by the Governor General and such moneys have been appropriated by Parliament.</Text></Subsection></Section></Body></Bill>