<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet href='BillExchange.css' type='text/css'?><Bill bill-origin="senate" bill-type="private-public" xml:lang="en" date-time="2015-10-07 09:26:14"><Identification><BillNumber>S-216</BillNumber><Parliament><Session>1</Session><Number>42</Number><RegnalYear><Year-s>64</Year-s><Monarch>Elizabeth II</Monarch></RegnalYear><Year-s>2015-2016</Year-s></Parliament><LongTitle>An Act to provide the means to rationalize the governance of Canadian public corporations</LongTitle><ShortTitle status="unofficial">Canadian Public Corporations Governance Act</ShortTitle><RunningHead>Canadian Public Corporations Governance</RunningHead><BillHistory><Stages stage="first-reading-senate"><Date><YYYY>2016</YYYY><MM>1</MM><DD>26</DD></Date></Stages></BillHistory><BillSponsor>HERVIEUX-PAYETTE, P.C.</BillSponsor><BillRefNumber date-time="2015-10-07">4210838</BillRefNumber></Identification><Introduction><Summary><TitleText><Emphasis style="bold">SUMMARY</Emphasis></TitleText><Provision><Text>This enactment limits the cumulative period that an individual may sit on the board of directors of a Canadian public corporation to 96 months and prohibits an individual from sitting on the board of more than four Canadian public corporations at the same time. It also places strict limits on the remuneration these corporations may pay their officers and directors and the benefits they may grant in connection with their functions.</Text></Provision></Summary><Enacts><Provision><Text>Her Majesty, by and with the advice and consent of the Senate and House of Commons of Canada, <Keep>enacts</Keep> as follows:</Text></Provision></Enacts></Introduction><Body><Heading level="1"><TitleText>Short Title</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Short title</MarginalNote><Label>1</Label><Text>This Act may be cited as the <Emphasis style="italic">Canadian Public Corporations Governance Act</Emphasis>.</Text></Section><Heading level="1"><TitleText>Interpretation</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Definitions</MarginalNote><Label>2</Label><Text>The following definitions apply in this Act.</Text><Definition><MarginalNote><DefinedTermEn>board of directors</DefinedTermEn></MarginalNote><MarginalNote><DefinedTermFr>conseil d’administration</DefinedTermFr></MarginalNote><Text><DefinedTermEn>board of directors</DefinedTermEn> means all the directors of a public corporation.</Text></Definition><Definition><MarginalNote><DefinedTermEn>body corporate</DefinedTermEn></MarginalNote><MarginalNote><DefinedTermFr>personne morale</DefinedTermFr></MarginalNote><Text><DefinedTermEn>body corporate</DefinedTermEn> means an incorporated body wherever or however incorporated.</Text></Definition><Definition><MarginalNote><DefinedTermEn>corporation</DefinedTermEn></MarginalNote><MarginalNote><DefinedTermFr>société</DefinedTermFr></MarginalNote><Text><DefinedTermEn>corporation</DefinedTermEn> means</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>a body corporate incorporated or continued under the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Canada Business Corporations Act</XRefExternal>;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>a bank governed by the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Bank Act</XRefExternal>;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(c)</Label><Text>a body corporate governed by the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Trust and Loan Companies Act</XRefExternal>;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(d)</Label><Text>an association governed by the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Cooperative Credit Associations Act</XRefExternal>; or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(e)</Label><Text>an insurance company or a fraternal benefit society incorporated or formed under the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Insurance Companies Act</XRefExternal>.</Text></Paragraph></Definition><Definition><MarginalNote><DefinedTermEn>director</DefinedTermEn></MarginalNote><MarginalNote><DefinedTermFr>administrateur</DefinedTermFr></MarginalNote><Text><DefinedTermEn>director</DefinedTermEn> means an individual who is a member of the board of directors of a public corporation.</Text></Definition><Definition><MarginalNote><DefinedTermEn>family member</DefinedTermEn></MarginalNote><MarginalNote><DefinedTermFr>membre de la famille</DefinedTermFr></MarginalNote><Text><DefinedTermEn>family member</DefinedTermEn>, in relation to an individual, means</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>a spouse or common-law partner of the individual;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>a child of the individual or a child of the individual’s spouse or common-law partner; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(c)</Label><Text>a parent of the individual or a spouse or common-law partner of the parent.</Text></Paragraph></Definition><Definition><MarginalNote><DefinedTermEn>individual</DefinedTermEn></MarginalNote><MarginalNote><DefinedTermFr>particulier</DefinedTermFr></MarginalNote><Text><DefinedTermEn>individual</DefinedTermEn> means a natural person.</Text></Definition><Definition><MarginalNote><DefinedTermEn>officer</DefinedTermEn></MarginalNote><MarginalNote><DefinedTermFr>dirigeant</DefinedTermFr></MarginalNote><Text><DefinedTermEn>officer</DefinedTermEn> means the president, vice-president, secretary, treasurer, comptroller, general counsel, general manager or managing director of a public corporation, or any other individual who performs functions similar to those normally performed by an individual occupying any of those offices.</Text></Definition><Definition><MarginalNote><DefinedTermEn>public corporation</DefinedTermEn></MarginalNote><MarginalNote><DefinedTermFr>société publique</DefinedTermFr></MarginalNote><Text><DefinedTermEn>public corporation</DefinedTermEn> means a corporation that is a distributing corporation whose securities are listed and posted for trading on a recognized stock exchange in Canada or elsewhere.</Text></Definition></Section><Heading level="1"><TitleText>Board of Directors</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Restriction</MarginalNote><Label>3</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>No individual may sit on the board of directors of more than four public corporations at the same time.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Incapacity</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>No individual who is already sitting on the board of directors of four public corporations may be appointed to another board of directors.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Term of office</MarginalNote><Label>4</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>No individual may sit on the board of directors of a public corporation for a cumulative period of more than 96 months.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Ceasing to hold office</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>A director ceases to hold office when he or she becomes disqualified under subsection (1).</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Exception</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>Subsections (1) and (2) do not apply to an individual who was a director of the corporation at the time of its incorporation or became one within one year after that date.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><Label>(4)</Label><Text>Subsections (1) and (2) do not apply to an individual if that individual or members of that individual’s family, or the entities they control, beneficially own securities carrying more than 50% of the voting rights attached to all of the securities of the public corporation.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Remuneration</MarginalNote><Label>5</Label><Text>A public corporation must remunerate its directors by paying a sum of money composed of the directors’ annual fees and directors’ fees for attendance at meetings of the corporation’s board of directors.</Text></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Financial investment</MarginalNote><Label>6</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Every director of a public corporation must invest a sum of money, in the form of common shares, equivalent to three times the annual remuneration he or she is paid by the corporation.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Coming into effect</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Subsection (1) becomes effective one year after this section comes into force.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Purchase options or rights</MarginalNote><Label>7</Label><Text>A public corporation must not grant share purchase options or rights to their directors.</Text></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Remuneration committee</MarginalNote><Label>8</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The board of directors of a public corporation must constitute a remuneration committee responsible for preparing a plan setting out the principles and structure for the remuneration of the corporation’s directors and officers.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Coming into effect</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The remuneration plan becomes effective after it is submitted to the shareholders of the public corporation and after it has been the subject of an advisory vote by an assembly of the shareholders.</Text></Subsection></Section><Heading level="1"><TitleText>Officers</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Definition of <DefinedTermEn>total remuneration</DefinedTermEn></MarginalNote><Label>9</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>For the purposes of this section, <DefinedTermEn>total remuneration</DefinedTermEn> means the salary, for a fiscal year, that a public corporation pays to one of its officers and the benefits, within the meaning of subsection 10(1), that it grants to the officer.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Remuneration</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The remuneration committee of the public corporation must determine the total remuneration of each of its officers based on the following criteria:</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>the amount of that remuneration must not be more than 20 times greater than the annual average wage of the corporation; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>the book value of the corporation for the current fiscal year compared to its book value for the preceding fiscal year.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Definition of <DefinedTermEn>benefits</DefinedTermEn> — officers</MarginalNote><Label>10</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>In this section, <DefinedTermEn>benefits</DefinedTermEn> means the expenses incurred by a public corporation during a fiscal year for the professional training of its officers, for the payment to those officers of reasonable performance incentives or for the allocation to its officers of any other similar benefits directly linked to the normal activities of the corporation.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Aggregate value of benefits</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The remuneration committee, in order to ensure that its decision protects the interests of the shareholders of the public corporation and does not adversely affect its long-term profitability, must determine the aggregate value of the benefits, other than salary, that the corporation grants its officers based on its financial situation during the current fiscal year compared with its financial situation during the preceding fiscal year.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Liquidation</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>No officer of the public corporation may liquidate any of those benefits that may be converted into cash at a date that is less than three years from the date on which the benefits were awarded.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Termination pay and severance pay</MarginalNote><Label>11</Label><Text>A public corporation must not grant termination pay, severance pay or any other related payment related to the termination of an officer in an amount that, in aggregate, exceeds twice the amount of his or her total remuneration as defined in subsection 9(1).</Text></Section><Heading level="1"><TitleText>Reports</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Financial statements</MarginalNote><Label>12</Label><Text>Every public corporation must include in its financial statements the amount paid during the fiscal year to each of its officers as retirement benefits.</Text></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Definition of <DefinedTermEn>benefits</DefinedTermEn> — directors</MarginalNote><Label>13</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>In this section, <DefinedTermEn>benefits</DefinedTermEn> means the benefits, other than the remuneration described in section 5, granted by a public corporation during a fiscal year in the form of</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>the use of its motor vehicles or aircraft;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>expenses incurred by it for</Text><Subparagraph><Label>(i)</Label><Text>living and travel expenses, including expenses to attend congresses, symposiums, conferences, seminars, reunions or meetings, and</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph><Label>(ii)</Label><Text>entertainment expenses for meals, drinks or entertainment; and</Text></Subparagraph></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(c)</Label><Text>personal benefits in the form of loans, advances, gifts, insurance or medical care.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Annual report</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Every public corporation must include in the annual report that it submits to its shareholders a statement of the benefits provided to its directors during the fiscal year.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Details</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>The statement must include</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>a detailed list of the benefits provided to each of its directors; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>a mention of the cash value of each of these benefits.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection></Section><Heading level="1"><TitleText>Enforcement</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Offences: individuals</MarginalNote><Label>14</Label><Text>Every individual who contravenes section 3 or subsection 4(1), 6(1) or 10(3) is guilty of an offence and liable on summary conviction to a fine not exceeding $100,000.</Text></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Offences: corporations</MarginalNote><Label>15</Label><Text>Every corporation that contravenes section 7, 11, 12, or 13 is guilty of an offence and liable on summary conviction to a fine not exceeding $500,000.</Text></Section><Heading level="1"><TitleText>Coming into Force</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Order in Council</MarginalNote><Label>16</Label><Text>The provisions of this Act come into force on a day or days to be fixed by order of the Governor in Council.</Text></Section></Body></Bill>