<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><Bill bill-origin="senate" bill-type="private-public" xml:lang="en" date-time="2016-01-28 16:32:45"><Identification><BillNumber>S-217</BillNumber><Parliament><Session>1</Session><Number>42</Number><RegnalYear><Year-s>64</Year-s><Monarch>Elizabeth II</Monarch></RegnalYear><Year-s>2015-2016</Year-s></Parliament><LongTitle>An Act to amend the Criminal Code (detention in custody)</LongTitle><ShortTitle status="unofficial" /><RunningHead>An Act to amend the Criminal Code (detention in custody)</RunningHead><BillHistory><Stages stage="first-reading-senate"><Date><YYYY>2016</YYYY><MM>2</MM><DD>3</DD></Date></Stages></BillHistory><BillSponsor>Runciman</BillSponsor><BillRefNumber date-time="">4211524</BillRefNumber></Identification><Introduction><Summary><TitleText>SUMMARY</TitleText><Provision><Text>This enactment amends the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Criminal Code</XRefExternal> to</Text><Provision first-line-indent="1" subsequent-line-indent="1"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>expand the grounds for the justification of detention in custody;</Text></Provision><Provision first-line-indent="1" subsequent-line-indent="1"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>require that, in any proceeding under section 515, the prosecutor lead evidence to prove the fact that the accused has failed to appear in court when required to do so and the fact that the accused has previously been convicted of a criminal offence or has been charged with and is awaiting trial for another criminal offence; and</Text></Provision><Provision first-line-indent="1" subsequent-line-indent="1"><Label>(c)</Label><Text>require that a court, when exercising its discretion to grant credit for time spent in custody in determining the sentence to be imposed on a person convicted of an offence, consider the reasons for detaining the person in custody.</Text></Provision></Provision></Summary><Enacts><Provision><MarginalNote><HistoricalNote>R.S., c. C-46</HistoricalNote></MarginalNote><Text>Her Majesty, by and with the advice and consent of the Senate and House of Commons of Canada, <Keep>enacts</Keep> as follows:</Text></Provision></Enacts></Introduction><Body><Section type="amending"><Label>1</Label><Text>Paragraph 515(10)(c) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Criminal Code</XRefExternal> is amended by striking out “and” at the end of subparagraph (iii) and by adding the following after subparagraph (iv):</Text><AmendedText change="ins"><SectionPiece><Subparagraph><Label>(v)</Label><Text>the fact that the accused has failed to appear in court on one or more occasions when required to do so, and </Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph><Label>(vi)</Label><Text>the fact that the accused has previously been convicted of a criminal offence or has been charged with and is awaiting trial for another criminal offence.</Text></Subparagraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText><ExplanatoryNote><TitleText>Criminal Code</TitleText><Label><Emphasis style="italic">Clause 1</Emphasis>: </Label><ExplanatoryText>Existing text of relevant portions of subsection 515(10):</ExplanatoryText><ExistingText><Subsection><MarginalNote>Justification for detention in custody</MarginalNote><Label>(10)</Label><Text>For the purposes of this section, the detention of an accused in custody is justified only on one or more of the following grounds:</Text><Paragraph><Label> . . .</Label><Text /></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(c)</Label><Text>if the detention is necessary to maintain confidence in the administration of justice, having regard to all the circumstances, including</Text><Subparagraph><Label><?xm-replace_text Subparagraph?></Label><Text> . . .</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph><Label>(iii)</Label><Text>the circumstances surrounding the commission of the offence, including whether a firearm was used, and</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph><Label>(iv)</Label><Text>the fact that the accused is liable, on conviction, for a potentially lengthy term of imprisonment or, in the case of an offence that involves, or whose subject-matter is, a firearm, a minimum punishment of imprisonment for a term of three years or more.</Text></Subparagraph></Paragraph></Subsection></ExistingText></ExplanatoryNote></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>2</Label><Text>Paragraph 518(1)(c) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(c)</Label><Text>the prosecutor <Ins>shall</Ins>, in addition to any other relevant evidence, lead evidence</Text><Subparagraph><Label>(i)</Label><Text>to prove <Ins>the fact</Ins> that the accused has previously been convicted of a criminal offence,</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph><Label>(ii)</Label><Text>to prove <Ins>the fact</Ins> that the accused has been charged with and is awaiting trial for another criminal offence,</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph><Label>(iii)</Label><Text>to prove <Ins>the fact</Ins> that the accused has previously committed an offence under section 145,</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph><Label>(iv)</Label><Text>to show the circumstances of the alleged offence, particularly as they relate to the probability of conviction of the accused<Ins>, or</Ins></Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph change="ins"><Label>(v)</Label><Text>to prove the fact that the accused has failed to appear in court on one or more occasions when required to do so;</Text></Subparagraph></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText><ExplanatoryNote><Label><Emphasis style="italic">Clause 2</Emphasis> :</Label><ExplanatoryText>Existing text of relevant portions of subsection 518(1):</ExplanatoryText><ExistingText><Section><MarginalNote>Inquiries to be made by justice and evidence</MarginalNote><Label>518</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>In any proceedings under section 515,</Text><Paragraph><Label>. . .</Label><Text><?xm-replace_text Text?></Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(c)</Label><Text>the prosecutor may, in addition to any other relevant evidence, lead evidence</Text><Subparagraph><Label>(i)</Label><Text>to prove that the accused has previously been convicted of a criminal offence,</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph><Label>(ii)</Label><Text>to prove that the accused has been charged with and is awaiting trial for another criminal offence,</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph><Label>(iii)</Label><Text>to prove that the accused has previously committed an offence under section 145, or</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph><Label>(iv)</Label><Text>to show the circumstances of the alleged offence, particularly as they relate to the probability of conviction of the accused;</Text></Subparagraph></Paragraph></Subsection></Section></ExistingText></ExplanatoryNote></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>3</Label><Text>Section 719 of the Act is amended by adding the following after subsection (3):  </Text><AmendedText change="ins"><Subsection><MarginalNote>Considerations</MarginalNote><Label>(3.01)</Label><Text>In exercising its discretion under subsection (3), a court shall take into account that the person was detained in custody for the reasons stated in the record referred to in subsection 515(9.1).</Text></Subsection></AmendedText><ExplanatoryNote><Label><Emphasis style="italic">Clause 3</Emphasis> :</Label><ExplanatoryText>New.</ExplanatoryText></ExplanatoryNote></Section></Body></Bill>