<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>


<Bill bill-origin="senate" bill-type="private-public" xml:lang="en" date-time="2013-12-12 17:19:34"><Identification><BillNumber>S-221</BillNumber><Parliament><Session>1</Session><Number>41</Number><RegnalYear><Year-s>64-65</Year-s><Monarch>Elizabeth II</Monarch></RegnalYear><Year-s>2015-2016</Year-s></Parliament><LongTitle>An Act to amend the Constitution Act, 1867 (Property qualifications of Senators)</LongTitle><ShortTitle status="unofficial">Constitution Act, 2016 (Property qualifications of Senators)</ShortTitle><RunningHead>An Act to amend the Constitution Act, 1867 (Property qualifications of Senators)</RunningHead><BillHistory><Stages stage="first-reading-senate"><Date><YYYY>2016</YYYY><MM>3</MM><DD>10</DD></Date></Stages></BillHistory><BillSponsor> Patterson</BillSponsor><BillRefNumber date-time="2013-12-10">4211325-2</BillRefNumber></Identification><Introduction><Summary><TitleText>SUMMARY</TitleText><Provision language-align="yes"><Text>The enactment amends the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Constitution Act, 1867</XRefExternal> to eliminate the requirement that Senators have a personal net worth of at least four thousand dollars and to eliminate the real property requirement for Senators representing a province other than Quebec.</Text></Provision></Summary><Preamble><Provision language-align="yes"><MarginalNote>Preamble</MarginalNote><Text>Whereas the Senate provides representation for groups that are often underrepresented in Parliament, such as Aboriginal peoples, visible minorities and women;</Text></Provision><Provision><Text>Whereas the Constitution of Canada requires that, in order to be qualified for appointment to and to maintain a place in the Senate, a person must own land with a net worth of at least four thousand dollars in the province for which he or she is appointed and must own real and personal property with a combined net worth of at least four thousand dollars;</Text></Provision><Provision><Text>Whereas a person’s personal circumstances or the availability of real property in a particular location may prevent him or her from owning the required property;</Text></Provision><Provision><Text>Whereas appointment to the Senate should not be restricted to those who own real and personal property of a  minimum net worth;</Text></Provision><Provision><Text>Whereas the existing property qualifications are inconsistent with the democratic values of modern Canadian society and are no longer appropriate or relevant measures of the fitness of a person to serve in the Senate;</Text></Provision><Provision><Text>Whereas the Parliament of Canada, by virtue of section 44 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Constitution Act, 1982</XRefExternal>, may make laws to amend the Constitution of Canada in relation to the Senate;</Text></Provision><Provision><Text>Whereas, in the case of Quebec, each of the twenty-four Senators representing the province must be appointed for and must have either their real property qualification in or be resident of a specified Electoral Division;</Text></Provision><Provision><Text>Whereas the Supreme Court of Canada has determined that a full repeal of paragraph (3) of section 23 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Constitution Act, 1867</XRefExternal> respecting the real property qualification of Senators would require a resolution of the National Assembly of Quebec;</Text></Provision><Provision><Text>And whereas the Supreme Court of Canada has confirmed the legislative authority of the Parliament of Canada to repeal paragraph (4) of section 23 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Constitution Act, 1867</XRefExternal> respecting the requirement that Senators have a personal net worth of at least four thousand dollars;</Text></Provision></Preamble><Enacts><Provision language-align="yes"><Text>Now, therefore, Her Majesty, by and with the advice and consent of the Senate and House of Commons of Canada, <Keep>enacts</Keep> as follows:</Text></Provision></Enacts></Introduction><Body><Heading level="1"><TitleText>Short Title</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Short title</MarginalNote><Label>1</Label><Text>This Act may be cited as the <Emphasis style="italic">Constitution Act, 2016 (Property qualifications of Senators)</Emphasis>.</Text></Section><Heading level="1"><MarginalNote><HistoricalNote>30 &amp; 31 Victoria, c. 3 <Keep>(U.K.)</Keep></HistoricalNote></MarginalNote><TitleText>Constitution Act, 1867</TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><Label>2</Label><Text>Paragraph (4) of section 23 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Constitution Act, 1867</XRefExternal> is repealed.</Text><ExplanatoryNote><TitleText><XRefExternal reference-type="act">Constitution Act, 1867</XRefExternal></TitleText><Label><Emphasis style="italic">Clause 2</Emphasis>:</Label><ExplanatoryText>Existing text of relevant portions of section 23:</ExplanatoryText><ExistingText><Section><Label>23.</Label><Text>The Qualifications of a Senator shall be as follows:</Text><Provision first-line-indent="1" subsequent-line-indent="2.5"><Label>. . .</Label><Text /></Provision><Provision first-line-indent="1" subsequent-line-indent="2.5"><Text>(4) His Real and Personal Property shall be together worth Four thousand Dollars over and above his Debts and Liabilities;</Text></Provision><Provision first-line-indent="1" subsequent-line-indent="2.5"><Label>. . .</Label><Text /></Provision></Section></ExistingText></ExplanatoryNote></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>3</Label><Text>The Act is amended by adding the following after section 23:</Text><AmendedText><Section><MarginalNote>Real property qualification</MarginalNote><Label>23A.</Label><Text>Paragraph (3) of section 23 ceases to apply, after the coming into force of this section, to Senators representing a province other than Quebec.</Text></Section></AmendedText><ExplanatoryNote><Label><Emphasis style="italic">Clause 3</Emphasis> :</Label><ExplanatoryText>New.</ExplanatoryText></ExplanatoryNote></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>4</Label><Text>The Declaration of Qualification set out in The Fifth Schedule to the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText change="ins"><Provision justification="center"><Text><Emphasis style="smallcaps">Declaration of Qualification</Emphasis></Text></Provision><Provision first-line-indent="1"><Text>I, <Emphasis style="italic">A.B.</Emphasis>, do  declare  and  testify that I am  by  law  duly  qualified  to  be appointed a member of the Senate of Canada.</Text></Provision></AmendedText><ExplanatoryNote><Label><Emphasis style="italic">Clause 4</Emphasis>:</Label><ExplanatoryText>Existing text of the Declaration of Qualification:</ExplanatoryText><ExistingText><Provision first-line-indent="1"><Text>I <Emphasis style="italic">A.B.</Emphasis> do declare and testify, That I am by Law duly qualified to be appointed a Member of the Senate of Canada [<Emphasis style="italic">or as the Case may be</Emphasis>], and that I am legally or equitably seised as of Freehold for my own Use and Benefit of Lands or Tenements held in Free and Common Socage [<Emphasis style="italic">or</Emphasis> seised or possessed for my own Use and Benefit of Lands or Tenements held in Franc-alleu or in Roture (<Emphasis style="italic">as the Case may be</Emphasis>),] in the Province of Nova Scotia [<Emphasis style="italic">or as the Case may be</Emphasis>] of the Value of Four thousand Dollars over and above all Rents, Dues, Debts, Mortgages, Charges, and Incumbrances due or payable out of or charged on or affecting the same, and that I have not collusively or colourably obtained a Title to or become possessed of the said Lands and Tenements or any Part thereof for the Purpose of enabling me to become a Member of the Senate of Canada [<Emphasis style="italic">or as the Case may be</Emphasis>], and that my Real and Personal Property are together worth Four thousand Dollars over and above my Debts and Liabilities.</Text></Provision></ExistingText></ExplanatoryNote></Section><Heading level="1"><TitleText>Coordinating Amendments</TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote><DefinedTermEn>Amendment</DefinedTermEn></MarginalNote><Label>5</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>In this section, <DefinedTermEn>Amendment</DefinedTermEn> means the repeal of paragraphs (3) and (6) of section 23 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Constitution Act, 1867</XRefExternal>.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><Label>(2)</Label><Text>If section 3 of this Act comes into force before the Amendment is made, then, on the day on which the Amendment is made, section 23A of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Constitution Act, 1867</XRefExternal>, as enacted by section 3 of this Act, is repealed.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><Label>(3)</Label><Text>If the Amendment is made before section 3 of this Act comes into force, then that section 3 is deemed never to have come into force and is repealed.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><Label>(4)</Label><Text>If section 3 of this Act comes into force on the same day as the Amendment is made, then the Amendment is deemed to have been made before that section 3 and subsection (3) applies as a consequence.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><Label>(5)</Label><Text>On the first day on which both the Amendment is made and this Act is in force, paragraph 5 of section 31 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Constitution Act, 1867</XRefExternal>, is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><Provision first-line-indent="1.6" subsequent-line-indent="2.5"><Text>(5) If he ceases to be qualified in respect of Residence; provided, that a Senator shall not be deemed to have ceased to be qualified in respect of Residence by reason only of his residing at the Seat of the Government of Canada while holding an Office under that Government requiring his Presence there.</Text></Provision></AmendedText><ExplanatoryNote><Label><Emphasis style="italic">Clause 5</Emphasis>:</Label><ExplanatoryText>Existing text of paragraph 5 of section 31:</ExplanatoryText><ExistingText><Section><Label>31.</Label><Text>The Place of a Senator shall become vacant in any of the following Cases:</Text><Provision first-line-indent="1" subsequent-line-indent="2.5"><Label>. . .</Label><Text /></Provision><Provision first-line-indent="1.6" subsequent-line-indent="2.5"><Text>(5) If he ceases to be qualified in respect of Property or of Residence; provided, that a Senator shall not be deemed to have ceased to be qualified in respect of Residence by reason only of his residing at the Seat of the Government of Canada while holding an Office under that Government requiring his presence there.</Text></Provision><Provision first-line-indent="1" subsequent-line-indent="2.5"><Label>. . .</Label><Text /></Provision></Section></ExistingText></ExplanatoryNote></Subsection></Section><Heading level="1"><TitleText>Interpretation</TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote>Interpretation</MarginalNote><Label>6</Label><Text>A reference to the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Constitution Acts, 1867 to 1982</XRefExternal> is deemed to include a reference to this Act.</Text></Section></Body></Bill>