<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><Bill bill-origin="senate" bill-type="private-public" xml:lang="en" date-time="2016-11-16 11:04:16"><Identification><BillNumber>S-235</BillNumber><Parliament><Session>1</Session><Number>42</Number><RegnalYear><Year-s>64-65</Year-s><Monarch>Elizabeth II</Monarch></RegnalYear><Year-s>2015-2016</Year-s></Parliament><LongTitle> An Act to amend the Prohibiting Cluster Munitions Act (investments)</LongTitle><ShortTitle status="unofficial">Prohibiting Investments in Cluster Munitions Act</ShortTitle><RunningHead>An Act to amend the Prohibiting Cluster Munitions Act (investments)</RunningHead><BillHistory><Stages stage="first-reading-senate"><Date><YYYY>2016</YYYY><MM>12</MM><DD>15</DD></Date></Stages></BillHistory><BillSponsor>Senator Ataullahjan</BillSponsor><BillRefNumber date-time="">4211620</BillRefNumber></Identification><Introduction><Summary><TitleText>SUMMARY</TitleText><Provision><Text>This enactment creates a new prohibition against investing in an entity that has breached a prohibition relating to cluster munitions, explosive submunitions and explosive bomblets.</Text></Provision></Summary></Introduction><Body><Heading level="1"><TitleText>Short Title</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Short title</MarginalNote><Label>1</Label><Text>This Act may be cited as the <Emphasis style="italic">Prohibiting Investments in Cluster Munitions Act</Emphasis>.</Text></Section><Heading level="1"><MarginalNote><HistoricalNote>2014, c. 27</HistoricalNote></MarginalNote><TitleText><XRefExternal reference-type="act">Prohibiting Cluster Munitions Act</XRefExternal></TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><Label>2</Label><Text>Section 4 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Prohibiting Cluster Munitions Act</XRefExternal> is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><Section><MarginalNote>Purpose</MarginalNote><Label>4</Label><Text>The purpose of this Act is to implement Canada’s commitments under the Convention <Ins>and to provide other measures respecting cluster munitions, explosive submunitions and explosive bomblets</Ins>.</Text><ExplanatoryNote><TitleText><XRefExternal reference-type="act">Prohibiting Cluster Munitions Act</XRefExternal></TitleText><Label><Emphasis style="italic">Clause 2</Emphasis>:</Label><ExplanatoryText>Existing text of section 4:</ExplanatoryText><ExistingText><Section><Label>4</Label><Text>The purpose of this Act is to implement Canada’s commitments under the Convention.</Text></Section></ExistingText></ExplanatoryNote></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>3</Label><Text>Paragraphs 6(e) to (h) of the Act are replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><SectionPiece><Paragraph change="ins"><Label>(d.1)</Label><Text>acquire or have, directly or indirectly and individually or as a shareholder, partner or otherwise, any pecuniary interest in, or loan funds or guarantee a loan of funds to, a person knowing that the person has committed or has aided or abetted in the commission of any act referred to in paragraphs (a) to (d);</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(e)</Label><Text>attempt to commit any act referred to in paragraphs (a) to (<Ins>d.1</Ins>);</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(f)</Label><Text>aid, abet or counsel another person to commit any act referred to in paragraphs (a) to (<Ins>d.1</Ins>);</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(g)</Label><Text>conspire with another person to commit any act referred to in paragraphs (a) to (<Ins>d.1</Ins>); or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(h)</Label><Text>receive, comfort or assist another person, knowing that the person has committed, or has aided or abetted in the commission of, any act referred to in paragraphs (a) to (<Ins>d.1</Ins>), for the purpose of enabling the person to escape.</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText><ExplanatoryNote><Label><Emphasis style="italic">Clause 3</Emphasis>:</Label><ExplanatoryText>Existing text of relevant portions of section 6:</ExplanatoryText><ExistingText><Section><Label>6</Label><Text>Subject to sections 7, 8 and 10 to 12, it is prohibited for any person to</Text><Paragraph><Label>. . .</Label><Text /></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(e)</Label><Text>attempt to commit any act referred to in paragraphs (a) to (d);</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(f)</Label><Text>aid, abet or counsel another person to commit any act referred to in paragraphs (a) to (d);</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(g)</Label><Text>conspire with another person to commit any act referred to in paragraphs (a) to (d); or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(h)</Label><Text>receive, comfort or assist another person, knowing that the person has committed, or has aided or abetted in the commission of, any act referred to in paragraphs (a) to (d), for the purpose of enabling the person to escape.</Text></Paragraph></Section></ExistingText></ExplanatoryNote></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>4</Label><Text>Paragraphs 11(3)(a) to (c) of the Act are replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>aiding, abetting or counselling another person to commit any act referred to in paragraphs 6(a) to (<Ins>d.1</Ins>), if it would not be an offence for that other person to commit that act;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>conspiring with another person to commit any act referred to in paragraphs 6(a) to (<Ins>d.1</Ins>), if it would not be an offence for that other person to commit that act; or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(c)</Label><Text>receiving, comforting or assisting another person, knowing that that other person has committed, or has aided or abetted in the commission of, any act referred to in paragraphs 6(a) to (<Ins>d.1</Ins>), for the purpose of enabling that other person to escape, if it was not an offence for that other person to commit that act.</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText><ExplanatoryNote><Label><Emphasis style="italic">Clause 4</Emphasis>:</Label><ExplanatoryText>Existing text of subsection 11(3):</ExplanatoryText><ExistingText><Subsection><Label>(3)</Label><Text>Section 6 does not prohibit a person, in the course of military cooperation or combined military operations involving Canada and a state that is not a party to the Convention, from</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>aiding, abetting or counselling another person to commit any act referred to in paragraphs 6(a) to (d), if it would not be an offence for that other person to commit that act;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>conspiring with another person to commit any act referred to in paragraphs 6(a) to (d), if it would not be an offence for that other person to commit that act; or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(c)</Label><Text>receiving, comforting or assisting another person, knowing that that other person has committed, or has aided or abetted in the commission of, any act referred to in paragraphs 6(a) to (d), for the purpose of enabling that other person to escape, if it was not an offence for that other person to commit that act.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection></ExistingText></ExplanatoryNote></Section><Heading level="1"><TitleText>Transitional Provision</TitleText></Heading><Section type="transitional"><MarginalNote>Divestment</MarginalNote><Label>5</Label><Text>Paragraph 6(d.1) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Prohibiting Cluster Munitions Act</XRefExternal>, as enacted by section 2 of this Act, does not apply to a person in respect of a pecuniary interest that they have or a loan of funds or the guarantee of such a loan that they made before the coming into force of this Act, provided that they divest themselves of the pecuniary interest, loan or guarantee within one year after the coming into force of this Act.</Text></Section></Body></Bill>