<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>


<Bill bill-origin="senate" bill-type="private-public" xml:lang="en" date-time="2011-05-02 13:34:11"><Identification><BillNumber>S-237</BillNumber><Parliament><Session>1</Session><Number>42</Number><RegnalYear><Year-s>64-65-66</Year-s><Monarch>Elizabeth II</Monarch></RegnalYear><Year-s>2015-2016-2017</Year-s></Parliament><LongTitle>An Act to amend the Criminal Code (criminal interest rate)</LongTitle><ShortTitle status="unofficial" /><RunningHead>Criminal Code (criminal interest rate)</RunningHead><BillHistory><Stages stage="first-reading-senate"><Date><YYYY>2017</YYYY><MM>3</MM><DD>9</DD></Date></Stages></BillHistory><BillSponsor> RINGUETTE</BillSponsor><BillRefNumber date-time="2010-09-27">4211017</BillRefNumber></Identification><Introduction><Summary><TitleText>SUMMARY</TitleText><Provision><Text>     This enactment amends the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Criminal Code</XRefExternal> to reduce the criminal rate of interest from sixty per cent to the Bank of Canada’s overnight rate plus twenty per cent on credit advanced for certain purposes, which would include personal, family and household purposes.  It maintains the criminal rate at sixty per cent on credit advanced for business or commercial purposes.  However, business or commercial agreements under which the credit advanced equals or exceeds one million dollars are exempt from the offence of charging a criminal rate of interest.  </Text></Provision></Summary><Enacts><Provision first-line-indent="1"><Text>Her Majesty, by and with the advice and consent of the Senate and House of Commons of Canada, enacts as follows:</Text></Provision></Enacts></Introduction><Body><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote><HistoricalNote>R.S., c. C-46</HistoricalNote></MarginalNote><Label>1</Label><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The definition <DefinedTermEn>criminal rate</DefinedTermEn> in subsection 347(2) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Criminal Code</XRefExternal> is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><SectionPiece><Definition><Text><DefinedTermEn>criminal rate</DefinedTermEn> means an effective annual rate of interest calculated in accordance with generally accepted actuarial practices and principles</Text><Paragraph change="off"><Label><Ins>(a)</Ins></Label><Text>that exceeds sixty per cent on the credit advanced under an agreement or arrangement<Ins>, if the credit is or is to be advanced for business or commercial purposes, or</Ins></Text></Paragraph><Paragraph change="ins"><Label><Ins>(b)</Ins></Label><Text>that exceeds the Bank of Canada’s overnight rate plus twenty per cent on the credit advanced under an agreement or arrangement, in  any other case; (<DefinedTermFr>taux criminel</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Paragraph></Definition></SectionPiece></AmendedText><ExplanatoryNote><TitleText><XRefExternal reference-type="act">Criminal Code</XRefExternal></TitleText><Label><Emphasis style="italic">Clause 1</Emphasis>: (1)</Label><ExplanatoryText>Existing text of the definition:</ExplanatoryText><ExistingText><SectionPiece><Definition><Text><DefinedTermEn>criminal rate</DefinedTermEn> means an effective annual rate of interest calculated in accordance with generally accepted actuarial practices and principles that exceeds sixty per cent on the credit advanced under an agreement or arrangement;</Text></Definition></SectionPiece></ExistingText></ExplanatoryNote></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Subsection 347(2) of the Act is amended by adding the following in alphabetical order:</Text><AmendedText change="ins"><SectionPiece><Definition><Text><DefinedTermEn>Bank of Canada’s overnight rate</DefinedTermEn>, in relation to credit advanced, means the Bank of Canada’s overnight rate on the day on which the agreement or arrangement under which the credit is or is to be advanced is entered into or renewed; (<DefinedTermFr>taux de financement à un jour de la Banque du Canada</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Definition></SectionPiece></AmendedText><ExplanatoryNote><Label>(2)</Label><ExplanatoryText>New.</ExplanatoryText></ExplanatoryNote></Subsection><Subsection><Label>(3)</Label><Text>Section 347 of the Act is amended by adding the following after subsection (2):</Text><AmendedText change="ins"><Subsection><MarginalNote>Meaning of business or commercial purposes</MarginalNote><Label>(2.1)</Label><Text>For the purposes of this section, credit is advanced for business or commercial purposes if</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>it is advanced to an organization that operates for profit or to an individual who operates a business or engages in a commercial activity for profit; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>it is not advanced for personal, family or household purposes.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection></AmendedText><ExplanatoryNote><Label>(3)</Label><ExplanatoryText>New.</ExplanatoryText></ExplanatoryNote></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(4)</Label><Text>Section 347 of the Act is amended by adding the following after subsection (8):</Text><AmendedText change="ins"><Subsection><MarginalNote>Application —  advancing credit over $1,000,000 for business purposes</MarginalNote><Label>(9)</Label><Text>This section does not apply in respect of an agreement or arrangement under which credit is or is to be advanced for business or commercial purposes if the credit advanced at any one time under the agreement or arrangement equals or exceeds one million dollars.</Text></Subsection></AmendedText><ExplanatoryNote><Label>(4)</Label><ExplanatoryText>New.</ExplanatoryText></ExplanatoryNote></Subsection></Section><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote>Coming into force</MarginalNote><Label>2</Label><Text>This Act comes into force 60 days after the day on which it receives royal assent.</Text></Section></Body></Bill>