<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><Bill bill-origin="senate" bill-type="private-public" xml:lang="en" date-time="2017-03-23 08:03:56"><Identification><BillNumber>S-238</BillNumber><Parliament><Session>1</Session><Number>42</Number><RegnalYear><Year-s>64-65-66</Year-s><Monarch>Elizabeth II</Monarch></RegnalYear><Year-s>2015-2016-2017</Year-s></Parliament><LongTitle>An Act to amend the Fisheries Act and the Wild Animal and Plant Protection and Regulation of International and Interprovincial Trade Act (importation of shark fins)</LongTitle><ShortTitle status="unofficial">Ban on Shark Fin Importation Act</ShortTitle><RunningHead>An Act to amend the Fisheries Act and the Wild Animal and Plant Protection and Regulation of International and Interprovincial Trade Act (importation of shark fins)</RunningHead><BillHistory><Stages stage="first-reading-senate"><Date><YYYY>2017</YYYY><MM>4</MM><DD>11</DD></Date></Stages></BillHistory><BillSponsor>Senator MacDonald</BillSponsor><BillRefNumber date-time="">4211630</BillRefNumber></Identification><Introduction><Summary><TitleText>SUMMARY</TitleText><Provision><Text>This enactment amends the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Fisheries Act</XRefExternal> to prohibit the practice of shark finning.</Text></Provision><Provision><Text>It also amends the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Wild Animal and Plant Protection and Regulation of International and Interprovincial Trade Act</XRefExternal> to prohibit the importation in Canada of shark fins that are not attached to the shark carcass.</Text></Provision></Summary><Preamble><Provision language-align="yes"><Text>Whereas in 1994 the Canadian Government banned shark finning — namely, the practice of removing the fins from live sharks and discarding the remainder of the sharks while at sea — in Canadian fisheries waters and with respect to Canadian licensed vessels fishing outside of Canada’s exclusive economic zone;</Text></Provision><Provision><Text>Whereas Canadians are increasingly aware of the devastating effect of the continuing practice of shark finning and the resulting decline in shark species in Canadian waters and around the world, and are in support of measures to stop this practice and ensure the responsible conservation, management and exploitation of sharks;</Text></Provision><Provision><Text>And whereas the importation of shark fins is not justifiable in the face of the dramatic decline in shark species and losses in shark populations worldwide;</Text></Provision></Preamble><Enacts><Provision><Text>Now, therefore, Her Majesty, by and with the advice and consent of the Senate and House of Commons of Canada, enacts as follows:</Text></Provision></Enacts></Introduction><Body><Heading level="1"><TitleText>Short Title</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Short Title</MarginalNote><Label>1</Label><Text>This Act may be cited as the <Emphasis style="italic">Ban on Shark Fin Importation Act</Emphasis>.</Text></Section><Heading level="1"><MarginalNote><HistoricalNote>R.‍S.‍, c. F-14</HistoricalNote></MarginalNote><TitleText>Fisheries Act</TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><Label>2</Label><Text>The <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Fisheries Act</XRefExternal> is amended by adding the following after section 31:</Text><AmendedText change="ins"><Section><MarginalNote>Prohibition</MarginalNote><Label>32</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>No person shall engage in the practice of shark finning. </Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Definition of <DefinedTermEn>shark finning</DefinedTermEn></MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>In this section, <DefinedTermEn>shark finning</DefinedTermEn> means the practice of removing the fins from live sharks and discarding the remainder of the sharks while at sea.</Text></Subsection></Section></AmendedText><ExplanatoryNote><TitleText>Fisheries Act</TitleText><Label><Emphasis style="italic">Clause 2</Emphasis>:</Label><ExplanatoryText>New.</ExplanatoryText></ExplanatoryNote></Section><Heading level="1"><MarginalNote><HistoricalNote>1992, c. 52</HistoricalNote></MarginalNote><TitleText>Wild Animal and Plant Protection and Regulation of International and Interprovincial Trade Act</TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><Label>3</Label><Text>Section 6 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Wild Animal and Plant Protection and Regulation of International and Interprovincial Trade Act</XRefExternal> is amended by adding the following after subsection (1):</Text><AmendedText change="ins"><Subsection><MarginalNote>Importation of shark fins</MarginalNote><Label>(1.1)</Label><Text>No person shall, except under and in accordance with a permit issued pursuant to subsection 10(1.‍1), import, or attempt to import, into Canada shark fins that are not attached to a shark carcass.</Text></Subsection></AmendedText><ExplanatoryNote><TitleText>Wild Animal and Plant Protection and Regulation of International and Interprovincial Trade Act</TitleText><Label><Emphasis style="italic">Clause 3</Emphasis>:</Label><ExplanatoryText>New.</ExplanatoryText></ExplanatoryNote></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>4</Label><Text>Section 10 of the Act is amended by adding the following after subsection (1): </Text><AmendedText change="ins"><Subsection><MarginalNote>Permit — importation of shark fins</MarginalNote><Label>(1.1)</Label><Text>The Minister may, on application and on such terms and conditions as the Minister thinks fit, issue a permit authorizing the importation of shark fins that are not attached to a shark carcass if the Minister is of the opinion that</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>the importation is for the purpose of scientific research relating to shark conservation that is conducted by qualified persons; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>the activity benefits the survival of shark species or is required to enhance their chance of survival in the wild.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection></AmendedText><ExplanatoryNote><Label><Emphasis style="italic">Clause 4</Emphasis>:</Label><ExplanatoryText>New.</ExplanatoryText></ExplanatoryNote></Section></Body></Bill>