<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><Bill bill-origin="senate" bill-type="private-public" xml:lang="en" date-time="2016-11-04 12:11:36"><Identification><BillNumber>S-232</BillNumber><Parliament><Session>1</Session><Number>42</Number><RegnalYear><Year-s>64-65-66-67</Year-s><Monarch>Elizabeth II</Monarch></RegnalYear><Year-s>2015-2016-2017-2018</Year-s></Parliament><LongTitle>An Act respecting Canadian Jewish Heritage Month</LongTitle><ShortTitle status="unofficial">Canadian Jewish Heritage Month Act</ShortTitle><RunningHead>An Act respecting Canadian Jewish Heritage Month</RunningHead><BillHistory><Stages stage="assented-to"><Date><YYYY>2018</YYYY><MM>3</MM><DD>29</DD></Date></Stages></BillHistory><Chapter><ConsolidatedNumber /><AnnualStatuteId><AnnualStatuteNumber>5</AnnualStatuteNumber><YYYY>2018</YYYY></AnnualStatuteId></Chapter><BillRefNumber date-time="">4211622</BillRefNumber></Identification><Introduction><Summary><TitleText>SUMMARY</TitleText><Provision language-align="no"><Text>This enactment designates the month of May in each and <Keep>every</Keep> year as “Canadian Jewish Heritage Month”.</Text></Provision></Summary><Preamble><Provision language-align="yes"><MarginalNote>Preamble</MarginalNote><Text>Whereas the Jewish population in Canada is approximately 400,000 people, making it the fourth-largest Jewish population in the world;</Text></Provision><Provision><Text>Whereas the Canadian Jewish community has made significant contributions to the growth and prosperity of Canada while overcoming tremendous obstacles;</Text></Provision><Provision><Text>Whereas the month of May is meaningful for the Jewish community around the world;</Text></Provision><Provision><Text>Whereas, by designating the month of May as Canadian Jewish Heritage Month, the Parliament of Canada recognizes the important contributions that Jewish Canadians have made to Canada's social, economic, political and cultural fabric;</Text></Provision><Provision><Text>And whereas Canadian Jewish Heritage Month would provide an opportunity to remember, celebrate and educate future generations about the inspirational role that Jewish Canadians have played and continue to play in communities across the country;</Text></Provision></Preamble><Enacts><Provision language-align="yes"><Text>Now, therefore, Her Majesty, by and with the advice and consent of the Senate and House of Commons of Canada, enacts as follows:</Text></Provision></Enacts></Introduction><Body><Heading level="1"><TitleText>Short title</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Short title</MarginalNote><Label>1</Label><Text>This Act may be cited as the <Emphasis style="italic">Canadian Jewish <Keep>Heritage</Keep> Month Act</Emphasis>.</Text></Section><Heading level="1"><TitleText>Canadian Jewish Heritage Month</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Canadian Jewish Heritage Month</MarginalNote><Label>2</Label><Text>Throughout Canada, in each and every year, the month of May is to be known as “Canadian Jewish Heritage Month”.</Text></Section></Body></Bill>