<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><Bill bill-origin="senate" bill-type="private-public" xml:lang="en" date-time="2018-02-09 13:32:34"><Identification><BillNumber>S-245</BillNumber><Parliament><Session>1</Session><Number>42</Number><RegnalYear><Year-s>64-65-66-67</Year-s><Monarch>Elizabeth II</Monarch></RegnalYear><Year-s>2015-2016-2017-2018</Year-s></Parliament><LongTitle>An Act to declare the Trans Mountain Pipeline Project and related works to be for the general advantage of Canada</LongTitle><ShortTitle status="unofficial">Trans Mountain Pipeline Project Act</ShortTitle><RunningHead>An Act to declare the Trans Mountain Pipeline Project and related works to be for the general advantage of Canada</RunningHead><BillHistory><Stages stage="first-reading-senate"><Date><YYYY>2018</YYYY><MM>2</MM><DD>15</DD></Date></Stages></BillHistory><BillSponsor>Senator Black</BillSponsor><BillRefNumber date-time="">4211726</BillRefNumber></Identification><Introduction><Summary><TitleText>SUMMARY</TitleText><Provision><Text>This enactment declares the Trans Mountain Pipeline Project and related works to be works for the general advantage of Canada. </Text></Provision></Summary><Preamble><Provision><MarginalNote>Preamble</MarginalNote><Text>Whereas the Government of Canada has approved the Trans Mountain Pipeline Project, which, among other things, twins the existing pipeline from Edmonton, Alberta, to Burnaby, British Columbia;</Text></Provision><Provision><Text>Whereas the Government of British Columbia has indicated that it is considering imposing restrictions on bitumen shipments through the pipeline;</Text></Provision><Provision><Text>And whereas, for greater certainty regarding jurisdiction, the Parliament of Canada has deemed it necessary to declare this project to be a work for the general advantage of Canada under the authority of class 29 of section 91 and paragraph (c) of class 10 of section 92 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Constitution Act, 1867</XRefExternal>;</Text></Provision></Preamble><Enacts><Provision language-align="yes"><Text>Now, therefore, Her Majesty, by and with the advice and consent of the Senate and House of Commons of Canada, enacts as follows:</Text></Provision></Enacts></Introduction><Body><Heading level="1"><TitleText>Short Title</TitleText></Heading><Section><Label>1</Label><Text>This Act may be cited as the <Emphasis style="italic">Trans Mountain Pipeline Project Act</Emphasis>.</Text></Section><Heading level="1"><TitleText>Interpretation</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Definition of <Emphasis style="italic">Trans Mountain Pipeline Project</Emphasis></MarginalNote><Label>2</Label><Text>In this Act, <DefinedTermEn>Trans Mountain Pipeline Project</DefinedTermEn> means the Trans Mountain Pipeline Expansion Project approved by Order in Council P.C. 2016-1069 of November 29, 2016, which includes the building of a new pipeline along the existing Trans Mountain pipeline route between Edmonton, Alberta, and Burnaby, British Columbia, as well as the expansion of the Westridge Marine Terminal in Burnaby.</Text></Section><Heading level="1"><TitleText>Purpose</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Purpose</MarginalNote><Label>3</Label><Text>The purpose of this Act is to ensure that the Trans Mountain Pipeline Project and any works related to it that are carried out in accordance with federal legislation and with the Certificate of Public Convenience and Necessity OC-064 issued by the National Energy Board on December 1, 2016, are not frustrated or delayed.</Text></Section><Heading level="1"><TitleText>Application</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Declaration</MarginalNote><Label>4</Label><Text>The Trans Mountain Pipeline Project and related works are declared to be works for the general advantage of Canada.</Text></Section></Body></Bill>