<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><Bill bill-origin="senate" bill-type="private-public" xml:lang="en" date-time="2018-03-08 16:09:21"><Identification><BillNumber>S-248</BillNumber><Parliament><Session>1</Session><Number>42</Number><RegnalYear><Year-s>64-65-66-67</Year-s><Monarch>Elizabeth II</Monarch></RegnalYear><Year-s>2015-2016-2017-2018</Year-s></Parliament><LongTitle>An Act respecting National Physicians芒聙聶 Day</LongTitle><ShortTitle status="unofficial">National Physicians芒聙聶 Day</ShortTitle><RunningHead>An Act respecting National Physicians芒聙聶 Day</RunningHead><BillHistory><Stages stage="first-reading-senate"><Date><YYYY>2018</YYYY><MM>3</MM><DD>28</DD></Date></Stages></BillHistory><BillSponsor>Senator Eggleton, P.C.</BillSponsor><BillRefNumber date-time="">4211731</BillRefNumber></Identification><Introduction><Summary><TitleText>SUMMARY</TitleText><Provision><Text>This enactment designates May 1 as 芒聙聹National Physicians芒聙聶 Day芒聙聺.</Text></Provision></Summary><Preamble><Provision language-align="yes"><MarginalNote>Preamble</MarginalNote><Text>Whereas, throughout Canada芒聙聶s history, physicians have played not only a vital role in caring for patients, but also in increasing the life expectancy and well-being of all Canadians from coast to coast to coast;</Text></Provision><Provision><Text>Whereas medical students, residents, and practising and retired physicians are an inherent and essential component of Canada芒聙聶s health care system 芒聙聰 one of Canada芒聙聶s most cherished social programs;</Text></Provision><Provision><Text>Whereas the medical achievements of Canada芒聙聶s physicians, including innovations in stem cell research, the discovery of insulin, and world-leading medical technologies are merely a fraction of what the medical profession in Canada has done and will do to improve the health of Canadians;</Text></Provision><Provision><Text>Whereas declaring a day as National Physicians芒聙聶 Day would provide an opportunity for patients and all Canadians to show their appreciation to and recognition of the more than 125,000 physicians, residents and medical students across the country;</Text></Provision><Provision><Text>Whereas the first of May 芒聙聰 which is the birthday of Dr. Emily Stowe, the first woman to practise medicine in Canada 芒聙聰 has already been declared Doctors芒聙聶 Day in Ontario and Nova Scotia;</Text></Provision><Provision><Text>And whereas a national day of recognition for the extraordinary contributions and sacrifices of all of Canada芒聙聶s physicians is long overdue;</Text></Provision></Preamble><Enacts><Provision language-align="yes"><Text>Now, therefore, Her Majesty, by and with the advice and consent of the Senate and House of Commons of Canada, enacts as follows:</Text></Provision></Enacts></Introduction><Body><Heading level="1"><TitleText>SHORT TITLE</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Short Title</MarginalNote><Label>1</Label><Text>This Act may be cited as the <Emphasis style="italic">National Physicians芒聙聶 Day Act</Emphasis>.</Text></Section><Heading level="1"><TitleText>NATIONAL PHYSICIANS芒聙聶 DAY</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>National Physicians芒聙聶 Day </MarginalNote><Label>2</Label><Text>Throughout Canada, in each and every year, the first day of May shall be known as 芒聙聹National Physicians芒聙聶 Day.芒聙聺</Text></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Not a legal holiday</MarginalNote><Label>3</Label><Text>For greater certainty, National Physicians芒聙聶 Day is not a legal holiday or a non-juridical day.</Text></Section></Body></Bill>