<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><Bill bill-origin="senate" bill-type="private-public" xml:lang="en" date-time="2018-09-27 16:43:36"><Identification><BillNumber>S-256</BillNumber><Parliament><Session>1</Session><Number>42</Number><RegnalYear><Year-s>64-65-66-67</Year-s><Monarch>Elizabeth II</Monarch></RegnalYear><Year-s>2015-2016-2017-2018</Year-s></Parliament><LongTitle>An Act respecting the development of a national framework for essential workforce skills</LongTitle><ShortTitle status="unofficial">National Framework for Essential Workforce Skills Act</ShortTitle><RunningHead>An Act respecting the development of a national framework for essential workforce skills</RunningHead><BillHistory><Stages stage="first-reading-senate"><Date><YYYY>2018</YYYY><MM>10</MM><DD>30</DD></Date></Stages></BillHistory><BillSponsor>Senator Bellemare</BillSponsor><BillRefNumber date-time="">4211732</BillRefNumber></Identification><Introduction><Summary><TitleText>SUMMARY</TitleText><Provision><Text>This enactment provides for the development of a national framework for essential workforce skills by the Minister of Employment and Social Development in partnership with the competent provincial and territorial government representatives. The framework also includes result targets for each essential skill and a timeline for achieving each target.</Text></Provision></Summary><Preamble><Provision language-align="yes"><MarginalNote>Preamble</MarginalNote><Text>Whereas the United Nations General Assembly unanimously adopted the 2030 Agenda for Sustainable Development and its 17 Sustainable Development Goals on September 25, 2015;</Text></Provision><Provision><Text>Whereas the United Nations General Assembly declared Sustainable Development Goal 4 to be to “[e]nsure inclusive and equitable quality education and promote lifelong learning opportunities for all”;</Text></Provision><Provision><Text>Whereas the United Nations General Assembly declared Sustainable Development Goal 8 to be to “[p]romote sustained, inclusive and sustainable economic growth, full and productive employment and decent work for all”;</Text></Provision><Provision><Text>Whereas a significant proportion of working-age Canadians do not have the essential skills to fully participate in the labour market;</Text></Provision><Provision><Text>Whereas major regional and demographic disparities in workforce skills exist in Canada;</Text></Provision><Provision><Text>Whereas the development of new technologies, including those relating to artificial intelligence, requires ongoing workforce skills renewal;</Text></Provision><Provision><Text>Whereas improving workforce skills has a positive impact on economic growth, the integration of workers into the labour market and their standard of living;</Text></Provision><Provision><Text>And whereas a national framework contributes to the development of essential workforce skills by establishing a common language, recognized across the country;</Text></Provision></Preamble><Enacts><Provision language-align="yes"><Text>Now, therefore, Her Majesty, by and with the advice and consent of the Senate and House of Commons of Canada, <Keep>enacts</Keep> as follows:</Text></Provision></Enacts></Introduction><Body><Section><MarginalNote>Short title</MarginalNote><Label>1</Label><Text>This Act may be cited as the <Emphasis style="italic">National Framework for Essential Workforce Skills Act</Emphasis>.</Text></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Definitions</MarginalNote><Label>2</Label><Text>The following definitions apply in this Act.</Text><Definition><Text><DefinedTermEn>framework</DefinedTermEn> means the national framework for essential workforce skills. (<DefinedTermFr>cadre</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Definition><Definition><Text><DefinedTermEn>Minister</DefinedTermEn> means the Minister of Employment and Social Development. (<DefinedTermFr>ministre</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Definition></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Framework — development</MarginalNote><Label>3</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The Minister, in partnership with the provincial and territorial government representatives responsible for the development of current and future workforce skills, must develop a national framework respecting the essential skills of the Canadian working-age population.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Framework — content</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The framework must include the following:</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>the current and future essential skills for the Canadian working-age population and the competency levels for each such skill;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>result targets for each essential skill; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(c)</Label><Text>a timeline for meeting each result target.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Consideration</MarginalNote><Label>4</Label><Text>In developing the framework, the Minister must take into account the following factors:</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>the division of powers between federal, provincial and territorial authorities, including in matters of education, training, employment insurance and labour;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>the importance of stakeholder participation in essential skills development, including that of employers and labour representatives;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(c)</Label><Text>the Organisation for Economic Co-operation and Development’s Programme for the International Assessment of Adult Competencies; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(d)</Label><Text>the specific needs of the various regions and communities, including Indigenous communities, in relation to the development of essential workforce skills.</Text></Paragraph></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Conference</MarginalNote><Label>5</Label><Text>Within one year after the day on which this Act comes into force, the Minister must convene a conference with the provincial and territorial representatives responsible for the development of current and future workforce skills in order to develop the national framework for essential workforce skills.</Text></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Report to Parliament</MarginalNote><Label>6</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Within two years after the day on which this Act comes into force, the Minister must prepare a report setting out the national framework for essential workforce skills and cause the report to be laid before each House of Parliament on any of the first 15 days on which that House is sitting after the report is completed.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Publication of report</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The Minister must publish the report on the departmental website within 30 days after the day on which the report is tabled in Parliament.</Text></Subsection></Section></Body></Bill>