<?xml version="1.0"?>
<Bill RHead_reign="57-58 Eliz. II" RHead_ParlYear="2009" DocumentTitle="BILL C-18" Bill_No="C-18" Document_No="90491" xml:lang="EN" Bill_Type="Non-amending" Stage_Name="Assented-to" Reprint="No" xml:space="preserve" ChapterNo_E="C. 13" ChapterNo_F="ch. 13" Bill-Origin="commons"><Bill_Part Part_Type="Cover" CountLines="No"><Block><Para TopMargin="24" Size="9" Leading="10" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0" TextAlign="Center">Second Session, Fortieth Parliament,</Para></Block><Block><Para Size="9" Leading="10" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0" TextAlign="Center">57-58 Elizabeth II, 2009</Para></Block><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="COV@StatutesTitle">STATUTES OF CANADA 2009<br/>CHAPTER 13</Para></Block><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="CovLongTitle">An Act to amend the Royal Canadian Mounted Police Superannuation Act, to validate certain calculations and to amend other Acts</Para></Block><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="COV_StageLine"></Para></Block><Block><Para BottomMargin="14" Size="11" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0" Bold="Yes" TextAlign="Center">ASSENTED TO</Para></Block><Block><Para Size="8" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0" TextAlign="Center">18th JUNE, 2009</Para></Block><Block><Para TopMargin="4" Size="8" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0" TextAlign="Center">BILL C-18</Para></Block><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="COV_StageLine"></Para></Block></Bill_Part><Bill_Part CountLines="No" Part_Type="InsideCover"><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="BPT_InsideCoverE">Also available on the Parliament of Canada Web Site at the following address:<br/><B>http://www.parl.gc.ca</B></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><Para TopMargin="108" BottomMargin="4" Size="10" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">RECOMMENDATION</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" Size="8" Leading="9" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">Her Excellency the Governor General recommends to the House of Commons the appropriation of public revenue under the circumstances, in the manner and for the purposes set out in a measure entitled 芒聙聹<I>An Act to amend the Royal Canadian Mounted Police Superannuation Act, to validate certain calculations and to amend other Acts</I>芒聙聺.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><Para TopMargin="60" BottomMargin="4" Size="10" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">SUMMARY</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" Size="8" Leading="9" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">This enactment amends the <I>Royal Canadian Mounted Police Superannuation Act</I> to add the provisions necessary for the implementation of amendments made to that Act by the <I>Public Sector Pension Investment Board Act</I> that relate to elective service and pension transfer agreements. It also brings into force certain provisions enacted by the <I>Public Sector Pension Investment Board Act</I>. Finally, the enactment validates certain calculations and amends other Acts.</Para></Block></Bill_Part><Bill_Part Part_Type="MainText" CountLines="No" RunningHead_E="Royal Canadian Mounted Police Superannuation"><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="MAIN@RoyalAssentTitle">57-58 ELIZABETH II</Para></Block><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="MAIN@RoyalAssentTitle">芒聙聰芒聙聰芒聙聰芒聙聰芒聙聰芒聙聰</Para></Block><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="MAIN@RoyalAssentTitle">CHAPTER 13</Para></Block><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="LongTitleAssent">An Act to amend the Royal Canadian Mounted Police Superannuation Act, to validate certain calculations and to amend other Acts</Para></Block><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="MAIN@RoyalAssentDate">[<I>Assented to 18th June, 2009</I>]</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">Her Majesty, by and with the advice and consent of the Senate and House of Commons of Canada, enacts as follows:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:ROYAL CANADIAN MOUNTED POLICE SUPERANNUATION ACT--><MarginalNote>R.S., c. R-11<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="10" Bold="Yes" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">ROYAL CANADIAN MOUNTED POLICE SUPERANNUATION ACT</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>1.</B> The headings before section 3 of the <I>Royal Canadian Mounted Police Superannu- ation Act</I> are replaced by the following:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes"><!--Heading:INTERPRETATION--><Para TopMargin="10" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">INTERPRETATION</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>2.</B> (1) The portion of subsection 3(1) of the Act before the definition 芒聙聹active service芒聙聺 is replaced by the following:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Definitions<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>3.</B> (1) In this Act,</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes">(2) The definitions 芒聙聹active service芒聙聺, 芒聙聹disabled芒聙聺, 芒聙聹member of the Force芒聙聺, 芒聙聹service in the Force芒聙聺, 芒聙聹World War I芒聙聺 and 芒聙聹World War II芒聙聺 in subsection 3(1) of the Act are replaced by the following:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>芒聙聹active service芒聙聺<br/>脗芦 <I>activit脙漏 de service</I> 脗禄<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0">芒聙聹active service芒聙聺 means any service that is specified in the regulations to be active service and is deemed for the purposes of this Act to have terminated on discharge or, in the case of a person who underwent treatment in a veterans芒聙聶 hospital, as defined in the regulations, immediately following their discharge, on their release from that hospital;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><MarginalNote>芒聙聹disabled芒聙聺<br/>脗芦 <I>invalide</I> 脗禄<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0">芒聙聹disabled芒聙聺, except in Part II, as applied to any member of the Force, means incapable, by reason of any condition, of performing their duties as a member of the Force, and, for the purposes of section 12 as applied to any person, means ordinarily incapable, by reason of any condition, of pursuing any substantially gainful occupation;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><MarginalNote>芒聙聹member of the Force芒聙聺<br/>脗芦 <I>membre de la Gendarmerie</I> 脗禄<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0">芒聙聹member of the Force芒聙聺 means a member of the Force, as those terms are defined in the <I>Royal Canadian Mounted Police Act</I>, holding a rank in the Force, and any other member of the Force, as those terms are defined in that Act, of a class designated in accordance with the regulations for the purposes of this Act;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><MarginalNote>芒聙聹service in the Force芒聙聺<br/>脗芦 <I>service dans la Gendarmerie</I> 脗禄<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0">芒聙聹service in the Force芒聙聺 includes any period of service</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>a</I>) as a special constable of the Force before April 1, 1960,</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>b</I>) as a police officer that is counted as pensionable service under subsection 24.1(9),</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>c</I>) as a police officer that is described in clause 6(<I>b</I>)(ii)(A) or (L) if the contributor elects to pay for that service, and</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>d</I>) as a police officer or as a member of the Force that forms part of any period of service described in any of clauses 6(<I>b</I>)(ii)(H), (I), (O) and (P) if the contributor elects to pay for that service;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><MarginalNote>芒聙聹World War I芒聙聺<br/>脗芦 <I>Premi脙篓re Guerre mondiale</I> 脗禄<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0">芒聙聹World War I芒聙聺 means the war that was declared on August 4, 1914 and that is deemed, for the purposes of this Act, to have terminated on August 31, 1921;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><MarginalNote>芒聙聹World War II芒聙聺<br/>脗芦 <I>Seconde Guerre mondiale</I> 脗禄<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0">芒聙聹World War II芒聙聺 means the war that was declared on September 10, 1939 and that is deemed, for the purposes of this Act, to have terminated on September 30, 1947.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>2003, c. 22, par. 225(<I>z.21</I>)(E)<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes">(3) Subsections 3(2) and (3) of the Act are replaced by the following:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>References to <I>Canadian Forces Superannuation Act</I><br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(2) A reference in this Act to the <I>Canadian Forces Superannuation Act</I> includes a reference to any other Act of Parliament in force either before or after April 1, 1960 providing for the payment of pensions to members of the Canadian Forces based on length of service.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Persons employed under <I>Royal Canadian Mounted Police Act</I><br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(3) For the purposes of this Act, the <I>Public Service Superannuation Act</I> and the <I>Canadian Forces Superannuation Act</I>, a person who is employed under the authority of the <I>Royal Canadian Mounted Police Act</I> but who is not a member of the Force is deemed to be employed in the public service, and any period of service of a person during which they were employed under the authority of that Act but were not a member of the Force or during which they were a person to whom Part VII of the former Act applied is deemed to be a period of service during which they were employed in the public service.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>3.</B> The Act is amended by adding the following after section 3:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Previous"><Para TopMargin="10" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">PART I</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes"><!--Heading:SUPERANNUATION--><Para TopMargin="5" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">SUPERANNUATION</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>4.</B> Subsection 10(4) of the Act is amended by adding the following after paragraph (<I>a</I>):</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>b</I>) a person who has to their credit pensionable service that includes any period described in any of clauses 6(<I>b</I>)(ii)(L), (O) and (P) and subsection 24.1(9) is deemed to have received during that period the annual rate of pay that is fixed by or determined in the manner prescribed by the regulations.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>2003, c. 26, s. 45(4)<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>5.</B> (1) Subsection 11(11) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Return of contributions<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(11) Despite anything in this section, except as provided for in subsection (2), (7), (8), (10) or (11.1), a contributor who ceases to be a member of the Force after serving in the Force for a period less than the period prescribed by the regulations for the purposes of paragraph <keep>(7)(<I>a</I>)</keep> is entitled only to a return of contributions.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Entitlement to deferred annuity<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(11.1) A contributor who ceases to be a member of the Force after serving in the Force for a period less than the period prescribed by the regulations for the purposes of paragraph <keep>(7)(<I>a</I>)</keep> is entitled to a deferred annuity if they</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>a</I>) have to their credit two or more years of pensionable service in respect of which they have made an election under subsection 24(5) or under any regulations made under subsection 27(2); and</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>b</I>) are not entitled to an immediate annuity.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote><br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes">(2) Section 11 of the Act is amended by adding the following after subsection (12):</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Service in Force<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(13) For the purposes of this section, in calculating the length of service in the Force of a contributor, there shall not be included any period of service in respect of which they were paid a return of contributions or other lump sum payment under this Part and for which they did not elect to pay.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>6.</B> The Act is amended by adding the following after section 12.1:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Return of contributions<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>12.2</B> (1) Any return of contributions to which a contributor is entitled shall be paid in accordance with section 12.1 in respect of any period of service that is included in the contributor芒聙聶s pensionable service and in respect of which</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>a</I>) a payment has been made into the Superannuation Account or the Royal Canadian Mounted Police Pension Fund</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="4" FirstLineIndent="0">(i) under an agreement entered into under section 24.1, or</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="4" FirstLineIndent="0">(ii) in respect of an election made by a contributor under this Part; and</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>b</I>) at the time the payment was made, the <I>Pension Benefits Standards Act, 1985</I> or a substantially similar provincial law required the locking-in of contributions.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Deeming<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(2) For the purposes of this section, paragraph (<I>b</I>) of the definition 芒聙聹return of contributions芒聙聺 in subsection 9(1) is deemed to include a reference to the total payment made under an agreement entered into under section 24.1 or in respect of an election made by a contributor under this Part.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Commuted value or transfer value<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>12.3</B> If a contributor is entitled to a return of contributions in respect of any period of service for which the contributor has made an election referred to in clause 6(<I>b</I>)(ii)(O), the return of contributions in respect of that period shall be paid in accordance with section 12.1.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>7.</B> Paragraph 26(<I>d</I>) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>d</I>) prescribing the circumstances under which and the terms and conditions on which an election under this Part may be revoked by any elector, either in whole or in part, and a new election made or deemed to have been made under this Part;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>1999, c. 34, s. 194(1)<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>8.</B> (1) Paragraph 26.1(1)(<I>a</I>) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>a</I>) fixing an annual rate of pay for the purposes of subsection 5(9) or paragraph 10(4)(<I>b</I>) or prescribing the manner of determining the annual rate of pay;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>a.1</I>) determining, for the purposes of paragraphs (<I>b</I>) to (<I>d</I>) of the definition 芒聙聹service in the force芒聙聺 in subsection 3(1), who is a police officer;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>1992, c. 46, s. 77<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes">(2) Subsection 26.1(2) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Retroactive application of regulations<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(2) Regulations made under paragraph <keep>(1)(<I>a</I>),</keep> (<I>c</I>), (<I>d</I>), (<I>h</I>) or (<I>h.4</I>) may, if they so provide, have retroactive effect.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>9.</B> The Act is amended by adding the following before section 32:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Definition of 芒聙聹service in the Force芒聙聺<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>31.1</B> For the purposes of this Part, paragraphs (<I>b</I>), (<I>c</I>) and (<I>d</I>) of the definition 芒聙聹service in the Force芒聙聺 in subsection 3(1) apply only in respect of service as a member of a provincial or municipal police force with which the Minister has entered into an arrangement under section 20 of the <I>Royal Canadian Mounted Police Act</I>.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>2000, c. 34, s. 46<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>10.</B> Section 32 of the Act is replaced by the following:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Eligibility for awards under <I>Pension Act</I><br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>32.</B> Subject to this Part and the regulations, an award in accordance with the <I>Pension Act</I> shall be granted to or in respect of the following persons if the injury or disease 芒聙聰 or the aggravation of the injury or disease 芒聙聰 resulting in the disability or death in respect of which the application for the award is made arose out of, or was directly connected with, the person芒聙聶s service in the Force:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>a</I>) any person to whom Part VI of the former Act applied at any time before April 1, 1960 who, either before or after that time, has suffered a disability or has died; and</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>b</I>) any person who served in the Force at any time after March 31, 1960 as a contributor under Part I of this Act and who has suffered a disability, either before or after that time, or has died.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>11.</B> Subsection 34(2) of the Act is repealed.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:VALIDATION--><Para TopMargin="10" Bold="Yes" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">VALIDATION</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Payments for part-time service<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>12.</B> Every calculation made before October 26, 2006 of benefits payable under the <I>Royal Canadian Mounted Police Superannu- ation Act</I> 芒聙聰 to or in respect of a former member of the Force within the meaning of subsection 3(1) of that Act 芒聙聰 in respect of part-time service is valid to the extent that the result of the calculation is the same as it would have been if the calculation had been made in accordance with the <I>Royal Canadian Mounted Police Superannuation Regulations</I>, as those regulations read on October 26, 2006.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Manner of determination<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>13.</B> The manner in which any amount required to be paid in respect of a period of service referred to in clause 6(<I>b</I>)(ii)(A) of the <I>Royal Canadian Mounted Police Superannu- ation Act</I> is determined before the regulations referred to in paragraph 7(1)(<I>c</I>) of that Act come into force is valid.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:CONSEQUENTIAL AND RELATED AMENDMENTS--><Para TopMargin="10" Bold="Yes" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">CONSEQUENTIAL AND RELATED AMENDMENTS</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:An Act to amend certain Acts in relation to pensions and to enact the Special Retirement Arrangements Act and the Pension Benefits Division Act--><MarginalNote>1992, c. 46<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" Bold="Yes" SmallCaps="Yes" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">An Act to amend certain Acts in relation to pensions and to enact the Special Retirement Arrangements Act and the Pension Benefits Division Act</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>14.</B> Subsection 69(3) of <I>An Act to amend certain Acts in relation to pensions and to enact the Special Retirement Arrangements Act and the Pension Benefits Division Act</I> is repealed.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:Public Sector Pension Investment Board Act--><MarginalNote>1999, c. 34<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="10" Bold="Yes" SmallCaps="Yes" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">Public Sector Pension Investment Board Act</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>15.</B> Subsection 172(3) of the <I>Public Sector Pension Investment Board Act</I> is repealed.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:An Act to amend the Canadian Forces Superannuation Act and to make consequential amendments to other Acts--><MarginalNote>2003, c. 26<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="10" Bold="Yes" SmallCaps="Yes" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">An Act to amend the Canadian Forces Superannuation Act and to make consequential amendments to other Acts</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>16.</B> Subsection 57(2) of <I>An Act to amend the Canadian Forces Superannuation Act and to make consequential amendments to other Acts</I> is repealed.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:COMING INTO FORCE--><Para TopMargin="10" Bold="Yes" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">COMING INTO FORCE</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Royal assent<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>17.</B> Despite subsection 230(3) of the <I>Public Sector Pension Investment Board Act</I> and section 71 of <I>An Act to amend the Canadian Forces Superannuation Act and to make consequential amendments to other Acts</I>, chapter 26 of the Statutes of Canada, 2003, the following provisions come into force on the day on which this Act receives royal assent:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0" Bold="Yes">(<I>a</I>) subsection 172(2) and section 191 of the <I>Public Sector Pension Investment Board Act</I>;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0" Bold="Yes">(<I>b</I>) clauses 6(<I>b</I>)(ii)(L), (O) and (P) of the <I>Royal Canadian Mounted Police Superannuation Act,</I> as enacted by subsection 172(4) of the <I>Public Sector Pension Investment Board Act</I>; and</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0" Bold="Yes">(<I>c</I>) section 44 of <I>An Act to amend the Canadian Forces Superannuation Act and to make consequential amendments to other Acts</I>, chapter 26 of the Statutes of Canada, 2003.</Para></Block><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="BPT_ImprintE">Published under authority of the Speaker of the House of Commons<br/>Available from:<br/>Publishing and Depository Services<br/>Public Works and Government Services Canada<br/>Ottawa, Ontario K1A 0S5<br/>Telephone: 613-941-5995 or 1-800-635-7943<br/>Fax: 613-954-5779 or 1-800-565-7757<br/>publications@tpsgc-pwgsc.gc.ca<br/>http://publications.gc.ca</Para></Block><Block Align="Yes" LineCnt="N"><Para NoLineBreak="Yes" NoHtml="Yes" Leading="0" Size="0" TopMargin="0" BottomMargin="0">脗聞</Para></Block></Bill_Part></Bill>
