<?xml version="1.0"?>
<Bill RHead_reign="57-58 Eliz. II" RHead_ParlYear="2009" DocumentTitle="BILL C-19" Bill_No="C-19" Document_No="90416" xml:lang="EN" Bill_Type="Amending" Stage_Name="First-Reading-House" Reprint="No" xml:space="preserve" ChapterNo_E="C. " ChapterNo_F="ch. " Bill-Origin="commons"><Bill_Part Part_Type="Cover" CountLines="No"><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="CovBillNo">C-19</Para></Block><Block><Para TopMargin="24" Size="9" Leading="10" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0" TextAlign="Center">Second Session, Fortieth Parliament,</Para></Block><Block><Para Size="9" Leading="10" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0" TextAlign="Center">57-58 Elizabeth II, 2009</Para></Block><Block><Para TopMargin="48" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0" Bold="Yes" TextAlign="Center">HOUSE OF COMMONS OF CANADA</Para></Block><Block><Para TopMargin="42" Size="18" Leading="20" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0" Bold="Yes" TextAlign="Center">BILL C-19</Para></Block><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="CovLongTitle">An Act to amend the Criminal Code (investigative hearing and recognizance with conditions)</Para></Block><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="COV_StageLine"></Para></Block><Block><Para Size="9" AllCaps="Yes" Hyphenate="OFF">first reading, March 12, 2009</Para></Block><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="COV_StageLine"></Para></Block><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="Cover_Sponsors">MINISTER OF JUSTICE</Para></Block><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="Cover_DocNo">90416</Para></Block></Bill_Part><Bill_Part CountLines="No" Part_Type="InsideCover"><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="BPT_InsideCoverE">Also available on the Parliament of Canada Web Site at the following address:<br/><B>http://www.parl.gc.ca</B></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><Para TopMargin="108" BottomMargin="4" Size="10" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">SUMMARY</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" Size="8" Leading="9" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">This enactment replaces sections 83.28 to 83.3 of the <I>Criminal Code</I> to provide for an investigative hearing to gather information for the purposes of an investigation of a terrorism offence and to provide for the imposition of a recognizance with conditions on a person to prevent them from carrying out a terrorist activity. It also provides for those sections to cease to have effect or for the possible extension of their operation.</Para></Block></Bill_Part><Bill_Part Part_Type="MainText" CountLines="Yes" RunningHead_E="Criminal Code (investigative hearing and recognizance with conditions)"><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="MainText_DocNo">90416</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes"><Para Style="Session_Reign">2nd Session, 40th Parliament,</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes"><Para Style="Session_Reign">57-58 Elizabeth II, 2009</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes"><Para Style="MainBillOrigin">house of commons of canada</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes"><Para Bold="Yes" Style="MAIN@BillNo_Title">BILL C-19</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes"><Para Style="MAIN@ti;04">An Act to amend the Criminal Code (investigative hearing and recognizance with conditions)</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>R.S., c. C-46<br/></MarginalNote><Para LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">Her Majesty, by and with the advice and consent of the Senate and House of Commons of Canada, enacts as follows:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>2001, c. 41, s. 4<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>1.</B> The heading before section 83.28 and sections 83.28 to 83.3 of the <I>Criminal Code</I> are replaced by the following:</Para><ExplNote><Para Align="Yes" TopMargin="10" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0" Italic="Yes" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">Criminal Code</Para><Para Align="Yes" TopMargin="10" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><I>Clause 1</I>: Existing text of the heading and sections 83.28 to 83.3 (which ceased to have effect on March 1, 2007):</Para><Para Align="Yes" TopMargin="10" Size="8" Leading="9" SmallCaps="Yes" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">Investigative Hearing</Para><Para Align="Yes" TopMargin="5" Size="8" Leading="9" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>83.28</B> (1) In this section and section 83.29, “judge” means a provincial court judge or a judge of a superior court of criminal jurisdiction.</Para><Para Align="Yes" TopMargin="5" Size="8" Leading="9" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(2) Subject to subsection (3), a peace officer may, for the purposes of an investigation of a terrorism offence, apply <I>ex parte</I> to a judge for an order for the gathering of information.</Para><Para Align="Yes" TopMargin="5" Size="8" Leading="9" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(3) A peace officer may make an application under subsection (2) only if the prior consent of the Attorney General was obtained.</Para><Para Align="Yes" TopMargin="5" Size="8" Leading="9" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(4) A judge to whom an application is made under subsection (2) may make an order for the gathering of information if the judge is satisfied that the consent of the Attorney General was obtained as required by subsection (3) and</Para><Para Align="No" TopMargin="5" Size="8" Leading="9" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>a</I>) that there are reasonable grounds to believe that</Para><Para Align="No" TopMargin="5" Size="8" Leading="9" LeftMargin="4" FirstLineIndent="0">(i) a terrorism offence has been committed, and</Para><Para Align="No" TopMargin="5" Size="8" Leading="9" LeftMargin="4" FirstLineIndent="0">(ii) information concerning the offence, or information that may reveal the whereabouts of a person suspected by the peace officer of having committed the offence, is likely to be obtained as a result of the order; or</Para><Para Align="No" TopMargin="5" Size="8" Leading="9" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>b</I>) that</Para><Para Align="No" TopMargin="5" Size="8" Leading="9" LeftMargin="4" FirstLineIndent="0">(i) there are reasonable grounds to believe that a terrorism offence will be committed,</Para><Para Align="No" TopMargin="5" Size="8" Leading="9" LeftMargin="4" FirstLineIndent="0">(ii) there are reasonable grounds to believe that a person has direct and material information that relates to a terrorism offence referred to in subparagraph (i), or that may reveal the whereabouts of an individual who the peace officer suspects may commit a terrorism offence referred to in that subparagraph, and</Para><Para Align="No" TopMargin="5" Size="8" Leading="9" LeftMargin="4" FirstLineIndent="0">(iii) reasonable attempts have been made to obtain the information referred to in subparagraph (ii) from the person referred to in that subparagraph.</Para><Para Align="Yes" TopMargin="5" Size="8" Leading="9" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(5) An order made under subsection (4) may</Para><Para Align="No" TopMargin="5" Size="8" Leading="9" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>a</I>) order the examination, on oath or not, of a person named in the order;</Para><Para Align="No" TopMargin="5" Size="8" Leading="9" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>b</I>) order the person to attend at the place fixed by the judge, or by the judge designated under paragraph (<I>d</I>), as the case may be, for the examination and to remain in attendance until excused by the presiding judge;</Para><Para Align="No" TopMargin="5" Size="8" Leading="9" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>c</I>) order the person to bring to the examination any thing in their possession or control, and produce it to the presiding judge;</Para><Para Align="No" TopMargin="5" Size="8" Leading="9" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>d</I>) designate another judge as the judge before whom the examination is to take place; and</Para><Para Align="No" TopMargin="5" Size="8" Leading="9" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>e</I>) include any other terms or conditions that the judge considers desirable, including terms or conditions for the protection of the interests of the person named in the order and of third parties or for the protection of any ongoing investigation.</Para><Para Align="Yes" TopMargin="5" Size="8" Leading="9" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(6) An order made under subsection (4) may be executed anywhere in Canada.</Para><Para Align="Yes" TopMargin="5" Size="8" Leading="9" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(7) The judge who made the order under subsection (4), or another judge of the same court, may vary its terms and conditions.</Para><Para Align="Yes" TopMargin="5" Size="8" Leading="9" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(8) A person named in an order made under subsection (4) shall answer questions put to the person by the Attorney General or the Attorney General’s agent, and shall produce to the presiding judge things that the person was ordered to bring, but may refuse if answering a question or producing a thing would disclose information that is protected by any law relating to non-disclosure of information or to privilege.</Para><Para Align="Yes" TopMargin="5" Size="8" Leading="9" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(9) The presiding judge shall rule on any objection or other issue relating to a refusal to answer a question or to produce a thing.</Para><Para Align="Yes" TopMargin="5" Size="8" Leading="9" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(10) No person shall be excused from answering a question or producing a thing under subsection (8) on the ground that the answer or thing may tend to incriminate the person or subject the person to any proceeding or penalty, but</Para><Para Align="No" TopMargin="5" Size="8" Leading="9" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>a</I>) no answer given or thing produced under subsection (8) shall be used or received against the person in any criminal proceedings against that person, other than a prosecution under section 132 or 136; and</Para><Para Align="No" TopMargin="5" Size="8" Leading="9" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>b</I>) no evidence derived from the evidence obtained from the person shall be used or received against the person in any criminal proceedings against that person, other than a prosecution under section 132 or 136.</Para><Para Align="Yes" TopMargin="5" Size="8" Leading="9" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(11) A person has the right to retain and instruct counsel at any stage of the proceedings.</Para><Para Align="Yes" TopMargin="5" Size="8" Leading="9" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(12) The presiding judge, if satisfied that any thing produced during the course of the examination will likely be relevant to the investigation of any terrorism offence, shall order that the thing be given into the custody of the peace officer or someone acting on the peace officer’s behalf.</Para><Para Align="Yes" TopMargin="5" Size="8" Leading="9" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>83.29</B> (1) The judge who made the order under subsection 83.28(4), or another judge of the same court, may issue a warrant for the arrest of the person named in the order if the judge is satisfied, on an information in writing and under oath, that the person</Para><Para Align="No" TopMargin="5" Size="8" Leading="9" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>a</I>) is evading service of the order;</Para><Para Align="No" TopMargin="5" Size="8" Leading="9" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>b</I>) is about to abscond; or</Para><Para Align="No" TopMargin="5" Size="8" Leading="9" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>c</I>) did not attend the examination, or did not remain in attendance, as required by the order.</Para><Para Align="Yes" TopMargin="5" Size="8" Leading="9" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(2) A warrant issued under subsection (1) may be executed at any place in Canada by any peace officer having jurisdiction in that place.</Para><Para Align="Yes" TopMargin="5" Size="8" Leading="9" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(3) A peace officer who arrests a person in the execution of a warrant issued under subsection (1) shall, without delay, bring the person, or cause the person to be brought, before the judge who issued the warrant or another judge of the same court. The judge in question may, to ensure compliance with the order, order that the person be detained in custody or released on recognizance, with or without sureties.</Para><Para Align="Yes" TopMargin="10" Size="8" Leading="9" SmallCaps="Yes" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">Recognizance with Conditions</Para><Para Align="Yes" TopMargin="5" Size="8" Leading="9" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>83.3</B> (1) The consent of the Attorney General is required before a peace officer may lay an information under subsection (2).</Para><Para Align="Yes" TopMargin="5" Size="8" Leading="9" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(2) Subject to subsection (1), a peace officer may lay an information before a provincial court judge if the peace officer</Para><Para Align="No" TopMargin="5" Size="8" Leading="9" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>a</I>) believes on reasonable grounds that a terrorist activity will be carried out; and</Para><Para Align="No" TopMargin="5" Size="8" Leading="9" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>b</I>) suspects on reasonable grounds that the imposition of a recognizance with conditions on a person, or the arrest of a person, is necessary to prevent the carrying out of the terrorist activity.</Para><Para Align="Yes" TopMargin="5" Size="8" Leading="9" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(3) A provincial court judge who receives an information under subsection (2) may cause the person to appear before the provincial court judge.</Para><Para Align="Yes" TopMargin="5" Size="8" Leading="9" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(4) Notwithstanding subsections (2) and (3), if</Para><Para Align="No" TopMargin="5" Size="8" Leading="9" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>a</I>) either</Para><Para Align="No" TopMargin="5" Size="8" Leading="9" LeftMargin="4" FirstLineIndent="0">(i) the grounds for laying an information referred to in paragraphs (2)(<I>a</I>) and (<I>b</I>) exist but, by reason of exigent circumstances, it would be impracticable to lay an information under subsection (2), or</Para><Para Align="No" TopMargin="5" Size="8" Leading="9" LeftMargin="4" FirstLineIndent="0">(ii) an information has been laid under subsection (2) and a summons has been issued, and</Para><Para Align="No" TopMargin="5" Size="8" Leading="9" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>b</I>) the peace officer suspects on reasonable grounds that the detention of the person in custody is necessary in order to prevent a terrorist activity,</Para><Para Align="No" TopMargin="5" Size="8" Leading="9" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0">the peace officer may arrest the person without warrant and cause the person to be detained in custody, to be taken before a provincial court judge in accordance with subsection (6).</Para><Para Align="Yes" TopMargin="5" Size="8" Leading="9" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(5) If a peace officer arrests a person without warrant in the circumstance described in subparagraph (4)(<I>a</I>)(i), the peace officer shall, within the time prescribed by paragraph (6)(<I>a</I>) or (<I>b</I>),</Para><Para Align="No" TopMargin="5" Size="8" Leading="9" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>a</I>) lay an information in accordance with subsection (2); or</Para><Para Align="No" TopMargin="5" Size="8" Leading="9" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>b</I>) release the person.</Para><Para Align="Yes" TopMargin="5" Size="8" Leading="9" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(6) A person detained in custody shall be taken before a provincial court judge in accordance with the following rules:</Para><Para Align="No" TopMargin="5" Size="8" Leading="9" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>a</I>) if a provincial court judge is available within a period of twenty-four hours after the person has been arrested, the person shall be taken before a provincial court judge without unreasonable delay and in any event within that period, and</Para><Para Align="No" TopMargin="5" Size="8" Leading="9" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>b</I>) if a provincial court judge is not available within a period of twenty-four hours after the person has been arrested, the person shall be taken before a provincial court judge as soon as possible,</Para><Para Align="No" TopMargin="5" Size="8" Leading="9" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0">unless, at any time before the expiry of the time prescribed in paragraph (<I>a</I>) or (<I>b</I>) for taking the person before a provincial court judge, the peace officer, or an officer in charge within the meaning of Part XV, is satisfied that the person should be released from custody unconditionally, and so releases the person.</Para><Para Align="Yes" TopMargin="5" Size="8" Leading="9" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(7) When a person is taken before a provincial court judge under subsection (6),</Para><Para Align="No" TopMargin="5" Size="8" Leading="9" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>a</I>) if an information has not been laid under subsection (2), the judge shall order that the person be released; or</Para><Para Align="No" TopMargin="5" Size="8" Leading="9" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>b</I>) if an information has been laid under subsection (2),</Para><Para Align="No" TopMargin="5" Size="8" Leading="9" LeftMargin="4" FirstLineIndent="0">(i) the judge shall order that the person be released unless the peace officer who laid the information shows cause why the detention of the person in custody is justified on one or more of the following grounds:</Para><Para Align="No" TopMargin="5" Size="8" Leading="9" LeftMargin="6" FirstLineIndent="0">(A) the detention is necessary to ensure the person’s appearance before a provincial court judge in order to be dealt with in accordance with subsection (8),</Para><Para Align="No" TopMargin="5" Size="8" Leading="9" LeftMargin="6" FirstLineIndent="0">(B) the detention is necessary for the protection or safety of the public, including any witness, having regard to all the circumstances including</Para><Para Align="No" TopMargin="5" Size="8" Leading="9" LeftMargin="8" FirstLineIndent="0">(I) the likelihood that, if the person is released from custody, a terrorist activity will be carried out, and</Para><Para Align="No" TopMargin="5" Size="8" Leading="9" LeftMargin="8" FirstLineIndent="0">(II) any substantial likelihood that the person will, if released from custody, interfere with the administration of justice, and</Para><Para Align="No" TopMargin="5" Size="8" Leading="9" LeftMargin="6" FirstLineIndent="0">(C) any other just cause and, without limiting the generality of the foregoing, that the detention is necessary in order to maintain confidence in the administration of justice, having regard to all the circumstances, including the apparent strength of the peace officer’s grounds under subsection (2), and the gravity of any terrorist activity that may be carried out, and</Para><Para Align="No" TopMargin="5" Size="8" Leading="9" LeftMargin="4" FirstLineIndent="0">(ii) the judge may adjourn the matter for a hearing under subsection (8) but, if the person is not released under subparagraph (i), the adjournment may not exceed forty-eight hours.</Para><Para Align="Yes" TopMargin="5" Size="8" Leading="9" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(8) The provincial court judge before whom the person appears pursuant to subsection (3)</Para><Para Align="No" TopMargin="5" Size="8" Leading="9" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>a</I>) may, if satisfied by the evidence adduced that the peace officer has reasonable grounds for the suspicion, order that the person enter into a recognizance to keep the peace and be of good behaviour for any period that does not exceed twelve months and to comply with any other reasonable conditions prescribed in the recognizance, including the conditions set out in subsection (10), that the provincial court judge considers desirable for preventing the carrying out of a terrorist activity; and</Para><Para Align="No" TopMargin="5" Size="8" Leading="9" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>b</I>) if the person was not released under subparagraph (7)(<I>b</I>)(i), shall order that the person be released, subject to the recognizance, if any, ordered under paragraph (<I>a</I>).</Para><Para Align="Yes" TopMargin="5" Size="8" Leading="9" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(9) The provincial court judge may commit the person to prison for a term not exceeding twelve months if the person fails or refuses to enter into the recognizance.</Para><Para Align="Yes" TopMargin="5" Size="8" Leading="9" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(10) Before making an order under paragraph (8)(<I>a</I>), the provincial court judge shall consider whether it is desirable, in the interests of the safety of the person or of any other person, to include as a condition of the recognizance that the person be prohibited from possessing any firearm, cross-bow, prohibited weapon, restricted weapon, prohibited device, ammunition, prohibited ammunition or explosive substance, or all of those things, for any period specified in the recognizance, and where the provincial court judge decides that it is so desirable, the provincial court judge shall add such a condition to the recognizance.</Para><Para Align="Yes" TopMargin="5" Size="8" Leading="9" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(11) If the provincial court judge adds a condition described in subsection (10) to a recognizance, the provincial court judge shall specify in the recognizance the manner and method by which</Para><Para Align="No" TopMargin="5" Size="8" Leading="9" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>a</I>) the things referred to in that subsection that are in the possession of the person shall be surrendered, disposed of, detained, stored or dealt with; and</Para><Para Align="No" TopMargin="5" Size="8" Leading="9" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>b</I>) the authorizations, licences and registration certificates held by the person shall be surrendered.</Para><Para Align="Yes" TopMargin="5" Size="8" Leading="9" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(12) If the provincial court judge does not add a condition described in subsection (10) to a recognizance, the provincial court judge shall include in the record a statement of the reasons for not adding the condition.</Para><Para Align="Yes" TopMargin="5" Size="8" Leading="9" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(13) The provincial court judge may, on application of the peace officer, the Attorney General or the person, vary the conditions fixed in the recognizance.</Para><Para Align="Yes" TopMargin="5" Size="8" Leading="9" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(14) Subsections 810(4) and (5) apply, with any modifications that the circumstances require, to proceedings under this section.</Para></ExplNote></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:Investigative Hearing--><Para TopMargin="10" SmallCaps="Yes" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">Investigative Hearing</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Definition of “judge”<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>83.28</B> (1) In this section and section 83.29, “judge” means a provincial court judge or a judge of a superior court of criminal jurisdiction.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Order for gathering information<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(2) Subject to subsection (3), a peace officer may, for the purposes of an investigation of a terrorism offence, apply <I>ex parte</I> to a judge for an order for the gathering of information.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Attorney General’s consent<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(3) A peace officer may make an application under subsection (2) only if the Attorney <change>General’s</change> prior consent was obtained.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Making of order<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(4) <change>The</change> judge to whom <change>the</change> application is made may make an order for the gathering of information if <change>they are</change> satisfied that the Attorney <change>General’s</change> consent was obtained as required by subsection (3), and</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>a</I>) that there are reasonable grounds to believe that</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="4" FirstLineIndent="0">(i) a terrorism offence has been committed,</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="4" FirstLineIndent="0">(ii) information concerning the offence, or information that may reveal the whereabouts of a person suspected by the peace officer of having committed the offence, is likely to be obtained as a result of the order, <change>and</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="4" FirstLineIndent="0"><change>(iii) reasonable attempts have been made to obtain the information referred to in subparagraph (ii) by other means; or</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>b</I>) that</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="4" FirstLineIndent="0">(i) there are reasonable grounds to believe that a terrorism offence will be committed,</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="4" FirstLineIndent="0">(ii) there are reasonable grounds to believe that a person has direct and material information that relates to <change>the</change> offence referred to in subparagraph (i), or that may reveal the whereabouts of an individ- ual who the peace officer suspects may commit <change>the</change> offence referred to in that subparagraph, and</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="4" FirstLineIndent="0">(iii) reasonable attempts have been made to obtain the information referred to in subparagraph (ii) <change>by other means</change>.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Contents of order<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(5) An order made under subsection (4) <change>shall</change> order the examination, on oath or not, of <change>the</change> person named in the order <change>and require</change> the person to attend at the place fixed by the judge, or by the judge designated under paragraph (<I><change>b</change></I>), as the case may be, for the examination and to remain in attendance until excused by the presiding judge, <change>and may</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>a</I>) order the person to bring to the examination any thing in their possession or control, and produce it to the presiding judge;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>b</I>) designate another judge as the judge before whom the examination is to take place; and</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>c</I>) include any other terms or conditions that the judge considers desirable, including terms or conditions for the protection of the interests of the person named in the order and of third parties or for the protection of any ongoing investigation.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Execution of order<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(6) <change>The</change> order may be executed anywhere in Canada.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Variation of order<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(7) The judge who made the order, or another judge of the same court, may vary its terms and conditions.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Obligation to answer questions and produce things<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(8) A person named in an order made under subsection (4) shall answer questions put to <change>them</change> by the Attorney General or the Attorney General’s agent, and shall produce to the presiding judge things that the person was ordered to bring, but may refuse if answering a question or producing a thing would disclose information that is protected by any law relating to privilege or to disclosure of information.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Judge to rule<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(9) The presiding judge shall rule on any objection or other issue relating to a refusal to answer a question or to produce a thing.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>No person excused from complying with subsection (8)<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(10) No person shall be excused from answering a question or producing a thing under subsection (8) on the ground that the answer or thing may tend to incriminate <change>them</change> or subject <change>them</change> to any proceeding or penalty, but</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>a</I>) no answer given or thing produced under subsection (8) shall be used or received against the person in any criminal proceedings against <change>them</change>, other than a prosecution under section 132 or 136; and</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>b</I>) no evidence derived from the evidence obtained from the person shall be used or received against the person in any criminal proceedings against <change>them</change>, other than a prosecution under section 132 or 136.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Right to counsel<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(11) A person has the right to retain and instruct counsel at any stage of the proceedings.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Order for custody of thing<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(12) The presiding judge, if satisfied that any thing produced during the course of the examination will likely be relevant to the investigation of any terrorism offence, <change>may</change> order that the thing be given into the custody of the peace officer or someone acting on the peace officer’s behalf.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Arrest warrant<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>83.29</B> (1) The judge who made the order under subsection 83.28(4), or another judge of the same court, may issue a warrant for the arrest of the person named in the order if the judge is satisfied, on an information in writing and under oath, that the person</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>a</I>) is evading service of the order;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>b</I>) is about to abscond; or</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>c</I>) did not attend the examination, or did not remain in attendance, as required by the order.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Execution of warrant<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(2) <change>The</change> warrant may be executed at any place in Canada by any peace officer having jurisdiction in that place.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Person to be brought before judge<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(3) A peace officer who arrests a person in the execution of <change>the</change> warrant shall, without delay, bring the person, or cause <change>them</change> to be brought, before the judge who issued the warrant or another judge of the same court. The judge in question may, to ensure compliance with the order, order that the person be detained in custody or released on recognizance, with or without sureties.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Application of section 707<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><change>(4) Section 707 applies, with any necessary modifications, to persons detained in custody under this section.</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:Recognizance with Conditions--><Para TopMargin="10" SmallCaps="Yes" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">Recognizance with Conditions</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Attorney General’s consent<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>83.3</B> (1) The Attorney <change>General’s</change> consent is required before a peace officer may lay an information under subsection (2).</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Terrorist activity<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(2) Subject to subsection (1), a peace officer may lay an information before a provincial court judge if the peace officer</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>a</I>) believes on reasonable grounds that a terrorist activity will be carried out; and</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>b</I>) suspects on reasonable grounds that the imposition of a recognizance with conditions on a person, or the arrest of a person, is necessary to prevent the carrying out of the terrorist activity.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Appearance<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(3) <change>The</change> judge who receives <change>the</change> information may cause the person to appear before <change>any</change> provincial court judge.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Arrest without warrant<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(4) <change>Despite</change> subsections (2) and (3), <change>a</change> peace officer may arrest <change>a</change> person without <change>a</change> warrant and cause the person to be detained in custody, <change>in order to bring them</change> before a provincial court judge in accordance with subsection (6), if</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>a</I>) either</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="4" FirstLineIndent="0">(i) the grounds for laying an information referred to in paragraphs (2)(<I>a</I>) and (<I>b</I>) exist but, by reason of exigent circumstances, it would be impracticable to lay an information under subsection (2), or</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="4" FirstLineIndent="0">(ii) an information has been laid under subsection (2) and a summons has been issued; and</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>b</I>) the peace officer suspects on reasonable grounds that the detention of the person in custody is necessary in order to prevent a terrorist activity.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Duty of peace officer<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(5) If a peace officer arrests a person without <change>a</change> warrant in the circumstance described in subparagraph (4)(<I>a</I>)(i), the peace officer shall, within the time prescribed by paragraph (6)(<I>a</I>) or (<I>b</I>),</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>a</I>) lay an information in accordance with subsection (2); or</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>b</I>) release the person.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>When person to be taken before judge<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(6) Unless <change>a</change> peace officer, or an officer in charge <change>as defined in</change> Part <change>XVI</change>, is satisfied that a person should be released from custody unconditionally before <change>their appearance</change> before a provincial court judge <change>in accordance with</change> the <change>rules</change> in paragraph (<I>a</I>) or (<I>b</I>), and so releases the person, <change>the</change> person detained in custody shall be taken before a provincial court judge in accordance with the following rules:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>a</I>) if a provincial court judge is available within 24 hours after the person has been arrested, the person shall be taken before a provincial court judge without unreasonable delay and in any event within that period; and</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>b</I>) if a provincial court judge is not available within 24 hours after the person has been arrested, the person shall be taken before a provincial court judge as soon as <change>feasible</change>.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>How person dealt with<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(7) When a person is taken before a provincial court judge under subsection (6),</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>a</I>) if an information has not been laid under subsection (2), the judge shall order that the person be released; or</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>b</I>) if an information has been laid under subsection (2),</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="4" FirstLineIndent="0">(i) the judge shall order that the person be released unless the peace officer who laid the information shows cause why the <change>person’s</change> detention in custody is justified on one or more of the following grounds:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="6" FirstLineIndent="0">(A) the detention is necessary to ensure the person’s appearance before a provincial court judge in order to be dealt with in accordance with subsection (8),</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="6" FirstLineIndent="0">(B) the detention is necessary for the protection or safety of the public, including any witness, having regard to all the circumstances including</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="8" FirstLineIndent="0">(I) the likelihood that, if the person is released from custody, a terrorist activity will be carried out, and</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="8" FirstLineIndent="0">(II) any substantial likelihood that the person will, if released from custody, interfere with the administration of justice, and</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="6" FirstLineIndent="0">(C) the detention is necessary to maintain confidence in the administration of justice, having regard to all the circumstances, including the apparent strength of the peace officer’s grounds under subsection (2), and the gravity of any terrorist activity that may be carried out, and</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="4" FirstLineIndent="0">(ii) the judge may adjourn the matter for a hearing under subsection (8) but, if the person is not released under subparagraph (i), the adjournment may not exceed 48 hours.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Hearing before judge<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(8) The judge before whom the person appears <change>in accordance with</change> subsection (3)</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>a</I>) may, if satisfied by the evidence adduced that the peace officer has reasonable grounds for the suspicion, order that the person enter into a recognizance to keep the peace and be of good behaviour for any period that does not exceed 12 months and to comply with any other reasonable conditions prescribed in the recognizance, including the condition set out in subsection (10), that the judge considers desirable for preventing the carrying out of a terrorist activity; and</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>b</I>) if the person was not released under subparagraph (7)(<I>b</I>)(i), shall order that the person be released, subject to the recognizance, if any, ordered under paragraph (<I>a</I>).</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Refusal to enter into recognizance<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(9) The judge may commit the person to prison for a term not exceeding 12 months if the person fails or refuses to enter into the recognizance.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Conditions — firearms<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(10) Before making an order under paragraph (8)(<I>a</I>), the judge shall consider whether it is desirable, in the interests of the safety of the person or of any other person, to include as a condition of the recognizance that the person be prohibited from possessing any firearm, cross-bow, prohibited weapon, restricted weapon, prohibited device, ammunition, prohibited ammunition or explosive substance, or all of those things, for any period specified in the recognizance, and <change>if</change> the judge decides that it is so desirable, <change>they</change> shall add <change>the</change> condition to the recognizance.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Surrender, etc.<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(11) If the judge adds <change>the</change> condition described in subsection (10) to a recognizance, <change>they</change> shall specify in <change>it</change> the manner and method by which</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>a</I>) the things referred to in that subsection that are in the <change>person’s</change> possession shall be surrendered, disposed of, detained, stored or dealt with; and</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>b</I>) the authorizations, licences and registration certificates <change>that are</change> held by the person shall be surrendered.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Reasons<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(12) If the judge does not add <change>the</change> condition to a recognizance, <change>they</change> shall include in the record a statement of the reasons for not adding <change>it</change>.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Variance of conditions<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(13) The judge may, on application of the peace officer, the Attorney General or the person, vary the conditions fixed in the recognizance.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Other provisions to apply<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(14) Subsections 810(4) and (5) apply, with any <change>necessary</change> modifications, to proceedings under this section.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>2.</B> (1) Section 83.31 of the Act is amended by adding the following after subsection (1):</Para><ExplNote><Para Align="Yes" TopMargin="10" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><I>Clause 2</I>: (1) and (2) New.</Para></ExplNote></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Attorney General’s opinion<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><change>(1.1) The Attorney General of Canada shall include in the annual report under subsection (1) his or her opinion, supported by reasons, on whether the operation of sections 83.28 and 83.29 should be extended.</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes">(2) Section 83.31 of the Act is amended by adding the following after subsection (3):</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Opinions<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><change>(3.1) The Attorney General of Canada and the Minister of Public Safety and Emergency Preparedness shall include in their annual reports under subsections (2) and (3), respectively, their opinion, supported by reasons, on whether the operation of section 83.3 should be extended.</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>2001, c. 41, s. 4<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>3.</B> (1) Subsections 83.32(1) and (2) of the Act are replaced by the following:</Para><ExplNote><Para Align="Yes" TopMargin="10" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><I>Clause 3</I>: (1) Existing text of subsections 83.32(1) and (2):</Para><Para Align="Yes" TopMargin="5" Size="8" Leading="9" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>83.32</B> (1) Sections 83.28, 83.29 and 83.3 cease to apply at the end of the fifteenth sitting day of Parliament after December 31, 2006 unless, before the end of that day, the application of those sections is extended by a resolution — the text of which is established under subsection (2) — passed by both Houses of Parliament in accordance with the rules set out in subsection (3).</Para><Para Align="Yes" TopMargin="5" Size="8" Leading="9" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(2) The Governor General in Council may, by order, establish the text of a resolution providing for the extension of the application of sections 83.28, 83.29 and 83.3 and specifying the period of the extension, which may not exceed five years from the first day on which the resolution has been passed by both Houses of Parliament.</Para></ExplNote></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Sunset provision<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>83.32</B> (1) Sections 83.28, 83.29 and 83.3 cease to <change>have effect</change> at the end of the 15th sitting day of Parliament after <change>the fifth anniversary of the coming into force of this subsection</change> unless, before the end of that day, the <change>operation</change> of those sections is extended by resolution — <change>whose</change> text is established under subsection (2) — passed by both Houses of Parliament in accordance with the rules set out in subsection (3).</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Review<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><change>(1.1) A comprehensive review of sections 83.28, 83.29 and 83.3 and their operation shall be undertaken by any committee of the Senate, of the House of Commons or of both Houses of Parliament that may be designated or established by the Senate or the House of Commons, or by both Houses of Parliament, as the case may be, for that purpose.</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Report<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><change>(1.2) The committee referred to in subsection (1.1) shall, within a year after a review is undertaken under that subsection or within any further time that may be authorized by the Senate, the House of Commons or both Houses of Parliament, as the case may be, submit a report on the review to Parliament, including its recommendation with respect to extending the operation of section 83.28, 83.29 or 83.3.</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Order in council<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(2) The Governor in Council may, by order, establish the text of a resolution <change>that provides</change> for the extension of the <change>operation</change> of section 83.28, 83.29 <change>or</change> 83.3 and <change>that specifies</change> the period of the extension, which may not exceed five years from the first day on which the resolution has been passed by both Houses of Parliament.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>2001, c. 41, s. 4<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes">(2) Subsection 83.32(4) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Para><ExplNote><Para Align="Yes" TopMargin="10" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(2) Existing text of subsection 83.32(4):</Para><Para Align="Yes" TopMargin="5" Size="8" Leading="9" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(4) The application of sections 83.28, 83.29 and 83.3 may be further extended in accordance with the procedure set out in this section, with the words “December 31, 2006” in subsection (1) read as “the expiration of the most recent extension under this section”.</Para></ExplNote></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Subsequent extensions<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(4) The <change>operation</change> of section 83.28, 83.29 <change>or</change> 83.3 may be further extended in accordance with the procedure set out in this section, <change>but the reference to</change> “<change>the fifth anniversary of the coming into force of this subsection</change>” in subsection (1) <change>is to be</change> read as <change>a reference to</change> “the <change>expiry</change> of the most recent extension under this section”.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>2001, c. 41, s. 4<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>4.</B> Section 83.33 of the Act is replaced by the following:</Para><ExplNote><Para Align="Yes" TopMargin="10" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><I>Clause 4</I>: Existing text of section 83.33:</Para><Para Align="Yes" TopMargin="5" Size="8" Leading="9" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>83.33</B> (1) In the event that sections 83.28 and 83.29 cease to apply pursuant to section 83.32, proceedings commenced under those sections shall be completed if the hearing before the judge of the application made under subsection 83.28(2) began before those sections ceased to apply.</Para><Para Align="Yes" TopMargin="5" Size="8" Leading="9" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(2) In the event that section 83.3 ceases to apply pursuant to section 83.32, a person detained in custody under section 83.3 shall be released when that section ceases to apply, except that subsections 83.3(7) to (14) continue to apply to a person who was taken before a judge under subsection 83.3(6) before section 83.3 ceased to apply.</Para></ExplNote></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Transitional provision — sections 83.28 and 83.29<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>83.33</B> (1) In the event that sections 83.28 and 83.29 cease to <change>have effect in accordance with</change> section 83.32, proceedings commenced under those sections shall be completed if the hearing before the judge of the application made under subsection 83.28(2) began before those sections ceased to <change>have effect</change>.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Transitional provision — section 83.3<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(2) In the event that section 83.3 ceases to <change>have effect in accordance with</change> section 83.32, a person detained in custody under section 83.3 shall be released when that section ceases to <change>have effect</change>, except that subsections 83.3(7) to (14) continue to apply to a person who was taken before a judge under subsection 83.3(6) before section 83.3 ceased to <change>have effect</change>.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Coming into force<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>5.</B> This Act comes into force on a day to be fixed by order of the Governor in Council.</Para></Block><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="BPT_ImprintE">Published under authority of the Speaker of the House of Commons<br/>Available from:<br/>Publishing and Depository Services<br/>Public Works and Government Services Canada<br/>Ottawa, Ontario K1A 0S5<br/>Telephone: 613-941-5995 or 1-800-635-7943<br/>Fax: 613-954-5779 or 1-800-565-7757<br/>publications@tpsgc-pwgsc.gc.ca<br/>http://publications.gc.ca</Para></Block><Block Align="Yes" LineCnt="N"><Para NoLineBreak="Yes" NoHtml="Yes" Leading="0" Size="0" TopMargin="0" BottomMargin="0"></Para></Block></Bill_Part></Bill>
