<?xml version="1.0"?>
<Bill RHead_reign="57-58 Eliz. II" RHead_ParlYear="2009" DocumentTitle="BILL C-306" Bill_No="C-306" Document_No="402045" xml:lang="EN" Bill_Type="Non-amending" Stage_Name="First-Reading-House" Reprint="No" xml:space="preserve" ChapterNo_E="C. " ChapterNo_F="ch. " Bill-Origin="commons"><Bill_Part Part_Type="Cover" CountLines="No"><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="CovBillNo">C-306</Para></Block><Block><Para TopMargin="24" Size="9" Leading="10" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0" TextAlign="Center">Second Session, Fortieth Parliament,</Para></Block><Block><Para Size="9" Leading="10" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0" TextAlign="Center">57-58 Elizabeth II, 2009</Para></Block><Block><Para TopMargin="48" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0" Bold="Yes" TextAlign="Center">HOUSE OF COMMONS OF CANADA</Para></Block><Block><Para TopMargin="42" Size="18" Leading="20" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0" Bold="Yes" TextAlign="Center">BILL C-306</Para></Block><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="CovLongTitle">An Act respecting the use of government contracts to promote economic development</Para></Block><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="COV_StageLine"></Para></Block><Block><Para Size="9" AllCaps="Yes" Hyphenate="OFF">first reading, February 10, 2009</Para></Block><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="COV_StageLine"></Para></Block><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="Cover_Sponsors"><SC SC_PerCent="85">Ms. Guay</SC></Para></Block><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="Cover_DocNo">402045</Para></Block></Bill_Part><Bill_Part CountLines="No" Part_Type="InsideCover"><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="BPT_InsideCoverE">Also available on the Parliament of Canada Web Site at the following address:<br/><B>http://www.parl.gc.ca</B></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><Para TopMargin="108" BottomMargin="4" Size="10" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">SUMMARY</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" Size="8" Leading="9" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">The purpose of this enactment is to promote economic development in Canada by ensuring that, in the procurement of its goods and services, the Government of Canada gives preference to Canadian products while complying with its international obligations.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" Size="8" Leading="9" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">The enactment requires, however, that the price of a Canadian product not exceed by more than 7.5% the price of a non-Canadian similar product.</Para></Block></Bill_Part><Bill_Part Part_Type="MainText" CountLines="Yes" RunningHead_E="Canadian Products Promotion"><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="MainText_DocNo">402045</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes"><Para Style="Session_Reign">2nd Session, 40th Parliament,</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes"><Para Style="Session_Reign">57-58 Elizabeth II, 2009</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes"><Para Style="MainBillOrigin">house of commons of canada</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes"><Para Bold="Yes" Style="MAIN@BillNo_Title">BILL C-306</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes"><Para Style="MAIN@ti;04">An Act respecting the use of government contracts to promote economic development</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">Her Majesty, by and with the advice and consent of the Senate and House of Commons of Canada, enacts as follows:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:SHORT TITLE--><Para TopMargin="10" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">SHORT TITLE</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Short title<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>1.</B> This Act may be cited as the <I>Canadian Products Promotion Act</I>.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:INTERPRETATION--><Para TopMargin="10" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">INTERPRETATION</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Definitions<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>2.</B> The following definitions apply in this Act.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><MarginalNote>“acquisition”<br/>« <I>acquisition</I> »<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0">“acquisition” means acquisition by such methods as purchase, lease or rental, with or without an option to purchase.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><MarginalNote>“Canada”<br/>« <I>Canada</I> »<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0">“Canada” means the territory of Canada, including the exclusive economic zone of Canada.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><MarginalNote>“Canadian product”<br/>« <I>produit canadien</I> »<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0">“Canadian product” means any product</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>a</I>) of which more than 50% of the total value originates in Canada; or</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>b</I>) in the case of a natural resource, of which more than 75% of the total value originates in Canada.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><MarginalNote>“Government of Canada”<br/>« <I>gouvernement du Canada</I> »<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0">“Government of Canada” means</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>a</I>) the Government of Canada or any department or agent of that government;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>b</I>) any Crown corporation; or</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>c</I>) any foundation or trust established by the Government of Canada that receives over 75% of its income or funding from that government.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><MarginalNote>“NAFTA country”<br/>« <I>pays
ALÉNA</I> »<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0">“NAFTA country” means a country that is a party to the North American Free Trade Agreement.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><MarginalNote>“partially Canadian product”<br/>« <I>produit partiellement canadien</I> »<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0">“partially Canadian product” means</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>a</I>) any good or service of which more than 25% but less than 50% of the total value originates in Canada; or</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>b</I>) in the case of a natural resource, any good of which more than 37.5% but less than 75% of the total value originates in Canada.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><MarginalNote>“product”<br/>« <I>produit</I> »<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0">“product” means a good or a service.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><MarginalNote>“similar price”<br/>« <I>prix
similaire</I> »<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0">“similar price” means a final delivery price that</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>a</I>) in the case of a Canadian product, does not exceed the price of a non-Canadian product by an amount greater than 7.5%; or</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>b</I>) in the case of a partially Canadian product, does not exceed the price of a non-Canadian product by an amount greater than the amount determined by the formula</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="4" FirstLineIndent="0">(i) 7.5% x (the percentage of the product’s total value that originates in Canada) / 50, or</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="4" FirstLineIndent="0">(ii) in the case of a natural resource, <keep>7.5% x</keep> (the percentage of the product’s total value that originates in Canada) / 75.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><MarginalNote>“similar product”<br/>« <I>produit similaire</I> »<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0">“similar product” means any product whose nature, quality or terms of delivery are substantially the same as those of another product and meet the requirements of the entity that procures it.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:ABSOLUTE PREFERENCE GIVEN TO CANADIAN PRODUCTS--><Para TopMargin="10" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">ABSOLUTE PREFERENCE GIVEN TO CANADIAN PRODUCTS</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Preference<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>3.</B> When the Government of Canada procures a product, it shall, where similar products at similar prices are available,</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>a</I>) give preference to a Canadian product over a partially Canadian product or a non-Canadian product; and</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>b</I>) give preference to a partially Canadian product over a non-Canadian product.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Absolute preference<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>4.</B> Where the Government of Canada considers it advisable, it shall give absolute preference to Canadian products by</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>a</I>) giving them exclusive access to a government contract; or</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>b</I>) giving them a price preference greater than the 7.5% specified in paragraph (<I>a</I>) of the definition “similar price” in section 2.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Additional conditions<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>5.</B> Where the Government of Canada considers it appropriate, it may impose additional conditions on access to a government contract, notably in order to benefit small business, suppliers from certain minority groups or suppliers from certain regions or communities.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Equitable distribution between provinces<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>6.</B> Insofar as possible, the Government of Canada shall ensure an equitable distribution of the acquisitions it makes among the provinces and shall not, in a fiscal year, obtain more than 50% of the value of its Canadian products from a single province.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:DEVELOPMENT OF POLICIES--><Para TopMargin="10" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">DEVELOPMENT OF POLICIES</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Development of policy by President of Treasury Board<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>7.</B> Not later than six months after this Act receives royal assent, the President of the Treasury Board shall develop and adopt a policy respecting the goods and services procured by every department and agent of the Government of Canada, and shall cause the policy to be laid before each House of Parliament and published in the <I>Canada Ga- zette</I>.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Development of policy by ministers responsible for Crown corporations<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>8.</B> Not later than six months after this Act receives royal assent, each minister shall develop and adopt a policy respecting the goods and services procured by every Crown corporation for which the minister is responsible, unless that Crown corporation is subject to the policy described in section 7, and shall cause the policy to be laid before each House of Parliament and published in the <I>Canada Gazette</I>.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Development of policy by boards of directors of foundations and trusts<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>9.</B> Not later than six months after this Act receives royal assent, the board of directors of every foundation and trust referred to in the definition “Government of Canada” in section 2 shall develop and adopt a policy respecting the goods and services procured by that foundation or trust. The policy shall be submitted to the minister responsible for the department from which the foundation or trust receives the largest share of its funding, and the minister shall cause the policy to be laid before each House of Parliament.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:EXCEPTIONS--><Para TopMargin="10" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">EXCEPTIONS</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Exceptions<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>10.</B> A policy referred to in section 7, 8 or 9 may provide for exceptions to sections 3 to 6 if</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>a</I>) a product is required to deal with an emergency in which there is danger to public health or safety, and there are reasonable grounds to believe that it would not be possible to procure the product in the quantity or within the time period required to deal with the emergency;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>b</I>) there are reasonable grounds to believe that it would not be possible to procure a product in the quantity or within the time period required;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>c</I>) a product is acquired to provide humanitarian assistance outside Canada or for the purposes of international development, and the acquisition of a Canadian product could reasonably be expected to decrease the effectiveness of the assistance or development; or</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>d</I>) access to a government contract is extended to a least developed country for the purposes of international development.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Notice<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>11.</B> The minister responsible for an entity that avails itself of an exception under section 10 in the acquisition of a product whose value exceeds $5,000 shall, within 30 days after the start of the acquisition process, cause a notice justifying the exception to be published in the <I>Canada Gazette</I>.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:NON-APPLICATION--><Para TopMargin="10" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">NON-APPLICATION</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>North American Free Trade Agreement<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>12.</B> As regards NAFTA countries, this Act does not apply to contracts in respect of which the North American Free Trade Agreement requires that Canada accord to the suppliers of another NAFTA country treatment no less favourable than that which it accords to its own suppliers.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Agreement on Government Procurement of the World Trade Organization<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>13.</B> As regards countries that are parties to the Agreement on Government Procurement of the World Trade Organization and with which Canada has negotiated mutually acceptable commitments, this Act does not apply to contracts subject to that Agreement in respect of which Canada has made specific commitments.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Reciprocity<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>14.</B> Section 13 does not apply in respect of a country that is a party to the Agreement referred to in that section if the acquisition is for a service in respect of which the country has not accorded Canada reciprocal access.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:REGULATIONS--><Para TopMargin="10" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">REGULATIONS</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Orders and regulations<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>15.</B> The Governor in Council may make any orders and regulations that are necessary for carrying out the provisions of this Act, and, without restricting the generality of the foregoing, orders and regulations</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>a</I>) for ensuring reciprocity between Canada and any other NAFTA country by expanding the benefits accorded to the enterprises of that NAFTA country if that country provides Canadian suppliers with greater access to its government contracts than the access required by the North American Free Trade Agreement;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>b</I>) for suspending certain benefits accorded to the enterprises of any NAFTA country in accordance with the provisions of Chapter Twenty of the North American Free Trade Agreement;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>c</I>) for ensuring reciprocity between Canada and any country that is a party to the Agreement on Government Procurement of the World Trade Organization by expanding the benefits accorded to the enterprises of that country if that country provides Canadian suppliers with greater access to its government contracts than the access required by that Agreement; and</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>d</I>) for suspending certain benefits accorded to the enterprises of any country that is a party to the Agreement on Government Procurement of the World Trade Organization.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:COMING INTO FORCE--><Para TopMargin="10" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">COMING INTO FORCE</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Coming into force<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>16.</B> This Act comes into force six months after the day on which it receives royal assent.</Para></Block><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="BPT_ImprintE">Published under authority of the Speaker of the House of Commons<br/>Available from:<br/>Publishing and Depository Services<br/>Public Works and Government Services Canada<br/>Ottawa, Ontario K1A 0S5<br/>Telephone: 613-941-5995 or 1-800-635-7943<br/>Fax: 613-954-5779 or 1-800-565-7757<br/>publications@tpsgc-pwgsc.gc.ca<br/>http://publications.gc.ca</Para></Block><Block Align="Yes" LineCnt="N"><Para NoLineBreak="Yes" NoHtml="Yes" Leading="0" Size="0" TopMargin="0" BottomMargin="0"></Para></Block></Bill_Part></Bill>
