<?xml version="1.0"?>
<Bill RHead_reign="57-58 Eliz. II" RHead_ParlYear="2009" DocumentTitle="BILL C-383" Bill_No="C-383" Document_No="402106" xml:lang="EN" Bill_Type="Non-amending" Stage_Name="First-Reading-House" Reprint="No" xml:space="preserve" ChapterNo_E="C. " ChapterNo_F="ch. " Bill-Origin="commons"><Bill_Part Part_Type="Cover" CountLines="No"><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="CovBillNo">C-383</Para></Block><Block><Para TopMargin="24" Size="9" Leading="10" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0" TextAlign="Center">Second Session, Fortieth Parliament,</Para></Block><Block><Para Size="9" Leading="10" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0" TextAlign="Center">57-58 Elizabeth II, 2009</Para></Block><Block><Para TopMargin="48" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0" Bold="Yes" TextAlign="Center">HOUSE OF COMMONS OF CANADA</Para></Block><Block><Para TopMargin="42" Size="18" Leading="20" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0" Bold="Yes" TextAlign="Center">BILL C-383</Para></Block><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="CovLongTitle">An Act respecting education benefits for spouses and children of certain deceased federal enforcement officers</Para></Block><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="COV_StageLine"></Para></Block><Block><Para Size="9" AllCaps="Yes" Hyphenate="OFF">first reading, May 12, 2009</Para></Block><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="COV_StageLine"></Para></Block><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="Cover_Sponsors"><SC SC_PerCent="85">Mr. Wrzesnewskyj</SC></Para></Block><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="Cover_DocNo">402106</Para></Block></Bill_Part><Bill_Part CountLines="No" Part_Type="InsideCover"><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="BPT_InsideCoverE">Also available on the Parliament of Canada Web Site at the following address:<br/><B>http://www.parl.gc.ca</B></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><Para TopMargin="108" BottomMargin="4" Size="10" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">SUMMARY</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" Size="8" Leading="9" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">This enactment permits the Minister to grant education benefits of a financial nature to the surviving spouse and children of federal enforcement officers who die from injuries received or illnesses contracted in the discharge of their duties.</Para></Block></Bill_Part><Bill_Part Part_Type="MainText" CountLines="Yes" RunningHead_E="Education Benefits"><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="MainText_DocNo">402106</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes"><Para Style="Session_Reign">2nd Session, 40th Parliament,</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes"><Para Style="Session_Reign">57-58 Elizabeth II, 2009</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes"><Para Style="MainBillOrigin">house of commons of canada</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes"><Para Bold="Yes" Style="MAIN@BillNo_Title">BILL C-383</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes"><Para Style="MAIN@ti;04">An Act respecting education benefits for spouses and children of certain deceased federal enforcement officers</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">Her Majesty, by and with the advice and consent of the Senate and House of Commons of Canada, enacts as follows:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:SHORT TITLE--><Para TopMargin="10" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">SHORT TITLE</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Short title<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>1.</B> This Act may be cited as the <I>Education Benefits Act</I>.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:INTERPRETATION--><Para TopMargin="10" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">INTERPRETATION</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Definitions<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>2.</B> The definitions in this section apply in this Act.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><MarginalNote>ГўВЂВњchildГўВЂВќ<br/>Г‚В« <I>enfant</I> Г‚В»<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0">ГўВЂВњchildГўВЂВќ means a child of a federal enforcement officer, including a natural child, stepchild or adopted child.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><MarginalNote>ГўВЂВњeducational institutionГўВЂВќ<br/>Г‚В« <I>ГѓВ©tablissement dГўВЂВ™enseigne-ment</I> Г‚В»<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0">ГўВЂВњeducational institutionГўВЂВќ means a technical or vocational school, university, college or other school of higher education in Canada that provides training or instruction of an educational, professional, vocational or technical nature and is approved by the Minister for the education or instruction of students pursuant to this Act.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><MarginalNote>ГўВЂВњeducation benefitsГўВЂВќ<br/>Г‚В« <I>prestations dГўВЂВ™ГѓВ©ducation</I> Г‚В»<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0">ГўВЂВњeducation benefitsГўВЂВќ means an allowance or costs paid to or in respect of students to enable them to continue their education or instruction at an educational institution.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><MarginalNote>ГўВЂВњfederal enforcement officerГўВЂВќ<br/>Г‚В« <I>agent fГѓВ©dГѓВ©ral</I> Г‚В»<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0">ГўВЂВњfederal enforcement officerГўВЂВќ means</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>a</I>) a member of the Correctional Service of Canada who is designated as a peace officer pursuant to section 10 of the <I>Corrections and Conditional Release Act</I>,  or a person employed by the federal government who is a warden, deputy warden, instructor, keeper, jailer, guard or any other officer or permanent employee of a prison other than a penitentiary as defined in Part I of  that Act;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>b</I>) a person employed by the federal government who is a member of the Royal Canadian Mounted Police, a police constable, a bailiff, a constable or any other person employed by the federal government, or a Crown corporation within the meaning of section 83 of the <I>Financial Administration Act</I>, for the preservation and maintenance of the public peace or for the service or execution of civil process;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>c</I>) an officer or a person having the powers of a customs or excise officer when performing any duty or function in the enforcement of the <I>Customs Act</I>, the <I>Excise Act</I> or the <I>Excise Act, 2001</I>;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>d</I>) a person designated as a fishery guardian under the <I>Fisheries Act</I> when performing any duty or function in the enforcement of that Act or a person designated as a fishery officer under the <I>Fisheries Act</I> when performing any duty or function in the enforcement of that Act or the <I>Coastal Fisheries Protection Act</I>;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>e</I>) an officer or employee of the Parks Canada Agency, established by the <I>Parks Canada Agency Act</I>, an employee of the Canadian Security Intelligence Service, established by the <I>Canadian Security Intelligence Service Act</I>, or an officer designated under the <I>Immigration and Refugee Protection Act</I>, when performing any duty or function in the enforcement of their respective Act; or</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>f</I>) an officer or non-commissioned member of the Canadian Forces.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><MarginalNote>ГўВЂВњMinisterГўВЂВќ<br/>Г‚В« <I>ministre</I> Г‚В»<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0">ГўВЂВњMinisterГўВЂВќ means the member of the QueenГўВЂВ™s Privy Council for Canada who is designated by the Governor in Council as the Minister for the purposes of this Act.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><MarginalNote>ГўВЂВњpeace officerГўВЂВќ<br/>Г‚В« <I>agent de la paix</I> Г‚В»<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0">ГўВЂВњpeace officerГўВЂВќ has the same meaning as in section 2 of the <I>Criminal Code</I>.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><MarginalNote>ГўВЂВњspouseГўВЂВќ<br/>Г‚В« <I>conjoint</I> Г‚В»<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0">ГўВЂВњspouseГўВЂВќ means a person who is</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>a</I>) married to a federal enforcement officer; or</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>b</I>) cohabiting with a federal enforcement officer in a conjugal relationship, having so cohabited for a period of at least one year.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><MarginalNote>ГўВЂВњstudentГўВЂВќ<br/>Г‚В« <I>ГѓВ©tudiant</I> Г‚В»<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0">ГўВЂВњstudentГўВЂВќ means a person who is a spouse or child of a federal enforcement officer who has died from an injury received or an illness contracted in the discharge of their duty.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:EDUCATION BENEFITS--><Para TopMargin="10" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">EDUCATION BENEFITS</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Application<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>3.</B> This Act applies only to the surviving spouse and children of a federal enforcement officer who has died from an injury received or an illness contracted in the discharge of their duty on or after the day this Act comes into force.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Surviving spouse and children only<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>4.</B> No education benefits shall be paid under this Act to or in respect of any person other than the surviving spouse and children of the federal enforcement officer on account of whose death the education benefits are claimed.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Allowances and costs of instruction<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>5.</B> The Minister may, in accordance with this Act and the regulations and out of money appropriated for that purpose by Parliament,</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>a</I>) provide allowances to or in respect of students to enable them to continue their education or instruction at an educational institution; and</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>b</I>) pay in whole or in part the cost of such education or instruction.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Amount of allowance<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>6.</B> (1) The amount of the monthly allowance that may be paid to or in respect of a student during the period in which the student pursues a program of study at an educational institution shall be,</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>a</I>) for a full-time program of study in the case of a child, equal to the monthly rate of pension for one orphan child provided in Schedule II to the <I>Pension Act</I>; and</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>b</I>) for a full-time or part-time program of study in the case of a spouse, equal to the monthly rate of pension for a survivor provided in Schedule II to the <I>Pension Act</I>.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Total period covered<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(2) The total period for which education benefits may be paid to or in respect of a student under this Act shall not exceed</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>a</I>) in the case of a child, four academic years or thirty-six months, whichever is the lesser; and</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>b</I>) in the case of a spouse, the period of time required by the spouse to complete a program of study, either full-time or part-time, that is considered by the educational institution to be equivalent to or be, in terms of years, an undergraduate or a graduate program of study at a university.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Costs<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(3) The costs of education or instruction that may be paid in respect of a student under this Act shall include such tuition and other fees and costs as may be prescribed by regulation.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Minister may extend<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(4) The Minister may extend the total period for which education benefits may be paid to or in respect of a student under this Act if the Minister is of the opinion that the studentГўВЂВ™s progress and achievements in their program of study or their personal circumstances are such that it would be in the interest both of the student and of the public that the payments under section 5 be continued during a further period.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Age restriction ГўВЂВ”  child<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>7.</B> (1) No education benefits shall be paid under this Act to or in respect of a child who has attained the age set out below, except as may be necessary to enable the child to complete the academic year in which the child  attains that age:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>a</I>) twenty-five years; or</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>b</I>) thirty years where, pursuant to sub-section 6(4), the Minister has extended the total period for which education benefits may be paid beyond the year in which the student attains the age of twenty-five years.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>No age restriction  ГўВЂВ”spouse<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(2) For greater certainty, no age restriction exists in respect of the education benefits that may be paid to or in respect of a spouse under this Act.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Program limit ГўВЂВ”  child<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>8.</B> (1) No education benefits shall be paid under this Act to or in respect of a child for</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>a</I>) a program of study that is considered by the educational institution to be equivalent to or be a graduate program of study at a university; or</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>b</I>) a program of study that is considered by the educational institution to be part of a graduate program of study at a university.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Program limit ГўВЂВ”  spouse<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(2) No education benefits shall be paid under this Act to or in respect of a spouse for more than one program of study that is considered by the educational institution to be equivalent to or be, in terms of years, an undergraduate or a graduate program of study at a university.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Proof of enrolment<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>9.</B> In support of each claim for education benefits by a student enrolled in an educational institution, the student shall submit to the Minister, in a form satisfactory to the Minister,</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>a</I>) a declaration signed by a responsible officer of the educational institution certifying that the student is or has been enrolled in a program of study requiring full-time or part-time attendance at the educational institution; and</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>b</I>) a declaration signed by the student certifying that the student is or has been for a period of time in full-time or part-time attendance at the educational institution.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Failure to be promoted<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>10.</B> (1) Subject to subsection (2), no educa-tion benefits shall be paid to or in respect of a student for any education or instruction obtained after the student fails to meet the requirements of an educational institution for promotion to the next succeeding level of the full-time or part-time program of study that the student is pursuing at that educational institution.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Continuation of education benefits<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(2) Where the student fails to meet the requirements of an educational institution for promotion to the next succeeding level of the full-time or part-time program of study that the student is pursuing at that educational institution, the Minister may authorize the continuation of education benefits if</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>a</I>) in the opinion of the Minister, the student failed to meet the requirements for promotion for reasons beyond the studentГўВЂВ™s control; or</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>b</I>) the student is subsequently promoted, at that or another educational institution, to the next succeeding level of that full-time or part-time program of study or of another full-time or part-time program of study having, in the opinion of the Minister, equivalent levels.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Costs paid to educational institution<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>11.</B> The Minister may, in accordance with the regulations, pay to the educational institution in which any student receiving education benefits under this Act is taking their program of education or instruction any of the costs of the program that are payable to the educational institution.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:ANNUAL ADJUSTMENT OF ALLOWANCES--><Para TopMargin="10" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">ANNUAL ADJUSTMENT OF ALLOWANCES</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Annual adjustment<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>12.</B> (1) Where any allowance is payable under this Act, the basic monthly amount of that allowance shall be adjusted annually, in such manner as may be prescribed by the Governor in Council, so that the amount payable for a month in any following year is an amount equal to the product obtained by multiplying</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>a</I>) the amount that would have been payable for that month if no adjustment had been made under this section with respect to that following year,</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0">by</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>b</I>) the ratio that the Consumer Price Index for the twelve-month period ending on the thirty-first day of October immediately before that following year bears to the Consumer Price Index for the twelve-month period immediately before that twelve-month period.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Meaning of certain references<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(2) In this section and section 14,</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>a</I>) a reference to the Consumer Price Index for any twelve-month period means the average of the Consumer Price Index for Canada, as published by Statistics Canada under the authority of the <I>Statistics Act</I>, for each month in that twelve-month period; and</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>b</I>) a reference to the basic monthly amount of any allowance shall be construed as a reference to the amount of that allowance, expressed in terms of a monthly amount and calculated without regard to the provisions of this section.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Limitation<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>13.</B> Notwithstanding anything in section 12, the amount of any allowance that may be paid to or in respect of a person for a month in any calendar year shall not, by reason only of that section, be less than the amount of the allowance that was or may be paid to or in respect of that person for any month in the immediately preceding calendar year.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Where basis of Consumer Price Index changed<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>14.</B> Where at any time the Consumer Price Index for Canada, as published by Statistics Canada under the authority of the <I>Statistics Act</I>, is adjusted to reflect a new time basis or a new content basis, a corresponding adjustment shall be made in the Consumer Price Index for any twelve-month period that is used for the purpose of calculating the amount of any allowance that may be paid.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:REGULATIONS--><Para TopMargin="10" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">REGULATIONS</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Regulations<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>15.</B> The Minister may make regulations</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>a</I>) prescribing the manner of payment of the education benefits under this Act to or in respect of students and the manner of computing the amount of costs payable in respect of a student for any period;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>b</I>) prescribing the conditions in addition to those specified in this Act under which the payment of education benefits may be terminated;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>c</I>) prescribing the criteria to be used for the purpose of establishing or deeming what constitutes full-time or part-time attendance at an educational institution;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>d</I>) prescribing the form and manner of submitting a claim for education benefits;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>e</I>) prescribing anything that, by this Act, is to be prescribed; and</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>f</I>) for any other purpose deemed necessary to give effect to this Act.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:COMING INTO FORCE--><Para TopMargin="10" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">COMING INTO FORCE</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Coming into force<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>16.</B> The provisions of this Act come into force on a day or days to be fixed by order of the Governor in Council.</Para></Block><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="BPT_ImprintE">Published under authority of the Speaker of the House of Commons<br/>Available from:<br/>Publishing and Depository Services<br/>Public Works and Government Services Canada<br/>Ottawa, Ontario K1A 0S5<br/>Telephone: 613-941-5995 or 1-800-635-7943<br/>Fax: 613-954-5779 or 1-800-565-7757<br/>publications@tpsgc-pwgsc.gc.ca<br/>http://publications.gc.ca</Para></Block><Block Align="Yes" LineCnt="N"><Para NoLineBreak="Yes" NoHtml="Yes" Leading="0" Size="0" TopMargin="0" BottomMargin="0">Г‚В„</Para></Block></Bill_Part></Bill>
