<?xml version="1.0"?>
<Bill RHead_reign="56-57 Eliz. II" RHead_ParlYear="2007-2008" DocumentTitle="BILL C-29" Bill_No="C-29" Document_No="90410" xml:lang="EN" Bill_Type="Non-amending" Stage_Name="Third-Reading-House" Reprint="No" xml:space="preserve" ChapterNo_E="C. " ChapterNo_F="ch. " Bill-Origin="commons"><Bill_Part Part_Type="Cover" CountLines="No"><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="CovBillNo">C-29</Para></Block><Block><Para TopMargin="24" Size="9" Leading="10" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0" TextAlign="Center">Second Session, Thirty-ninth Parliament,</Para></Block><Block><Para Size="9" Leading="10" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0" TextAlign="Center">56-57 Elizabeth II, 2007-2008</Para></Block><Block><Para TopMargin="48" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0" Bold="Yes" TextAlign="Center">HOUSE OF COMMONS OF CANADA</Para></Block><Block><Para TopMargin="42" Size="18" Leading="20" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0" Bold="Yes" TextAlign="Center">BILL C-29</Para></Block><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="CovLongTitle">An Act to amend the Canada Elections Act (accountability with respect to loans)</Para></Block><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="COV_StageLine"></Para></Block><Block><Para BottomMargin="14" Size="11" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0" Bold="Yes" TextAlign="Center">AS PASSED</Para></Block><Block><Para Size="8" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0" TextAlign="Center">BY THE HOUSE OF COMMONS<br/>0 0, 2008</Para></Block><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="COV_StageLine"></Para></Block><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="Cover_DocNo">90410</Para></Block></Bill_Part><Bill_Part CountLines="No" Part_Type="InsideCover"><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="BPT_InsideCoverE">Also available on the Parliament of Canada Web Site at the following address:<br/><B>http://www.parl.gc.ca</B></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><Para TopMargin="108" BottomMargin="4" Size="10" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">SUMMARY</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" Size="8" Leading="9" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">This enactment amends the <I>Canada Elections Act</I> to enact rules concerning loans, guarantees and suretyships with respect to registered parties, registered associations, candidates, leadership contestants and nomination contestants.</Para></Block></Bill_Part><Bill_Part Part_Type="MainText" CountLines="Yes" RunningHead_E="Canada Elections (accountability with respect to loans)"><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="MainText_DocNo">90410</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes"><Para Style="Session_Reign">2nd Session, 39th Parliament,</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes"><Para Style="Session_Reign">56-57 Elizabeth II, 2007-2008</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes"><Para Style="MainBillOrigin">house of commons of canada</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes"><Para Bold="Yes" Style="MAIN@BillNo_Title">BILL C-29</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes"><Para Style="MAIN@ti;04">An Act to amend the Canada Elections Act (accountability with respect to loans)</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">Her Majesty, by and with the advice and consent of the Senate and House of Commons of Canada, enacts as follows:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:CANADA ELECTIONS ACT--><MarginalNote>2000, c. 9<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="10" Bold="Yes" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">CANADA ELECTIONS ACT</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>2003, c. 19, s. 23<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>1.</B> Subsection 403.28(3) of the <I>Canada Elections Act</I> is replaced by the following:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Prohibition 芒聙聰 accepting contributions, borrowing<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(3) No person, other than an electoral district agent of a registered association, shall accept contributions to the registered association or borrow money on its behalf.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>2003, c. 19, s. 23<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>2.</B> Paragraph 403.31(1)(<I>b</I>) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>b</I>) the payment was not made in the six-month period referred to in section 403.3.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>2.1</B> Subsection 403.34(1) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>403.34</B> (1) An unpaid claim mentioned in a return referred to in subsection 403.35(1) is deemed to be a contribution of the unpaid amount to the registered association made as of the day on which the expense was incurred or the loan was made, as the case may be, if the claim remains unpaid in whole or in part</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>a</I>) 18 months after the end of the fiscal period to which the return relates, in the case of a claim to be paid for an expense; or</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>b</I>) three years after the day on which the amount is due according to the terms of the loan, in the case of a claim for a loan made to the registered association under section 405.5.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>2003, c. 19, s. 23<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>3.</B> (1) Subparagraph 403.35(2)(<I>e</I>)(ii) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="4" FirstLineIndent="0">(ii) unpaid claims that are, or may be, the subject of an application referred to in subsection 403.31(1) or section 403.32, and loans made to the registered association under section 405.5 that remain unpaid in whole or in part;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>2003, c. 19, s. 23<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes">(2) Paragraphs 403.35(2)(<I>i</I>) and (<I>i.1</I>) of the Act are replaced by the following:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>i</I>) a statement of each loan made to the registered association under section 405.5, including the amount of the loan, the interest rate, the lender芒聙聶s name and address, the dates and amounts of repayments of principal and payments of interest and, if there is a guarantor, the guarantor芒聙聶s name and address and the amount guaranteed; and</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>2003, c. 19, s. 23<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes">(3) Subsection 403.35(3) of the Act is repealed.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>2006, c. 9, s. 46(1)<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>4.</B> (1) The portion of subsection 405(1) of the Act before paragraph (<I>a</I>) is replaced by the following:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Contribution limits<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>405.</B> (1) Subject to subsection 405.5(4), no individual shall make contributions that exceed</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes">(2) Paragraph 405(1)(<I>c</I>) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>c</I>) $1,000 in total in any calendar year to the leadership contestants in a particular leadership contest.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>5.</B> The Act is amended by adding the following after section 405.4:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:Loans, Guarantees and Suretyships--><Para TopMargin="10" Italic="Yes" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">Loans, Guarantees and Suretyships</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Ineligible lenders and guarantors<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>405.5</B> (1) Except as permitted under this section, no person or entity shall</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>a</I>) make a loan to a registered party or a registered association;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>b</I>) make a loan to a candidate, a leadership contestant or a nomination contestant in relation to the candidate芒聙聶s or contestant芒聙聶s campaign; or</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>c</I>) guarantee a loan referred to in paragraph (<I>a</I>) or (<I>b</I>).</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Ineligible borrowers<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(2) Except if the loan is permitted under this section, no chief agent of a registered party or financial agent of a registered association shall borrow money on behalf of the party or association, and no official agent of a candidate or financial agent of a leadership contestant or nomination contestant shall borrow money for the purposes of the candidate芒聙聶s or contestant芒聙聶s campaign.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Exception 芒聙聰 financial institutions<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(3) A financial institution as defined in section 2 of the <I>Bank Act</I> may in writing make a loan referred to in subsection (1) at a fair market rate of interest.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Exception 芒聙聰 individuals<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(4) An individual who is a citizen or a permanent resident as defined in subsection 2(1) of the <I>Immigration and Refugee Protection Act</I> may, in writing, make a loan referred to in subsection (1) or guarantee such a loan. However, the total of the following amounts shall not at any time exceed the individual芒聙聶s relevant contribution limit set out in paragraphs 405(1)(<I>a</I>) to (<I>c</I>) and (4)(<I>a</I>) to (<I>c</I>):</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>a</I>) the amounts of the individual芒聙聶s contributions;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>b</I>) the amounts of the individual芒聙聶s loans made in the relevant contribution period, not including any amount that has been repaid in the calendar year in which the loan was made; and</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>c</I>) the amounts guaranteed by the individual in the relevant contribution period, not including any amount for which the individ-<keep>ual has</keep> ceased to be liable in the calendar year in which the guarantee was given.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Exception 芒聙聰 certain loans<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(5) A loan may be made, in writing,</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>a</I>) by a registered party to a registered association of the party or a candidate endorsed by the party; or</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>b</I>) by a registered association to the registered party with which it is affiliated, another registered association of the party or a candidate endorsed by the party.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Exception 芒聙聰 certain guarantees and suretyships<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(6) A registered party or registered association may, in writing, guarantee a loan made in writing to a party, association or candidate to which it itself is permitted to make a loan under subsection (5).</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Report 芒聙聰 loans<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>405.6</B> (1) The chief agent of a registered party, the financial agent of a registered association, the official agent of a candidate or the financial agent of a leadership contestant or nomination contestant shall provide the Chief Electoral Officer with a report in the prescribed form on every loan made under section 405.5 to the party, association, candidate or contestant, as the case may be. The report shall make full disclosure of the loan芒聙聶s terms and conditions, including</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>a</I>) the amount of the loan;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>b</I>) the interest rate;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>c</I>) the lender芒聙聶s name and address; and</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>d</I>) if there is a guarantor, the guarantor芒聙聶s name and address and the amount guaranteed.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>When report must be sent<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(2) The report shall be provided at the same time as the financial transactions return provided under paragraph 403.35(1)(<I>a</I>) or 424(1)(<I>a</I>) or the leadership campaign return, electoral campaign return or nomination campaign return provided under paragraph 435.3(1)(<I>a</I>), 451(1)(<I>a</I>) or 478.23(1)(<I>a</I>) respectively, as the case may be.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Amendments<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(3) If there is any amendment to the terms and conditions of the loan 芒聙聰 including the giving of a guarantee or suretyship in respect of the loan 芒聙聰 after the report on the loan is provided, then the person responsible for providing reports under subsection (1) shall without delay provide the Chief Electoral Officer with a report on the amendment in the prescribed form.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Publication<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(4) The Chief Electoral Officer shall publish a report provided under subsection (1) or (3) as soon as practicable after it is received, in the manner that he or she considers appropriate.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Deemed contributions<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>405.7</B> (1) A loan made under subsection 405.5(3) or (4) that remains unpaid, in whole or in part, three years after polling day in the case of a candidate, the selection day in the case of a nomination contestant, the day of the leadership contest in the case of a leadership contestant, and in the case of a registered party and registered association the day that the amount is due according to the terms of the loan, is deemed to be a contribution of the unpaid amount to the registered party, registered association, candidate, leadership contestant or nomination contestant made on the day on which the loan was made.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>When no deemed contribution<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(2) Subsection (1) does not apply to an unpaid amount that, at the end of the three-year period,</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>a</I>) is the subject of a binding agreement to pay;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>b</I>) is the subject of a legal proceeding to secure its payment;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>c</I>) is the subject of a dispute as to the amount that was to be paid or the amount that remains unpaid; or</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>d</I>) has been written off by the lender as an uncollectable debt in accordance with the lender芒聙聶s normal accounting practices.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Notice by registered party, etc.<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(3) A registered party, registered association, candidate, leadership contestant or nomination contestant or the registered agent, financial agent or official agent, as the case may be, that believes that any of paragraphs (2)(<I>a</I>) to (<I>d</I>) prevents subsection (1) from applying to a liability of the party, association, candidate or contestant to pay an amount shall so notify the Chief Electoral Officer before the end of the three-year period.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Representations<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(3.1) Before a determination is made under subsection (4), an electoral district association, registered party or lender shall be given the opportunity to make representations to the Chief Electoral Officer.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Chief Electoral Officer芒聙聶s decision<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(4) The Chief Electoral Officer shall without delay determine whether any of those paragraphs applies to the liability and shall inform the person or entity of his or her decision.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Uncollectable debts<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(5) If the Chief Electoral Officer determines that an unpaid amount of a loan to a candidate of a registered party has been written off under paragraph (2)(<I>d</I>), then the Chief Electoral Officer shall inform the claimant, the candidate's registered association or, if there is no registered association, the registered party of his or her decision.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Publication<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(6) As soon as practicable after the end of the three-year period, the Chief Electoral Officer shall publish in any manner that he or she considers appropriate</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>a</I>) a notice of any unpaid amount that is deemed to be a contribution under subsection (1); and</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>b</I>) a notice of any unpaid amount that, under subsection (2), is not deemed to be a contribution, as well as the paragraph of that subsection that prevents it from being deemed to be a contribution.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>2003, c. 19, s. 31<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>6.</B> Subsection 416(3) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Prohibition 芒聙聰 accepting contributions, borrowing<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(3) No person or entity, other than a registered agent of a registered party, shall accept contributions to the registered party or borrow money on its behalf.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>7.</B> Paragraph 419(1)(<I>b</I>) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>b</I>) the payment was not made in the six-month period mentioned in section 418.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>7.1</B> Subsection 423.1(1) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>423.1</B> (1) An unpaid claim mentioned in the financial transactions return referred to in subsection 424(1) or in an election expenses return referred to in subsection 429(1) is deemed to be a contribution to the registered party of the unpaid amount on the day on which the expense was incurred or the loan was made, as the case may be, if the claim remains unpaid in whole or in part</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>a</I>) 18 months after the end of the fiscal period to which the return relates or in which the polling day fell, as the case may be, in the case of a claim to be paid for an expense; or</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>b</I>) three years after the end of that fiscal period, in the case of a claim for a loan made to the registered party under section 405.5.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>8.</B> (1) Subparagraph 424(2)(<I>f</I>)(ii) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="4" FirstLineIndent="0">(ii) unpaid claims that are, or may be, the subject of an application referred to in subsection 419(1) or section 420, and loans made to the registered party under section 405.5 that remain unpaid in whole or in part;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes">(2) Paragraph 424(2)(<I>j</I>) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>j</I>) a statement of each loan made to the registered party under section 405.5, including the amount of the loan, the interest rate, the lender芒聙聶s name and address, the dates and amounts of repayments of principal and payments of interest and, if there is a guarantor, the guarantor芒聙聶s name and address and the amount guaranteed; and</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes">(3) Subsection 424(3) of the Act is repealed.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>2003, c. 19, s. 40<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>9.</B> Subsection 435.22(1) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Prohibition 芒聙聰 accepting contributions, borrowing<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>435.22</B> (1) No person, other than a leadership campaign agent of a leadership contestant, shall accept contributions to the contestant芒聙聶s leadership campaign or borrow money on the contestant芒聙聶s behalf under section 405.5.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>2003, c. 19, s. 40<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>10.</B> (1) Subsection 435.24(1) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Payment within three years<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>435.24</B> (1) A claim for leadership campaign expenses that has been sent in accordance with section 435.23, as well as a claim for repayment of a loan made under section 405.5, must be paid within three years after the day on which the leadership contest ends.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes">(2) The portion of subsection 435.24(2) of the Act before paragraph (<I>a</I>) is replaced by the following:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes">(2) The requirement to pay a claim within three years does not apply to a claim in respect of which</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>2003, c. 19, s. 40<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>11.</B> Subsection 435.26(1) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Irregular claims or payments 芒聙聰 Chief Electoral Officer<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>435.26</B> (1) On the written application of a person with a claim to be paid for a leadership campaign expense in relation to a leadership contestant or for a loan made to the leadership contestant under section 405.5, or of the contestant芒聙聶s financial agent or the contestant in relation to such a claim, the Chief Electoral Officer may, on being satisfied that there are reasonable grounds for so doing, in writing authorize the payment, through the contestant芒聙聶s financial agent, of the amount claimed if</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>a</I>) in the case of an expense, the invoice or other document evidencing the claim was not sent in accordance with section 435.23 or the payment was not made in the three-year period referred to in subsection 435.24(1); or</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>b</I>) in the case of a loan, the repayment of the loan was not made in the three-year period referred to in subsection 435.24(1).</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>2003, c. 19, s. 40<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>12.</B> (1) Paragraph 435.27(<I>a</I>) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>a</I>) the applicant establishes that an authorization under subsection 435.26(1) has been refused and that the invoice or other document evidencing the claim was not sent in accordance with section 435.23 or the payment has not been made in the three-year period referred to in subsection 435.24(1); or</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>2003, c. 19, s. 40<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes">(2) Section 435.27 of the Act is renumbered as subsection 435.27(1) and is amended by adding the following:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Irregular claims and payments 芒聙聰 judge<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(2) On the application of a person with a claim to be paid for a loan made to a leadership contestant under section 405.5 or on the application of the contestant芒聙聶s financial agent or the contestant, as the case may be, a judge who is competent to conduct a recount may, on being satisfied that there are reasonable grounds for so doing, by order authorize the payment, through the contestant芒聙聶s financial agent, of the amount claimed if</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>a</I>) the applicant establishes that an authorization under subsection 435.26(1) has been refused and that the payment has not been made in the three-year period referred to in subsection 435.24(1); or</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>b</I>) the amount claimed has not been paid in accordance with an authorization obtained under subsection 435.26(1) and the applicant establishes their inability to comply with the authorization for reasons beyond their control.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0">The applicant shall notify the Chief Electoral Officer that the application has been made.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>2003, c. 19, s. 40<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>13.</B> The portion of subsection 435.28(1) of the Act before paragraph (<I>a</I>) is replaced by the following:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Proceedings to recover payment<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>435.28</B> (1) A person who has sent a claim in accordance with section 435.23, or has sent a claim for repayment of a loan made to a leadership contestant under section 405.5, may commence proceedings in a court of competent jurisdiction to recover any unpaid amount</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>13.1</B> Subsection 435.29(1) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>435.29</B> (1) An unpaid claim mentioned in a return referred to in subsection 435.3(1) is deemed to be a contribution of the unpaid amount to the leadership contestant made as of the day on which the expense was incurred if the claim remains unpaid, in whole or in part, three years after the end of the leadership contest.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>2003, c. 19, s. 40<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>14.</B> (1) Paragraph 435.3(2)(<I>c</I>) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>c</I>) a statement of unpaid claims 芒聙聰 including loans made to the leadership contestant under section 405.5 that remain unpaid in whole or in part 芒聙聰 that are, or may be, the subject of an application under section 435.26 or 435.27;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>2003, c. 19, s. 40<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes">(2) Paragraph 435.3(2)(<I>d.1</I>) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>d.1</I>) a statement of each loan made to the leadership contestant under section 405.5, including the amount of the loan, the interest rate, the lender芒聙聶s name and address, the dates and amounts of repayments of principal and payments of interest, the unpaid principal remaining at the end of each calendar year and, if there is a guarantor, the guarantor芒聙聶s name and address and the amount guaranteed;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>2003, c. 19, s. 40<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes">(3) Subsection 435.3(5) of the Act is repealed.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>15.</B> Subsection 438(2) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Prohibition 芒聙聰 accepting contributions, borrowing<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(2) No person, other than an official agent of a candidate, shall accept contributions to the candidate芒聙聶s electoral campaign or borrow money on the candidate芒聙聶s behalf under section 405.5.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>16.</B> (1) Section 445 of the Act is amended by adding the following after subsection (1):</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Payment 芒聙聰 loans<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(1.1) A loan made to a candidate under section 405.5 must be repaid within three years after polling day.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes">(2) The portion of subsection 445(2) of the Act before paragraph (<I>a</I>) is replaced by the following:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Exceptions<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(2) The requirement to pay within the period set out in subsection (1) or (1.1) does not apply to a claim or loan in respect of which</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>17.</B> Subsection 447(1) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Irregular claims or payments 芒聙聰 Chief Electoral Officer<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>447.</B> (1) On the written application of a person with a claim to be paid for a candidate芒聙聶s electoral campaign expense or for a loan made to the candidate under section 405.5, or of the candidate芒聙聶s official agent or the candidate in relation to such a claim, the Chief Electoral Officer may, on being satisfied that there are reasonable grounds for so doing, in writing authorize the payment, through the candidate芒聙聶s official agent, of the amount claimed if</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>a</I>) in the case of an expense, the invoice or other document evidencing the claim was not sent in accordance with section 444 or the payment was not made in the four-month period mentioned in subsection 445(1); and</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>b</I>) in the case of a loan, the repayment of the loan was not made in the three-year period mentioned in subsection 445(1.1).</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>18.</B> Section 448 of the Act is renumbered as subsection 448(1) and is amended by adding the following:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Irregular claims and payments 芒聙聰 judge<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(2) On the application of a person with a claim to be paid for a loan made to a candidate under section 405.5 or on the application of the candidate芒聙聶s official agent or the candidate, as the case may be, a judge who is competent to conduct a recount may, on being satisfied that there are reasonable grounds for so doing, by order authorize the payment, through the candidate芒聙聶s official agent, of the amount claimed if</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>a</I>) the applicant establishes that an authorization under subsection 447(1) has been refused and that the payment has not been made in the three-year period mentioned in subsection 445(1.1); or</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>b</I>) the amount claimed has not been paid in accordance with an authorization obtained under subsection 447(1) and the applicant establishes their inability to comply with the authorization for reasons beyond their control.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0">The applicant shall notify the Chief Electoral Officer that the application has been made.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>19.</B> Subsection 449(1) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Proceedings to recover payment<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>449.</B> (1) A person who has sent a claim in accordance with section 444, or has sent a claim for repayment of a loan made to a candidate under section 405.5, may commence proceedings in a court of competent jurisdiction to recover any unpaid amount</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>a</I>) at any time, if the candidate or his or her official agent refuses to pay that amount or disputes that it is payable; or</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>b</I>) after the end of the period mentioned in subsection 445(1) or (1.1) or any extension of that period authorized by subsection 447(1) or section 448, in any other case.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>19.1.</B> Subsection 450(1) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>450.</B> (1) An unpaid claim mentioned in a return referred to in subsection 451(1) is deemed to be a contribution of the unpaid amount to the candidate made as of the day on which the expense was incurred or the loan was made, as the case may be, if the claim remains unpaid in whole or in part</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0" Bold="Yes">(<I>a</I>) 18 months after polling day for the election to which the return relates, in the case of a claim to be paid for a candidate's electoral campaign expense; or</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0" Bold="Yes">(<I>b</I>) three years after that polling day, in the case of a claim for a loan made to the candidate under section 405.5.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>20.</B> (1) Paragraph 451(2)(<I>e</I>) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>e</I>) a statement of unpaid claims 芒聙聰 including loans made to the candidate under section 405.5 that remain unpaid in whole or in part 芒聙聰 that are, or may be, the subject of an application under section 447 or 448;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>e.1</I>) a statement of each loan made to the candidate under section 405.5, including the amount of the loan, the interest rate, the lender芒聙聶s name and address, the dates and amounts of repayments of principal and payments of interest, the unpaid principal remaining at the end of each calendar year and, if there is a guarantor, the guarantor芒聙聶s name and address and the amount guaranteed;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes">(2) Subsection 451(3) of the Act is repealed.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>2003, c. 19, s. 57<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>21.</B> Subsection 478.13(1) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Prohibition 芒聙聰 accepting contributions, borrowing<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>478.13</B> (1) No person, other than the financial agent of a nomination contestant, shall accept contributions to the contestant芒聙聶s nomination campaign or borrow money on the contestant芒聙聶s behalf under section 405.5.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>2003, c. 19, s. 57<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>22.</B> Subsection 478.17(1) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Payment within four months<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>478.17</B> (1) A claim for nomination campaign expenses that has been sent in accordance with section 478.16, as well as a claim for repayment of a loan made to the nomination contestant under section 405.5, must be paid within four months after the selection date or, in the case referred to in subsection 478.23(7), the polling day.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>2003, c. 19, s. 57<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>23.</B> Subsection 478.19(1) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Irregular claims or payments 芒聙聰 Chief Electoral Officer<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>478.19</B> (1) On the written application of a person with a claim to be paid for a nomination campaign expense in relation to a nomination contestant or for a loan made to the contestant under section 405.5, or of the contestant芒聙聶s financial agent or the contestant in relation to such a claim, the Chief Electoral Officer may, on being satisfied that there are reasonable grounds for so doing, in writing authorize the payment, through the contestant芒聙聶s financial agent, of the amount claimed if</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>a</I>) in the case of an expense, the invoice or other document evidencing the claim was not sent in accordance with section 478.16 or the payment was not made in the four-month period referred to in subsection 478.17(1); and</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>b</I>) in the case of a loan, the repayment of the loan was not made in the four-month period referred to in subsection 478.17(1).</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>2003, c. 19, s. 57<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>24.</B> Section 478.2 of the Act is renumbered as subsection 478.2(1) and is amended by adding the following:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Irregular claims and payments 芒聙聰 judge<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(2) On the application of a person with a claim to be paid for a loan made to a nomination contestant under section 405.5 or on the application of the contestant芒聙聶s financial agent or the contestant, as the case may be, a judge who is competent to conduct a recount may, on being satisfied that there are reasonable grounds for so doing, by order authorize the payment, through the contestant芒聙聶s financial agent, of the amount claimed if</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>a</I>) the applicant establishes that an authorization under subsection 478.19(1) has been refused and that the payment has not been made in the four-month period referred to in subsection 478.17(1); or</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>b</I>) the amount claimed has not been paid in accordance with an authorization obtained under subsection 478.19(1) and the applicant establishes their inability to comply with the authorization for reasons beyond their control.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0">The applicant shall notify the Chief Electoral Officer that the application has been made.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>2003, c. 19, s. 57<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>25.</B> The portion of subsection 478.21(1) of the Act before paragraph (<I>a</I>) is replaced by the following:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Proceedings to recover payment<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>478.21</B> (1) A person who has sent a claim in accordance with section 478.16, or has sent a claim for repayment of a loan made to a nomination contestant under section 405.5, may commence proceedings in a court of competent jurisdiction to recover any unpaid amount</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>25.1</B> Subsection 478.22(1) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>478.22</B> (1) An unpaid claim mentioned in a return referred to in subsection 478.23(1) is deemed to be a contribution of the unpaid amount to the nomination contestant made as of the day on which the expense was incurred or the loan was made, as the case may be, if the claim remains unpaid in whole or in part </Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0" Bold="Yes">(<I>a</I>) 18 months after the selection date 芒聙聰 or in the case referred to in subsection 478.23(7), after the polling day 芒聙聰 in the case of a claim to be paid for a nomination contestant's nomination campaign expense; or</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0" Bold="Yes">(<I>b</I>) three years and one day after the selection date 芒聙聰 or in the case referred to in subsection 478.23(7), after the polling day 芒聙聰 in the case of a claim for a loan made to the nomination contestant under section 405.5.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>2003, c. 19, s. 57<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>26.</B> (1) Paragraph 478.23(2)(<I>c</I>) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>c</I>) a statement of unpaid claims 芒聙聰 including loans made to the nomination contestant under section 405.5 that remain unpaid in whole or in part 芒聙聰 that are, or may be, the subject of an application under section 478.19 or 478.2;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>c.1</I>) a statement of each loan made to the nomination contestant under section 405.5, including the amount of the loan, the interest rate, the lender芒聙聶s name and address, the dates and amounts of repayments of principal and payments of interest, the unpaid principal remaining at the end of each calendar year and, if there is a guarantor, the guarantor芒聙聶s name and address and the amount guaranteed;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>2003, c. 19, s. 57<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes">(2) Subsection 478.23(5) of the Act is repealed.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>27.</B> (1) Subsection 497(1) of the Act is amended by adding the following after paragraph (<I>i.7</I>):</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>i.8</I>) being a person or entity, contravenes subsection 405.5(1) or (2) (making a loan, guaranteeing a loan or borrowing money);</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>i.9</I>) being the chief agent of a registered party, the financial agent of a registered association, the official agent of a candidate or the financial agent of a leadership contestant or nomination contestant, contravenes subsection 405.6(1) or (3) (failure to report to the Chief Electoral Officer);</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>2003, c. 19, s. 58(6)<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes">(2) Paragraphs 497(1)(<I>t</I>) and (<I>u</I>) of the Act are replaced by the following:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>t</I>) being an official agent, contravenes subsection 445(1) or (1.1) (failure to pay recoverable claim or loan in timely manner);</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>u</I>) being an official agent, contravenes subsection 451(1), (2) or (4) (failure to provide electoral campaign return or related documents);</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes">(3) Subsection 497(3) of the Act is amended by adding the following after paragraph (<I>f.19</I>):</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>f.2</I>) being a person or entity, wilfully contravenes subsection 405.5(1) or (2) (making a loan, guaranteeing a loan or borrowing money);</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>f.21</I>) being the chief agent of a registered party, the financial agent of a registered association, the official agent of a candidate or the financial agent of a leadership contestant or nomination contestant, wilfully contravenes subsection 405.6(1) or (3) (failure to report to the Chief Electoral Officer);</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>2003, c. 19, s. 58(15)<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes">(4) Paragraph 497(3)(<I>r</I>) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>r</I>) being an official agent, wilfully contravenes subsection 451(1), (2) or (4) (failure to provide electoral campaign return or related documents);</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:TRANSITIONAL PROVISION--><Para TopMargin="10" Bold="Yes" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">TRANSITIONAL PROVISION</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Prior loans<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>28.</B> Loans made before the coming into force of this Act continue to be subject to the provisions of the <I>Canada Elections Act</I>, as they read immediately before the coming into force of this Act.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:COMING INTO FORCE--><Para TopMargin="10" Bold="Yes" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">COMING INTO FORCE</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Coming into force<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>29.</B> This Act comes into force six months after the day on which it is assented to unless, before then, the Chief Electoral Officer publishes a notice in the <I>Canada Gazette</I> that the necessary preparations for the bringing into operation of this Act have been made and that this Act may come into force accordingly, in which case it comes into force on the day on which the notice is published.</Para></Block><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="BPT_ImprintE">Published under authority of the Speaker of the House of Commons<br/>Available from:<br/>Publishing and Depository Services<br/>Public Works and Government Services Canada<br/>Ottawa, Ontario K1A 0S5<br/>Telephone: 613-941-5995 or 1-800-635-7943<br/>Fax: 613-954-5779 or 1-800-565-7757<br/>publications@tpsgc-pwgsc.gc.ca<br/>http://publications.gc.ca</Para></Block><Block Align="Yes" LineCnt="N"><Para NoLineBreak="Yes" NoHtml="Yes" Leading="0" Size="0" TopMargin="0" BottomMargin="0">脗聞</Para></Block></Bill_Part></Bill>
