<?xml version="1.0"?>
<Bill RHead_reign="56-57 Eliz. II" RHead_ParlYear="2007-2008" DocumentTitle="BILL C-293" Bill_No="C-293" Document_No="391338" xml:lang="EN" Bill_Type="Non-amending" Stage_Name="Assented-to" Reprint="No" xml:space="preserve" ChapterNo_E="C. 17" ChapterNo_F="ch. 17" Bill-Origin="commons"><Bill_Part Part_Type="Cover" CountLines="No"><Block><Para TopMargin="24" Size="9" Leading="10" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0" TextAlign="Center">Second Session, Thirty-ninth Parliament,</Para></Block><Block><Para Size="9" Leading="10" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0" TextAlign="Center">56-57 Elizabeth II, 2007-2008</Para></Block><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="COV@StatutesTitle">STATUTES OF CANADA 2008<br/>CHAPTER 17</Para></Block><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="CovLongTitle">An Act respecting the provision of official development assistance abroad</Para></Block><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="COV_StageLine"></Para></Block><Block><Para BottomMargin="14" Size="11" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0" Bold="Yes" TextAlign="Center">ASSENTED TO</Para></Block><Block><Para Size="8" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0" TextAlign="Center">29th MAY, 2008</Para></Block><Block><Para TopMargin="4" Size="8" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0" TextAlign="Center">BILL C-293</Para></Block><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="COV_StageLine"></Para></Block></Bill_Part><Bill_Part CountLines="No" Part_Type="InsideCover"><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="BPT_InsideCoverE">Also available on the Parliament of Canada Web Site at the following address:<br/><B>http://www.parl.gc.ca</B></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><Para TopMargin="108" BottomMargin="4" Size="10" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">SUMMARY</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" Size="8" Leading="9" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">This enactment sets out criteria respecting resource allocation to international development agencies and enhances transparency and monitoring of Canada芒聙聶s international development efforts.</Para></Block></Bill_Part><Bill_Part Part_Type="MainText" CountLines="No" RunningHead_E="Official Development Assistance Accountability"><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="MAIN@RoyalAssentTitle">56-57 ELIZABETH II</Para></Block><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="MAIN@RoyalAssentTitle">芒聙聰芒聙聰芒聙聰芒聙聰芒聙聰芒聙聰</Para></Block><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="MAIN@RoyalAssentTitle">CHAPTER 17</Para></Block><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="LongTitleAssent">An Act respecting the provision of official development assistance abroad</Para></Block><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="MAIN@RoyalAssentDate">[<I>Assented to 29th May, 2008</I>]</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">Her Majesty, by and with the advice and consent of the Senate and House of Commons of Canada, enacts as follows:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><Para TopMargin="10" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">SHORT TITLE</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Short title<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>1.</B> This Act may be cited as the <I>Official Development Assistance Accountability Act</I>.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><Para TopMargin="10" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">PURPOSE</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Purpose<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>2.</B> (1) The purpose of this Act is to ensure that all Canadian official development assist- ance abroad is provided with a central focus on poverty reduction and in a manner that is consistent with Canadian values, Canadian foreign policy, the principles of the Paris Declaration on Aid Effectiveness of March 2, 2005, sustainable development and democracy promotion and that promotes international human rights standards.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Official development assistance<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(2) Canadian official development assistance abroad shall be defined exclusively with regard to these values.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><Para TopMargin="10" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">INTERPRETATION</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Definitions<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>3.</B> The following definitions apply in this Act.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><MarginalNote>芒聙聹Canadian values芒聙聺<br/>脗芦 <I>valeurs canadiennes</I> 脗禄<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0">芒聙聹Canadian values芒聙聺 means, amongst others, values of global citizenship, equity and envi- ronmental sustainability.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><MarginalNote>芒聙聹civil society organization芒聙聺<br/>脗芦 <I>organisme de la soci脙漏t脙漏 civile</I> 脗禄<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0">芒聙聹civil society organization芒聙聺 means a not-for-profit or charitable organization whose governing structure is independent of government direction, and includes, but is not limited to, registered charities, non-governmental development organizations, community groups, wom- en芒聙聶s organizations, faith-based organizations, professional associations, trade unions, self-help groups, social movements, business associations, coalitions, human rights organizations and advocacy groups.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><MarginalNote>芒聙聹competent minister芒聙聺<br/>脗芦 <I>ministre comp脙漏tent</I> 脗禄<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0">芒聙聹competent minister芒聙聺 means the Minister of International Cooperation, the Minister of Finance, the Minister of Foreign Affairs or any other minister who is providing official development assistance.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><MarginalNote>芒聙聹democracy芒聙聺<br/>脗芦 <I>d脙漏mocratie</I> 脗禄<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0">芒聙聹democracy芒聙聺 includes, but is not limited to, political and civil rights as defined by the <I>International Covenant on Civil and Political Rights</I>. </Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><MarginalNote>芒聙聹international agency芒聙聺<br/>脗芦 <I>agence internationale</I> 脗禄<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0">芒聙聹international agency芒聙聺 means any organization whose objectives include global poverty reduction or international human脗颅itarian assistance.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><MarginalNote>芒聙聹international assistance芒聙聺<br/>脗芦 <I>aide internationale</I> 脗禄<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0">芒聙聹international assistance芒聙聺 means funding provided by government for international development, international financial institutions, global peace and security, crises overseas and international development research.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><MarginalNote>芒聙聹international human rights standards芒聙聺<br/>脗芦 <I>normes internationales en mati脙篓re de droits de la personne</I> 脗禄<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0">芒聙聹international human rights standards芒聙聺 means standards that are based on international human rights conventions to which Canada is a party and on international customary law.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><MarginalNote>芒聙聹Minister芒聙聺<br/>脗芦 <I>ministre</I> 脗禄<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0">芒聙聹Minister芒聙聺 means the Minister of International Cooperation or any other minister designated by the Governor in Council as the Minister for the purposes of this Act.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><MarginalNote>芒聙聹official development assistance芒聙聺<br/>脗芦 <I>aide au d脙漏veloppement officielle</I> 脗禄<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0">芒聙聹official development assistance芒聙聺 means international assistance</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>a</I>) that is administered with the principal objective of promoting the economic development and welfare of developing countries, that is concessional in character, that conveys a grant element of at least 25%, and that meets the requirements set out in section 4; or</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>b</I>) that is provided for the purpose of alleviating the effects of a natural or artificial disaster or other emergency occurring outside Canada.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><Para TopMargin="10" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center"> OFFICIAL DEVELOPMENT ASSISTANCE</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Official development assistance<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>4.</B> (1) Official development assistance may be provided only if the competent minister is of the opinion that it</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>a</I>) contributes to poverty reduction;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>b</I>) takes into account the perspectives of the poor; and</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>c</I>) is consistent with international human rights standards.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Disaster or other emergency occurring outside Canada<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(1.1) Notwithstanding subsection (1), official development assistance may be provided for the purposes of alleviating the effects of a natural or artificial disaster or other emergency occurring outside Canada.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Consultation<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(2) The competent minister shall consult with governments, international agencies and Canadian civil society organizations at least once every two years, and shall take their views and recommendations into consideration when forming an opinion described in subsection (1).</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Calculation of contribution<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(3) In calculating Canada芒聙聶s official development assistance contribution in Government of Canada publications, the competent minister or the Governor in Council shall consider only official development assistance as defined by this Act that meets the criteria in subsections (1) and (1.1).</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>No limit or restriction imposed<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(4) Nothing in this Act shall be construed so as to limit the funding or restrict the activities of the International Development Research Centre.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><Para TopMargin="10" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">REPORTS</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Report to Parliament<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>5.</B> (1) The Minister or the competent minister shall cause to be submitted to each House of  Parliament, within six months after the termination of each fiscal year or, if that House is not then sitting, on any of the first five days next thereafter that the House is sitting, a report containing</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>a</I>) the total amount spent by the Government of Canada on official development assistance in the previous fiscal year;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>b</I>) a summary of any activity or initiative taken under this Act;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>c</I>) a summary of the annual report submitted under the <I>Bretton Woods and Related Agreements Act</I>;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>d</I>) a summary of any representation made by Canadian representatives with respect to priorities and policies of the Bretton Woods Institutions; and</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>e</I>) a summary of the Departmental Perform脗颅ance Report of the Canadian International Development Agency.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Statistical report<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(2) The Minister shall issue a statistical report on the disbursement of official development assistance within one year after the end of each fiscal year.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Report to Parliament<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(3) The Minister of Finance shall, in addition to preparing the report required under section 13 of the <I>Bretton Woods and Related Agreements Act</I>, contribute the following to the report submitted to Parliament under subsection (1):</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>a</I>) the position taken by Canada on any resolution that is adopted by the Board of Governors of the Bretton Woods Institutions; and</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>b</I>) a summary of the manner in which Canada's activities under the <I>Bretton Woods and Related Agreements Act</I> have contributed to carrying out the purpose of this Act.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Information not to be disclosed<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(4) Despite subsections (1) and (3), information shall not be reported under this section if its disclosure is prohibited by the policies of the Bretton Woods Institutions.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:COMING INTO FORCE--><Para TopMargin="10" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">COMING INTO FORCE</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Coming into force<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>6.</B> This Act comes into force 30 days after the day on which it receives royal assent.</Para></Block><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="BPT_ImprintE">Published under authority of the Speaker of the House of Commons<br/>Available from:<br/>Publishing and Depository Services<br/>Public Works and Government Services Canada<br/>Ottawa, Ontario K1A 0S5<br/>Telephone: 613-941-5995 or 1-800-635-7943<br/>Fax: 613-954-5779 or 1-800-565-7757<br/>publications@tpsgc-pwgsc.gc.ca<br/>http://publications.gc.ca</Para></Block><Block Align="Yes" LineCnt="N"><Para NoLineBreak="Yes" NoHtml="Yes" Leading="0" Size="0" TopMargin="0" BottomMargin="0">脗聞</Para></Block></Bill_Part></Bill>
