<?xml version="1.0"?>
<Bill RHead_reign="55 Eliz. II" RHead_ParlYear="2006" DocumentTitle="BILL C-312" Bill_No="C-312" Document_No="391190" xml:lang="EN" Bill_Type="Non-amending" Stage_Name="First-Reading-House" Reprint="No" xml:space="preserve" ChapterNo_E="C. " ChapterNo_F="ch. " Bill-Origin="commons"><Bill_Part Part_Type="Cover" CountLines="No"><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="CovBillNo">C-312</Para></Block><Block><Para TopMargin="24" Size="9" Leading="10" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0" TextAlign="Center">First Session, Thirty-ninth Parliament,</Para></Block><Block><Para Size="9" Leading="10" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0" TextAlign="Center">55 Elizabeth II, 2006</Para></Block><Block><Para TopMargin="48" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0" Bold="Yes" TextAlign="Center">HOUSE OF COMMONS OF CANADA</Para></Block><Block><Para TopMargin="42" Size="18" Leading="20" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0" Bold="Yes" TextAlign="Center">BILL C-312</Para></Block><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="CovLongTitle">An Act to establish and maintain a national Breast Implant Registry</Para></Block><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="COV_StageLine"></Para></Block><Block><Para Size="9" AllCaps="Yes" Hyphenate="OFF">first reading, May 29, 2006</Para></Block><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="COV_StageLine"></Para></Block><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="Cov_StartBox"></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes"><Para Style="Cov_Box_Heading">NOTE</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes"><Para Style="Cov_Box_Para" TextAlign="Justify">        2nd Session, 39th Parliament</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes"><Para Style="Cov_Box_Para" TextAlign="Justify">This bill was introduced during the First Session of the 39th Parliament. Pursuant to the Standing Orders of the House of Commons, it is deemed to have been considered and approved at all stages completed at the time of prorogation of the First Session. The number of the bill remains unchanged.</Para></Block><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="Cov_EndBox"></Para></Block><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="Cover_Sponsors"><SC SC_PerCent="85">Ms. Wasylycia-Leis</SC></Para></Block><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="Cover_DocNo">391190</Para></Block></Bill_Part><Bill_Part CountLines="No" Part_Type="InsideCover"><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="BPT_InsideCoverE">Also available on the Parliament of Canada Web Site at the following address:<br/><B>http://www.parl.gc.ca</B></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><Para TopMargin="108" BottomMargin="4" Size="10" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">SUMMARY</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" Size="8" Leading="9" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">This enactment requires the Minister of Health to establish and maintain a national Breast Implant Registry. The Registry will contain information relating to persons who have undergone breast implant surgery, including surgery to explant a breast implant, along with a description of the implant and other prescribed information. The information in the Registry will be available only to the Registrar for the purpose of notifying those persons of a risk to their health.</Para></Block></Bill_Part><Bill_Part Part_Type="MainText" CountLines="Yes" RunningHead_E="Breast Implant Registry"><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="MainText_DocNo">391190</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes"><Para Style="Session_Reign">1st Session, 39th Parliament,</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes"><Para Style="Session_Reign">55 Elizabeth II, 2006</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes"><Para Style="MainBillOrigin">house of commons of canada</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes"><Para Bold="Yes" Style="MAIN@BillNo_Title">BILL C-312</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes"><Para Style="MAIN@ti;04">An Act to establish and maintain a national Breast Implant Registry</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">Her Majesty, by and with the advice and consent of the Senate and House of Commons of Canada, enacts as follows:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:SHORT TITLE--><Para TopMargin="10" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">SHORT TITLE</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Short title<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>1.</B> This Act may be cited as the <I>Breast Implant Registry Act</I>.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:INTERPRETATION--><Para TopMargin="10" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">INTERPRETATION</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Definitions<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>2.</B> The definitions in this section apply in this Act.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><MarginalNote>“medical practitioner”<br/>« <I>médecin</I> »<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0">“medical practitioner” means a person lawfully entitled to practise medicine in the place in which the practice is carried on by that person.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><MarginalNote>“prescribed”<br/><I>Version anglaise seulement</I><br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0">“prescribed” means prescribed by regulation.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><MarginalNote>“Registry”<br/>« <I>Registre</I> »<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0">“Registry” means the Breast Implant Registry established under subsection 4(1).</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><MarginalNote>“user”<br/>« <I>utilisateur</I> »<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0">“user” means a person who has had the breast implant implanted, whether or not it has been explanted.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:BREAST IMPLANT REGISTRY--><Para TopMargin="10" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">BREAST IMPLANT REGISTRY</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Registrar appointed<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>3.</B> The Minister of Health shall appoint a Registrar for the purposes of this Act.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Breast Implant Registry<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>4.</B> (1) The Registrar shall establish and maintain a registry, to be known as the Breast Implant Registry, containing</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>a</I>) information submitted by medical practitioners on persons who have undergone breast implant surgery, including surgery to explant a breast implant;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>b</I>) a record of information supplied by the manufacturer, importer or distributor of a breast implant that identifies any health risk to the user; and</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>c</I>) any other prescribed information.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Operation<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(2) The Registrar is responsible for the day-to-day operation of the Registry.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Destruction of information<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(3) The Registrar may destroy information kept in the Registry at the times and in the circumstances that may be prescribed.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Reporting by medical practitioners<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>5.</B> (1) A medical practitioner who performs breast implant surgery on a person, including surgery to explant a breast implant, shall as soon as possible after completing the surgery submit to the Registrar the following information:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>a</I>) the name, date of birth and address of the person who underwent the surgery;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>b</I>) the medical practitioner’s name, the date of the surgery and the name and address of the health care facility at which the surgery was performed;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>c</I>) in respect of each breast implant that was implanted or explanted,</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="4" FirstLineIndent="0">(i) the name and address of the manufacturer of the breast implant,</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="4" FirstLineIndent="0">(ii) the lot or serial number and the nomi- nal and actual volume of the breast  implant,</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="4" FirstLineIndent="0">(iii) the type of filler used in the breast implant, and</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="4" FirstLineIndent="0">(iv) whether the surgery was to the right or left breast;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>d</I>) in the case of an implant, the technique used for the implantation, the position of the breast implant, the type of incision and the indications for the implantation;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>e</I>) in the case of an explant, any intra-operative findings related to the breast implant and the indications for the explantation; and</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>f</I>) any other prescribed information.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Format of report<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(2) The information submitted under subsection (1) shall be in a format established by the Minister of Health.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Obligation to inform<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(3) The medical practitioner referred to in subsection (1) shall inform the person who is to undergo the surgery of the existence and purpose of the Registry, the requirement to submit information to the Registrar and the subsequent opportunity under section 6 to correct the personal information on file.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Change of address<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>6.</B> The Registrar shall, on receipt of the information submitted under subsection 5(1), provide the person in respect of whom the information is submitted, by notice in writing delivered personally or sent by registered mail, with a copy of the information and a statement advising the person to notify the Registrar of any change in the person’s permanent address.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Obligation of manufacturer, importer or distributor to report<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>7.</B> (1) A manufacturer, importer or distributor of a breast implant that has been sold shall notify the Registrar immediately after becoming aware that the implant may present a health risk to the user.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Information to be provided<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(2) The manufacturer, importer or distributor shall, as soon as possible after notifying the Registrar in accordance with subsection (1), provide the Registrar with the following:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>a</I>) information as to the nature of the health risk that has been identified in respect of the breast implant and the date on and circumstances under which the health risk or potential health risk was discovered;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>b</I>) an evaluation of the health risk associated with the breast implant;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>c</I>) a copy of any communication issued with respect to that risk; and</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>d</I>) any other prescribed information.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Obligation of Registrar to notify persons of risks to health<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>8.</B> (1) When the Registrar receives a notification under subsection 7(1), or otherwise has reasonable grounds to believe that a breast implant may pose a health risk to the user, the Registrar shall, without delay, contact each user listed in the Registry.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Information to be provided<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(2) When the Registrar contacts a person under subsection (1), the Registrar shall provide to the person any information that the Registrar considers necessary to assist the person in assessing the risk to their health.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:ELECTRONIC FILING--><Para TopMargin="10" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">ELECTRONIC FILING</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Electronic filing<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>9.</B> Subject to the regulations, information, notices and documents that are sent to or issued by the Registrar under this or any other Act of Parliament may be sent or issued in electronic or other form in any manner specified by the Registrar.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Records of Registrar<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>10.</B> Information that is required to be kept by the Registrar under subsection 4(1) may</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>a</I>) be in bound or loose-leaf form or in photographic film form; or</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>b</I>) be entered or recorded by any system of mechanical or electronic data processing or by any other information storage device that is capable of reproducing any required information in intelligible written or printed form within a reasonable time.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:PRIVACY AND DISCLOSURE OF INFORMATION--><Para TopMargin="10" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">PRIVACY AND DISCLOSURE OF INFORMATION</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Consent to disclosure<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>11.</B> Despite section 8 of the <I>Privacy Act</I> but subject to sections 12 to 14, information contained in the Registry respecting the identity, personal characteristics and medical history of a person who has undergone breast implant surgery, including surgery to explant a breast implant, is confidential and shall be disclosed only with the written consent of the person, which may not be given unless the person giving the consent has been informed of the purpose for which the consent is sought.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Obligation to disclose<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>12.</B> The Registrar shall disclose confidential information contained in the Registry</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>a</I>) for the purpose of complying with a subpoena or warrant issued or order made by a court, person or body with jurisdiction to compel the production of information, or for the purpose of complying with rules of court relating to the production of information; and</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>b</I>) to the extent required by provisions of any federal or provincial law respecting health and safety that are specified in the regulations.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Discretion to disclose<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>13.</B> (1) The Registrar may disclose confidential information contained in the Registry</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>a</I>) for the purposes of enforcing this Act;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>b</I>) to the extent required for the administration of a health care insurance plan within the meaning of the <I>Canada Health Act</I>; and</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>c</I>) for the purposes of disciplinary proceedings undertaken by any professional licensing or disciplinary body established under the laws of Canada or a province and specified in the regulations.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Research and statistics<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(2) The Registrar may disclose confidential information contained in the Registry to an individual or organization for scientific research or statistical purposes, other than information that identifies any person or information that can reasonably be expected to be used in the identification of any person.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Disclosure to address health risk<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>14.</B> The Registrar may disclose to a medical practitioner the identity of a person whose name is recorded in the Registry if, in the Registrar’s opinion, the disclosure is necessary to address a risk to the health of the person. The medical practitioner may not disclose that identity.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:OFFENCES--><Para TopMargin="10" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">OFFENCES</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Offence and punishment<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>15.</B> Every person who contravenes any provision of this Act is guilty of an offence and</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>a</I>) is liable, on conviction on indictment, to a fine not exceeding $250,000 or to imprisonment for a term not exceeding five years, or to both; or</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>b</I>) is liable, on summary conviction, to a fine not exceeding $100,000 or to imprisonment for a term not exceeding two years, or to both.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Court order<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>16.</B> A court that imposes a fine or term of imprisonment on a person in respect of an offence under this Act may, on application by the Attorney General of Canada, order the person not to engage in any activity that, in the court’s opinion, may lead to the commission of an offence under this Act.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Consent of Attorney General<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>17.</B> A prosecution for an offence under this Act may be instituted only with the consent of the Attorney General of Canada.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:REGULATIONS--><Para TopMargin="10" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">REGULATIONS</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Regulations<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>18.</B> The Governor in Council may make regulations for carrying out the purposes and provisions of this Act, including regulations</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>a</I>) for the purposes of paragraph 4(1)(<I>c</I>), specifying information to be contained in the Registry;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>b</I>) for the purposes of subsection 4(3), respecting the destruction of information kept in the Registry;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>c</I>) for the purposes of paragraph 5(1)(<I>f</I>), specifying information to be submitted by a medical practitioner;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>d</I>) for the purposes of paragraph 7(2)(<I>d</I>), respecting information to be provided by manufacturers, importers or distributors;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>e</I>) for the purposes of paragraph 12(<I>b</I>), specifying the provisions of any federal or provincial law;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>f</I>) for the purposes of paragraph 13(1)(<I>c</I>), identifying professional licensing and disciplinary bodies; and</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>g</I>) excluding any type of breast implant from the application of this Act if the Governor in Council is of the opinion that the exclusion is in the public interest and consistent with public health and safety.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:CONSEQUENTIAL AMENDMENTS--><Para TopMargin="10" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center"><B>CONSEQUENTIAL AMENDMENTS</B></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:Access to Information Act--><MarginalNote>R.S., c. A-1<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" SmallCaps="Yes" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center"><B>Access to Information Act</B></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>19.</B> Schedule I to the <I>Access to Information Act</I> is amended by adding the following in alphabetical order under the heading “<I>Other Government Institutions</I>”:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="-2" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify"><change> Registrar of the Breast Implant Registry</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="4" FirstLineIndent="-2" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify"><change><I>Directeur du Registre des implants     mammaires</I></change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>20.</B> Schedule II to the Act is amended by adding, in alphabetical order, a reference to</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="-2" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify"><change>Breast Implant Registry Act</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="4" FirstLineIndent="-2" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify"><change><I>Loi sur le Registre des implants mammaires</I></change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0" Bold="Yes">and a corresponding reference to “section 11”.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:Privacy Act--><MarginalNote>R.S., c. P-21<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="10" SmallCaps="Yes" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center"><B>Privacy Act</B></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>21.</B> The schedule to the <I>Privacy Act</I> is amended by adding the following in alphabetical order under the heading “<I>Other Government Institutions</I>”:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="-2" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify"><change> Registrar of the Breast Implant Registry</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="4" FirstLineIndent="-2" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify"><change><I>Directeur du Registre des implants mammaires</I></change></Para></Block><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="BPT_ImprintE">Published under authority of the Speaker of the House of Commons<br/>Available from:<br/>Publishing and Depository Services<br/>Public Works and Government Services Canada<br/>Ottawa, Ontario K1A 0S5<br/>Telephone: 613-941-5995 or 1-800-635-7943<br/>Fax: 613-954-5779 or 1-800-565-7757<br/>publications@tpsgc-pwgsc.gc.ca<br/>http://publications.gc.ca</Para></Block><Block Align="Yes" LineCnt="N"><Para NoLineBreak="Yes" NoHtml="Yes" Leading="0" Size="0" TopMargin="0" BottomMargin="0"></Para></Block></Bill_Part></Bill>
