<?xml version="1.0"?>
<Bill RHead_reign="55 Eliz. II" RHead_ParlYear="2006" DocumentTitle="BILL C-318" Bill_No="C-318" Document_No="391063" xml:lang="EN" Bill_Type="Non-amending" Stage_Name="First-Reading-House" Reprint="No" xml:space="preserve" ChapterNo_E="C. " ChapterNo_F="ch. " Bill-Origin="commons"><Bill_Part Part_Type="Cover" CountLines="No"><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="CovBillNo">C-318</Para></Block><Block><Para TopMargin="24" Size="9" Leading="10" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0" TextAlign="Center">First Session, Thirty-ninth Parliament,</Para></Block><Block><Para Size="9" Leading="10" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0" TextAlign="Center">55 Elizabeth II, 2006</Para></Block><Block><Para TopMargin="48" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0" Bold="Yes" TextAlign="Center">HOUSE OF COMMONS OF CANADA</Para></Block><Block><Para TopMargin="42" Size="18" Leading="20" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0" Bold="Yes" TextAlign="Center">BILL C-318</Para></Block><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="CovLongTitle">An Act to provide for a House of Commons committee to study proportional representation in federal elections</Para></Block><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="COV_StageLine"></Para></Block><Block><Para Size="9" AllCaps="Yes" Hyphenate="OFF">first reading, June 6, 2006</Para></Block><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="COV_StageLine"></Para></Block><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="Cov_StartBox"></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes"><Para Style="Cov_Box_Heading">NOTE</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes"><Para Style="Cov_Box_Para" TextAlign="Justify">        2nd Session, 39th Parliament</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes"><Para Style="Cov_Box_Para" TextAlign="Justify">This bill was introduced during the First Session of the 39th Parliament. Pursuant to the Standing Orders of the House of Commons, it is deemed to have been considered and approved at all stages completed at the time of prorogation of the First Session. The number of the bill remains unchanged.</Para></Block><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="Cov_EndBox"></Para></Block><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="Cover_Sponsors"><SC SC_PerCent="85">Mr. Martin</SC> (<I>Winnipeg Centre</I>)</Para></Block><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="Cover_DocNo">391063</Para></Block></Bill_Part><Bill_Part CountLines="No" Part_Type="InsideCover"><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="BPT_InsideCoverE">Also available on the Parliament of Canada Web Site at the following address:<br/><B>http://www.parl.gc.ca</B></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><Para TopMargin="108" BottomMargin="4" Size="10" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">SUMMARY</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" Size="8" Leading="9" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">The purpose of this enactment is to provide for the consideration of proportional representation in the House of <keep>Commons.  </keep>  A standing committee of the House will be designated to consider the matter and to report with recommendations after public hearings.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" Size="8" Leading="9" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">A referendum may be held and the question shall be whether electors favour replacing the present system with a system proposed by the Proportional Representation Committee as concurred in by the House.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" Size="8" Leading="9" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">The referendum must be held at the same time as the next general election.</Para></Block></Bill_Part><Bill_Part Part_Type="MainText" CountLines="Yes" RunningHead_E="Proportional Representation Review"><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="MainText_DocNo">391063</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes"><Para Style="Session_Reign">1st Session, 39th Parliament,</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes"><Para Style="Session_Reign">55 Elizabeth II, 2006</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes"><Para Style="MainBillOrigin">house of commons of canada</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes"><Para Bold="Yes" Style="MAIN@BillNo_Title">BILL C-318</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes"><Para Style="MAIN@ti;04">An Act to provide for a House of Commons committee to study proportional representation in federal elections</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">Her Majesty, by and with the advice and consent of the Senate and House of Commons of Canada, enacts as follows:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Short title<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>1.</B> This Act may be cited as the <I>Proportional Representation Review Act</I>.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Definitions<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>2.</B> The definitions in this section apply in this Act.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><MarginalNote>芒聙聹Minister芒聙聺<br/>脗芦 <I>ministre</I> 脗禄<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0">芒聙聹Minister芒聙聺 means the member of the Queen芒聙聶s Privy Council for Canada designated by the Governor in Council for the purposes of the <I>Canada Elections Act</I>.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><MarginalNote>芒聙聹proportional representation芒聙聺<br/>脗芦 <I>repr脙漏sentation proportionnelle</I> 脗禄<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0">芒聙聹proportional representation芒聙聺 means an election process that provides for the allocation of some of the seats in a legislative body or chamber to members democratically designated by parties so that the overall proportion of seats held in the body or chamber by each party approximates to the proportion of votes cast for the party on a national basis.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><MarginalNote>芒聙聹Proportional Representation Committee芒聙聺<br/>脗芦 <I>Comit脙漏 de la repr脙漏sentation proportionnelle</I> 脗禄<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0">芒聙聹Proportional Representation Committee芒聙聺 means the standing committee of the House of Commons designated under section 3.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Committee study<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>3.</B> Within 30 sitting days after the coming into force of this Act, the Minister shall, by a motion in the House of Commons, propose that a standing committee of the House, designated therein,</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>a</I>) conduct a process of public consultation on the question of whether the electoral process for membership of the House of Commons should include the principle of proportional representation; </Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>b</I>) conduct public hearings in every <keep>province</keep> and territory as part of the public consultation; </Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>c</I>) study election systems outside Canada that include an element of proportional representation; and </Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>d</I>)  report to the House of Commons with recommendations within 180 days of adoption of the motion by the House.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Draft question<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>4.</B> If the Proportional Representation Committee report provided for in paragraph 3(<I>d</I>) endorses an electoral system based on proportional representation, the Proportional Representation Committee shall include in its report a draft question to be put to the electors of Canada, in a referendum to be held in accordance with section 6, which asks whether the present system of electing members of the House of Commons should be replaced with a proportional representation system as set out in the question.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Information to public on recommendations
<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>5.</B> Upon concurrence by the House of Commons with the Proportional Representa-tion Committee芒聙聶s report and proposed referendum question, the Minister shall, within 30 sitting days after the concurrence, table in the House of Commons a detailed plan by which the government will inform electors of the report and the referendum question with sufficient information to allow electors to make an informed decision when voting in the referendum to be held in accordance with section 6.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Proclamation of referendum<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>6.</B> Where a referendum question is approved by the House of Commons, the Governor in Council shall, by proclamation issued in the manner provided for in section 3 of the <I>Referendum Act</I>, direct that the opinion of electors be obtained on the question, by putting the question to the electors of Canada at a referendum to be held on the date of the next general election of members of the House of Commons.</Para></Block><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="BPT_ImprintE">Published under authority of the Speaker of the House of Commons<br/>Available from:<br/>Publishing and Depository Services<br/>Public Works and Government Services Canada<br/>Ottawa, Ontario K1A 0S5<br/>Telephone: 613-941-5995 or 1-800-635-7943<br/>Fax: 613-954-5779 or 1-800-565-7757<br/>publications@tpsgc-pwgsc.gc.ca<br/>http://publications.gc.ca</Para></Block><Block Align="Yes" LineCnt="N"><Para NoLineBreak="Yes" NoHtml="Yes" Leading="0" Size="0" TopMargin="0" BottomMargin="0">脗聞</Para></Block></Bill_Part></Bill>
