<?xml version="1.0"?>
<Bill RHead_reign="55 Eliz. II" RHead_ParlYear="2006" DocumentTitle="BILL C-387" Bill_No="C-387" Document_No="391314" xml:lang="EN" Bill_Type="Non-amending" Stage_Name="First-Reading-House" Reprint="No" xml:space="preserve" ChapterNo_E="C. " ChapterNo_F="ch. " Bill-Origin="commons"><Bill_Part Part_Type="Cover" CountLines="No"><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="CovBillNo">C-387</Para></Block><Block><Para TopMargin="24" Size="9" Leading="10" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0" TextAlign="Center">First Session, Thirty-ninth Parliament,</Para></Block><Block><Para Size="9" Leading="10" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0" TextAlign="Center">55 Elizabeth II, 2006</Para></Block><Block><Para TopMargin="48" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0" Bold="Yes" TextAlign="Center">HOUSE OF COMMONS OF CANADA</Para></Block><Block><Para TopMargin="42" Size="18" Leading="20" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0" Bold="Yes" TextAlign="Center">BILL C-387</Para></Block><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="CovLongTitle">An Act respecting the National Ecosystems Council of Canada</Para></Block><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="COV_StageLine"></Para></Block><Block><Para Size="9" AllCaps="Yes" Hyphenate="OFF">first reading, November 27, 2006</Para></Block><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="COV_StageLine"></Para></Block><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="Cov_StartBox"></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes"><Para Style="Cov_Box_Heading">NOTE</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes"><Para Style="Cov_Box_Para" TextAlign="Justify">        2nd Session, 39th Parliament</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes"><Para Style="Cov_Box_Para" TextAlign="Justify">This bill was introduced during the First Session of the 39th Parliament. Pursuant to the Standing Orders of the House of Commons, it is deemed to have been considered and approved at all stages completed at the time of prorogation of the First Session. The number of the bill remains unchanged.</Para></Block><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="Cov_EndBox"></Para></Block><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="Cover_Sponsors"><SC SC_PerCent="85">Ms. Neville</SC></Para></Block><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="Cover_DocNo">391314</Para></Block></Bill_Part><Bill_Part CountLines="No" Part_Type="InsideCover"><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="BPT_InsideCoverE">Also available on the Parliament of Canada Web Site at the following address:<br/><B>http://www.parl.gc.ca</B></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><Para TopMargin="108" BottomMargin="4" Size="10" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">SUMMARY</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" Size="8" Leading="9" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">This enactment establishes a national council to study the sustainability of Canadian ecosystems and to implement measures to protect those ecosystems.</Para></Block></Bill_Part><Bill_Part Part_Type="MainText" CountLines="Yes" RunningHead_E="National Ecosystems Council of Canada"><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="MainText_DocNo">391314</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes"><Para Style="Session_Reign">1st Session, 39th Parliament,</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes"><Para Style="Session_Reign">55 Elizabeth II, 2006</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes"><Para Style="MainBillOrigin">house of commons of canada</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes"><Para Bold="Yes" Style="MAIN@BillNo_Title">BILL C-387</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes"><Para Style="MAIN@ti;04">An Act respecting the National Ecosystems Council of Canada</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><MarginalNote>Preamble<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">WHEREAS Parliament recognizes that the sustainability of many of Canada’s ecosystems is at risk and that it is of vital importance to the Canadian environment to preserve and protect those ecosystems;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">NOW, THEREFORE, Her Majesty, by and with the advice and consent of the Senate and House of Commons of Canada, enacts as follows:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:SHORT TITLE--><Para TopMargin="10" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">SHORT TITLE</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Short title<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>1.</B> This Act may be cited as the <I>National Ecosystems Council of Canada Act</I>.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:INTERPRETATION--><Para TopMargin="10" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">INTERPRETATION</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Definitions<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>2.</B> The following definitions apply in this Act.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><MarginalNote>“Council”<br/>« <I>Conseil</I> »<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0">“Council” means the National Ecosystems Council of Canada established by subsection 3(1).</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><MarginalNote>“Minister”<br/>« <I>ministre</I> »<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0">“Minister” means such member of the Queen's Privy Council for Canada as may be designated by the Governor in Council as the Minister for the purposes of this Act.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><MarginalNote>“President”<br/>« <I>président</I> »<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0">“President” means the President of the Council appointed under subsection 3(1).</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:ESTABLISHMENT OF COUNCIL--><Para TopMargin="10" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">ESTABLISHMENT OF COUNCIL</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Council established<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>3.</B> (1) There is hereby established a Council, to be called the National Ecosystems Council of Canada, consisting of a President and not more than twelve other members to be appointed by the Governor in Council.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Council incorporated<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(2) The Council is a body corporate that has power to acquire and hold real, personal, movable and immovable property for the purposes of and subject to this Act.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:DUTIES AND POWERS--><Para TopMargin="10" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">DUTIES AND POWERS</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Duties of Council <br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>4.</B> The Council has charge of such matters affecting Canadian ecosystems and related environmental matters as may be assigned to it by the Governor in Council.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Powers of Council<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>5.</B> Without limiting the general powers conferred on or vested in the Council by this Act, the Council may</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>a</I>) subject to the approval of the Governor in Council, make by-laws for the conduct of its business;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>b</I>) control and direct the work of the Council through the President;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>c</I>) undertake all necessary studies and make recommendations to the Government of Canada as to the measures that must be taken in order to</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="4" FirstLineIndent="0">(i) restore degraded and threatened areas in the Great Lakes and the St. Lawrence River and estuary,</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="4" FirstLineIndent="0">(ii) reopen closed shellfish harvesting areas in the Gulf of St. Lawrence through remediation of land-based sources of pollution,</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="4" FirstLineIndent="0">(iii) remediate the damage due to harmful pollutants and practices in the Areas of Concern identified under the Great Lakes Water Quality Agreement of 1978 concluded between Canada and the United States, as amended from time to time, including remediation of contaminated sediments in Hamilton Harbour,</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="4" FirstLineIndent="0">(iv) in the Toronto area, improve urban water quality, restore fish and wildlife populations and reopen contaminated <keep>beaches,</keep></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="4" FirstLineIndent="0">(v) help decontaminate and restore the health of the rivers that flow into the Great Lakes and the St. Lawrence River, </Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="4" FirstLineIndent="0">(vi) identify and remediate the environmental impact of those persistent toxic substances that have a widespread harmful effect on the environment,</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="4" FirstLineIndent="0">(vii) develop technology to allow municipal wastewater systems to treat and remove chemicals of concern,</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="4" FirstLineIndent="0">(viii) facilitate research to improve our understanding of the effect of key pollutants on Canadian ecosystems, the impact of toxic discharges and poor air quality on human health, the impact of climate change on our planet and the effects of environmental damage on biodiversity,</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="4" FirstLineIndent="0">(ix) integrate the monitoring of air quality, water quality and quantity, biodiversity and habitat to provide better information about the state of the Great Lakes and <keep>St. Lawrence</keep> ecosystem,</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="4" FirstLineIndent="0">(x) restore the health of Lake Winnipeg in partnership with those jurisdictions in Canada and the United States that comprise the Lake Winnipeg watershed, </Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="4" FirstLineIndent="0">(xi) make a valid assessment of the health of the Mackenzie River and Columbia River basins, in consultation with the governments of the affected First Nations peoples, British Columbia, the Northwest Territories, the affected municipalities and the affected states of the United States, and</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="4" FirstLineIndent="0">(xii) in collaboration with the Government of British Columbia, develop and implement a comprehensive water use and air quality plan for the Okanagan watershed.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:ORGANIZATION--><Para TopMargin="10" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">ORGANIZATION</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Tenure of office<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>6.</B> Each member of the Council, other than the President, shall be appointed to hold office for a term of not more than three years.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Appointment of President<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>7.</B> The President shall be appointed to hold office for such term, not exceeding five years, as the Governor in Council may determine.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Executive capacity of President<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>8.</B> The President is the chief executive officer of the Council and has supervision over and direction of the work of the Council and of the officers, technical and otherwise, appointed for the purpose of carrying on the work of the Council.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Acting President <br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>9.</B> If the President is absent or unable to act or if the office of President is vacant, the Minister may appoint, for a period not exceeding ninety days, an acting President who, while so acting, is a member of the Council and has all the powers of the President.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Re-appointment<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>10.</B> Any retiring President or other retiring member of the Council is eligible for re-appointment.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Salary and expenses of President<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>11.</B> (1) The President shall be paid such salary and expenses as are fixed by the Governor in Council.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Acting President's salary and expenses<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(2) An acting President shall be paid such salary and expenses as are fixed by the Governor in Council.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Travel and other expenses<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(3) The members of the Council, other than the President, shall serve without remuneration but each of those members is entitled to be paid reasonable travel and other expenses incurred while absent from their ordinary place of residence in the course of performing duties under this Act.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Remuneration for additional duties<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(4) Notwithstanding subsection (3), a member of the Council, other than the President, shall, for any period during which the member performs with the approval of the Council any duties on its behalf in addition to their ordinary duties, be paid such remuneration therefor as may be authorized by the Council.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Head office<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>12.</B> The head office of the Council shall be at such place in Canada as may be designated by the Governor in Council.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Meetings <br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>13.</B> The Council shall meet at least three times a year at such times and at such places in Canada as it considers necessary.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Executive committee<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>14.</B> (1) There is hereby established an executive committee of the Council consisting of the President and at least six other members to be selected by the Council.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Powers of executive committee<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(2) The executive committee of the Council may exercise the powers of the Council and shall submit, at each meeting of the Council, minutes of the proceedings of that committee since the last preceding meeting of the Council.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Agent of Her Majesty <br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>15.</B> (1) The Council is for all purposes of this Act an agent of Her Majesty and it may exercise its powers under this Act only as an agent of Her Majesty.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Proceedings by and against the Council <br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(2) Actions, suits or other legal proceedings in respect of any right or obligation acquired or incurred by the Council on behalf of Her Majesty, whether in its name or in the name of Her Majesty, may be brought or taken by or against the Council in the name of the Council in any court that would have jurisdiction if the Council were not an agent of Her Majesty.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:AUDIT--><Para TopMargin="10" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">AUDIT</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Audit relating to Council <br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>16.</B> All the receipts and expenditures of the Council are subject to examination and audit by the Auditor General of Canada.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:ANNUAL REPORT--><Para TopMargin="10" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">ANNUAL REPORT</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Annual report to Parliament<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>17.</B> The President shall, within four months after the termination of each fiscal year, transmit to the Minister a report on the operations of the Council in that fiscal year, the recommendations made by the Council to the Government of Canada in that fiscal year and the progress made by the Government of Canada in implementing recommendations of the Council during that fiscal year, and the Minister shall cause that report to be laid before Parliament within fifteen days after the receipt thereof or, if Parliament is not then sitting, on any of the first fifteen days next thereafter that either House of Parliament is sitting.</Para></Block><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="BPT_ImprintE">Published under authority of the Speaker of the House of Commons<br/>Available from:<br/>Publishing and Depository Services<br/>Public Works and Government Services Canada<br/>Ottawa, Ontario K1A 0S5<br/>Telephone: 613-941-5995 or 1-800-635-7943<br/>Fax: 613-954-5779 or 1-800-565-7757<br/>publications@tpsgc-pwgsc.gc.ca<br/>http://publications.gc.ca</Para></Block><Block Align="Yes" LineCnt="N"><Para NoLineBreak="Yes" NoHtml="Yes" Leading="0" Size="0" TopMargin="0" BottomMargin="0"></Para></Block></Bill_Part></Bill>
