<?xml version="1.0"?>
<Bill RHead_reign="56-57 Eliz. II" RHead_ParlYear="2007-2008" DocumentTitle="BILL C-474" Bill_No="C-474" Document_No="392039" xml:lang="EN" Bill_Type="Non-amending" Stage_Name="Assented-to" Reprint="No" xml:space="preserve" ChapterNo_E="C. 33" ChapterNo_F="ch. 33" Bill-Origin="commons"><Bill_Part Part_Type="Cover" CountLines="No"><Block><Para TopMargin="24" Size="9" Leading="10" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0" TextAlign="Center">Second Session, Thirty-ninth Parliament,</Para></Block><Block><Para Size="9" Leading="10" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0" TextAlign="Center">56-57 Elizabeth II, 2007-2008</Para></Block><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="COV@StatutesTitle">STATUTES OF CANADA 2008<br/>CHAPTER 33</Para></Block><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="CovLongTitle">An Act to require the development and implementation of a Federal Sustainable Development Strategy and the development of goals and targets with respect to sustainable development in Canada, and to make consequential amendments to <keep>another Act</keep></Para></Block><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="COV_StageLine"></Para></Block><Block><Para BottomMargin="14" Size="11" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0" Bold="Yes" TextAlign="Center">ASSENTED TO</Para></Block><Block><Para Size="8" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0" TextAlign="Center">26th JUNE, 2008</Para></Block><Block><Para TopMargin="4" Size="8" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0" TextAlign="Center">BILL C-474</Para></Block><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="COV_StageLine"></Para></Block></Bill_Part><Bill_Part CountLines="No" Part_Type="InsideCover"><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="BPT_InsideCoverE">Also available on the Parliament of Canada Web Site at the following address:<br/><B>http://www.parl.gc.ca</B></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><Para TopMargin="108" BottomMargin="4" Size="10" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">SUMMARY</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" Size="8" Leading="9" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">This enactment provides the legal framework for developing and implementing a Federal Sustainable Development Strategy that will make environmental decision-making more transparent and accountable to Parliament.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" Size="8" Leading="9" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">The enactment gives a committee of the Queen’s Privy Council for Canada responsibility for overseeing the development and implementation of the Federal Sustainable Development Strategy. It also provides for the creation of the Sustainable Development Office to develop and maintain systems and procedures to monitor progress on implementation of the Strategy and for the creation of the Sustainable Development Advisory Council to offer the Government of Canada advice on the Strategy.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" Size="8" Leading="9" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">It requires certain departments and agencies to develop and implement sustainable development strategies that contain objectives and action plans for each department and agency, that comply with the Federal Sustainable Development Strategy and that contribute to the attainment of the Strategy’s objectives.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" Size="8" Leading="9" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">It also amends the <I>Auditor General Act</I> to give the Commissioner the mission to monitor the progress that these departments and agencies make in implementing the Federal Sustainable Development Strategy and to assess the Sustainable Development Office’s report of the implementation of the Strategy. As well, it sets out the Commissioner’s powers and obligations.</Para></Block></Bill_Part><Bill_Part Part_Type="MainText" CountLines="No" RunningHead_E="Federal Sustainable Development"><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="MAIN@RoyalAssentTitle">56-57 ELIZABETH II</Para></Block><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="MAIN@RoyalAssentTitle">——————</Para></Block><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="MAIN@RoyalAssentTitle">CHAPTER 33</Para></Block><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="LongTitleAssent">An Act to require the development and implementation of a Federal Sustainable Development Strategy and the development of goals and targets with respect to sustainable development in Canada, and to make consequential amendments to <keep>another Act</keep></Para></Block><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="MAIN@RoyalAssentDate">[<I>Assented to 26th June, 2008</I>]</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">Her Majesty, by and with the advice and consent of the Senate and House of Commons of Canada, enacts as follows:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:SHORT TITLE--><Para TopMargin="10" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">SHORT TITLE</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Short title<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>1.</B> This Act may be cited as the <I>Federal Sustainable Development Act</I>.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:INTERPRETATION--><Para TopMargin="10" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">INTERPRETATION</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Definitions<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>2.</B> The following definitions apply in this Act.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><MarginalNote>“Commissioner”<br/>« <I>commissaire</I> »<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0">“Commissioner” means the Commissioner of the Environment and Sustainable Development appointed under subsection 15.1(1) of the <I>Auditor General Act</I>.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><MarginalNote>“Minister”<br/>« <I>ministre</I> »<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0">“Minister” means the Minister of the Environment. </Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><MarginalNote>“precautionary principle”<br/>« <I>principe de la prudence</I> »<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0">“precautionary principle” means the principle that where there are threats of serious or irreversible damage, lack of full scientific certainty shall not be used as a reason for postponing cost-effective measures to prevent environmental degradation.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><MarginalNote>“sustainability”<br/>« <I>durabilité</I> »<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0">“sustainability” means the capacity of a thing, action, activity, or process to be 
maintained indefinitely.
</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><MarginalNote>“sustainable development”<br/>« <I>développement durable</I> »<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0">“sustainable development” means development that meets the needs of the present without compromising the ability of future generations to meet their own needs.
</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><MarginalNote>“target”<br/>« <I>cible</I> »<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0">“target” means a measurable objective.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:PURPOSE--><Para TopMargin="10" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">PURPOSE</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Purpose<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>3.</B> The purpose of this Act is to provide the legal framework for developing and implementing a Federal Sustainable Development Strategy that will make environmental decision-making more transparent and accountable to Parliament.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:HER MAJESTY--><Para TopMargin="10" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">HER MAJESTY</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Application<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>4.</B> This Act and the regulations are binding on Her Majesty in right of Canada.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:BASIC PRINCIPLE--><Para TopMargin="10" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">BASIC PRINCIPLE</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Basic principle of sustainable development<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>5.</B> The Government of Canada accepts the basic principle that sustainable development is based on an ecologically efficient use of natural, social and economic resources and acknowledges the need to integrate environmental, economic and social factors in the making of all decisions by government.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:COMMITTEE--><Para TopMargin="10" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">COMMITTEE</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Committee on Sustainable Development<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>6.</B> A committee of the Queen’s Privy Council for Canada, consisting of a Chairperson and other members of the Queen’s Privy Council for Canada, shall have oversight of the development and implementation of the Federal Sustainable Development Strategy.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:OFFICE--><Para TopMargin="10" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">OFFICE</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Sustainable Development Office<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>7.</B> (1) The Minister shall establish a Sustainable Development Office within the Department of the Environment to develop and maintain systems and procedures to monitor progress on implementation of the Federal Sustainable Development Strategy.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Report<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(2) The Office shall, at least once every three years after the day on which this Act comes into force, provide the Minister with a report on the progress of the federal government in implementing the Federal Sustainable Development Strategy. The Minister shall cause the report to be laid before the House of Commons on any of the first 15 days on which that House is sitting after the Minister receives it.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:SUSTAINABLE DEVELOPMENT ADVISORY COUNCIL--><Para TopMargin="10" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">SUSTAINABLE DEVELOPMENT ADVISORY COUNCIL</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Sustainable Development Advisory Council<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>8.</B> (1)  The Minister shall appoint a Sustainable Development Advisory Council composed of one representative from each province and territory, and three representatives from each of the following:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>a</I>) Aboriginal peoples;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>b</I>) environmental non-governmental organizations;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>c</I>) organizations representative of business; and</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>d</I>) organizations representative of labour.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Chair<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(2) The Minister is the chair of the Sustainable Development Advisory Council.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Remuneration<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(3) The representatives appointed to the Sustainable Development Advisory Council shall hold office without remuneration and shall not be reimbursed for expenses incurred in the course of their duties.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:FEDERAL SUSTAINABLE DEVELOPMENT STRATEGY--><Para TopMargin="10" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">FEDERAL SUSTAINABLE DEVELOPMENT STRATEGY</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Preparation<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>9.</B> (1) Within two years after this Act comes into force and within every three-year period after that, the Minister shall develop, in accordance with this section, a Federal Sustainable Development Strategy based on the precautionary principle.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Content<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(2) The Federal Sustainable Development Strategy shall set out federal sustainable development goals and targets and an implementation strategy for meeting each target and identify the minister responsible for meeting each target.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Consultation: first draft<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(3)  The Minister shall submit a draft of the Federal Sustainable Development Strategy to the Sustainable Development Advisory Council, the standing committee of the House of Commons that normally considers matters relating to the environment or to any other committee that the House may designate for the purpose of this section and the public for review and comment, for which the Minister shall allow a period of not less than 120 days.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Consultation: first draft<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(4) The Minister shall at the same time submit the draft of the Federal Sustainable Development Strategy to the Commissioner for review and comment as to whether the targets and implementation strategies can be assessed, for which the Minister shall allow a period of not less than 120 days.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Submission to Governor in Council<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>10.</B> (1) The Minister shall, within the period referred to in subsection 9(1), submit the Federal Sustainable Development Strategy to the Governor in Council for approval as the official Federal Sustainable Development Strategy.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Tabling in each House of Parliament<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(2) The Minister shall table the official Federal Sustainable Development Strategy in each House of Parliament within the period referred to in subsection 9(1) or on any of the first 15 days thereafter on which that House is sitting.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Deemed referred to appropriate committee<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(3) A Federal Sustainable Development Strategy that is tabled in the House of Commons is deemed to be referred to the standing committee of the House that normally considers matters relating to the environment or to any other committee that the House may designate for the purposes of this section.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Sustainable development strategies of departments and agencies<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>11.</B> (1) Each Minister presiding over a department named in Schedule I to the <I>Financial Administration Act</I>, or an agency named in the schedule of this Act shall cause the department or agency to prepare a sustainable development strategy containing objectives and plans for the department or agency that complies with and contributes to the Federal Sustainable Development Strategy, appropriate to the department or agency's mandate and shall cause the strategy to be laid before the House of Commons within one year after the Federal Sustainable Development Strategy is tabled in that House under section 10.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Updating and tabling<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(2) A minister to whom subsection (1) applies shall cause the department's sustainable development strategy to be updated at least once every three years and shall cause each updated strategy to be laid before the House of Commons on any of the next 15 days on which that House is sitting after the strategy is updated.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Application to other departments and agencies<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(3) The Governor in Council may, on the recommendation of a minister presiding over a department not named in Schedule I to the <I>Financial Administration Act</I>, or agency not named in the schedule of this Act, direct that the requirements of subsections (1) and (2) apply in respect of the department or agency.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Regulations<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(4) The Governor in Council may, on the recommendation of the Minister, make regulations prescribing the form in which sustainable development strategies are to be prepared and the information required to be contained in them.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Performance-based contracts<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>12.</B> Performance-based contracts with the Government of Canada shall include provisions for meeting the applicable targets referred to in the Federal Sustainable Development Strategy and the Departmental Sustainable Development Strategies.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:REGULATIONS--><Para TopMargin="10" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">REGULATIONS</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Regulations<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>13.</B> The Governor in Council may make regulations for the purpose of achieving any of the goals of this Act.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:TRANSITIONAL PROVISION--><Para TopMargin="10" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center"><B>TRANSITIONAL PROVISION</B></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Directions<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>14.</B> <B>The directions made under subsection 24(3) of the <I>Auditor General Act</I>, as this subsection read immediately before the coming into force of section 18 of this Act, remain in force and are deemed to have been made under subsection 11(3) of this Act.</B></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:CONSEQUENTIAL AMENDMENTS--><Para TopMargin="10" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center"><B>CONSEQUENTIAL AMENDMENTS</B></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:Auditor General Act--><MarginalNote>R.S., c. A-17<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" Bold="Yes" SmallCaps="Yes" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">Auditor General Act</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B><B>15.</B></B> <B>(1)</B> <B>The definition “sustainable development strategy” in section 2 of the <I>Auditor General Act</I> is repealed.</B></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>(2)</B> <B>The definition “category I department” in section 2 of the Act is replaced by the following:</B></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><MarginalNote>“category I department”<br/>« <I>ministère de catégorie I</I> »<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0">“category I department” means</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>a</I>) any department named in schedule I to the <I>Financial Administration Act</I>;
</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>b</I>) any department in respect of which a direction has been made under subsection 11(3) of the <I>Federal Sustainable Development Act</I>; and</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>c</I>) any agency set out in the schedule to the <I>Federal Sustainable Development Act</I>.
</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>16.</B> The portion of section 21.1 of the Act before paragraph (<I>a</I>) is replaced by the following:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Purpose<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>
21.1</B> In addition to carrying out the functions referred to in subsections 23(3) and (4), the purpose of the Commissioner is to provide sustainable development monitoring and reporting on the progress of category I departments towards sustainable development, which is a continually evolving concept based on the integration of social, economic and environmental concerns, and which may be achieved by, among other things,</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>17.</B>  Section 23 of the Act is replaced by the following:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Duty to monitor<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>23.</B> (1) The Commissioner shall make any examinations and inquiries that the Commissioner considers necessary in order to monitor</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>a</I>) the extent to which category I departments have contributed to meeting the targets set out in the Federal Sustainable Development Strategy and have met the objectives, and implemented the plans, set out in their own sustainable development strategies laid before the House of Commons under section 11 of the <I>Federal Sustainable Development Act</I>; and</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>b</I>)  the replies by Ministers required by subsection 22(3).</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Commissioner's report<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(2) The Commissioner shall, on behalf of the Auditor General, report annually to the House of Commons concerning anything that the Commissioner considers should be brought to the attention of that House in relation to environmental and other aspects of sustainable development, including</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>a</I>) the extent to which category I departments have contributed to meeting the targets set out in the Federal Sustainable Development Strategy and have met the objectives, and implemented the plans, set out in their own sustainable development strategies laid before that House under section 11 of the <I>Federal Sustainable Development Act</I>;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>b</I>) the number of petitions recorded as required by subsection 22(1), the subject-matter of the petitions and their status; and</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>c</I>) the exercising of the authority of the Governor in Council under subsections 11(3) and (4) of the <I>Federal Sustainable Development Act</I>.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Duty to examine<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(3) The Commissioner shall examine the report required under subsection 7(2) of the <I>Federal Sustainable Development Act</I> in order to assess the fairness of the information contained in the report with respect to the progress of the federal government in implementing the Federal Sustainable Development Strategy and meeting its targets.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Duty to report<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(4) The Commissioner shall include in the report referred to in subsection (2) the results of any assessment conducted under subsection (3) since the last report was laid before the House of Commons under subsection (5).</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Submission and tabling of report<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(5) The report required by subsection (2) shall be submitted to the Speaker of the House of Commons and shall be laid before that House by the Speaker on any of the next 15 days on which that House is sitting after the Speaker receives it.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>18.</B>  Section 24 of the Act is repealed.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>19.</B>  The schedule to the Act is repealed.</Para></Block><Block Align="Yes" LineCnt="N"><Para NoLineBreak="Yes" NoHtml="Yes" Leading="0" Size="0" TopMargin="0" BottomMargin="0"></Para></Block></Bill_Part><Bill_Part Part_Type="Schedule" CountLines="No" RunningHead_E="Federal Sustainable Development — Schedule "><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><Para TopMargin="10" Size="9" Leading="10" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">SCHEDULE  </Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><Para Size="9" Leading="10" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0" Italic="Yes" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">(Subsection 11(1))</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" Size="9" Leading="10" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="-2" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">Atlantic Canada Opportunities Agency</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" Size="9" Leading="10" LeftMargin="4" FirstLineIndent="-2" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify"><I>Agence de promotion économique du Canada atlantique</I></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" Size="9" Leading="10" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="-2" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">Canada Border Services Agency</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" Size="9" Leading="10" LeftMargin="4" FirstLineIndent="-2" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify"><I>Agence des services frontaliers du Canada</I></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" Size="9" Leading="10" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="-2" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">Canada Revenue Agency
</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" Size="9" Leading="10" LeftMargin="4" FirstLineIndent="-2" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify"><I>Agence du revenu du Canada 
</I></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" Size="9" Leading="10" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="-2" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">Canadian International Development Agency</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" Size="9" Leading="10" LeftMargin="4" FirstLineIndent="-2" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify"><I>Agence canadienne de développement international 
</I></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" Size="9" Leading="10" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="-2" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">Economic Development Agency of Canada for the Regions of Quebec</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" Size="9" Leading="10" LeftMargin="4" FirstLineIndent="-2" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify"><I>Agence de développement économique du Canada pour les régions du Québec</I></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" Size="9" Leading="10" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="-2" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">Parks Canada Agency</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" Size="9" Leading="10" LeftMargin="4" FirstLineIndent="-2" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify"><I>Agence Parcs Canada</I></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" Size="9" Leading="10" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="-2" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">Public Health Agency of Canada</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" Size="9" Leading="10" LeftMargin="4" FirstLineIndent="-2" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify"><I>Agence de la santé publique du Canada</I></Para></Block><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="BPT_ImprintE">Published under authority of the Speaker of the House of Commons<br/>Available from:<br/>Publishing and Depository Services<br/>Public Works and Government Services Canada<br/>Ottawa, Ontario K1A 0S5<br/>Telephone: 613-941-5995 or 1-800-635-7943<br/>Fax: 613-954-5779 or 1-800-565-7757<br/>publications@tpsgc-pwgsc.gc.ca<br/>http://publications.gc.ca</Para></Block><Block Align="Yes" LineCnt="N"><Para NoLineBreak="Yes" NoHtml="Yes" Leading="0" Size="0" TopMargin="0" BottomMargin="0"></Para></Block></Bill_Part></Bill>
