<?xml version="1.0"?>
<Bill RHead_reign="56 Eliz. II" RHead_ParlYear="2007-2008" DocumentTitle="BILL C-500" Bill_No="C-500" Document_No="392001" xml:lang="EN" Bill_Type="Non-amending" Stage_Name="First-Reading-House" Reprint="No" xml:space="preserve" ChapterNo_E="C. " ChapterNo_F="ch. " Bill-Origin="commons"><Bill_Part Part_Type="Cover" CountLines="No"><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="CovBillNo">C-500</Para></Block><Block><Para TopMargin="24" Size="9" Leading="10" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0" TextAlign="Center">Second Session, Thirty-ninth Parliament,</Para></Block><Block><Para Size="9" Leading="10" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0" TextAlign="Center">56 Elizabeth II, 2007-2008</Para></Block><Block><Para TopMargin="48" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0" Bold="Yes" TextAlign="Center">HOUSE OF COMMONS OF CANADA</Para></Block><Block><Para TopMargin="42" Size="18" Leading="20" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0" Bold="Yes" TextAlign="Center">BILL C-500</Para></Block><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="CovLongTitle">An Act to amend the Criminal Code (trafficking and transplanting human organs and other body parts)</Para></Block><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="COV_StageLine"></Para></Block><Block><Para Size="9" AllCaps="Yes" Hyphenate="OFF">first reading, February 5, 2008</Para></Block><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="COV_StageLine"></Para></Block><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="Cover_Sponsors"><SC SC_PerCent="85">Mr. Wrzesnewskyj</SC></Para></Block><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="Cover_DocNo">392001</Para></Block></Bill_Part><Bill_Part CountLines="No" Part_Type="InsideCover"><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="BPT_InsideCoverE">Also available on the Parliament of Canada Web Site at the following address:<br/><B>http://www.parl.gc.ca</B></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><Para TopMargin="108" BottomMargin="4" Size="10" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">SUMMARY</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" Size="8" Leading="9" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">This enactment provides for the imposition of penal sanctions  for persons who, in Canada or outside Canada, are involved in the medical transplant of human organs or other body parts obtained or acquired as a consequence of a direct or indirect financial transaction or without the donor’s consent.</Para></Block></Bill_Part><Bill_Part Part_Type="MainText" CountLines="Yes" RunningHead_E="Criminal Code (trafficking and transplanting human organs and other body parts)"><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="MainText_DocNo">392001</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes"><Para Style="Session_Reign">2nd Session, 39th Parliament,</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes"><Para Style="Session_Reign">56 Elizabeth II, 2007-2008</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes"><Para Style="MainBillOrigin">house of commons of canada</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes"><Para Bold="Yes" Style="MAIN@BillNo_Title">BILL C-500</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes"><Para Style="MAIN@ti;04">An Act to amend the Criminal Code (trafficking and transplanting human organs and other body parts)</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">Her Majesty, by and with the advice and consent of the Senate and House of Commons of Canada, enacts as follows:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:CRIMINAL CODE--><MarginalNote>R.S., c. C-46<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="10" Bold="Yes" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">CRIMINAL CODE</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>1.</B> (1) Section 7 of the <I>Criminal Code</I> is amended by adding the following after subsection (4.1):</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Offence in relation to the purchase of human organs or other body parts<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><change>(4.11) Notwithstanding anything in this Act or any other Act, every one who, outside Canada, commits an act or omission that if committed in Canada would be an offence against section 240.1 shall be deemed to commit that act or omission in Canada if the person who commits the act or omission is a Canadian citizen or a permanent resident within the meaning of subsection 2(1) of the <I>Immigration and Refugee Protection Act</I>.</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes">(2) Subsection 7(4.3) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Consent of Attorney General<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(4.3) Proceedings with respect to an act or omission deemed to have been committed in Canada under subsection (4.1) <change>or (4.11)</change> may be instituted only with the consent of the Attorney General.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>2.</B> The Act is amended by adding the following after section 240:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:Human Organs and other Body Parts--><Para TopMargin="10" SmallCaps="Yes" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center"><change>Human Organs and other Body Parts</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Without donor’s consent<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><change><B>240.1</B> (1) Every one commits an offence who</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0"><change>(<I>a</I>) is the recipient of a human organ or other body part removed without the donor’s consent, and knew, at the time the organ or body part was transplanted or earlier, that the organ or other body part was removed without the donor’s consent;</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0"><change>(<I>b</I>) participates in or facilitates the removal of a human organ or other body part without the donor’s consent; or </change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0"><change>(<I>c</I>) knowingly acts on behalf of, at the direction of or in association with a person who removes a human organ or other body part without the donor’s consent or a person who purchases the organ or other body part.</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Financial transaction<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><change>(2) Every one commits an offence who</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0"><change>(<I>a</I>) obtains or acquires a human organ or other body part with the intention of having that organ or other body part transplanted into his or her body or the body of another person, and knew, at the time of the obtaining or acquisition or earlier, that the organ or other body part was obtained or acquired as a consequence of a direct or indirect financial transaction; or</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0"><change>(<I>b</I>) participates in or facilitates the obtaining or acquisition of a human organ or other body part, and knew, at the time of the obtaining or acquisition or earlier, that the organ or other body part was obtained or acquired as a consequence of a direct or indirect financial transaction.</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Without donor’s consent — negligence<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><change>(3) Every one commits an offence who is the recipient of a human organ or other body part removed without the donor’s consent, and ought to have known, at the time the organ or other body part was transplanted or earlier, that the organ or other body part was removed without the donor’s consent.</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Financial transaction —negligence<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><change>(4) Every one commits an offence who</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0"><change>(<I>a</I>) obtains or acquires a human organ or other body part with the intention of having that organ or other body part transplanted into his or her body or the body of another person, and ought to have known, at the time of the obtaining or acquisition or earlier, that the organ or other body part was obtained or acquired as a consequence of a direct or indirect financial transaction; or</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0"><change>(<I>b</I>) participates in or facilitates the obtaining or acquisition of a human organ or other body part, and ought to have known, at the time of the obtaining or acquisition or earlier, that the organ or other body part was obtained or acquired as a consequence of a direct or indirect financial transaction.</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Punishment<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><change>(5) Every one who commits an offence under any of subsections (1) to (4) is guilty of an indictable offence and liable to imprisonment for life and to a minimum punishment of imprisonment for a term of five years.</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Exception<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><change>(6) The punishment to be imposed shall be equal to or greater than the minimum punishment, unless the court that sentences the accused is satisfied that exceptional circumstances warrant the imposition of a punishment that is less than the prescribed minimum punishment. The court shall give reasons for its decision.</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Certificate<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><change>(7) Anyone who has a human organ or other body part transplanted into his or her body shall, at any time prior to the transplant but not later that 30 days after the transplant,</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0"><change>(<I>a</I>) obtain a certificate establishing that the organ or other body part was donated and that no money was paid for it; and</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0"><change>(<I>b</I>) provide that certificate to the Canadian entities designated by regulation.</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote><keep>Certificate</keep> <keep>— outside</keep> Canada<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><change>(8) Despite subsection (7), a Canadian citizen or a permanent resident within the meaning of subsection 2(1) of the <I>Immigration and Refugee Protection Act</I> who has a human organ or other body part transplanted into his or her body outside Canada shall, at any time prior to the transplant but not later that 30 days after the transplant, obtain a certificate establishing that the organ or other body part was donated and that no money was paid for it, and shall, prior to or upon his or her return to Canada, provide that certificate to the Canadian entities designated by regulation.</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Reporting<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><change>(9) Any medical practitioner or nurse duly qualified under the laws of a province to practice his or her profession shall report to the Canadian entities designated by regulation the identity of any person that the medical practitioner or nurse has examined in the course of his or her duties and that has had a human organ or other body part transplanted into his or her body.</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Regulations<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><change>(10) For the purposes of subsections (7) to (9), the Governor in Council shall, by regulation,</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0"><change>(<I>a</I>) establish a certification program;</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0"><change>(<I>b</I>) designate Canadian entities; and</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0"><change>(<I>c</I>) establish a registry for the purposes of keeping a record of every certificate provided to Canadian entities under subsection (7) or (8) and of every report made under subsection (9).</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Definition of “person”<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><change><B>240.2</B> (1) In this section, “person” means a person other than a Canadian citizen or a permanent resident within the meaning of subsection 2(1) of the <I>Immigration and Refugee Protection Act</I>. </change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Establishment of a list<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><change>(2) The Governor in Council shall establish a list on which the Governor in Council may place any person if, on the recommendation of the Attorney General of Canada, the Governor in Council is satisfied that there are reasonable grounds to believe that the person was involved in the transplant of a human organ or other body part obtained or acquired without the donor's consent or as a consequence of a financial transaction.</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Recommendation<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><change>(3) The Attorney General of Canada may make a recommendation referred to in subsection (2) only if he or she has reasonable grounds to believe that the person to whom the recommendation relates is a person referred to in subsection (2).</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><change>(4) The Attorney General of Canada shall take all reasonable measures to notify a person that the person has been placed on the list.</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Application to Attorney General<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><change>(5) On application in writing by a person placed on the list referred to in subsection (2), the Attorney General of Canada shall decide whether there are reasonable grounds to recommend to the Governor in Council that the applicant no longer be on the list.</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Deeming<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><change>(6) If the Attorney General of Canada does not make a decision on the application referred to in subsection (3) within 60 days after receipt of the application, he or she is deemed to have decided to recommend that the applicant remain on the list.</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Notice of decision to applicant<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><change>(7) The Attorney General of Canada shall give notice without delay to the applicant of any decision taken or deemed to have been taken respecting the application referred to in subsection (5).</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Judicial review<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><change>(8) Within 60 days after the receipt of the notice of the decision referred to in subsection (7), the applicant may apply to a judge of the Federal Court, for judicial review of the decision.</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Review of list<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><change>(9) Two years after the establishment of the list referred to in subsection (2), and every two years after that, the Attorney General of Canada shall review the list to determine whether there are still reasonable grounds, as set out in subsection (2), for a person to be on the list and make a recommendation to the Governor in Council as to whether the person should remain on the list. The review does not affect the validity of the list.</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Deletion from list<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><change>(10) The Governor in Council shall delete from the list the name of any person in respect of whom  the Attorney General of Canada has recommended that the person no longer be on the list.</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote><I>Statutory Instruments Act</I><br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><change>(11) The list referred to in subsection (2) is not a statutory instrument for the purposes of the <I>Statutory Instruments Act</I>.</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:COMING INTO FORCE--><Para TopMargin="10" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center"><B>COMING INTO FORCE</B></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Coming into force<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>3.</B> Subsections 240.1(7) to (10) of the <I>Criminal Code</I>, as enacted by section 2 of this Act, come into force on the day that is one year after the day on which this Act receives royal assent.</Para></Block><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="BPT_ImprintE">Published under authority of the Speaker of the House of Commons<br/>Available from:<br/>Publishing and Depository Services<br/>Public Works and Government Services Canada<br/>Ottawa, Ontario K1A 0S5<br/>Telephone: 613-941-5995 or 1-800-635-7943<br/>Fax: 613-954-5779 or 1-800-565-7757<br/>publications@tpsgc-pwgsc.gc.ca<br/>http://publications.gc.ca</Para></Block><Block Align="Yes" LineCnt="N"><Para NoLineBreak="Yes" NoHtml="Yes" Leading="0" Size="0" TopMargin="0" BottomMargin="0"></Para></Block></Bill_Part></Bill>
