<?xml version="1.0"?>
<Bill RHead_reign="56 Eliz. II" RHead_ParlYear="2007" DocumentTitle="BILL S-202" Bill_No="S-202" Document_No="0610" xml:lang="EN" Bill_Type="Amending" Stage_Name="First-Reading-Senate" Reprint="No" xml:space="preserve" ChapterNo_E="C. " ChapterNo_F="ch. " Bill-Origin="senate"><Bill_Part Part_Type="Cover" CountLines="No"><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="CovBillNo">S-202</Para></Block><Block><Para TopMargin="24" Size="9" Leading="10" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0" TextAlign="Center">Second Session, Thirty-ninth Parliament,</Para></Block><Block><Para Size="9" Leading="10" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0" TextAlign="Center">56 Elizabeth II, 2007</Para></Block><Block><Para TopMargin="48" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0" Bold="Yes" TextAlign="Center">SENATE OF CANADA</Para></Block><Block><Para TopMargin="42" Size="18" Leading="20" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0" Bold="Yes" TextAlign="Center">BILL S-202</Para></Block><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="CovLongTitle">An Act to amend certain Acts to provide job protection for members of the reserve force</Para></Block><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="COV_StageLine"></Para></Block><Block><Para Size="9" AllCaps="Yes" Hyphenate="OFF">first reading, October 17, 2007</Para></Block><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="COV_StageLine"></Para></Block><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="Cover_Sponsors">THE HONOURABLE SENATOR SEGAL</Para></Block><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="Cover_DocNo">0610</Para></Block></Bill_Part><Bill_Part CountLines="No" Part_Type="InsideCover"><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="BPT_InsideCoverE">Available on the Parliament of Canada Web Site at the following address:<br/><B>http://www.parl.gc.ca</B></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><Para TopMargin="108" BottomMargin="4" Size="10" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">SUMMARY</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" Size="8" Leading="9" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">This enactment amends certain Acts to provide a right to a twelve-month leave of absence from and subsequent reinstatement in civil employment under federal jurisdiction for members of the Canadian Forces Reserve if those members are called to or volunteer for active military duty.  It also provides extended protection for any members who are injured during the course of their service.</Para></Block></Bill_Part><Bill_Part Part_Type="MainText" CountLines="Yes" RunningHead_E="Job Protection for Reservists"><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="MainText_DocNo">0610</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes"><Para Style="Session_Reign">2nd Session, 39th Parliament,</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes"><Para Style="Session_Reign">56 Elizabeth II, 2007</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes"><Para Style="MainBillOrigin">senate of canada</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes"><Para Bold="Yes" Style="MAIN@BillNo_Title">BILL S-202</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes"><Para Style="MAIN@ti;04">An Act to amend certain Acts to provide job protection for members of the reserve force</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">Her Majesty, by and with the advice and consent of the Senate and House of Commons of Canada, enacts as follows:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:CANADA LABOUR CODE--><MarginalNote>R.S., c. L–2<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="10" Bold="Yes" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">CANADA LABOUR CODE</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>1.</B> The <I>Canada Labour Code</I> is amended by adding the following after section 203:</Para><ExplNote><Para Align="Yes" TopMargin="10" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0" Italic="Yes" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">Canada Labour Code</Para><Para Align="Yes" TopMargin="10" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><I>Clause 1</I>: New.</Para></ExplNote></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:DIVISION VI.1--><Para TopMargin="10" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center"><change>DIVISION VI.1</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:LEAVE FOR RESERVISTS--><Para TopMargin="5" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center"><change>LEAVE FOR RESERVISTS</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Definition of “reserve force”<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><change><B>203.01</B> In this Division, “reserve force” means the component of the Canadian Forces that is referred to in subsection 15(3) of the <I>National Defence Act</I>.</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Entitlement to leave<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><change><B>203.02</B> An employee who is an officer or non-commissioned member of the reserve force who is called out on service or volunteers for active service, and who has completed six consecutive months of continuous employment with an employer, is entitled to and shall be granted a leave of absence from employment during the period of that service, up to a maximum period of twelve months.</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Notification to employer<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><change><B>203.03</B> (1) Every employee who intends to take a leave of absence from employment under this Division shall</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0"><change>(<I>a</I>) give at least four weeks notice in writing to the employer unless there is a valid reason why that notice cannot be given; and</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0"><change>(<I>b</I>) inform the employer in writing of the length of leave intended to be taken.</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Notice of change in length of leave<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><change>(2) Every employee who intends to take or who is on a leave of absence from employment under this Division shall give at least four weeks notice in writing to the employer of any change in the length of leave intended to be taken, unless there is a valid reason why that notice cannot be given.</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Resumption of employment in same position<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><change><B>203.04</B> (1) Every employee who takes a leave of absence from employment under this Division is entitled to be reinstated in the position that the employee occupied when the leave of absence from employment commenced, and every employer of such an employee shall, on the expiration of any such leave, reinstate the employee in that position.</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Comparable position<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><change>(2) Where for any valid reason an employer cannot reinstate an employee in the position referred to in subsection (1), the employer shall reinstate the employee in a comparable position with the same wages and benefits and in the same location.</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Wages and benefits affected by reorganization<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><change>(3) Where an employee takes leave under this Division and, during the period of that leave, the wages and benefits of the group of employees of which that employee is a member are changed as part of a plan to reorganize the industrial establishment in which that group is employed, that employee is entitled, on being reinstated in employment under this section, to receive the wages and benefits in respect of that employment that that employee would have been entitled to receive had that employee been working when the reorganization took place.</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Notice of changes in wages and benefits<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><change>(4) The employer of every employee who is on a leave of absence from employment under this Division and whose wages and benefits would be changed as a result of a reorganization referred to in subsection (3) shall notify the employee in writing of that change as soon as possible.</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Right to benefits<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><change><B>203.05</B> (1) The pension, health and disability benefits and the seniority of any employee who takes a leave of absence from employment under this Division shall accumulate during the entire period of the leave.</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Contributions by employee<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><change>(2) Where contributions are required from an employee in order for the employee to be entitled to a benefit referred to in subsection (1), the employee is responsible for and must, within a reasonable time, pay those contributions for the period of any leave of absence under this Division unless, before taking leave or within a reasonable time thereafter, the employee notifies the employer of the employee’s intention to discontinue contributions during that period.</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Contributions by employer<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><change>(3) An employer who pays contributions in respect of a benefit referred to in subsection (1) shall continue to pay those contributions during an employee’s leave of absence under this Division in at least the same proportion as if the employee were not on leave unless the employee does not pay the employee’s contributions, if any, within a reasonable time.</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Failure to pay contributions<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><change>(4) For the purposes of calculating the pension, health and disability benefits of an employee in respect of whom contributions have not been paid as required by subsections (2) and (3), the benefits shall not accumulate during the leave of absence and employment on the employee’s return to work shall be deemed to be continuous with employment before the employee’s absence.</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Deemed continuous employment<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><change>(5) For the purposes of calculating benefits of an employee who takes a leave of absence from employment under this Division, other than benefits referred to in subsection (1), employment on the employee’s return to work shall be deemed to be continuous with employment before the employee’s absence.</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Hospitalization or incapacity<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><change><B>203.06</B> (1) If, immediately following the employee’s service as an officer or non-commissioned member of the reserve force, the employee is hospitalized or is physically or mentally incapable of performing the duties of the position to which the employee would have been entitled on reinstatement, the period of hospitalization or incapacity is deemed for the purposes of this Division to be part of the period of the employee’s service as an officer or non-commissioned member of the reserve force.</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>No maximum period for hospitalization or incapacity<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><change>(2) The twelve-month maximum referred to in section 203.02 does not apply to any period of hospitalization or incapacity that is deemed to be part of the period of the employee’s service by virtue of subsection (1).</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Prohibition<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><change><B>203.07</B> No employer shall dismiss, suspend, lay off, demote or discipline an employee because the employee has applied for leave of absence in accordance with this Division or take into account the intention of an employee to take leave of absence from employment under this Division in any decision to promote or train the employee.</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Prohibition<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><change><B>203.08</B> During the one-year period following an employee’s reinstatement under this Division,</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0"><change>(<I>a</I>) the employer shall not terminate the employee’s employment without reasonable cause; and</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0"><change>(<I>b</I>) if the employer terminates the employee’s employment, the onus is on the employer to establish that the employer had reasonable cause.</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Regulations<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><change><B>203.09</B> The Governor in Council may make regulations</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0"><change>(<I>a</I>) specifying the absences from employment that shall be deemed not to have interrupted continuous employment referred to in section 203.02, for the purposes of this Division; and</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0"><change>(<I>b</I>) specifying what does not constitute a valid reason for not reinstating an employee in the position referred to in subsection 203.04(2).</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Application of section 189<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><change><B>203.1</B> Section 189 applies for the purposes of this Division.</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Inconsistency with <I>National Defence Act</I><br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><change><B>203.11</B> Despite section 285.12 of the <I>National Defence Act</I>, in the event of any inconsistency between the provisions of this Division, or regulations made under it, and the provisions of Part VII of the <I>National Defence Act</I> or regulations made for the purposes of that Part, the provisions that are most favourable in respect of the employee’s rights and benefits prevail to the extent of the inconsistency.</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:PUBLIC SERVICE LABOUR RELATIONS ACT--><MarginalNote>2003, c. 22, s. 2<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="10" Bold="Yes" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">PUBLIC SERVICE LABOUR RELATIONS ACT</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>2.</B> The portion of the definition “public service” in subsection 2(1) of <I>Public Service Labour Relations Act</I> before paragraph (<I>a</I>) is replaced by the following:</Para><ExplNote><Para Align="Yes" TopMargin="10" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0" Italic="Yes" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">Public Service Labour Relations Act</Para><Para Align="Yes" TopMargin="10" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><I>Clause 2</I>: Relevant portion of definition:</Para><Para Align="Yes" TopMargin="5" Size="8" Leading="9" LeftMargin="0">“public service”, except in Part 3, means the several positions in or under</Para></ExplNote></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>“public service”<br/>« <I>fonction publique</I> »<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0">“public service”, except in <change>Parts 3 and 3.1</change>, means the several positions in or under</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>3.</B> The Act is amended by adding the following after section 240:</Para><ExplNote><Para Align="Yes" TopMargin="10" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><I>Clause 3</I>: New.</Para></ExplNote></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:PART 3.1--><Para TopMargin="10" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center"><change>PART 3.1</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:EMPLOYMENT PROTECTION FOR RESERVISTS--><Para TopMargin="5" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center"><change>EMPLOYMENT PROTECTION FOR RESERVISTS</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:Interpretation--><Para TopMargin="5" Italic="Yes" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center"><change>Interpretation</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Meaning of “public service”<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><change><B>240.1</B> In this Part, “public service” has the same meaning as in subsection 11(1) of the <I>Financial Administration Act</I>.</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:Division VI.1 of Part III of Canada Labour Code--><Para TopMargin="10" Italic="Yes" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center"><change>Division VI.1 of Part III of Canada Labour Code</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Application to public service<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><change><B>240.2</B> Division VI.1 of Part III of the <I>Canada Labour Code</I> applies to and in respect of the public service and persons employed in it as if the public service were a federal work, undertaking or business referred to in that Part except that, for the purpose of that application, “employee” is to be read as a reference to a person employed in the public service.</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:DEPARTMENT OF PUBLIC WORKS AND GOVERNMENT SERVICES ACT--><MarginalNote>1996, c. 16<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="10" Bold="Yes" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">DEPARTMENT OF PUBLIC WORKS AND GOVERNMENT SERVICES ACT</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>4.</B> The <I>Department of Public Works and Government Services Act</I> is amended by adding the following after section 22:</Para><ExplNote><Para Align="Yes" TopMargin="10" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0" Italic="Yes" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">Department of Public Works and Government Services Act</Para><Para Align="Yes" TopMargin="10" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><I>Clause 4</I>: New.</Para></ExplNote></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Definition of “reserve force”<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><change><B>22.1</B> (1) In this section, “reserve force” means the component of the Canadian Forces that is referred to in subsection 15(3) of the <I>National Defence Act</I>.</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Clause in all supply contracts<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><change>(2) In every contract for the supply of goods or services entered into under section 20, there shall be inserted an express condition that the supplier of the goods or services under the contract shall grant a leave of absence, on the terms and conditions set out in Division VI.1 of Part III of the <I>Canada Labour Code</I>, to any of its employees who is an officer or non-commissioned member of the reserve force and, for that purpose, “employee” in Division VI.1 is to be read as a reference to a person employed by the supplier.</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:COMING INTO FORCE--><Para TopMargin="10" Bold="Yes" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">COMING INTO FORCE</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Coming into force<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>5.</B> The provisions of this Act come into force one year after the day on which the Act receives royal assent or on any earlier day or days that may be fixed by order of the Governor in Council.</Para></Block><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="BPT_ImprintE"><br/><br/>Published under authority of the Senate of Canada</Para></Block><Block Align="Yes" LineCnt="N"><Para NoLineBreak="Yes" NoHtml="Yes" Leading="0" Size="0" TopMargin="0" BottomMargin="0"></Para></Block></Bill_Part></Bill>
