<?xml version="1.0"?>
<Bill RHead_reign="56-57 Eliz. II" RHead_ParlYear="2007-2008" DocumentTitle="BILL S-243" Bill_No="S-243" Document_No="0805" xml:lang="EN" Bill_Type="Amending" Stage_Name="First-Reading-Senate" Reprint="No" xml:space="preserve" ChapterNo_E="C. " ChapterNo_F="ch. " Bill-Origin="senate"><Bill_Part Part_Type="Cover" CountLines="No"><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="CovBillNo">S-243</Para></Block><Block><Para TopMargin="24" Size="9" Leading="10" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0" TextAlign="Center">Second Session, Thirty-ninth Parliament,</Para></Block><Block><Para Size="9" Leading="10" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0" TextAlign="Center">56-57 Elizabeth II, 2007-2008</Para></Block><Block><Para TopMargin="48" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0" Bold="Yes" TextAlign="Center">SENATE OF CANADA</Para></Block><Block><Para TopMargin="42" Size="18" Leading="20" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0" Bold="Yes" TextAlign="Center">BILL S-243</Para></Block><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="CovLongTitle">An Act respecting the office of the Commissioner of the Environment  and Sustainable Development</Para></Block><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="COV_StageLine"></Para></Block><Block><Para Size="9" AllCaps="Yes" Hyphenate="OFF">first reading, June 26, 2008</Para></Block><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="COV_StageLine"></Para></Block><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="Cover_Sponsors">THE HONOURABLE SENATOR McCOY</Para></Block><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="Cover_DocNo">0805</Para></Block></Bill_Part><Bill_Part CountLines="No" Part_Type="InsideCover"><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="BPT_InsideCoverE">Available on the Parliament of Canada Web Site at the following address:<br/><B>http://www.parl.gc.ca</B></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><Para TopMargin="108" BottomMargin="4" Size="10" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">SUMMARY</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" Size="8" Leading="9" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">This enactment establishes an independent Commissioner of the Environment and Sustainable Development who is directly accountable to both Houses of Parliament. It also makes related and consequential amendments to other Acts.</Para></Block></Bill_Part><Bill_Part Part_Type="MainText" CountLines="Yes" RunningHead_E="Commissioner of the Environment and Sustainable Development"><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="MainText_DocNo">0805</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes"><Para Style="Session_Reign">2nd Session, 39th Parliament,</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes"><Para Style="Session_Reign">56-57 Elizabeth II, 2007-2008</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes"><Para Style="MainBillOrigin">senate of canada</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes"><Para Bold="Yes" Style="MAIN@BillNo_Title">BILL S-243</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes"><Para Style="MAIN@ti;04">An Act respecting the office of the Commissioner of the Environment  and Sustainable Development</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">Her Majesty, by and with the advice and consent of the Senate and House of Commons of Canada, enacts as follows:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:SHORT TITLE--><Para TopMargin="10" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">SHORT TITLE</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Short title<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>1.</B> This Act may be cited as the <I>Commissioner of the Environment and Sustainable Development Act</I>.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:INTERPRETATION--><Para TopMargin="10" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">INTERPRETATION</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Definitions<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>2.</B> (1) The following definitions apply in this Act.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><MarginalNote>ГўВҖВңappropriate MinisterГўВҖВқ<br/>ГӮВ« <I>ministre compГғВ©tent</I> ГӮВ»<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0">ГўВҖВңappropriate MinisterГўВҖВқ has the meaning assigned by section 2 of the <I>Financial Administration Act</I>.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><MarginalNote>ГўВҖВңcategory I departmentГўВҖВқ<br/>ГӮВ« <I>ministГғВЁre de catГғВ©gorie I</I> ГӮВ»<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0">ГўВҖВңcategory I departmentГўВҖВқ means</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>a</I>) any department named in Schedule I to the <I>Financial Administration Act</I>;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>b</I>) any department in respect of which a direction has been made under subsection 10(3); and</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>c</I>) any department set out in the schedule.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><MarginalNote>ГўВҖВңCommissionerГўВҖВқ<br/>ГӮВ« <I>commissaire</I> ГӮВ»<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0">ГўВҖВңCommissionerГўВҖВқ means the Commissioner of the Environment and Sustainable Development appointed under subsection 3(1).</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><MarginalNote>ГўВҖВңdepartmentГўВҖВқ<br/>ГӮВ« <I>ministГғВЁre</I> ГӮВ»<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0">ГўВҖВңdepartmentГўВҖВқ has the meaning assigned by section 2 of the <I>Financial Administration Act</I>.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><MarginalNote>ГўВҖВңsustainable developmentГўВҖВқ<br/>ГӮВ« <I>dГғВ©veloppement durable</I> ГӮВ»<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0">ГўВҖВңsustainable developmentГўВҖВқ means development that meets the needs of the present without compromising the ability of future generations to meet their own needs.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><MarginalNote>ГўВҖВңsustainable development strategyГўВҖВқ<br/>ГӮВ« <I>stratГғВ©gie de dГғВ©veloppement durable</I> ГӮВ»<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0">ГўВҖВңsustainable development strategyГўВҖВқ, with respect to a category I department, means the departmentГўВҖВҷs objectives, and plans of action, to further sustainable development.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Clarification ГўВҖВ” sustainable development<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(2) In interpreting the expression ГўВҖВңsustainable developmentГўВҖВқ for the purposes of this Act, regard shall be had to the principle that sustainable development is a continually evolving concept based on the integration of social, economic and environmental concerns, which may be achieved by, among other things,</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>a</I>) the integration of the environment and the economy;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>b</I>) protecting the health of Canadians;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>c</I>) protecting ecosystems;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>d</I>) meeting international obligations;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>e</I>) promoting equity;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>f</I>) an integrated approach to planning and making decisions that takes into account the environmental and natural resource costs of different economic options and the economic costs of different environmental and natural resource options;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>g</I>) preventing pollution; and</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>h</I>) respect for nature and the needs of future generations.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:COMMISSIONER OF THE ENVIRONMENT AND SUSTAINABLE DEVELOPMENT--><Para TopMargin="10" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">COMMISSIONER OF THE ENVIRONMENT AND SUSTAINABLE DEVELOPMENT</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Appointment<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>3.</B> (1) The Governor in Council shall, by commission under the Great Seal, appoint a Commissioner of the Environment and Sustainable Development after consultation with the leader of every recognized party in the Senate and House of Commons and approval of the appointment by resolution of the Senate and House of Commons.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Tenure<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(2) The Commissioner holds office during good behaviour for a term of 10 years but may be removed for cause by the Governor in Council on address of the Senate and House of Commons.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Ceasing to hold office<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(3) Despite subsections (1) and (2), the Commissioner ceases to hold office on reaching 65 years of age.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Reappointment<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(4) Once having served as the Commissioner, a person is not eligible for reappointment to that office.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Interim appointment<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(5) In the event of the absence or incapacity of the Commissioner or if that office is vacant, the Governor in Council may appoint any qualified person to hold that office in the interim for a term not exceeding six months, and that person shall, while holding office, be paid the salary or other remuneration and expenses that may be fixed by the Governor in Council.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Salary<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>4.</B> (1) The Commissioner shall be paid a salary equal to the salary of a puisne judge of the Supreme Court of Canada.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Pension benefits<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(2) The provisions of the <I>Public Service Superannuation Act</I>, other than those relating to tenure of office, apply to the Commissioner except that a person appointed as Commissioner from outside the public service may, by notice in writing given to the President of the Treasury Board not more than 60 days after the date of appointment as Commissioner, elect to participate in the pension plan provided for in the <I>Diplomatic Service (Special) Superannuation Act</I> in which case the provisions of that Act, other than those relating to tenure of office, apply to the Commissioner and the provisions of the <I>Public Service Superannuation Act</I> do not apply to the Commissioner.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:POWERS AND DUTIES--><Para TopMargin="10" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">POWERS AND DUTIES</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Duty to monitor<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>5.</B> The Commissioner shall provide sustainable development monitoring and reporting on the progress of category I departments toward sustainable development and shall make any examinations and inquiries that the Commissioner considers necessary in order to monitor</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>a</I>) the extent to which category I departments have met the objectives, and implemented the plans, set out in their sustainable development strategies laid before the Senate and the House of Commons under section 10; and</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>b</I>) the replies by Ministers required by subsection 11(3).</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Advisory powers<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>6.</B> The Commissioner may advise appropriate officers and employees in the federal public administration of matters discovered in any examination and, in particular, may draw any such matter to the attention of officers and employees engaged in the conduct of the business of the Treasury Board.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Annual report<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>7.</B> The Commissioner shall report annually to the Senate and to the House of Commons, on or before December 31 in the year to which the report relates,</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>a</I>) on the work of the CommissionerГўВҖВҷs office during that year;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>b</I>) on whether, in carrying out the work of the CommissionerГўВҖВҷs office, the Commissioner received all the information and explanations that the Commissioner required; and</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>c</I>) concerning anything that the Commissioner considers should be brought to the attention of the Senate and the House of Commons, in relation to environmental and other aspects of sustainable development, including</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="4" FirstLineIndent="0">(i) the extent to which category I departments have met the objectives, and implemented the plans, set out in their sustainable development strategies laid before the Senate and the House of Commons under section 10,</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="4" FirstLineIndent="0">(ii) the number of petitions recorded as required by subsection 11(1), the subject-matter of the petitions and their status, and</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="4" FirstLineIndent="0">(iii) the exercising of the authority of the Governor in Council under any of subsections 10(3) to (5).</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Additional reports<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>8.</B> The Commissioner may, at any time, make an additional report to the Senate and the House of Commons referring to and commenting on any matter within the scope of the powers, duties and functions of the Commissioner where, in the opinion of the Commissioner, the matter is of such urgency or importance that a report on it should not be deferred until the time provided for transmission of the next annual report of the Commissioner under section 7.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Transmission of reports<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>9.</B> Every report to the Senate and the House of Commons made by the Commissioner shall be transmitted to the Speaker of the Senate and to the Speaker of the House of Commons for tabling in those Houses.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:SUSTAINABLE DEVELOPMENT STRATEGIES--><Para TopMargin="10" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">SUSTAINABLE DEVELOPMENT STRATEGIES</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Strategies to be tabled<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>10.</B> (1) The appropriate Minister for each category I department shall cause the department to prepare a sustainable development strategy for the department and shall cause the strategy to be laid before the Senate and the House of Commons</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>a</I>) within two years after this subsection comes into force; or</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>b</I>) in the case of a department that becomes a category I department on a day after this subsection comes into force, before the earlier of the second anniversary of that day and a day fixed by the Governor in Council pursuant to subsection (4).</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Updated strategies to be tabled<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(2) The appropriate Minister for a category I department shall cause the sustainable development strategy of the department to be updated at least every three years and shall cause each updated strategy to be laid before the Senate and the House of Commons on any of the next 15 days on which the House is sitting after the strategy is updated.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Governor in Council direction<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(3) The Governor in Council may, on the recommendation of the appropriate Minister for a department not named in Schedule I to the <I>Financial Administration Act</I>, direct that the requirements of subsections (1) and (2) apply in respect of the department.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Date fixed by Governor in Council<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(4) On the recommendation of the appropriate Minister for a department that becomes a category I department after this subsection comes into force, the Governor in Council may, for the purpose of subsection (1), fix the day before which the sustainable development strategy of the department shall be laid before the Senate and the House of Commons. </Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Regulations<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(5) The Governor in Council may, on the recommendation of the Minister of the Environment, make regulations prescribing the form in which sustainable development strategies are to be prepared and the information required to be contained in them.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:PETITIONS--><Para TopMargin="10" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">PETITIONS</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Petitions received<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>11.</B> (1) Where the Commissioner receives a petition in writing from a resident of Canada about an environmental matter in the context of sustainable development that is the responsibility of a category I department, the Commissioner shall make a record of the petition and forward the petition within 15 days after the day on which it is received to the appropriate Minister for the department.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Acknowledgement to be sent<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(2) Within 15 days after the day on which the Minister receives the petition from the Commissioner, the Minister shall send to the person who made the petition an acknowledgement of receipt of the petition and shall send a copy of the acknowledgement to the Commissioner.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Minister to respond<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(3) The Minister shall consider the petition and send to the person who made it a reply that responds to it, and shall send a copy of the reply to the Commissioner, within</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>a</I>) 120 days after the day on which the Minister receives the petition from the Commissioner; or</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>b</I>) any longer time, where the Minister personally, within those 120 days, notifies the person who made the petition that it is not possible to reply within those 120 days and sends a copy of that notification to the Commissioner.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Multiple petitioners<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(4) Where the petition is from more than one person, it is sufficient for the Minister to send the acknowledgement and reply, and the notification, if any, to one or more of the petitioners rather than to all of them.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:ACCESS TO INFORMATION--><Para TopMargin="10" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">ACCESS TO INFORMATION</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Access to information<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>12.</B> (1) Except as provided by any other Act of Parliament that expressly refers to this subsection, the Commissioner is entitled to free access at all convenient times to information that relates to the fulfilment of the CommissionerГўВҖВҷs responsibilities, and is also entitled to require and receive from members of the federal public administration any information, reports and explanations that the Commissioner considers necessary for that purpose.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Oath of secrecy<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(2) The Commissioner shall require every person employed in the CommissionerГўВҖВҷs office who is to examine the progress toward sustainable development by, or the sustainable development strategy of, a category I department pursuant to this Act to comply with any security requirements applicable to, and to take any oath of secrecy required to be taken by, persons employed in that department.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:STAFF OF THE COMMISSIONER--><Para TopMargin="10" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">STAFF OF THE COMMISSIONER</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Officers, etc.<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>13.</B> (1) The officers and employees that are necessary to enable the Commissioner to perform the CommissionerГўВҖВҷs duties are to be appointed in accordance with the <I>Public Service Employment Act</I>, and subject to subsections (2) to (5), the provisions of that Act apply to those officers and employees.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote><I>Public Service Employment Act</I> ГўВҖВ” employer and deputy head<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(2) The Commissioner may exercise the powers and perform the functions of the employer and deputy head under the <I>Public Service Employment Act</I> within the meaning of those terms in subsection 2(1) of that Act.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote><I>Public Service Employment Act</I> ГўВҖВ” Commission<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(3) The Commissioner may, in the manner and subject to the terms and conditions that the Public Service Commission directs, exercise the powers and perform the functions of that Commission under the <I>Public Service Employment Act</I>, other than its powers and functions in relation to the hearing of allegations by a candidate under sections 118 and 119 of that Act and its power to make regulations.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Delegation<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(4) The Commissioner may authorize any person employed in the CommissionerГўВҖВҷs office to exercise and perform, in any manner and subject to any terms and conditions that the Commissioner directs, any of his or her powers and functions under subsections (2) and (3).</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Sub-delegation<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(5) Any person authorized under subsection (4) may, subject to and in accordance with the authorization, authorize one or more persons under that personГўВҖВҷs jurisdiction to exercise any power or perform any function to which the authorization relates.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Responsibility for human resources management<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>14.</B> (1) The Commissioner is authorized, in respect of persons appointed in the CommissionerГўВҖВҷs office, to exercise the powers and perform the functions of the Treasury Board that relate to human resources management within the meaning of paragraph 7(1)(<I>e</I>) and section 11.1 of the <I>Financial Administration Act</I>, as well as those of deputy heads under subsection 12(2) of that Act, as that subsection reads without regard to any terms and conditions that the Governor in Council may direct, including the determination of terms and conditions of employment and the responsibility for employer and employee relations.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Delegation<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(2) The Commissioner may authorize any person employed in the CommissionerГўВҖВҷs office to exercise and perform, in any manner and subject to any terms and conditions that the Commissioner directs, any of his or her powers and functions in relation to human resources management.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Sub-delegation<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(3) Any person authorized under subsection (2) may, subject to and in accordance with the authorization, authorize one or more persons under that personГўВҖВҷs jurisdiction to exercise any power or perform any function to which the authorization relates.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Contract for professional services<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>15.</B> Subject to any other Act of Parliament or regulations made under any Act of Parliament, but without the approval of the Treasury Board, the Commissioner may, within the total dollar limitations established for the CommissionerГўВҖВҷs office in appropriation Acts, contract for professional services.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Classification standards<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>16.</B> Classification standards may be prepared for persons employed in the office of the Commissioner to conform to the classifications that the Commissioner recognizes for the purposes of that office.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:IMMUNITY--><Para TopMargin="10" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">IMMUNITY</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Immunity as witness<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>17.</B> The Commissioner, or any person acting on behalf or under the direction of the Commissioner, is not a competent or compellable witness, in respect of any matter coming to the knowledge of the Commissioner or that person as a result of exercising any powers or performing any duties or functions of the Commissioner under this Act, in any proceedings other than a prosecution for an offence under section 131 of the <I>Criminal Code</I> (perjury) in respect of a statement made under this Act.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Protection from prosecution<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>18.</B> (1) No criminal or civil proceedings lie against the Commissioner, or against any person acting on behalf or under the direction of the Commissioner, for anything done, reported or said in good faith in the course of the exercise or performance or purported exercise or performance of any power, duty or function of the Commissioner under this Act.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Defamation<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(2) For the purposes of any law relating to defamation,</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>a</I>) anything said, any information supplied or any document or thing produced in good faith by or on behalf of the Commissioner, in the course of the exercise or performance or purported exercise or performance of any power, duty or function of the Commissioner under this Act, is privileged; and</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>b</I>) any report made in good faith by the Commissioner in the course of the exercise or performance or purported exercise or performance of any power, duty or function of the Commissioner under this Act, and any fair and accurate account of the report made in good faith in a newspaper or any other periodical publication or in a broadcast, is privileged.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:ESTIMATES--><Para TopMargin="10" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">ESTIMATES</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Estimates<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>19.</B> (1) The Commissioner shall annually prepare an estimate of the sums that will be required to be provided by Parliament for the payment of the salaries, allowances and expenses of the CommissionerГўВҖВҷs office during the next ensuing fiscal year.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Special report<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(2) The Commissioner may make a special report to the Senate and to the House of Commons in the event that amounts provided for the CommissionerГўВҖВҷs office in the estimates submitted to Parliament are, in the CommissionerГўВҖВҷs opinion, inadequate to enable the Commissioner to fulfil the responsibilities of the office.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Appropriation allotments<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>20.</B> The provisions of the <I>Financial Administration Act</I> with respect to the division of appropriations into allotments do not apply in respect of appropriations for the office of the Commissioner.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:TRANSITIONAL PROVISIONS--><Para TopMargin="10" Bold="Yes" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">TRANSITIONAL PROVISIONS</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Commissioner<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>21.</B> (1) The person who holds the office of Commissioner of the Environment and Sustainable Development under the <I>Auditor General Act</I> immediately before the day on which subsection 3(1) of this Act comes into force is authorized to act as the Commissioner of the Environment and Sustainable Development under this Act until the appointment of a Commissioner under subsection 3(1).</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Eligibility for appointment<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(2) Despite subsection 3(4), a person is not ineligible for appointment under subsection 3(1) by reason only of having acted as the Commissioner of the Environment and Sustainable Development under subsection (1).</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Regulations<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>22.</B> (1) Every regulation made under subsection 24(5) of the <I>Auditor General Act</I> that is in force on the coming into force of subsection 10(5) of this Act is deemed to have been made under subsection 10(5) of this Act and shall remain in force until it is repealed or amended pursuant to this Act.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Directions<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(2) Every direction made by the Governor in Council under subsection 24(3) of the <I>Auditor General Act</I> that is in force on the coming into force of subsection 10(3) of this Act is deemed to have been made by the Governor in Council under subsection 10(3) of this Act.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:RELATED AND CONSEQUENTIAL AMENDMENTS--><Para TopMargin="10" Bold="Yes" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">RELATED AND CONSEQUENTIAL AMENDMENTS</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:ACCESS TO INFORMATION ACT--><Para TopMargin="5" Bold="Yes" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">ACCESS TO INFORMATION ACT</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>23.</B> Subsection 16.1(1) of the <I>Access to Information Act</I> is amended by adding the following after paragraph (<I>b</I>):</Para><ExplNote><Para Align="Yes" TopMargin="10" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0" Italic="Yes" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">Access to Information Act</Para><Para Align="Yes" TopMargin="10" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><I>Clause 23</I>: Relevant portion of subsection 16.1(1)</Para><Para Align="Yes" TopMargin="5" Size="8" Leading="9" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>16.1</B> (1) The following heads of government institutions shall refuse to disclose any record requested under this Act that contains information that was obtained or created by them or on their behalf in the course of an investigation, examination or audit conducted by them or under their authority:</Para><Para Align="No" TopMargin="5" Size="8" Leading="9" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">. . . </Para></ExplNote></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>b.1</I>) the Commissioner of the Environment and Sustainable Development;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>24.</B> Schedule I to the Act is amended by adding the following in alphabetical order under the heading ГўВҖВңOTHER GOVERNMENT INSTITUTIONSГўВҖВқ:</Para><ExplNote><Para Align="Yes" TopMargin="10" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><I>Clause 24</I>: New.</Para></ExplNote></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="-2" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">Office of the Commissioner of the Environment and Sustainable Development</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="-1" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify"><I>Commissariat ГғВ  lГўВҖВҷenvironnement et au dГғВ©veloppement durable</I></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:AUDITOR GENERAL ACT--><Para TopMargin="10" Bold="Yes" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">AUDITOR GENERAL ACT</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>25.</B> The long title of the <I>Auditor General Act</I> is replaced by the following:</Para><ExplNote><Para Align="Yes" TopMargin="10" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0" Italic="Yes" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">Auditor General Act</Para><Para Align="Yes" TopMargin="10" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><I>Clause 25</I>: Existing long title:</Para><Para Align="Yes" TopMargin="10" Size="8" Leading="9" LeftMargin="4" FirstLineIndent="-4" Hyphenate="OFF">An Act respecting the office of the Auditor General of Canada and sustainable development monitoring and reporting</Para></ExplNote></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="10" LeftMargin="4" FirstLineIndent="-4" Hyphenate="OFF">An Act respecting the office of the Auditor General of Canada</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>26.</B> The definitions ГўВҖВңappropriate MinisterГўВҖВқ, ГўВҖВңcategory I departmentГўВҖВқ, ГўВҖВңCommissionerГўВҖВқ and ГўВҖВңsustainable development strategyГўВҖВқ in section 2 of the Act are repealed.</Para><ExplNote><Para Align="Yes" TopMargin="10" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><I>Clause 26</I>: Existing text of the relevant definitions:</Para><Para Align="Yes" TopMargin="5" Size="8" Leading="9" LeftMargin="0">ГўВҖВңappropriate MinisterГўВҖВқ has the meaning assigned by section 2 of the <I>Financial Administration Act</I>;</Para><Para Align="No" TopMargin="5" Size="8" Leading="9" LeftMargin="0">. . .</Para><Para Align="No" TopMargin="5" Size="8" Leading="9" LeftMargin="0">ГўВҖВңcategory I departmentГўВҖВқ means</Para><Para Align="No" TopMargin="5" Size="8" Leading="9" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>a</I>) any department named in Schedule I to the <I>Financial Administration Act</I>,</Para><Para Align="No" TopMargin="5" Size="8" Leading="9" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>b</I>) any department in respect of which a direction has been made under subsection 24(3), and</Para><Para Align="No" TopMargin="5" Size="8" Leading="9" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>c</I>) any department set out in the schedule;</Para><Para Align="No" TopMargin="5" Size="8" Leading="9" LeftMargin="0">ГўВҖВңCommissionerГўВҖВқ means the Commissioner of the Environment and Sustainable Development appointed under subsection 15.1(1);</Para><Para Align="No" TopMargin="5" Size="8" Leading="9" LeftMargin="0">. . .</Para><Para Align="No" TopMargin="5" Size="8" Leading="9" LeftMargin="0">ГўВҖВңsustainable developmentГўВҖВқ means development that meets the needs of the present without compromising the ability of future generations to meet their own needs;</Para><Para Align="No" TopMargin="5" Size="8" Leading="9" LeftMargin="0">. . .</Para></ExplNote></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>27.</B> (1) The portion of subsection 7(1) of the Act before paragraph (<I>a</I>) is replaced by the following:</Para><ExplNote><Para Align="Yes" TopMargin="10" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><I>Clause 27</I>: (1) and (2) Relevant portion of section 7:</Para><Para Align="Yes" TopMargin="5" Size="8" Leading="9" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>7.</B> (1) The Auditor General shall report annually to the House of Commons and may make, in addition to any special report made under subsection 8(1) or 19(2) and the CommissionerГўВҖВҷs report under subsection 23(2), not more than three additional reports in any year to the House of Commons</Para><Para Align="No" TopMargin="5" Size="8" Leading="9" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">. . . </Para><Para Align="Yes" TopMargin="5" Size="8" Leading="9" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(2) Each report of the Auditor General under subsection (1) shall call attention to anything that he considers to be of significance and of a nature that should be brought to the attention of the House of Commons, including any cases in which he has observed that</Para><Para Align="No" TopMargin="5" Size="8" Leading="9" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">. . . </Para><Para Align="No" TopMargin="5" Size="8" Leading="9" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>d</I>) money has been expended without due regard to economy or efficiency;</Para><Para Align="No" TopMargin="5" Size="8" Leading="9" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>e</I>) satisfactory procedures have not been established to measure and report the effectiveness of programs, where such procedures could appropriately and reasonably be implemented, or</Para><Para Align="No" TopMargin="5" Size="8" Leading="9" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>f</I>) money has been expended without due regard to the environmental effects of those expenditures in the context of sustainable development.</Para></ExplNote></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Annual and additional reports to the House of Commons<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>7.</B> (1) The Auditor General shall report annually to the House of Commons and may make, in addition to any special report made under subsection 8(1) or 19(2), not more than three additional reports in any year to the House of Commons</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes">(2) Subsection 7(2) of the Act is amended by adding the word ГўВҖВңorГўВҖВқ at the end of paragraph (<I>d</I>), by striking out the word ГўВҖВңorГўВҖВқ at the end of paragraph (<I>e</I>) and by repealing paragraph (<I>f</I>).</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>28.</B> Section 15.1 of the Act is repealed.</Para><ExplNote><Para Align="Yes" TopMargin="10" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><I>Clause 28</I>: Existing text of section 15.1:</Para><Para Align="Yes" TopMargin="5" Size="8" Leading="9" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>15.1</B> (1) The Auditor General shall, in accordance with the <I>Public Service Employment Act</I>, appoint a senior officer to be called the Commissioner of the Environment and Sustainable Development who shall report directly to the Auditor General.</Para><Para Align="Yes" TopMargin="5" Size="8" Leading="9" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(2) The Commissioner shall assist the Auditor General in performing the duties of the Auditor General set out in this Act that relate to the environment and sustainable development.</Para></ExplNote></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>29.</B> Sections 21.1 to 24 of the Act are repealed.</Para><ExplNote><Para Align="Yes" TopMargin="10" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><I>Clause 29</I>: Existing text of sections 21.1 to 24:</Para><Para Align="Yes" TopMargin="5" Size="8" Leading="9" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>21.1</B> The purpose of the Commissioner is to provide sustainable development monitoring and reporting on the progress of category I departments towards sustainable development, which is a continually evolving concept based on the integration of social, economic and environmental concerns, and which may be achieved by, among other things,</Para><Para Align="No" TopMargin="5" Size="8" Leading="9" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>a</I>) the integration of the environment and the economy;</Para><Para Align="No" TopMargin="5" Size="8" Leading="9" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>b</I>) protecting the health of Canadians;</Para><Para Align="No" TopMargin="5" Size="8" Leading="9" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>c</I>) protecting ecosystems;</Para><Para Align="No" TopMargin="5" Size="8" Leading="9" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>d</I>) meeting international obligations;</Para><Para Align="No" TopMargin="5" Size="8" Leading="9" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>e</I>) promoting equity;</Para><Para Align="No" TopMargin="5" Size="8" Leading="9" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>f</I>) an integrated approach to planning and making decisions that takes into account the environmental and natural resource costs of different economic options and the economic costs of different environmental and natural resource options;</Para><Para Align="No" TopMargin="5" Size="8" Leading="9" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>g</I>) preventing pollution; and</Para><Para Align="No" TopMargin="5" Size="8" Leading="9" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>h</I>) respect for nature and the needs of future generations.</Para><Para Align="Yes" TopMargin="5" Size="8" Leading="9" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>22.</B> (1) Where the Auditor General receives a petition in writing from a resident of Canada about an environmental matter in the context of sustainable development that is the responsibility of a category I department, the Auditor General shall make a record of the petition and forward the petition within fifteen days after the day on which it is received to the appropriate Minister for the department.</Para><Para Align="Yes" TopMargin="5" Size="8" Leading="9" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(2) Within fifteen days after the day on which the Minister receives the petition from the Auditor General, the Minister shall send to the person who made the petition an acknowledgement of receipt of the petition and shall send a copy of the acknowledgement to the Auditor General.</Para><Para Align="Yes" TopMargin="5" Size="8" Leading="9" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(3) The Minister shall consider the petition and send to the person who made it a reply that responds to it, and shall send a copy of the reply to the Auditor General, within</Para><Para Align="No" TopMargin="5" Size="8" Leading="9" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>a</I>) one hundred and twenty days after the day on which the Minister receives the petition from the Auditor General; or</Para><Para Align="No" TopMargin="5" Size="8" Leading="9" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>b</I>) any longer time, where the Minister personally, within those one hundred and twenty days, notifies the person who made the petition that it is not possible to reply within those one hundred and twenty days and sends a copy of that notification to the Auditor General.</Para><Para Align="Yes" TopMargin="5" Size="8" Leading="9" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(4) Where the petition is from more than one person, it is sufficient for the Minister to send the acknowledgement and reply, and the notification, if any, to one or more of the petitioners rather than to all of them.</Para><Para Align="Yes" TopMargin="5" Size="8" Leading="9" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>23.</B> (1) The Commissioner shall make any examinations and inquiries that the Commissioner considers necessary in order to monitor</Para><Para Align="No" TopMargin="5" Size="8" Leading="9" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>a</I>) the extent to which category I departments have met the objectives, and implemented the plans, set out in their sustainable development strategies laid before the House of Commons under section 24; and</Para><Para Align="No" TopMargin="5" Size="8" Leading="9" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>b</I>) the replies by Ministers required by subsection 22(3).</Para><Para Align="Yes" TopMargin="5" Size="8" Leading="9" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(2) The Commissioner shall, on behalf of the Auditor General, report annually to the House of Commons concerning anything that the Commissioner considers should be brought to the attention of that House in relation to environmental and other aspects of sustainable development, including</Para><Para Align="No" TopMargin="5" Size="8" Leading="9" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>a</I>) the extent to which category I departments have met the objectives, and implemented the plans, set out in their sustainable development strategies laid before that House under section 24;</Para><Para Align="No" TopMargin="5" Size="8" Leading="9" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>b</I>) the number of petitions recorded as required by subsection 22(1), the subject-matter of the petitions and their status; and</Para><Para Align="No" TopMargin="5" Size="8" Leading="9" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>c</I>) the exercising of the authority of the Governor in Council under any of subsections 24(3) to (5).</Para><Para Align="Yes" TopMargin="5" Size="8" Leading="9" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(3) The report required by subsection (2) shall be submitted to the Speaker of the House of Commons and shall be laid before that House by the Speaker on any of the next fifteen days on which that House is sitting after the Speaker receives it.</Para><Para Align="Yes" TopMargin="5" Size="8" Leading="9" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>24.</B> (1) The appropriate Minister for each category I department shall cause the department to prepare a sustainable development strategy for the department and shall cause the strategy to be laid before the House of Commons</Para><Para Align="No" TopMargin="5" Size="8" Leading="9" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>a</I>) within two years after this subsection comes into force; or</Para><Para Align="No" TopMargin="5" Size="8" Leading="9" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>b</I>) in the case of a department that becomes a category I department on a day after this subsection comes into force, before the earlier of the second anniversary of that day and a day fixed by the Governor in Council pursuant to subsection (4).</Para><Para Align="Yes" TopMargin="5" Size="8" Leading="9" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(2) The appropriate Minister for the category I department shall cause the departmentГўВҖВҷs sustainable development strategy to be updated at least every three years and shall cause each updated strategy to be laid before the House of Commons on any of the next fifteen days on which that House is sitting after the strategy is updated.</Para><Para Align="Yes" TopMargin="5" Size="8" Leading="9" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(3) The Governor in Council may, on the recommendation of the appropriate Minister for a department not named in Schedule I to the <I>Financial Administration Act</I>, direct that the requirements of subsections (1) and (2) apply in respect of the department.</Para><Para Align="Yes" TopMargin="5" Size="8" Leading="9" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(4) On the recommendation of the appropriate Minister for a department that becomes a category I department after this subsection comes into force, the Governor in Council may, for the purpose of subsection (1), fix the day before which the sustainable development strategy of the department shall be laid before the House of Commons.</Para><Para Align="Yes" TopMargin="5" Size="8" Leading="9" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(5) The Governor in Council may, on the recommendation of the Minister of the Environment, make regulations prescribing the form in which sustainable development strategies are to be prepared and the information required to be contained in them.</Para></ExplNote></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>30.</B> The schedule to the Act is repealed.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:FINANCIAL ADMINISTRATION ACT--><Para TopMargin="10" Bold="Yes" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">FINANCIAL ADMINISTRATION ACT</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>31.</B> Schedule I.1 to the <I>Financial Administration Act</I> is amended by adding the following in alphabetical order in column I:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="-2" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">Office of the Commissioner of the Environment and Sustainable Development</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="-1" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify"><I>Commissariat ГғВ  lГўВҖВҷenvironnement et au dГғВ©veloppement durable</I></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0" Bold="Yes"><B>and a corresponding reference in column II to the ГўВҖВңPresident of the QueenГўВҖВҷs Privy Council for CanadaГўВҖВқ.</B></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>32.</B> Schedule IV to the Act is amended by adding the following in alphabetical order:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="-2" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">Office of the Commissioner of the Environment and Sustainable Development</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="-1" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify"><I>Commissariat ГғВ  lГўВҖВҷenvironnement et au dГғВ©veloppement durable</I></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>33.</B> Schedule VI to the Act is amended by adding the following in alphabetical order in column I of Part III:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="-2" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">Office of the Commissioner of the Environment and Sustainable Development</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="-1" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify"><I>Commissariat ГғВ  lГўВҖВҷenvironnement et au dГғВ©veloppement durable</I></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0" Bold="Yes"><B>and a corresponding reference in column II to the ГўВҖВңCommissioner of the Environment and Sustainable DevelopmentГўВҖВқ.</B></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:OFFICIAL LANGUAGES ACT--><Para TopMargin="10" Bold="Yes" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">OFFICIAL LANGUAGES ACT</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>34.</B> Subsection 24(3) of the <I>Official Languages Act</I> is amended by striking out the word ГўВҖВңandГўВҖВқ at the end of paragraph (<I>d</I>), by adding the word ГўВҖВңandГўВҖВқ at the end of paragraph (<I>e</I>) and by adding the following after paragraph (<I>e</I>):</Para><ExplNote><Para Align="Yes" TopMargin="10" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0" Italic="Yes" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">Official Languages Act</Para><Para Align="Yes" TopMargin="10" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><I>Clause 34</I>: Relevant portion of subsection 24(3):</Para><Para Align="Yes" TopMargin="5" Size="8" Leading="9" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(3) Without restricting the generality of subsection (2), the duty set out in that subsection applies in respect of</Para><Para Align="No" TopMargin="5" Size="8" Leading="9" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">. . . </Para><Para Align="No" TopMargin="5" Size="8" Leading="9" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>d</I>) the Office of the Information Commissioner; and</Para><Para Align="No" TopMargin="5" Size="8" Leading="9" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>e</I>) the Office of the Privacy Commissioner.</Para></ExplNote></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>f</I>) the Office of the Commissioner of the Environment and Sustainable Development.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:PRIVACY ACT--><Para TopMargin="10" Bold="Yes" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">PRIVACY ACT</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>35.</B> The schedule to the <I>Privacy Act</I> is amended by adding the following in alphabetical order under the heading ГўВҖВңOTHER GOVERNMENT INSTITUTIONSГўВҖВқ:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="-2" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">Office of the Commissioner of the Environment and Sustainable Development</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="-1" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify"><I>Commissariat ГғВ  lГўВҖВҷenvironnement et au dГғВ©veloppement durable</I></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:PUBLIC SECTOR COMPENSATION ACT--><Para TopMargin="10" Bold="Yes" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">PUBLIC SECTOR COMPENSATION ACT</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>36.</B> Schedule I to the <I>Public Sector Compensation Act</I> is amended by adding the following in alphabetical order under the heading ГўВҖВңOther Portions of the Public ServiceГўВҖВқ:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="-2" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">Office of the Commissioner of the Environment and Sustainable Development</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="-1" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify"><I>Commissariat ГғВ  lГўВҖВҷenvironnement et au dГғВ©veloppement durable</I></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:PUBLIC SERVANTS DISCLOSURE PROTECTION ACT--><Para TopMargin="10" Bold="Yes" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">PUBLIC SERVANTS DISCLOSURE PROTECTION ACT</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>37.</B> Schedule 2 to the <I>Public Servants Disclosure Protection Act</I> is amended by adding the following in alphabetical order:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="-2" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">Office of the Commissioner of the Environment and Sustainable Development</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="-1" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify"><I>Commissariat ГғВ  lГўВҖВҷenvironnement et au dГғВ©veloppement durable</I></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:COMING INTO FORCE--><Para TopMargin="10" Bold="Yes" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">COMING INTO FORCE</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Order of Governor in Council<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>38.</B> (1) Subject to subsection (2), the provisions of this Act come into force on a day or days to be fixed by order of the Governor in Council.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Royal recommendation<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes">(2) No order may be made under subsection (1) unless the appropriation of moneys for the purposes of this Act has been recommended by the Governor General and such moneys have been appropriated by Parliament.</Para></Block><Block Align="Yes" LineCnt="N"><Para NoLineBreak="Yes" NoHtml="Yes" Leading="0" Size="0" TopMargin="0" BottomMargin="0">ГӮВ„</Para></Block></Bill_Part><Bill_Part Part_Type="Schedule" CountLines="No" RunningHead_E="Commissioner of the Environment and Sustainable Development"><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"/><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:SCHEDULE--><Para TopMargin="10" Size="9" Leading="10" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center"><B>SCHEDULE</B></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:(Section 2)--><Para TopMargin="5" Size="9" Leading="10" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">(<I>Section 2</I>)</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" Size="9" Leading="10" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="-2" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">Atlantic Canada Opportunities Agency</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="-1" Size="9" Leading="10" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify"><I>Agence de promotion ГғВ©conomique du Canada atlantique</I></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" Size="9" Leading="10" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="-2" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">Canada Revenue Agency</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="-1" Size="9" Leading="10" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify"><I>Agence du revenu du Canada</I></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" Size="9" Leading="10" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="-2" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">Canadian International Development Agency</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="-1" Size="9" Leading="10" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify"><I>Agence canadienne de dГғВ©veloppement international</I></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" Size="9" Leading="10" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="-2" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">Economic Development Agency of Canada for the Regions of Quebec</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="-1" Size="9" Leading="10" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify"><I>Agence de dГғВ©veloppement ГғВ©conomique du Canada pour les rГғВ©gions du QuГғВ©bec</I></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" Size="9" Leading="10" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="-2" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">Parks Canada Agency</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="-1" Size="9" Leading="10" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify"><I>Agence Parcs Canada</I></Para></Block><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="BPT_ImprintE"><br/><br/>Published under authority of the Senate of Canada</Para></Block><Block Align="Yes" LineCnt="N"><Para NoLineBreak="Yes" NoHtml="Yes" Leading="0" Size="0" TopMargin="0" BottomMargin="0">ГӮВ„</Para></Block></Bill_Part></Bill>
