<?xml version="1.0"?>
<Bill RHead_reign="56-57 Eliz. II" RHead_ParlYear="2007-2008" DocumentTitle="BILL S-241" Bill_No="S-241" Document_No="0728" xml:lang="EN" Bill_Type="Amending" Stage_Name="First-Reading-Senate" Reprint="No" xml:space="preserve" ChapterNo_E="C. " ChapterNo_F="ch. " Bill-Origin="senate"><Bill_Part Part_Type="Cover" CountLines="No"><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="CovBillNo">S-241</Para></Block><Block><Para TopMargin="24" Size="9" Leading="10" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0" TextAlign="Center">Second Session, Thirty-ninth Parliament,</Para></Block><Block><Para Size="9" Leading="10" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0" TextAlign="Center">56-57 Elizabeth II, 2007-2008</Para></Block><Block><Para TopMargin="48" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0" Bold="Yes" TextAlign="Center">SENATE OF CANADA</Para></Block><Block><Para TopMargin="42" Size="18" Leading="20" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0" Bold="Yes" TextAlign="Center">BILL S-241</Para></Block><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="CovLongTitle">An Act to amend the Investment Canada Act (foreign investments)</Para></Block><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="COV_StageLine"></Para></Block><Block><Para Size="9" AllCaps="Yes" Hyphenate="OFF">first reading, June 17, 2008</Para></Block><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="COV_StageLine"></Para></Block><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="Cover_Sponsors">THE HONOURABLE SENATOR HERVIEUX-PAYETTE, P.C.</Para></Block><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="Cover_DocNo">0728</Para></Block></Bill_Part><Bill_Part CountLines="No" Part_Type="InsideCover"><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="BPT_InsideCoverE">Available on the Parliament of Canada Web Site at the following address:<br/><B>http://www.parl.gc.ca</B></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><Para TopMargin="108" BottomMargin="4" Size="10" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">SUMMARY</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" Size="8" Leading="9" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">This enactment amends the <I>Investment Canada Act</I> to provide for the review of foreign investments in Canada that could be contrary to the national interest. An investment is reviewable if the value of the asset is equal to or exceeds two hundred and ninety-five million dollars, the 2008 threshold for review of  investments by World Trade Organization member investors; if the investment is being made by a foreign government or political subdivision or agency thereof; if the business exploits non-renewable natural resources for export; if the investment is in a business in a strategic or emerging economic sector; or if the Governor in Council orders a review of the investment. This enactment also provides that the Governor in Council may, by order, take any measures that the Governor in Council considers advisable to protect the national interest.</Para></Block></Bill_Part><Bill_Part Part_Type="TableProvisions" CountLines="No"><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:TABLE OF PROVISIONS--><Para TopMargin="30" Size="10" Leading="12" AllCaps="Yes" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">TABLE OF PROVISIONS</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:AN ACT TO AMEND THE INVESTMENT CANADA ACT (FOREIGN INVESTMENTS)--><Para TopMargin="24" BottomMargin="4" Size="10" Leading="12" AllCaps="Yes" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">AN ACT TO AMEND THE INVESTMENT CANADA ACT (FOREIGN INVESTMENTS)</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:AMENDMENTS TO THE INVESTMENT CANADA ACT--><Para TopMargin="16" Size="9" Leading="10" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center"><B>AMENDMENTS TO THE INVESTMENT CANADA ACT</B></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" Size="9" Leading="10" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0"><B>1-9.</B> <Tab/><B>Amendments</B></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" Size="9" Leading="10" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0"><B>10.</B> <Tab/><B>Coming into force</B></Para></Block></Bill_Part><Bill_Part Part_Type="MainText" CountLines="Yes" RunningHead_E="Investment Canada (foreign investments)"><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="MainText_DocNo">0728</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes"><Para Style="Session_Reign">2nd Session, 39th Parliament,</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes"><Para Style="Session_Reign">56-57 Elizabeth II, 2007-2008</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes"><Para Style="MainBillOrigin">senate of canada</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes"><Para Bold="Yes" Style="MAIN@BillNo_Title">BILL S-241</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes"><Para Style="MAIN@ti;04">An Act to amend the Investment Canada Act (foreign investments)</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>R.S., c. 28 (1st Supp.)<br/></MarginalNote><Para LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">Her Majesty, by and with the advice and consent of the Senate and House of Commons of Canada, enacts as follows:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>1.</B> Section 2 of the <I>Investment Canada Act</I> is replaced by the following:</Para><ExplNote><Para Align="Yes" TopMargin="10" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0" Italic="Yes" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">Investment Canada Act</Para><Para Align="Yes" TopMargin="10" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><I>Clause 1</I>: Existing text of section 2:</Para><Para Align="Yes" TopMargin="5" Size="8" Leading="9" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>2.</B> Recognizing that increased capital and technology would benefit Canada, the purpose of this Act is to encourage investment in Canada by Canadians and non-Canadians that contributes to economic growth and employment opportunities and to provide for the review of significant investments in Canada by non-Canadians in order to ensure such benefit to Canada.</Para></ExplNote></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Purposes of Act<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>2.</B> Recognizing <change>the importance of foreign direct investment and the importance of protecting the national interest</change>, the purposes of this Act are</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>a</I>) to encourage investment in Canada by Canadians and non-Canadians that contributes to economic growth and employment opportunities and to provide for the review of significant investments in Canada by non-Canadians in order to ensure that <change>those investments</change> benefit Canada<change>; and</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0"><change>(<I>b</I>) to provide for the review of investments in Canada by non-Canadians that could be contrary to the national interest.</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>2.</B> Paragraph (<I>d</I>) of the definition “Canadian” in section 3 of the Act is replaced by the following:</Para><ExplNote><Para Align="Yes" TopMargin="10" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><I>Clause 2</I>: Existing text of relevant portion of the definition:</Para><Para Align="Yes" TopMargin="5" Size="8" Leading="9" LeftMargin="0">“Canadian” means</Para><Para Align="No" TopMargin="5" Size="8" Leading="9" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">. . . </Para><Para Align="No" TopMargin="5" Size="8" Leading="9" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>d</I>) an entity that is Canadian-controlled, as determined pursuant to subsection 26(1) or (2) and in respect of which no determination or declaration has been made under subsection 26(2.1) or (2.2);</Para></ExplNote></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>d</I>) an entity that is Canadian-controlled, as determined under subsection 26(1) or (2) and in respect of which no determination or declaration has been made under subsection 26(2.1)<change>, (2.11)</change> or (2.2);</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>3.</B> (1) The portion of subsection 10(1) of the Act before paragraph (<I>a</I>) is replaced by the following:</Para><ExplNote><Para Align="Yes" TopMargin="10" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><I>Clause 3</I>: (1) Existing text of relevant portion of subsection 10(1):</Para><Para Align="Yes" TopMargin="5" Size="8" Leading="9" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>10.</B> (1) This Act does not apply to</Para></ExplNote></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Exempt transactions<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>10.</B> (1) This Act<change>, other than Part IV.1,</change> does not apply <change>in respect of</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes">(2) Subsection 10(2) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Para><ExplNote><Para Align="Yes" TopMargin="10" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(2) Existing text of subsection (2):</Para><Para Align="Yes" TopMargin="5" Size="8" Leading="9" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(2) Where any condition referred to in paragraph (1)(<I>d</I>) or (<I>j</I>) is not complied with, the exemption under that paragraph does not apply and the transaction referred to in that paragraph is subject to this Act as if it had never been exempt.</Para></ExplNote></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Exempt transactions — Part IV.1<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><change>(1.1) Part IV.1 does not apply in respect of</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0"><change>(<I>a</I>) the acquisition of control of a Canadian business in connection with the realization of security granted for a loan or other financial assistance and not for any purpose related to the provisions of this Act, if the acquisition is subject to approval under the <I>Bank Act</I>, the <I>Cooperative Credit Associations Act</I>, the <I>Insurance Companies Act</I> or the <I>Trust and Loan Companies Act</I>;</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0"><change>(<I>b</I>) the acquisition of control of a Canadian business by reason of an amalgamation, a merger, a consolidation or a corporate reorganization following which the ultimate direct or indirect control in fact of the Canadian business, through the ownership of voting interests, remains unchanged, if the acquisition is subject to approval under the <I>Bank Act</I>, the <I>Cooperative Credit Associations Act</I>, the <I>Insurance Companies Act</I> or the <I>Trust and Loan Companies Act</I>;</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0"><change>(<I>c</I>) the acquisition of control of a Canadian business carried on by an agent of Her Majesty in right of Canada or a province or by a Crown corporation within the meaning of the <I>Financial Administration Act</I>;</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0"><change>(<I>d</I>) any transaction to which section 522.28 of the <I>Bank Act</I> applies; and</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0"><change>(<I>e</I>) the acquisition of control of a Canadian business by any of the following entities, if the acquisition is subject to approval under the <I>Bank Act</I>, the <I>Cooperative Credit Associations Act</I>, the <I>Insurance Companies Act</I> or the <I>Trust and Loan Companies Act</I>:</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="4" FirstLineIndent="0"><change>(i) an insurance company incorporated in Canada that is a company or a provincial company to which the <I>Insurance Companies Act</I> applies, on the condition that the gross investment revenue of the company from the Canadian business is included in computing the income of the company under subsection 138(9) of the <I>Income Tax Act</I>,</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="4" FirstLineIndent="0"><change>(ii) a non-resident insurance company the insurance of risks in Canada by which has been approved by order of the Superintendent of Financial Institutions under Part XIII of the <I>Insurance Companies Act</I>, on the condition that the gross investment revenue of the company from the Canadian business is included in computing the income of the company under subsection 138(9) of the <I>Income Tax Act</I> and the voting interests of the entity carrying on the Canadian business, or the assets used in carrying on the Canadian business, are vested in trust under that Part, or</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="4" FirstLineIndent="0"><change>(iii) a corporation incorporated in Canada, all the issued voting shares of which, other than the qualifying voting shares of directors, are owned by an insurance company described in subparagraph (i) or (ii) or by a corporation controlled directly or indirectly through the ownership of voting shares by such an insurance company, on the condition that, in the case of an insurance company described in subparagraph (ii), the voting interests of the entity carrying on the Canadian business, or the assets used in carrying on the Canadian business, are vested in trust under Part XIII of the <I>Insurance Companies Act</I>.</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>If condition not complied with<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(2) <change>If</change> any condition referred to in paragraph (1)(<I>d</I>) or (<I>j</I>) <change>or (1.1)(<I>e</I>)</change> is not complied with, the exemption under that paragraph does not apply and the transaction referred to in that paragraph is subject to this Act as if it had never been exempt.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>4.</B> The Act is amended by adding the following after section 25:</Para><ExplNote><Para Align="Yes" TopMargin="10" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><I>Clause 4</I>: New.</Para></ExplNote></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:PART IV.1--><Para TopMargin="10" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center"><change>PART IV.1</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:REVIEWABLE INVESTMENTS--><Para TopMargin="5" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center"><change>REVIEWABLE INVESTMENTS</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Application<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><change><B>25.1</B> This Part applies in respect of an investment by a non-Canadian</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0"><change>(<I>a</I>) to establish a new Canadian business;</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0"><change>(<I>b</I>) to acquire control of a Canadian business in any manner described in subsection 28(1); or</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0"><change>(<I>c</I>) to acquire, in whole or in part, or to establish an entity carrying on all or any part of its operations in Canada if the entity has</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="4" FirstLineIndent="0"><change>(i) a place of operations in Canada,</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="4" FirstLineIndent="0"><change>(ii) an individual or individuals in Canada who are employed or self-employed in connection with the entity’s operations, or</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="4" FirstLineIndent="0"><change>(iii) assets in Canada used in carrying on the entity’s operations.</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Notice<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><change><B>25.2</B> (1) If the Minister has reasonable grounds to believe that an investment by a non-Canadian could be contrary to the national interest, the Minister may send to the non-Canadian a notice that an order for the review of the investment may be made under subsection 25.3(1).</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Investment may not be implemented<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><change>(2) A non-Canadian that receives the notice shall not implement the investment unless they receive</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0"><change>(<I>a</I>) a notice under paragraph (3)(<I>a</I>) indicating that no order for the review of the investment will be made under subsection 25.3(1);</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0"><change>(<I>b</I>) a notice under paragraph 25.3(6)(<I>b</I>) indicating that no further action will be taken in respect of the investment; or</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0"><change>(<I>c</I>) a copy of an order made under section 25.5 authorizing the investment to be implemented.</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Ministerial action<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><change>(3) The Minister shall, within the prescribed period, send to the non-Canadian</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0"><change>(<I>a</I>) a notice indicating that no order for the review of the investment will be made under subsection 25.3(1); or</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0"><change>(<I>b</I>) a notice referred to in subsection 25.3(2) indicating that an order for the review of the investment has been made.</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Reviewable investment<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><change><B>25.3</B> (1) An investment is reviewable under this Part if</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0"><change>(<I>a</I>) the value of the assets, calculated in the manner described in section 25.4, is equal to or greater than two hundred and ninety-five million dollars or such greater amount as is prescribed by the Governor in Council, but no amount shall be prescribed that is less than a previously prescribed amount;</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0"><change>(<I>b</I>) it is being made by the government of a foreign country or any political subdivision thereof, an agent or agency of such a government or political subdivision, or an entity such as a body corporate, trust, partnership, fund, joint venture, unincorporated association or unincorporated organization in which such a government or political subdivision holds an interest specified by regulation;</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0"><change>(<I>c</I>) the business being invested in includes the export from Canada or the primary production for the purpose of export from Canada of non-renewable natural resources, forestry resources, electrical energy or water in bulk;</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0"><change>(<I>d</I>) the business being invested in operates in the aerospace sector, defence and weapons systems sector, health services sector (including bio-medical and clinical research), information infrastructure and services sector, or any other strategic or emerging economic sector prescribed by the Governor in Council; or</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0"><change>(<I>e</I>) the Governor in Council, on the recommendation of the Minister, where the Governor in Council considers that the investment could be contrary to the national interest, makes an order for the review of the investment.</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Notice<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><change>(2) The Minister shall, without delay after the order has been made, send to the non-Canadian making the investment and to any person or entity from whom or which the Canadian business or the entity referred to in paragraph 25.1(<I>c</I>) is being acquired, a notice indicating that an order for the review of the investment has been made and advising them of their right to make representations to the Minister.</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Investment may not be implemented<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><change>(3) A non-Canadian that receives a notice referred to in subsection (2) shall not implement the investment unless they receive</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0"><change>(<I>a</I>) a notice under paragraph (6)(<I>b</I>) indicating that no further action will be taken in respect of the investment; or</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0"><change>(<I>b</I>) a copy of an order made under section 25.5 authorizing the investment to be implemented.</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Representations<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><change>(4) If, after receipt of the notice referred to in subsection (2), the non-Canadian or the person or entity advises the Minister that they wish to make representations, the Minister shall afford them a reasonable opportunity to make representations in person or by an agent.</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Requirement to provide information<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><change>(5) The Minister may require the non-Canadian or other person or entity to provide, within the time and in the manner specified by the Minister, any prescribed information or any other information that the Minister considers necessary for the purposes of the review.</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Ministerial action<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><change>(6) The Minister shall, within the prescribed period,</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0"><change>(<I>a</I>) refer the investment under review to the Governor in Council, together with a report of the Minister’s findings and recommendations on the review, if</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="4" FirstLineIndent="0"><change>(i) the Minister is satisfied that the investment would be contrary to the national interest, or</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="4" FirstLineIndent="0"><change>(ii) on the basis of the information available, the Minister is not able to determine whether the investment would be contrary to the national interest; or</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0"><change>(<I>b</I>) send to the non-Canadian a notice indicating that no further action will be taken in respect of the investment, if the Minister is satisfied that the investment would not be contrary to the national interest.</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Ministerial action<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><change>(7) Notwithstanding subsection (6), the Minister shall refer an investment described in paragraphs (1)(<I>a</I>) to (<I>c</I>) to the Governor in Council, together with a report of the Minister’s findings and recommendations on the review.</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Value of assets<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><change><B>25.4</B> (1) For the purpose of determining the value of an investment referred to in paragraph 25.3(1)(<I>a</I>), where the non-Canadian acquires only assets used in carrying on a Canadian business or only control of an entity carrying on a Canadian business, the value of the assets shall be the aggregate of all assets acquired or of all assets of the entity, as shown in the audited financial statements of the entity carrying on the business for its fiscal year immediately preceding the implementation of the investment.</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Value of assets<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><change>(2) For the purpose of determining the value of an investment referred to in paragraph 25.3(1)(<I>a</I>), where the non-Canadian acquires, directly or indirectly, control of an entity carrying on a Canadian business and control of one or more other entities in Canada, the value of the assets shall be the aggregate of all assets shown in the audited financial statements consolidated for all the entities for their fiscal year immediately preceding the implementation of the investment.</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Value of assets<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><change>(3) For the purpose of determining the value of an investment referred to in paragraph 25.3(1)(<I>a</I>), where the non-Canadian acquires, directly or indirectly, control of a corporation incorporated elsewhere than in Canada that controls, directly or indirectly, an entity in Canada carrying on a Canadian business, the value of the assets of all entities, both inside and outside Canada, the control of which is acquired, directly or indirectly, shall be the aggregate of all assets shown in the audited financial statements consolidated for all the entities for their fiscal year immediately preceding the implementation of the investment.</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Consolidated financial statements not available<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><change>(4) Where consolidated financial statements of the entities referred to in subsection (2) or (3) are not available, the value of the assets for the purposes of paragraph 25.3(1)(<I>a</I>) shall be the aggregate of the assets of all the entities as shown in the audited financial statements for each such entity for its fiscal year immediately preceding the implementation of the investment, excluding</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0"><change>(<I>a</I>) any amount shown to represent an ownership interest in any other entity the control of which is acquired directly or indirectly; and</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0"><change>(<I>b</I>) any amount representing duplication arising from transactions between any entities the control of which is acquired directly or indirectly.</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Exception — use of unaudited statement<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><change>(5) For the purposes of this section, where an individual or entity does not ordinarily prepare financial statements for audit or where financial statements for the fiscal year of the individual or entity immediately preceding the implementation of the investment have not been audited, unaudited statements may be used.</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Where fiscal year of an entity not complete<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><change>(6) Where the first fiscal year of an entity has not been completed immediately preceding the implementation of the investment, a reference in this section to fiscal year shall mean the fiscal period that ends immediately preceding the implementation.</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Value to be calculated in Canadian dollars<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><change>(7) The value of the assets calculated under this section shall be expressed in Canadian dollars.</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Power of Governor in Council<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><change><B>25.5</B> (1) On the referral of an investment under paragraph 25.3(6)(<I>a</I>) or subsection 25.3(7), the Governor in Council may, by order, within the prescribed period, take any measures in respect of the investment that the Governor in Council considers advisable to protect the national interest, including</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0"><change>(<I>a</I>) directing the non-Canadian not to implement the investment;</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0"><change>(<I>b</I>) authorizing the investment on condition that the non-Canadian</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="4" FirstLineIndent="0"><change>(i) give any undertakings to Her Majesty in right of Canada relating to the investment that the Governor in Council considers necessary in the circumstances, or</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="4" FirstLineIndent="0"><change>(ii) implement the investment on the terms and conditions contained in the order; or</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0"><change>(<I>c</I>) requiring the non-Canadian to divest themself of control of the Canadian business or their investment in the entity.</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Condition<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><change>(2) Where the Governor in Council proposes to authorize an investment under paragraph 25.5(1)(<I>b</I>) that is an investment described in paragraph 25.3(1)(<I>b</I>), the Governor in Council shall make it a condition of the investment that the aggregate of the total investment in the business that is beneficially owned by or on behalf of the foreign government, entities controlled by it and other foreign governments and entities that have invested in the business and with which the foreign government or an entity controlled by it is acting in concert with respect to the business does not exceed</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0"><change>(<I>a</I>) 20 per cent of the outstanding shares of any class of voting shares of a body corporate;</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0"><change>(<I>b</I>) 30 per cent of the outstanding shares of any class of non-voting shares of a body corporate; or</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0"><change>(<I>c</I>) 20 per cent of the value of the assets of the business, calculated in the manner described in section 25.4.</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Publication<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><change>(3) Where the Governor in Council proposes to authorize an investment under paragraph 25.5(1)(<I>b</I>) that is an investment described in paragraph 25.3(1)(<I>c</I>), the Governor in Council shall publish, on a day that is no later than the day that the order authorizing the investment is made, a report that explains why the investment is not contrary to the national interest, either by</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0"><change>(<I>a</I>) causing the report to be laid before both Houses of Parliament; or</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0"><change>(<I>b</I>) causing the report to be published in the <I>Canada Gazette</I>.</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Notice of order<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><change>(4) The Minister shall send a copy of the order to the non-Canadian or person or entity to whom it is directed without delay after it has been made.</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Requirement to comply with order<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><change>(5) The non-Canadian or other person or entity to whom the order is directed shall comply with the order.</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote><I>Statutory Instruments Act</I> does not apply<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><change>(6) The <I>Statutory Instruments Act</I> does not apply in respect of the order.</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Information for monitoring<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><change><B>25.6</B> A non-Canadian who implements an investment that has been authorized by an order made under section 25.5 shall submit any information in their possession relating to the investment that is required from time to time by the Director in order to permit the Director to determine whether the investment is being carried out in accordance with the order.</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Decisions and orders are final<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><change><B>25.7</B> Decisions of the Minister and orders of the Governor in Council under this Part are final and binding and, except for judicial review under the <I>Federal Courts Act</I>, are not subject to appeal or to review by any court.</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>5.</B> (1) The portion of subsection 26(1) of the Act before paragraph (<I>a</I>) is replaced by the following:</Para><ExplNote><Para Align="Yes" TopMargin="10" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><I>Clause 5</I>: (1) Existing text of relevant portion of subsection 26(1):</Para><Para Align="Yes" TopMargin="5" Size="8" Leading="9" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>26.</B> (1) Subject to subsections (2.1) and (2.2), for the purposes of this Act,</Para></ExplNote></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Rules respecting control of entities<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>26.</B> (1) Subject to subsections (2.1) <change>to</change> (2.2), for the purposes of this Act,</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes">(2) Subsection 26(2) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Para><ExplNote><Para Align="Yes" TopMargin="10" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(2) Existing text of subsection (2):</Para><Para Align="Yes" TopMargin="5" Size="8" Leading="9" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(2) Subject to subsections (2.1) and (2.2), where it can be established that a trust is not controlled in fact through the ownership of its voting interests, subsection (1) does not apply and the trust is a Canadian-controlled entity where two-thirds of its trustees are Canadians.</Para></ExplNote></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Trusts<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(2) Subject to subsections (2.1) <change>to</change> (2.2), <change>if</change> it can be established that a trust is not controlled in fact through the ownership of its voting interests, subsection (1) does not apply, and the trust is a Canadian-controlled entity <change>if</change> two-thirds of its trustees are Canadians.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes">(3) Section 26 of the Act is amended by adding the following after subsection (2.1):</Para><ExplNote><Para Align="Yes" TopMargin="10" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(3) New.</Para></ExplNote></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Minister may determine<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><change>(2.11) For the purposes of Part IV.1, in the case of an entity that qualifies as a Canadian-controlled entity by virtue of subsection (1) or (2), the Minister may nevertheless determine that the entity is not a Canadian-controlled entity if, after considering any information and evidence submitted by or on behalf of the entity or otherwise made available to the Minister or the Director, the Minister is satisfied that the entity is controlled in fact by one or more non-Canadians.</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes">(4) Subsection 26(2.2) of the English version of the Act is replaced by the following:</Para><ExplNote><Para Align="Yes" TopMargin="10" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(4) Existing text of subsection (2.2):</Para><Para Align="Yes" TopMargin="5" Size="8" Leading="9" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(2.2) Where an entity referred to in subsection (2.1) has refused or neglected to provide, within a reasonable time, information that the Minister or the Director has requested and that the Minister considers necessary in order to make a decision under that subsection, the Minister may declare that the entity is not a Canadian-controlled entity.</Para></ExplNote></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Minister may declare<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(2.2) <change>If</change> an entity referred to in subsection (2.1) <change>or (2.11)</change> has refused or neglected to provide, within a reasonable time, information that the Minister or the Director has requested and that the Minister considers necessary in order to make a decision under that subsection, the Minister may declare that the entity is not a Canadian-controlled entity.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes">(5) Subsection 26(2.4) of the English version of the Act is replaced by the following:</Para><ExplNote><Para Align="Yes" TopMargin="10" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(5) Existing text of subsection (2.4):</Para><Para Align="Yes" TopMargin="5" Size="8" Leading="9" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(2.4) The Minister shall forthwith inform the entity concerned, in writing, of any determination made under subsection (2.1) or declaration made under subsection (2.2), and of any date specified under subsection (2.3).</Para></ExplNote></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Entity to be informed<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(2.4) The Minister shall<change>, without delay,</change> inform the entity concerned, in writing, of any determination made under subsection (2.1) <change>or (2.11)</change> or declaration made under subsection (2.2), and of any date specified under subsection (2.3).</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes">(6) Section 26 of the Act is amended by adding the following after subsection (3):</Para><ExplNote><Para Align="Yes" TopMargin="10" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(6) New.</Para></ExplNote></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Exception<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><change>(3.1) Subsection (3) does not apply to a corporation for the purposes of Part IV.1.</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>6.</B> (1) The portion of subsection 28(2) of the Act before paragraph (<I>a</I>) is replaced by the following:</Para><ExplNote><Para Align="Yes" TopMargin="10" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><I>Clause 6</I>: (1) Existing text of relevant portion of subsection 28(2):</Para><Para Align="Yes" TopMargin="5" Size="8" Leading="9" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(2) Subject to subsections (4) and (5), for the purposes of this Act,</Para></ExplNote></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Rules and presumptions respecting control of entities<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(2) Subject to subsections (4) <change>to</change> (5), for the purposes of this Act,</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes">(2) The portion of subsection 28(3) of the Act before paragraph (<I>a</I>) is replaced by the following:</Para><ExplNote><Para Align="Yes" TopMargin="10" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(2) Existing text of relevant portion of subsection 28(3):</Para><Para Align="Yes" TopMargin="5" Size="8" Leading="9" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(3) Subject to subsections (4) and (5), for the purposes of this Act,</Para></ExplNote></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Rules and presumptions respecting acquisition of control<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(3) Subject to subsections (4) <change>to</change> (5), for the purposes of this Act,</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes">(3) Section 28 of the Act is amended by adding the following after subsection (4):</Para><ExplNote><Para Align="Yes" TopMargin="10" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(3) New.</Para></ExplNote></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Minister may determine<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><change>(4.1) For the purposes of Part IV.1, the Minister may, after considering any information and evidence submitted by or on behalf of an entity or otherwise made available to the Minister or the Director, determine that the entity is or is not controlled by another entity or that there has or has not been an acquisition of control of the entity, if the Minister is satisfied that the entity is or is not controlled in fact by that other entity or that there has or has not in fact been an acquisition of control of that entity, as the case may be.</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes">(4) Subsection 28(5) of the English version of the Act is replaced by the following:</Para><ExplNote><Para Align="Yes" TopMargin="10" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(4) Existing text of subsection (5):</Para><Para Align="Yes" TopMargin="5" Size="8" Leading="9" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(5) Where an entity referred to in subsection (4) has refused or neglected to provide, within a reasonable time, information that the Minister or the Director has requested and that the Minister considers necessary in order to make a decision under that subsection, the Minister may declare that the entity is or is not controlled by another entity or that there has or has not been an acquisition of control of the entity, as the case may be.</Para></ExplNote></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Minister may declare<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(5) <change>If</change> an entity referred to in subsection (4) <change>or (4.1)</change> has refused or neglected to provide, within a reasonable time, information that the Minister or the Director has requested and that the Minister considers necessary in order to make a decision under that subsection, the Minister may declare that the entity is or is not controlled by another entity or that there has or has not been an acquisition of control of the entity, as the case may be.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes">(5) Subsection 28(7) of the English version of the Act is replaced by the following:</Para><ExplNote><Para Align="Yes" TopMargin="10" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(5) Existing text of paragraph (7):</Para><Para Align="Yes" TopMargin="5" Size="8" Leading="9" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(7) The Minister shall forthwith inform the entity concerned, in writing, of any determination made under subsection (4) or declaration made under subsection (5), and of any date specified under subsection (6).</Para></ExplNote></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Entity to be informed<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(7) The Minister shall<change>, without delay,</change> inform the entity concerned, in writing, of any determination made under subsection (4) <change>or (4.1)</change> or declaration made under subsection (5), and of any date specified under subsection (6).</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>7.</B> (1) Subsection 36(1) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Para><ExplNote><Para Align="Yes" TopMargin="10" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><I>Clause 7</I>: (1) Existing text of subsection 36(1):</Para><Para Align="Yes" TopMargin="5" Size="8" Leading="9" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>36.</B> (1) Subject to subsections (3) and (4), all information obtained with respect to a Canadian, a non-Canadian or a business by the Minister or an officer or employee of Her Majesty in the course of the administration or enforcement of this Act is privileged and no one shall knowingly communicate or allow to be communicated any such information or allow anyone to inspect or to have access to any such information.</Para></ExplNote></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Privileged information<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>36.</B> (1) Subject to subsections (3) <change>to</change> (4), all information obtained with respect to a Canadian, a non-Canadian, a business or <change>an entity referred to in paragraph 25.1(<I>c</I>)</change> by the Minister or an officer or employee of Her Majesty in the course of the administration or enforcement of this Act is privileged and no one shall knowingly communicate or allow to be communicated any such information or allow anyone to inspect or to have access to any such information.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes">(2) Section 36 of the Act is amended by adding the following after subsection (3):</Para><ExplNote><Para Align="Yes" TopMargin="10" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(2) New.</Para></ExplNote></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Investigative bodies<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><change>(3.1) Information that is privileged under subsection (1) may be communicated or disclosed by the Minister to a prescribed investigative body, or an investigative body of a prescribed class, if the communication or disclosure is for the purposes of the administration or enforcement of Part IV.1 and that body’s lawful investigations. The information may also be communicated or disclosed by that body for the purposes of those investigations.</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes">(3) Subparagraph 36(4)(<I>e</I>)(iii) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Para><ExplNote><Para Align="Yes" TopMargin="10" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(3) Relevant portion of subsection (4):</Para><Para Align="Yes" TopMargin="5" Size="8" Leading="9" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(4) Nothing in this section prohibits the communication or disclosure of</Para><Para Align="No" TopMargin="5" Size="8" Leading="9" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">. . . </Para><Para Align="No" TopMargin="5" Size="8" Leading="9" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>e</I>) information contained in</Para><Para Align="No" TopMargin="5" Size="8" Leading="9" LeftMargin="4" FirstLineIndent="0">. . . </Para><Para Align="No" TopMargin="5" Size="8" Leading="9" LeftMargin="4" FirstLineIndent="0">(iii) any demand sent by the Minister under section 39; or</Para></ExplNote></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="4" FirstLineIndent="0">(iii) any demand sent by the Minister under section 39<change>, other than a demand sent for the purposes of the administration or enforcement of Part IV.1</change>; or</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>8.</B> (1) Paragraph 39(1)(<I>b</I>) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Para><ExplNote><Para Align="Yes" TopMargin="10" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><I>Clause 8</I>: (1) Relevant portion of paragraph 39(1):</Para><Para Align="Yes" TopMargin="5" Size="8" Leading="9" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>39.</B> (1) Where the Minister believes that a non-Canadian, contrary to this Act,</Para><Para Align="No" TopMargin="5" Size="8" Leading="9" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">. . . </Para><Para Align="No" TopMargin="5" Size="8" Leading="9" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>b</I>) has implemented an investment the implementation of which is prohibited by section 16 or 24,</Para></ExplNote></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>b</I>) has implemented an investment the implementation of which is prohibited by section 16, 25, <change>25.2</change> or <change>25.3</change>,</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes">(2) Subsection 39(1) of the Act is amended by adding the following after paragraph 39(1)(<I>d</I>):</Para><ExplNote><Para Align="Yes" TopMargin="10" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(2) New.</Para></ExplNote></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0"><change>(<I>d.1</I>) has failed to divest themself of control of a Canadian business or of their investment in an entity as required by an order made under section 25.5,</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0"><change>(<I>d.2</I>) has failed to comply with an undertaking given to Her Majesty in right of Canada pursuant to an order made under section 25.5,</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0"><change>(<I>d.3</I>) has failed to comply with an order made under section 25.5,</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes">(3) Subsection 39(2) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Para><ExplNote><Para Align="Yes" TopMargin="10" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(3) Existing text of subsection (2):</Para><Para Align="Yes" TopMargin="5" Size="8" Leading="9" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(2) A demand under subsection (1) shall indicate the nature of the proceedings that may be taken under this Act against the non-Canadian to whom it is sent in the event that the non-Canadian fails to comply therewith.</Para></ExplNote></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Ministerial demand<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><change>(1.1) If the Minister believes that a person or an entity, contrary to this Act, has failed to comply with an order under subsection 25.5(5) or to submit any information under section 25.6, the Minister may send a demand to the person or entity requiring them immediately or within any period that may be specified in the demand, to cease the contravention, to remedy the default or to show cause why there is no contravention of the Act.</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Contents of demand<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(2) A demand under subsection (1) <change>or (1.1)</change> shall indicate the nature of the proceedings that may be taken under this Act against the non-Canadian <change>or person or entity</change> to whom it is sent in the event that the non-Canadian <change>or person or entity</change> fails to comply <change>with the demand</change>.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>9.</B> (1) Subsection 40(1) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Para><ExplNote><Para Align="Yes" TopMargin="10" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><I>Clause 9</I>: (1) Existing text of subsection 40(1):</Para><Para Align="Yes" TopMargin="5" Size="8" Leading="9" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>40.</B> (1) Where a non-Canadian fails to comply with a demand under section 39, an application on behalf of the Minister may be made to a superior court for an order under subsection (2).</Para></ExplNote></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Application for court order<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>40.</B> (1) <change>If</change> a non-Canadian <change>or any other person or entity</change> fails to comply with a demand under section 39, an application on behalf of the Minister may be made to a superior court for an order under subsection (2) <change>or (2.1)</change>.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes">(2) Paragraph 40(2)(<I>a</I>) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Para><ExplNote><Para Align="Yes" TopMargin="10" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(2) Relevant portion of subsection (2):</Para><Para Align="Yes" TopMargin="5" Size="8" Leading="9" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(2) Where, at the conclusion of the hearing on an application referred to in subsection (1), the superior court decides that the Minister was justified in sending a demand to the non-Canadian under section 39 and that the non-Canadian has failed to comply therewith, the court may make such order or orders as, in its opinion, the circumstances require, including, without limiting the generality of the foregoing, an order</Para><Para Align="No" TopMargin="5" Size="8" Leading="9" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>a</I>) directing the non-Canadian to divest himself of control of the Canadian business on such terms and conditions as the court deems just and reasonable;</Para></ExplNote></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>a</I>) directing the non-Canadian to divest <change>themself</change> of control of the Canadian business<change>, or to divest themself of their investment in the entity,</change> on <change>any</change> terms and conditions <change>that</change> the court deems just and reasonable;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes">(3) Subsection 40(2) of the Act is amended by adding the following after paragraph (<I>c</I>):</Para><ExplNote><Para Align="Yes" TopMargin="10" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(3) New.</Para></ExplNote></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0"><change>(<I>c.1</I>) directing the non-Canadian to comply with a written undertaking given to Her Majesty in right of Canada pursuant to an order made under section 25.5;</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes">(4) Subsections 40(3) and (4) of the Act are replaced by the following:</Para><ExplNote><Para Align="Yes" TopMargin="10" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(4) Existing text of subsections (3) and (4):</Para><Para Align="Yes" TopMargin="5" Size="8" Leading="9" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(3) A penalty imposed by an order made under paragraph (2)(<I>d</I>) is a debt due to Her Majesty in right of Canada and is recoverable as such in a superior court.</Para><Para Align="Yes" TopMargin="5" Size="8" Leading="9" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(4) Every one who fails or refuses to comply with an order made by a superior court under subsection (2) that is directed to him may be cited and punished by the court that made the order, as for other contempts of that court.</Para></ExplNote></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Court orders — person or entity<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><change>(2.1) If, at the conclusion of the hearing on an application referred to in subsection (1), the superior court decides that the Minister was justified in sending a demand to a person or an entity under section 39 and that the person or entity has failed to comply with it, the court may make any order or orders that, in its opinion, the circumstances require, including, without limiting the generality of the foregoing, an order against the person or entity imposing a penalty not exceeding ten thousand dollars for each day on which the person or entity is in contravention of any provision of this Act.</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Penalties recoverable as debts<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(3) A penalty imposed by an order made under paragraph (2)(<I>d</I>) <change>or subsection (2.1)</change> is a debt due to Her Majesty in right of Canada and is recoverable as such in a superior court.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Contempt of court<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(4) Every one who fails or refuses to comply with an order that is directed to <change>them</change> made by a superior court under subsection (2) <change>or (2.1)</change> may be cited and punished by the court that made the order, as for other contempts of that court.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Coming into force<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>10.</B> This Act comes into force on the earlier of</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0" Bold="Yes">(<I>a</I>) the day that is one year after the day on which it is assented to; and</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0" Bold="Yes">(<I>b</I>) the day that the Governor in Council orders it into force.</Para></Block><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="BPT_ImprintE"><br/><br/>Published under authority of the Senate of Canada</Para></Block><Block Align="Yes" LineCnt="N"><Para NoLineBreak="Yes" NoHtml="Yes" Leading="0" Size="0" TopMargin="0" BottomMargin="0"></Para></Block></Bill_Part></Bill>
