<?xml version="1.0"?>
<Bill RHead_reign="60 Eliz. II" RHead_ParlYear="2011" DocumentTitle="BILL C-319" Bill_No="C-319" Document_No="411249" xml:lang="EN" Bill_Type="Non-amending" Stage_Name="First-Reading-House" Reprint="No" xml:space="preserve" ChapterNo_E="C. " ChapterNo_F="ch. " Bill-Origin="commons"><Bill_Part Part_Type="Cover" CountLines="No"><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="CovBillNo">C-319</Para></Block><Block><Para TopMargin="24" Size="9" Leading="10" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0" TextAlign="Center">First Session, Forty-first Parliament,</Para></Block><Block><Para Size="9" Leading="10" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0" TextAlign="Center">60 Elizabeth II, 2011</Para></Block><Block><Para TopMargin="48" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0" Bold="Yes" TextAlign="Center">HOUSE OF COMMONS OF CANADA</Para></Block><Block><Para TopMargin="42" Size="18" Leading="20" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0" Bold="Yes" TextAlign="Center">BILL C-319</Para></Block><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="CovLongTitle">An Act respecting a national strategy to reduce the incidence of serious injury in amateur sport</Para></Block><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="COV_StageLine"></Para></Block><Block><Para Size="9" AllCaps="Yes" Hyphenate="OFF">first reading, October 4, 2011</Para></Block><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="COV_StageLine"></Para></Block><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="Cover_Sponsors"><SC SC_PerCent="85">Mr. Thibeault</SC></Para></Block><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="Cover_DocNo">411249</Para></Block></Bill_Part><Bill_Part CountLines="No" Part_Type="InsideCover"><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="BPT_InsideCoverE">Also available on the Parliament of Canada Web Site at the following address:<br/><B>http://www.parl.gc.ca</B></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><Para TopMargin="108" BottomMargin="4" Size="10" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">SUMMARY</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" Size="8" Leading="9" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">This enactment requires the Minister of Health and the Minister of State (Sport) to convene a conference with the provincial and territorial ministers responsible for health and sport and with representatives of the athletic and medical communities for the purpose of developing a national strategy to reduce the incidence of serious injury in amateur sport. It also authorizes the Minister of Finance to establish guidelines in respect of the allocation of funding to provincial and territorial governments that have enacted legislation to implement that strategy.</Para></Block></Bill_Part><Bill_Part Part_Type="MainText" CountLines="Yes" RunningHead_E="National Strategy for Serious Injury Reduction in Amateur Sport"><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="MainText_DocNo">411249</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes"><Para Style="Session_Reign">1st Session, 41st Parliament,</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes"><Para Style="Session_Reign">60 Elizabeth II, 2011</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes"><Para Style="MainBillOrigin">house of commons of canada</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes"><Para Bold="Yes" Style="MAIN@BillNo_Title">BILL C-319</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes"><Para Style="MAIN@ti;04">An Act respecting a national strategy to reduce the incidence of serious injury in amateur sport</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><MarginalNote>Preamble<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">Whereas sport is a cultural institution that merits protection and support from the Government of Canada; </Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">Whereas recent medical research has demonstrated the pervasiveness of serious injury in amateur sport;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">Whereas many sports injuries are preventable through the effective dissemination of appropriate information;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">Whereas a concerted effort by committed communities, governments and organizations across Canada can make a tangible difference in preventing deaths and serious injuries that result from participation in amateur sport and athletics;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">Whereas injuries in amateur sport are a significant public health issue and it is important to reduce the incidence of such injuries and their impact on Canadians, particularly the long-term individual and societal impacts that can result from serious sports injuries;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">Whereas cerebral concussions have demonstrated cumulative and long-lasting effects on memory, judgement, social conduct, reflexes, speech, balance and coordination;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">Whereas it is in the interest of all Canadians that a national strategy to reduce the incidence of injury in amateur sport be developed and implemented with a view to changing the existing attitudes of Canadians towards sports injuries, mobilizing individuals and organizations and fostering further policy development in this area;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">And whereas the Government of Canada, in consultation with the ministers responsible for health care and sport in each province and territory, wishes to encourage the development of a national strategy to reduce the incidence of injury in amateur sport;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">Now, therefore, Her Majesty, by and with the advice and consent of the Senate and House of Commons of Canada, enacts as follows:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:SHORT TITLE--><Para TopMargin="10" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">SHORT TITLE</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Short title<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>1.</B> This Act may be cited as the <I>National Strategy for Serious Injury Reduction in Amateur Sport Act</I>.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:INTERPRETATION--><Para TopMargin="10" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">INTERPRETATION</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Definitions<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>2.</B> The following definitions apply in this Act.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><MarginalNote>“Minister”<br/>« <I>ministre</I> »<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0">“Minister” means the Minister of Health.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><MarginalNote>“national strategy”<br/>« <I>stratégie nationale</I> »<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0">“national strategy” means a national strategy to reduce the incidence of serious injury in amateur sport.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><MarginalNote>“provincial and territorial ministers”<br/>« <I>ministres provinciaux et territoriaux</I> »<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0">“provincial and territorial ministers” means the provincial and territorial ministers responsible for health and the provincial and territorial ministers responsible for sport.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:NATIONAL STRATEGY--><Para TopMargin="10" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">NATIONAL STRATEGY</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Conference<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>3.</B> The Minister and the Minister of State (Sport) must, within six months after this Act comes into force, convene a conference with provincial and territorial ministers and representatives of the athletic and medical communities for the purpose of developing a national strategy that includes</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>a</I>) the establishment of a national medical surveillance program to properly track incidence rates and the associated economic costs of injuries in amateur sport;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>b</I>) the establishment of guidelines regarding the prevention, identification, treatment and management of cerebral concussions in amateur athletes, including the criteria that must be met before amateur athletes are permitted to return to play after suffering a cerebral concussion;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>c</I>) the preparation of a submission to the Minister of Justice proposing an amendment to the <I>Criminal Code</I> that would make it an offence for a coach or any other person in a position of authority to knowingly permit a participant to return to play without meeting the criteria specified under the guidelines referred to in paragraph (<I>b</I>);</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>d</I>) the establishment of national standards for the training of coaches and other persons involved in amateur sport with respect to the health and safety of participants; and</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>e</I>) the creation of a comprehensive standard- ized educational program for coaches and other persons involved in amateur sport that is designed to enhance participant safety at all levels of amateur sport.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Preparation and publication of report<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>4.</B> The Minister must prepare a report setting out the national strategy and publish it on the departmental website within one year after the conclusion of the conference referred to in section 3.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Report to Parliament<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>5.</B> The Minister must cause a copy of the report referred to in section 4 to be laid before each House of Parliament on any of the first 90 days on which that House is sitting after the report has been published on the departmental website.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Provincial and territorial funding<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>6.</B> The Minister of Finance may, on the advice of the Minister, establish guidelines regarding the allocation of funding, for the purpose of implementing the national strategy, to provincial and territorial governments that have enacted legislation to implement that strategy and have met the criteria prescribed by regulation.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:REVIEW AND REPORT--><Para TopMargin="10" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">REVIEW AND REPORT</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Review<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>7.</B> The Government of Canada must</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>a</I>) complete a review of the effectiveness of the national strategy no later than five years after the day on which the report referred to in section 4 is published on the departmental website; and</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>b</I>) table a report on its findings before each House of Parliament within the next ten sitting days after the review is completed.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:REGULATIONS--><Para TopMargin="10" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">REGULATIONS</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Regulations<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>8.</B> The Governor in Council may make regulations for carrying out the purposes and provisions of this Act.</Para></Block><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="BPT_ImprintE">Published under authority of the Speaker of the House of Commons<br/>Available from:<br/>Publishing and Depository Services<br/>Public Works and Government Services Canada<br/>Ottawa, Ontario K1A 0S5<br/>Telephone: 613-941-5995 or 1-800-635-7943<br/>Fax: 613-954-5779 or 1-800-565-7757<br/>publications@tpsgc-pwgsc.gc.ca<br/>http://publications.gc.ca</Para></Block><Block Align="Yes" LineCnt="N"><Para NoLineBreak="Yes" NoHtml="Yes" Leading="0" Size="0" TopMargin="0" BottomMargin="0"></Para></Block></Bill_Part></Bill>
