<?xml version="1.0"?>
<Bill RHead_reign="60 Eliz. II" RHead_ParlYear="2011" DocumentTitle="BILL C-330" Bill_No="C-330" Document_No="411371" xml:lang="EN" Bill_Type="Non-amending" Stage_Name="First-Reading-House" Reprint="No" xml:space="preserve" ChapterNo_E="C. " ChapterNo_F="ch. " Bill-Origin="commons"><Bill_Part Part_Type="Cover" CountLines="No"><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="CovBillNo">C-330</Para></Block><Block><Para TopMargin="24" Size="9" Leading="10" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0" TextAlign="Center">First Session, Forty-first Parliament,</Para></Block><Block><Para Size="9" Leading="10" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0" TextAlign="Center">60 Elizabeth II, 2011</Para></Block><Block><Para TopMargin="48" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0" Bold="Yes" TextAlign="Center">HOUSE OF COMMONS OF CANADA</Para></Block><Block><Para TopMargin="42" Size="18" Leading="20" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0" Bold="Yes" TextAlign="Center">BILL C-330</Para></Block><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="CovLongTitle">An Act to establish the Advisory Committee for Effective Treatment and Rehabilitation of Veterans with Service-Related Brain Injuries</Para></Block><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="COV_StageLine"></Para></Block><Block><Para Size="9" AllCaps="Yes" Hyphenate="OFF">first reading, October 7, 2011</Para></Block><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="COV_StageLine"></Para></Block><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="Cover_Sponsors"><SC SC_PerCent="85">Ms. Duncan</SC> (<I>Etobicoke North</I>)</Para></Block><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="Cover_DocNo">411371</Para></Block></Bill_Part><Bill_Part CountLines="No" Part_Type="InsideCover"><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="BPT_InsideCoverE">Also available on the Parliament of Canada Web Site at the following address:<br/><B>http://www.parl.gc.ca</B></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><Para TopMargin="108" BottomMargin="4" Size="10" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">SUMMARY</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" Size="8" Leading="9" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">This enactment establishes the Advisory Committee for Effective Treatment and Rehabilitation of Veterans with Service-Related Brain Injuries and sets out the composition, mandate and duties of the Committee.</Para></Block></Bill_Part><Bill_Part Part_Type="MainText" CountLines="Yes" RunningHead_E="Veterans with Service-Related Brain Injuries"><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="MainText_DocNo">411371</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes"><Para Style="Session_Reign">1st Session, 41st Parliament,</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes"><Para Style="Session_Reign">60 Elizabeth II, 2011</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes"><Para Style="MainBillOrigin">house of commons of canada</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes"><Para Bold="Yes" Style="MAIN@BillNo_Title">BILL C-330</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes"><Para Style="MAIN@ti;04">An Act to establish the Advisory Committee for Effective Treatment and Rehabilitation of Veterans with Service-Related Brain Injuries</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><MarginalNote>Preamble<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">Whereas former members of the Canadian Forces have made many sacrifices for their loved ones and their country;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">Whereas members of the Canadian Forces serving in Afghanistan are at increased risk from blast weapons, which cause injury as a result of supersonic waves of intense air pressure and a variety of other mechanisms, including blunt force;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">Whereas exposure to severe blast energy can cause multiple injuries, including blast lung, ruptured tympanic membranes, and transient cardio-respiratory effects, and evidence from animal research, case reports, and clinical experience show that lower primary energy may cause brain injuries;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">Whereas injuries caused by a blast effect are more common among combat troops in the Middle East than among those in everyday civilian life;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">Whereas American researchers have found that episodes of mild traumatic brain injury were self-reported by 12% to 20% of American military members returning from deployment in the Middle East;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">Whereas, although most patients who suffer from these episodes recover completely within three months, a small minority report persistent non-specific symptoms;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">Whereas persistent symptoms of a brain injury are difficult to recognize and require coordinated assessment from the primary health care provider;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">Whereas the Department of Veterans Affairs should develop additional services to respond to the health care needs of former members of the Canadian Forces suffering from persistent symptoms due to a service-related brain injury;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">And whereas it is part of the Canadian culture and heritage to acknowledge the services rendered by former members of the Canadian Forces and to be responsive to their health care needs;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">Now, therefore, Her Majesty, by and with the advice and consent of the Senate and House of Commons of Canada, enacts as follows:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:SHORT TITLE--><Para TopMargin="10" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">SHORT TITLE</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Short title<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>1.</B> This Act may be cited as the <I>Veterans with Service-Related Brain Injuries Act</I>.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:INTERPRETATION--><Para TopMargin="10" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">INTERPRETATION</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Definitions<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>2.</B> The definitions in this section apply in this Act.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><MarginalNote>“Committee”<br/>« <I>Comité</I> »<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0">“Committee” means the Advisory Committee for Effective Treatment and Rehabilitation of Veterans with Service-Related Brain Injuries established under section 3.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><MarginalNote>“Minister”<br/>« <I>ministre</I> »<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0">“Minister” means the Minister of Veterans Affairs.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><MarginalNote>“service-related brain injury”<br/>« <I>lésion cérébrale liée au service</I> »<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0">“service-related brain injury” means any injury to the brain that </Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>a</I>) was attributable to or was incurred during special duty service as defined in subsection 2(1) of the <I>Canadian Forces Members and Veterans Re-establishment and Compensation Act</I>; or</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>b</I>) arose out of or was directly connected with service in the Canadian Forces.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><MarginalNote>“veteran”<br/>« <I>vétéran</I> »<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0">“veteran” means a former officer or a former non-commissioned member of the Canadian Forces.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:COMMITTEE AND MEMBERS--><Para TopMargin="10" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">COMMITTEE AND MEMBERS</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Advisory committee<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>3.</B> (1) The Advisory Committee for Effective Treatment and Rehabilitation of Veterans with Service-Related Brain Injuries is established within the Department of Veterans Affairs.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Role<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(2) The role of the Committee is to report to, advise and assist the Minister on matters related to this Act.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Membership<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>4.</B> (1) The Committee must consist of not more than eight persons appointed by the Governor in Council on the recommendation of the Minister and selected from among</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>a</I>) persons employed in the Department of Veterans Affairs;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>b</I>) persons employed in the Department of National Defence;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>c</I>) officers or non-commissioned members of the Canadian Forces;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>d</I>) veterans suffering from a service-related brain injury or their family members;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>e</I>) health professionals; and</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>f</I>) persons associated with an advocacy group or a volunteer organization involved with veterans or other persons affected by a brain injury.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Term<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(2) A member of the Committee must be appointed to hold office for a term not exceeding three years and is eligible for reappointment for one or more additional terms.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Chairperson<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(3) The Minister must designate one of the members to be the chairperson of the Committee.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Remuneration<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>5.</B> (1) A member of the Committee must be paid, for the performance of his or her duties and functions, any remuneration that may be fixed by the Governor in Council.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Expenses<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(2) A member of the Committee is entitled to be reimbursed, in accordance with Treasury Board directives, for reasonable travel, living and other expenses incurred in the performance of his or her duties and functions while absent from his or her ordinary place of work, in the case of a full-time member, or from his or her ordinary place of residence, in the case of a part-time member.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Payment<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(3) The Minister must pay the remuneration and reimburse the expenses determined under subsections (1) and (2).</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Staff<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>6.</B> The Advisory Committee may employ any officers and employees and engage the services of any agents and mandataries, advisers and experts that it considers necessary to carry out its purpose.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:COMMITTEE OBJECTIVE--><Para TopMargin="10" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">COMMITTEE OBJECTIVE</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Objective<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>7.</B> The objective of the Committee is to ensure the effective treatment and rehabilitation of veterans with a service-related brain injury.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:DUTIES AND FUNCTIONS--><Para TopMargin="10" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">DUTIES AND FUNCTIONS</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Duties and functions<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>8.</B> (1) Within two years after the coming into force of this Act, the Committee must</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>a</I>) evaluate the care and support provided by the Department of Veterans Affairs to veterans with a service-related brain injury and to their families;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>b</I>) identify facilities within the Department of Veterans Affairs where program enhancement is needed to meet the objective set out in section 7;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>c</I>) identify successful programs for the treatment and rehabilitation of veterans with a service-related brain injury and recommend their implementation within facilities of the Department of Veterans Affairs;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>d</I>) advise the Minister on the development of policies related to the objective set out in section 7, including the improvement of care programs for veterans with a service-related brain injury, and the establishment of education and training programs for employees of the Department of Veterans Affairs;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>e</I>) advise the Minister on research needs and priorities relevant to the case of veterans with a service-related brain injury; and</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>f</I>) advise the Minister on the appropriate allocation of resources for the activities provided in paragraph (<I>e</I>).</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Representations<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(2) The Committee may, as it deems expedient, make written representations to the Minister on the matters enumerated in subsection (1).</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:REPORTS--><Para TopMargin="10" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">REPORTS</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Report<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>9.</B> (1) The Committee must report by April 1 of every year to the Minister on the measures put in place and the resources applied by Department of Veterans Affairs to achieve the objective set out in section 7.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Public report<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(2) The Committee report referred to in subsection (1), including its recommendations and reasons, must be made public and must be sent to the Minister, who must cause a copy of the report to be laid before each House of Parliament on any of the first 15 days on which that House is sitting after the Minister receives it.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Response<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(3) The Minister must prepare and publish a response to the report received pursuant to subsection (2) and must cause a copy of the response to be laid before each House of Parliament on any of the first 15 days on which that House is sitting after the expiry of 90 days from the day on which the Minister received the report.</Para></Block><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="BPT_ImprintE">Published under authority of the Speaker of the House of Commons<br/>Available from:<br/>Publishing and Depository Services<br/>Public Works and Government Services Canada<br/>Ottawa, Ontario K1A 0S5<br/>Telephone: 613-941-5995 or 1-800-635-7943<br/>Fax: 613-954-5779 or 1-800-565-7757<br/>publications@tpsgc-pwgsc.gc.ca<br/>http://publications.gc.ca</Para></Block><Block Align="Yes" LineCnt="N"><Para NoLineBreak="Yes" NoHtml="Yes" Leading="0" Size="0" TopMargin="0" BottomMargin="0"></Para></Block></Bill_Part></Bill>
