<?xml version="1.0"?>
<Bill RHead_reign="60 Eliz. II" RHead_ParlYear="2011" DocumentTitle="BILL C-359" Bill_No="C-359" Document_No="411326" xml:lang="EN" Bill_Type="Non-amending" Stage_Name="First-Reading-House" Reprint="No" xml:space="preserve" ChapterNo_E="C. " ChapterNo_F="ch. " Bill-Origin="commons"><Bill_Part Part_Type="Cover" CountLines="No"><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="CovBillNo">C-359</Para></Block><Block><Para TopMargin="24" Size="9" Leading="10" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0" TextAlign="Center">First Session, Forty-first Parliament,</Para></Block><Block><Para Size="9" Leading="10" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0" TextAlign="Center">60 Elizabeth II, 2011</Para></Block><Block><Para TopMargin="48" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0" Bold="Yes" TextAlign="Center">HOUSE OF COMMONS OF CANADA</Para></Block><Block><Para TopMargin="42" Size="18" Leading="20" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0" Bold="Yes" TextAlign="Center">BILL C-359</Para></Block><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="CovLongTitle">An Act to Protect Canadian Citizens Abroad</Para></Block><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="COV_StageLine"></Para></Block><Block><Para Size="9" AllCaps="Yes" Hyphenate="OFF">first reading, November 25, 2011</Para></Block><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="COV_StageLine"></Para></Block><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="Cover_Sponsors"><SC SC_PerCent="85">Mr. Cotler</SC></Para></Block><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="Cover_DocNo">411326</Para></Block></Bill_Part><Bill_Part CountLines="No" Part_Type="InsideCover"><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="BPT_InsideCoverE">Also available on the Parliament of Canada Web Site at the following address:<br/><B>http://www.parl.gc.ca</B></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><Para TopMargin="108" BottomMargin="4" Size="10" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">SUMMARY</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" Size="8" Leading="9" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">This enactment confirms and particularizes the obligations that the Government of Canada owes to Canadian citizens outside the country who are detained, stranded or in captivity or who have disappeared.</Para></Block></Bill_Part><Bill_Part Part_Type="MainText" CountLines="Yes" RunningHead_E="Protecting Canadians Abroad"><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="MainText_DocNo">411326</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes"><Para Style="Session_Reign">1st Session, 41st Parliament,</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes"><Para Style="Session_Reign">60 Elizabeth II, 2011</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes"><Para Style="MainBillOrigin">house of commons of canada</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes"><Para Bold="Yes" Style="MAIN@BillNo_Title">BILL C-359</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes"><Para Style="MAIN@ti;04">An Act to Protect Canadian Citizens Abroad</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Preamble<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">Whereas the conferral of Canadian citizenship upon an individual implies certain obligations on the part of the Government of Canada;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">Whereas all Canadian citizens deserve to benefit equally from the rights conferred through citizenship;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">And whereas all Canadian citizens deserve the protection of the Government of Canada while located abroad, in a manner consistent with domestic law and international obligations;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">Now, therefore, Her Majesty, by and with the advice and consent of the Senate and House of Commons of Canada, enacts as follows:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:SHORT TITLE--><Para TopMargin="10" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">SHORT TITLE</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Short title<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>1.</B> This Act may be cited as the <I>Protecting Canadians Abroad Act</I>.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:PART 1--><Para TopMargin="10" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">PART 1</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:INTERPRETATION--><Para TopMargin="5" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">INTERPRETATION</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Definitions<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>2.</B> The following definitions apply in this Act.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><MarginalNote>“Canadian”<br/>« <I>Canadien</I> »<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0">“Canadian” means a Canadian citizen and, for greater certainty, includes Canadian dual citizens.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><MarginalNote>“Canadian official”<br/>« <I>fonctionnaire canadien</I> »<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0">“Canadian official” means any employee of the Government of Canada or the government of a province or territory of Canada and, for greater certainty, includes consular officials.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><MarginalNote>“captured”<br/>« <I>capturé</I> »<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0">“captured” means being compelled, through force or threat of force, to remain in the custody of an entity, other than the Government of Canada or a foreign government, and includes being captured incommunicado where appli- cable.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><MarginalNote>“case management judge”<br/>« <I>juge responsable de la gestion de l’instance</I> »<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0">“case management judge” means a case management judge referred to in Rule 385 of the <I>Federal Courts Rules</I>.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><MarginalNote>“Committee against Torture”<br/>« <I>Comité contre la torture</I> »<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0">“Committee against Torture” means the body established pursuant to Article 17 of the <I>Convention against Torture and Other Cruel, Inhuman or Degrading Treatment or Punishment</I>.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><MarginalNote>“consular official”<br/>« <I>fonctionnaire consulaire</I> »<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0">“consular official” means an employee of the Government of Canada who is trained and employed to provide consular services to Canadians travelling or living outside of Canada.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><MarginalNote>“designated contact”<br/>« <I>contact désigné</I> »<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0">“designated contact” means:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>a</I>) any individual designated as a contact person by a Canadian under this Act orally or in writing; or</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>b</I>) in those circumstances where a consular official is unable to communicate with a Canadian for the purposes of this Act,</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="4" FirstLineIndent="0">(i) the individual designated as the emergency contact person in the Canadian’s passport application or, where an emergency contact is unavailable, the guarantor of the Canadian’s passport application, or</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="4" FirstLineIndent="0">(ii) where a Canadian passport is unavailable for the Canadian, an adult member of the Canadian’s family with whom he or she lives or, if such a member is unavailable, any member of the Canadian’s immediate family.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><MarginalNote>“detained”<br/>« <I>détenu</I> »<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0">“detained” means being compelled, through force or threat of force, to remain in the custody of a foreign government, and includes being detained incommunicado where applicable.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><MarginalNote>“disappeared”<br/>« <I>disparu</I> »<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0">“disappeared” means being detained or captured, followed by a refusal to acknowledge the deprivation of freedom or by concealment of the fate or whereabouts of the detained or captured Canadian.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><MarginalNote>“foreign government”<br/>« <I>gouvernement étranger</I> »<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0">“foreign government” means a governmental authority not constituted pursuant to the laws of Canada.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><MarginalNote>“incommunicado”<br/>« <I>sans contact avec l’extérieur</I> »<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0">“incommunicado” means being held in conditions that make it impossible to communicate with outsiders.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><MarginalNote>“Minister”<br/>« <I>ministre</I> »<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0">“Minister” means the Minister of Foreign Affairs and International Trade.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><MarginalNote>“personally identifiable information”<br/>« <I>renseignement d’identification personnelle</I> »<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0">“personally identifiable information” means information that can be used, alone or in conjunction with other information, to uniquely identify a single individual.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><MarginalNote>“repatriation”<br/>« <I>rapatriement</I> »<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0">“repatriation” means the return of a detained or stranded Canadian to Canada.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><MarginalNote>“specially managed proceeding”<br/>« <I>instance à gestion spéciale</I> »<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0">“specially managed proceeding” means a specially managed proceeding referred to in Rule 385 of the <I>Federal Courts Rules</I>.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><MarginalNote>“stranded”<br/>« <I>bloqué à l’étranger</I> »<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0">“stranded” means being outside of Canada and unable to return to Canada for any reason other than</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>a</I>) being detained or captured or having disappeared;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>b</I>) being involved in a judicial process that conforms to the principles of fundamental justice;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>c</I>) a natural disaster; or</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>d</I>) solely because the price of transportation to Canada cannot be paid.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><MarginalNote>“torture”<br/>« <I>torture</I> »<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0">“torture” means any act or omission by which severe pain or suffering, whether physical or mental, is intentionally inflicted on a person</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>a</I>) for a purpose including</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="4" FirstLineIndent="0">(i) obtaining from the person or from a third person information or a statement,</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="4" FirstLineIndent="0">(ii) punishing the person for an act that the person or a third person has committed or is suspected of having committed, and</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="4" FirstLineIndent="0">(iii) intimidating or coercing the person or a third person, or </Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>b</I>) for any reason based on discrimination of any kind,</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0">but does not include any act or omission arising only from, inherent in or incidental to lawful sanctions.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><MarginalNote>“trial management conference”<br/>« <I>conférence de gestion de l’instruction</I> »<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0">“trial management conference” means a trial management conference referred to in Rule 270 of the <I>Federal Courts Rules</I>.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Rights preserved<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>3.</B> Nothing in this Act is to be interpreted in a manner to read down, abrogate, eliminate, or otherwise limit in any way any rights held by individuals with ties to Canada, whether they be Canadian citizens or not.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:PART 2--><Para TopMargin="10" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">PART 2</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:DETAINED CANADIANS--><Para TopMargin="5" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">DETAINED CANADIANS</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Obligation to inform<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>4.</B> (1) A Canadian official, other than a consular official, who has reasonable grounds to believe that a Canadian is being detained must immediately inform a consular official.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Consular investigation<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(2) A consular official who has reasonable grounds to believe that a Canadian is being detained, or who has been contacted by a Canadian official pursuant to subsection (1), must investigate in a timely manner in order to determine the situation of that Canadian.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Continuation of obligation<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(3) The obligation referred to in subsection (2) remains until a consular official has either confirmed with a foreign government that it is detaining the Canadian referred to in that subsection or confirmed with that Canadian that he or she is not being detained.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Consular visits<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>5.</B> (1) A detained Canadian has the right to be visited by a consular official in a timely manner where possible once a consular official becomes apprised of his or her detention.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Visit at regular intervals<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(2) A detained Canadian, after the initial visit, has the right to be visited by a consular official at regular intervals thereafter where possible, the frequency of such visits being determined by all relevant circumstances, including the seriousness of the allegations against him or her, the conditions of his or her detention, and the likelihood of his or her being tortured.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Canadian released<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(3) Where a Canadian is detained and released before a consular official has the opportunity to visit him or her, he or she has the right to be visited by a consular official to discuss the circumstances surrounding his or her detention.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Monitoring conditions of detention<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>6.</B> (1) A consular official must, to the best of his or her ability, monitor the condition of the detained Canadian and the conditions of his or her detention.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Notification of torture<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(2) A Canadian official who has reasonable grounds to believe that a detained Canadian has been, is being or may be tortured, in the context of his or her detention, must as soon as possible notify the Minister, the highest-ranking member of the relevant Canadian embassy, consulate, high commission or other diplomatic mission and a designated contact of the detained Canadian of this belief.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Notification of torture<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(3) A Canadian official who is told by a detained Canadian that he or she has been tortured, or threatened with torture, in the context of his or her detention must as soon as possible notify the Minister, the highest-ranking member of the relevant Canadian embassy, consulate, high commission or other diplomatic mission and a designated contact of the detained Canadian of this statement.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Exception<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(4) Despite subsection (3), when a detained Canadian requests that the Canadian official not inform the designated contact of his or her allegations of torture, the Canadian official must note it and comply with the request.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Private access<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(5) A consular official who is unable to gain private access to a detained Canadian must as soon as possible notify the Minister, the highest-ranking member of the relevant Canadian embassy, consulate, high commission or other diplomatic mission and a designated contact of the detained Canadian of this situation.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Legal representation<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>7.</B> During each visit, a consular official must raise the issue of legal representation with a detained Canadian and must place him or her in contact with a lawyer or other legal representative should he or she desire one.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Obligation to notify<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>8.</B> (1) A consular official with reasonable grounds to believe that a Canadian has been detained must immediately notify a designated contact of that Canadian to inform him or her of the situation.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Further notification<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(2) A consular official must further notify a designated contact of the detained Canadian</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>a</I>) once the situation of the detained Canadian has been confirmed;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>b</I>) once a consular official has visited, or attempted to visit, the detained Canadian; and</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>c</I>) at least once every two weeks thereafter, for so long as the detention merits a repatriation request pursuant to section 9, in order to provide updates on the situation of the detained Canadian.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Obligation to respond<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(3) A consular official must respond to all reasonable requests for information by a designated contact of a detained Canadian to the best of his or her ability and in a timely manner.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Presumption<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(4) Despite subsection 8(1) of the <I>Privacy Act</I>, the consent of a detained Canadian to disclosure under subsection (3) is to be presumed unless he or she can expressly communicate otherwise.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Repatriation request<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>9.</B> The Minister must engage the foreign government that is detaining a Canadian and formally request the repatriation of that Canadian where:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>a</I>) the Minister has reasonable grounds to believe that the detained Canadian has suffered, is suffering or may suffer torture in the context of his or her detention;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>b</I>) the detained Canadian is being detained in conditions that involve acts of cruel, inhuman or degrading treatment or punishment which do not amount to torture; or</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>c</I>) the detained Canadian is being subjected to arbitrary detention.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Request denied<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>10.</B> (1) Where repatriation is requested pursuant to section 9, but this request is denied by the foreign government to which it is addressed, the Minister or a representative of the Government of Canada may bring the situation to the attention of</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>a</I>) the Committee against Torture, if the request was made pursuant to paragraph 9(<I>a</I>) or (<I>b</I>); and</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>b</I>) the United Nations Working Group on Arbitrary Detention, if the request was made pursuant to paragraph 9(<I>c</I>). </Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Request denied<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(2) Where repatriation is requested pursuant to section 9, but this request is denied by the foreign government to which it is addressed, the Minister must continue to request the repatriation of the detained Canadian and must consider using any other recourse available to the Government of Canada under international law.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Imprisonment after repatriation<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>11.</B> Upon repatriation, the imprisonment of a formerly-detained Canadian may continue, to the extent permitted by Canadian law and international law.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:PART 3--><Para TopMargin="10" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">PART 3</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:STRANDED CANADIANS--><Para TopMargin="5" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">STRANDED CANADIANS</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Consular access<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>12.</B> A stranded Canadian has the right to meet with a consular official to raise his or her situation and seek the assistance of the Government of Canada.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Repatriation<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>13.</B> Where a foreign government does not prohibit the repatriation of a stranded Canadian, the Minister must not prevent the repatriation of the stranded Canadian, and must permit the stranded Canadian to obtain a Canadian passport.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Repatriation request<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>14.</B> Where a foreign government prohibits the repatriation of a stranded Canadian, the Minister must engage that foreign government and formally request that Canadian’s repatriation.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Request denied<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>15.</B> Where repatriation is requested pursuant to section 14, but this request is denied by the foreign government to which it is addressed, the Minister must continue to request the repatriation of the stranded Canadian and must consider using any other recourse available to the Government of Canada under international law.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:PART 4--><Para TopMargin="10" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">PART 4</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:CAPTURED CANADIANS--><Para TopMargin="5" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">CAPTURED CANADIANS</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Captured Canadian<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>16.</B> (1) A Canadian official, other than a consular official, who has reasonable grounds to believe that a Canadian has been captured must immediately inform a consular official.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Investigation and notification<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(2) A consular official who has reasonable grounds to believe that a Canadian has been captured, or who has been contacted by a Canadian official pursuant to subsection (1), must</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>a</I>) immediately attempt to confirm the situation of that Canadian; and</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>b</I>) immediately contact a designated contact of that Canadian to inform him or her of the situation.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Further notification<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(3) A consular official must further notify a designated contact of a captured Canadian</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>a</I>) once the situation of that Canadian has been confirmed; and</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>b</I>) at least once every two weeks thereafter, for as long as that Canadian remains in captivity in order to provide updates on his or her situation.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Obligation to respond<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(4) A consular official must respond to all reasonable requests for information by a designated contact of a captured Canadian to the best of his or her ability and in a timely manner.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Attempt to visit<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(5) A consular official must use all reasonable means and exercise all reasonable options to attempt to visit a captured Canadian at regular intervals.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Presumption<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(6) Despite subsection 8(1) of the <I>Privacy Act</I>, the consent of a captured Canadian to disclosure under subsection (4) is to be presumed unless he or she can expressly communicate otherwise.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Attempt to gain access<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(7) A consular official must use all reasonable means and exercise all reasonable options to attempt to gain access for humanitarian organizations to visit a captured Canadian.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Monitoring conditions<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>17.</B> (1) A consular official must, to the best of his or her ability, monitor the condition of and conditions in which a captured Canadian is being held.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Notification of torture<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(2) A Canadian official who has reasonable grounds to believe that a captured Canadian has been, is being or may be tortured, in the context of his or her captivity, must as soon as possible notify the Minister, the highest-ranking member of the relevant Canadian embassy, consulate, high commission or other diplomatic mission and a designated contact of the captured Canadian of this belief.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Notification of torture<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(3) A Canadian official who is told by a captured Canadian that he or she has been tortured, or threatened with torture, in the context of his or her captivity must as soon as possible notify the Minister, the highest-ranking member of the relevant Canadian embassy, consulate, high commission or other diplomatic mission and a designated contact of the captured Canadian of this statement.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Exception<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(4) Despite subsection (3), when a captured Canadian requests that the Canadian official not inform the designated contact of his or her allegations of torture, the Canadian official must note it and comply with the request.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Release<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(5) The Minister must use all reasonable means and exercise all reasonable options to obtain the release of a captured Canadian.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:PART 5--><Para TopMargin="10" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">PART 5</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:DISAPPEARED CANADIANS--><Para TopMargin="5" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">DISAPPEARED CANADIANS</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Disappeared Canadian<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>18.</B> (1) A Canadian official, other than a consular official, who has reasonable grounds to believe that a Canadian has disappeared must immediately inform a consular official.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Investigation and notification<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(2) A consular official who has reasonable grounds to believe that a Canadian has disappeared, or who has been contacted by a Canadian official pursuant to subsection (1), must</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>a</I>) immediately and continuously attempt to confirm the situation of that Canadian; and</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>b</I>) immediately contact a designated contact of that Canadian to inform him or her of the situation.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Further notification<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(3) A consular official must further notify a designated contact of a Canadian who has disappeared</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>a</I>) once the situation of that Canadian has been confirmed; and</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>b</I>) at least once every two weeks thereafter, for as long as the disappearance of that Canadian lasts, in order to provide updates on his or her situation.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Obligation to respond<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(4) A consular official must respond to all reasonable requests for information by a designated contact of a Canadian who has disappeared to the best of his or her ability and in a timely manner.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Presumption<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(5) Despite subsection 8(1) of the <I>Privacy Act</I>, the consent of a disappeared Canadian to disclosure under subsection (4) is to be presumed.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:PART 6--><Para TopMargin="10" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">PART 6</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:REPORTS AND RECOURSES--><Para TopMargin="5" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">REPORTS AND RECOURSES</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Report to Parliament<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>19.</B> (1) The Minister must report quarterly to Parliament on all Canadians who are detained, stranded or captured or have disappeared, including, as applicable</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>a</I>) their names;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>b</I>) their places of residence in Canada;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>c</I>) where they are detained, stranded or captured or have disappeared;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>d</I>) whether they are incommunicado;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>e</I>) any allegations made against them in connection with their being detained, stranded, captured or having disappeared;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>f</I>) their conditions of detention or captivity;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>g</I>) the risk of their being subjected to torture;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>h</I>) a summary of any statements they have made to Canadian officials with respect to their treatment or general welfare in the context of being detained, stranded, captured or having disappeared; and</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>i</I>) a summary of the measures taken by the Minister and other representatives of the Government of Canada to seek their repatriation or release.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Information struck out<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(2) Before the report to Parliament is distributed, a consular official must give every Canadian mentioned in the report the opportunity to request that all his or her personally identifiable information be struck out, and must ensure that such information is struck out if the request is made or if a consular official is otherwise unable to communicate with the person concerned.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Writ of <I>mandamus</I><br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>20.</B> (1) Any Canadian may apply to the Federal Court of Canada for a writ of <I>mandamus</I> compelling the relevant department, agency, official, representative or Minister to fulfil their obligations pursuant to any of Parts 2 to 5.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Application for writ<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(2) Despite subsection 18.1(2) of the <I>Federal Courts Act</I>, an application for a writ of <I>mandamus</I> under subsection (1) may be made at any time that the subject of the application remains abroad.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Specially managed proceeding<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(3) A writ of <I>mandamus</I> under subsection (1) is to be conducted as a specially managed proceeding.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Case management judge<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(4) A case management judge is to be assigned to a proceeding under subsection (1).</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Trial management conference<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(5) In a proceeding under subsection (1), a trial management conference must be conducted before the case management judge assigned under subsection (3) within 15 days of the service of the notice of application.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Expedited hearing<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(6) At the trial management conference under subsection (5), the case management judge must fix the period for completion of all steps in the proceeding in order to ensure the most expeditious hearing as is just in the circumstances.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Civil liability<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>21.</B> (1) A Canadian who has suffered physical or psychological injury as a result of the failure of any department, agency, official, representative or Minister to fulfil their obligations pursuant to any of Parts 2 to 5 may apply to a court of competent jurisdiction for compensation.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Deeming<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(2) In the context of any action undertaken pursuant to subsection (1), a failure to request repatriation as prescribed by this Act is to be deemed to be the cause of a Canadian continuing to be detained or stranded.</Para></Block><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="BPT_ImprintE">Published under authority of the Speaker of the House of Commons<br/>Available from:<br/>Publishing and Depository Services<br/>Public Works and Government Services Canada<br/>Ottawa, Ontario K1A 0S5<br/>Telephone: 613-941-5995 or 1-800-635-7943<br/>Fax: 613-954-5779 or 1-800-565-7757<br/>publications@tpsgc-pwgsc.gc.ca<br/>http://publications.gc.ca</Para></Block><Block Align="Yes" LineCnt="N"><Para NoLineBreak="Yes" NoHtml="Yes" Leading="0" Size="0" TopMargin="0" BottomMargin="0"></Para></Block></Bill_Part></Bill>
