<?xml version="1.0"?>
<Bill RHead_reign="60 Eliz. II" RHead_ParlYear="2011" DocumentTitle="BILL C-373" Bill_No="C-373" Document_No="411480" xml:lang="EN" Bill_Type="Non-amending" Stage_Name="First-Reading-House" Reprint="No" xml:space="preserve" ChapterNo_E="C. " ChapterNo_F="ch. " Bill-Origin="commons"><Bill_Part Part_Type="Cover" CountLines="No"><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="CovBillNo">C-373</Para></Block><Block><Para TopMargin="24" Size="9" Leading="10" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0" TextAlign="Center">First Session, Forty-first Parliament,</Para></Block><Block><Para Size="9" Leading="10" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0" TextAlign="Center">60 Elizabeth II, 2011</Para></Block><Block><Para TopMargin="48" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0" Bold="Yes" TextAlign="Center">HOUSE OF COMMONS OF CANADA</Para></Block><Block><Para TopMargin="42" Size="18" Leading="20" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0" Bold="Yes" TextAlign="Center">BILL C-373</Para></Block><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="CovLongTitle">An Act to establish the Department of Peace</Para></Block><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="COV_StageLine"></Para></Block><Block><Para Size="9" AllCaps="Yes" Hyphenate="OFF">first reading, November 30, 2011</Para></Block><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="COV_StageLine"></Para></Block><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="Cover_Sponsors"><SC SC_PerCent="85">Mr. Atamanenko</SC></Para></Block><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="Cover_DocNo">411480</Para></Block></Bill_Part><Bill_Part CountLines="No" Part_Type="InsideCover"><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="BPT_InsideCoverE">Also available on the Parliament of Canada Web Site at the following address:<br/><B>http://www.parl.gc.ca</B></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><Para TopMargin="108" BottomMargin="4" Size="10" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">SUMMARY</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" Size="8" Leading="9" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">This enactment establishes the Department of Peace.</Para></Block></Bill_Part><Bill_Part Part_Type="MainText" CountLines="Yes" RunningHead_E="Department of Peace"><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="MainText_DocNo">411480</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes"><Para Style="Session_Reign">1st Session, 41st Parliament,</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes"><Para Style="Session_Reign">60 Elizabeth II, 2011</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes"><Para Style="MainBillOrigin">house of commons of canada</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes"><Para Bold="Yes" Style="MAIN@BillNo_Title">BILL C-373</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes"><Para Style="MAIN@ti;04">An Act to establish the Department of Peace</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><MarginalNote>Preamble<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">Whereas the Parliament of Canada is of the view that the establishment of a Department of Peace would help to advance the cause of peace in Canada and throughout the world;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">And whereas peace is not simply the absence of active hostilities but rather a state of non-violence, harmony and amity based on a foundation of principles supported by the United Nations;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">Now, therefore, Her Majesty, by and with the advice and consent of the Senate and House of Commons of Canada, enacts as follows:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:SHORT TITLE--><Para TopMargin="10" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">SHORT TITLE</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Short title<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>1.</B> This Act may be cited as the <I>Department of Peace Act</I>.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:INTERPRETATION--><Para TopMargin="10" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">INTERPRETATION</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Definitions<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>2.</B> The following definitions apply in this Act.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><MarginalNote>“Civilian Peace Service”<br/>« <I>service civil pour la paix</I> »<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0">“Civilian Peace Service” means the service established under paragraph 14(2)(<I>b</I>).</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><MarginalNote>“Department”<br/>« <I>ministère</I> »<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0">“Department” means the Department of Peace established under subsection 3(1).</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><MarginalNote>“Minister”<br/>« <I>ministre</I> »<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0">“Minister” means the Minister of Peace appointed under section 3.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:ESTABLISHMENT OF DEPARTMENT--><Para TopMargin="10" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">ESTABLISHMENT OF DEPARTMENT</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Department established<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>3.</B> (1) A department of the Government of Canada called the Department of Peace is established, over which the Minister of Peace, appointed by commission under the Great Seal, is to preside.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Minister<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(2) The Minister holds office during pleasure and has the management and direction of the Department.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:MISSION OF DEPARTMENT--><Para TopMargin="10" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">MISSION OF DEPARTMENT</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Mission<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>4.</B> The work of the Department is to be dedicated to peace-building and the study of conditions that are conducive to both domestic and international peace and, in particular, the Department must</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>a</I>) hold peace as an organizing principle in society, coordinating service with every level of Canadian society;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>b</I>) promote justice and democratic principles in order to expand human rights;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>c</I>) strengthen non-military means of peacemaking;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>d</I>) promote the development of human potential;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>e</I>) work to create peace, prevent violence, divert from armed conflict, use field-tested programs and develop new structures for non-violent dispute resolution;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>f</I>) take a proactive, strategic approach to the development of policies and programs that promote national and international conflict prevention, non-violent intervention, mediation, peaceful conflict resolution and structured mediation of conflict;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>g</I>) address matters both domestic and international in scope;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>h</I>) support the development of initiatives from local communities, religious groups and non-governmental organizations; and</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>i</I>) assume a leadership role among federal departments in addressing matters of peace, order, justice and good government, and in carrying out the responsibility to protect Canadians from harm.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:POWERS, DUTIES AND FUNCTIONS OF THE MINISTER--><Para TopMargin="10" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">POWERS, DUTIES AND FUNCTIONS OF THE MINISTER</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Powers, duties and functions<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>5.</B> (1) The powers, duties and functions of the Minister extend to and include all matters over which Parliament has jurisdiction — and that have not been assigned by law to another department, board or agency of the Government of Canada — relating to peacemaking and the study of conditions that are conducive to both domestic and international peace.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Minister's jurisdiction<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(2) The Minister's jurisdiction referred to in subsection (1) encompasses, but is not limited to, jurisdiction over the matters referred to in subsection (3).</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Powers, duties and functions<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(3) The Minister must</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>a</I>) work proactively and interactively with each branch of the federal public administration on all policy matters relating to conditions of peace;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>b</I>) serve as the Cabinet spokesperson on matters relating to peace;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>c</I>) include the intellectual and spiritual wealth of the people of Canada by involving private, public and non-governmental <keep>organ-</keep>izations in the administration of the Department and in its development of policy and programs;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>d</I>) monitor and analyse causative principles of conflict and make policy recommendations for developing and maintaining peaceful conduct, with a view to preventing crisis and violence;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>e</I>) promote and develop programs involving citizen participation, including a Canadian civilian peace service aimed at preventing crisis and violence, which would involve the participation of trained citizens in all elements of peace-building, peacemaking and peacekeeping;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>f</I>) develop an intercultural competence within the Department to manage conflicts between individuals and groups;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>g</I>) assist in the establishment and funding of community-based violence mitigation and prevention programs, including restorative justice practices and violence prevention models and their implementation; and</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>h</I>) develop strategies and implement programs to address unhealthy manifestations of violence in Canadian culture as they relate to both humans and animals.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:HUMAN SECURITY RESPONSIBILITIES--><Para TopMargin="10" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">HUMAN SECURITY RESPONSIBILITIES</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Non-violent conflict resolution strategies<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>6.</B> (1) The Minister must develop non-<keep>violent conflict</keep> resolution strategies applicable to situations where human security is threatened by conflict that</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>a</I>) is geographic, religious, ethnic, racial, gender-, sexuality- or class-based in its origin, or related to other human rights violations;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>b</I>) results from economic concerns, including trade or misdistribution of wealth; or</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>c</I>) is initiated through disputes concerning scarcity of food or natural resources, including water and energy resources, or environmental concerns.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Information relating to strategies<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(2) The Minister must offer to provide information relating to the strategies referred to in subsection (1) to all parties involved in a conflict referred to in that subsection.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:EDUCATIONAL RESPONSIBILITIES--><Para TopMargin="10" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">EDUCATIONAL RESPONSIBILITIES</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Education<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>7.</B> The Minister must</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>a</I>) consult with established and innovative peace educators, from across Canada to develop an agenda of peace themes, which is to include studies of</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="4" FirstLineIndent="0">(i) the human rights movement in Canada and throughout the world, with special emphasis on how cooperative endeavour and involvement have contributed to advancements in peace and justice, </Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="4" FirstLineIndent="0">(ii) peace agreements, and</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="4" FirstLineIndent="0">(iii) circumstances in which peaceful intervention has worked to stop conflict;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>b</I>) in cooperation with provincial and territorial ministers of education, </Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="4" FirstLineIndent="0">(i) offer incentives in the form of grants and training,</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="4" FirstLineIndent="0">(ii) work with educators to design and develop resources to achieve methods of instruction on peaceful conflict prevention and resolution, and</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="4" FirstLineIndent="0">(iii) develop an intercultural competence to manage conflicts between different groups;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>c</I>) establish and maintain a public website for the purposes of soliciting and receiving ideas for the development of peace from the people of Canada;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>d</I>) engage the critical thinking capabilities of grade-school, high-school and university students and teachers by means of the Internet and other media and issue periodic reports concerning submissions received from such persons;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>e</I>) establish, in collaboration with post-secondary institutions in Canada, a National Peace Academy to provide diploma or degree courses of instruction in peace education, whose graduates will be required to provide five years of public service in programs dedicated to domestic or international non-violent conflict resolution; and</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>f</I>) provide grants for peace studies departments in universities and colleges throughout Canada.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:DOMESTIC RESPONSIBILITIES--><Para TopMargin="10" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">DOMESTIC RESPONSIBILITIES</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Domestic responsibilities<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>8.</B> The Minister must</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>a</I>) provide financing for community initiatives that rely on local resources to create peace projects to facilitate the development of strategies for conflict prevention and resolution at a national level and thereby inform and inspire national policy;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>b</I>) assist in the development of community-based strategies for celebrating diversity, promoting respect and combating racism and sexism;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>c</I>) assist in the establishment and funding of community-based violence prevention programs;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>d</I>) develop policies that address family violence, including spousal abuse, child abuse and elder abuse;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>e</I>) develop policies to address violence against animals;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>f</I>) analyse existing policies, implement field-tested programs and develop new approaches to deal with the implements of violence, such as handguns and other firearms;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>g</I>) develop new programs that relate to the societal challenges of school violence, gangs, racial and ethnic violence, violence against gays and lesbians, transphobic violence and disputes involving relations between police services and communities;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>h</I>) make policy recommendations to the Minister of Justice regarding human rights, labour law and civil liberties;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>i</I>) provide counselling services for and advocate on behalf of women victimized by violence;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>j</I>) provide for public education programs concerning hate crimes so as to promote healing and respect for racial, religious, ethnic, gender and sexual diversity; and</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>k</I>) ensure, through such participatory and evaluative methods as social and narrative research, that federal official language policies and employment equity policies are guided by principles that are consistent with developing a culture of peace.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:INTERNATIONAL RESPONSIBILITIES--><Para TopMargin="10" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">INTERNATIONAL RESPONSIBILITIES</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>International responsibilities<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>9.</B> The Minister must</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>a</I>) advise the Minister of National Defence and the Minister of Foreign Affairs on all matters relating to national security, including the protection of human rights and the prevention, amelioration and de-escalation of unarmed and armed international conflict;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>b</I>) provide for the training of all Canadian personnel who administer post-conflict reconstruction or demobilization in war-torn societies;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>c</I>) sponsor national and regional conflict prevention and dispute resolution initiatives, create special task forces and draw on local, regional and national expertise to develop plans and programs for addressing the root sources of conflict in troubled areas;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>d</I>) provide, between Canada and other nations, for exchanges of individuals who work for governments and for non-governmental organizations that endeavour to develop domestic and international peace-based initiatives;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>e</I>) encourage the development of international sister city programs, pairing Canadian cities with cities around the globe for artistic, cultural, economic, educational, peace and faith-based exchanges;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>f</I>) develop and administer the training of civilian peacekeepers who participate in multinational non-violent police forces or provide support to civilian police participating in peacekeeping;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>g</I>) develop and administer a Civilian Peace Service cadet program to engage youth in community service in Canada and overseas;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>h</I>) work jointly with the Minister of Finance to strengthen peace enforcement through the hiring and training of monitors and investigators to help with the enforcement of international arms embargoes;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>i</I>) facilitate the development of peace summits at which parties to a conflict may gather — under carefully prepared conditions — to promote non-violent communication and mutually beneficial solutions;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>j</I>) submit to the Prime Minister recommendations for reducing the numbers of weapons of mass destruction and for stopping their proliferation;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>k</I>) submit an annual report to the Prime Minister on the sale of arms from Canada to other nations, including an analysis of the impact of such sales on the defence of Canada and how such sales affect peace;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>l</I>) in consultation with the Minister of Foreign Affairs, develop strategies for the sustainability and management of the distribution of international funds;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>m</I>) advise the Canadian Ambassador to the United Nations on matters pertaining to the United Nations Security Council; and</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>n</I>) provide to the Department of National Defence, on a regular basis, ethical and value-based analyses of programs and other initiatives of that Department.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:CONSULTATION WITH MINISTER--><Para TopMargin="10" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">CONSULTATION WITH MINISTER</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>In case of conflict<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>10.</B> (1) If it appears that Canada is about to be involved in an armed conflict with another government or entity, the Minister of National Defence and the Minister of Foreign Affairs must, in accordance with the process referred to in subsection (4), consult with the Minister with a view to resolving the conflict by non-violent means.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Diplomatic initiatives<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(2) If an armed conflict involving Canada and any other government or entity is ongoing or recently concluded, the Minister must arrange for independent study of diplomatic initiatives undertaken by Canada and other parties involved in the armed conflict.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Effectiveness of initiatives<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(3) Immediately after an armed conflict involving Canada and any other government or entity has concluded, the Minister must assess the effectiveness of any diplomatic initiatives that played a role in ending the conflict. The Minister must report to Parliament on the results of the assessment within six months after the end of the armed conflict.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Formal consultative process<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(4) The Minister must immediately establish a formal consultative process with the Minister of National Defence and the Minister of Foreign Affairs to address any issues that may arise in respect of </Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>a</I>) any potential or ongoing armed conflict involving Canada and another nation; and</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>b</I>) the use of Department of National Defence personnel within Canada.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Treaties and peace agreements<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>11.</B> The Minister is to be consulted before the Government of Canada enters into any treaty or peace agreement.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:DEPARTMENTAL OFFICERS--><Para TopMargin="10" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">DEPARTMENTAL OFFICERS</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Deputy Minister<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>12.</B> (1) The Governor in Council must appoint an officer called the Deputy Minister of Peace to hold office during pleasure and to be the deputy head of the Department.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Absence or disability<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(2) The Deputy Minister must designate other officers of the Department to act for and perform the functions of the Deputy Minister during his or her absence or disability.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Other officers<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>13.</B> (1) The Governor in Council must appoint the following departmental officers:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>a</I>) an Assistant Deputy Minister for Peace Education and Training, who is to be responsible for carrying out the functions and responsibilities referred to in section 14;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>b</I>) an Assistant Deputy Minister for Domestic Peace Activities, who is to be responsible for carrying out the functions and responsibilities referred to in section 15;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>c</I>) an Assistant Deputy Minister for International Peace Activities, who is to be responsible for carrying out the functions and responsibilities referred to in section 16;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>d</I>) an Assistant Deputy Minister for Arms Control and Disarmament, who is to be responsible for carrying out the functions and responsibilities referred to in section 17;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>e</I>) an Assistant Deputy Minister for Policies and Programs for Peaceful Engagement, who is to be responsible for carrying out the functions and responsibilities referred to in section 18;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>f</I>) an Assistant Deputy Minister for Human, Social and Economic Rights, who is to  be responsible for carrying out the functions and responsibilities referred to in section 19;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>g</I>) a general counsel to provide legal advice to the Minister and Deputy Minister on all matters relating to the administration of the Department and the activities of the Department and its officers; and</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>h</I>) four additional officers to perform general duties as prescribed by the Deputy Minister, including</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="4" FirstLineIndent="0">(i) parliamentary relations functions,</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="4" FirstLineIndent="0">(ii) public information functions, including providing, through the use of the latest technologies, useful information about peace and the work of the Department,</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="4" FirstLineIndent="0">(iii) management and budget functions, and</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="4" FirstLineIndent="0">(iv) planning, evaluation and policy development functions, including development of policies to promote the efficient and coordinated administration of the Department and its programs and to encourage improvements in conflict resolution and violence prevention methodologies.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Additional functions<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(2) Each officer referred to in this section must report to the Deputy Minister and must, in addition to any functions assigned to the officer under this Act, perform any functions assigned to the officer by the Minister or Deputy Minister.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Office of Peace Education and Training<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>14.</B> (1) The Assistant Deputy Minister for Peace Education and Training is responsible for the establishment and administration of the departmental Office of Peace Education and Training.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote> Functions<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(2) The Assistant Deputy Minister referred to in subsection (1) must</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>a</I>) carry out those functions of the Department relating to the creation, facilitation and support of peace education programs and training at the elementary, secondary, university and postgraduate levels;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>b</I>) establish a Civilian Peace Service to promote non-violent means of conflict resolution on a local, regional and international basis; and</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>c</I>) establish a Civilian Peace Service cadet program to engage young persons in community service in Canada and overseas and to prepare them for careers as peace professionals.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Specific responsibilities<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(3) The Assistant Deputy Minister referred to in subsection (1) must</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>a</I>) undertake research on and document peaceful approaches to conflict faced by Canadian society and by our allies, with the objective of making the Department a source of innovative approaches and practices for peace-related strategies; and</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>b</I>) hold a yearly conference with provincial and territorial ministers of education and other leaders in education to share new findings in peace-related strategies applicable in Canadian society and abroad and to demonstrate how these findings could be potential content for school curricula.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Grants<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(4) The Assistant Deputy Minister referred to in subsection (1) must</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>a</I>) provide peace education grants to universities and colleges for the creation and expansion of peace studies departments; and </Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>b</I>) create a community peace grant program under which grants are to be provided to not-for-profit community organizations and other non-governmental organizations for the purposes of developing local peace-building initiatives and innovative neighbourhood programs for non-violent conflict resolution.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Office of Domestic Peace Activities<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>15.</B> (1) The Assistant Deputy Minister for Domestic Peace Activities is responsible for the establishment and administration of the departmental Office of Domestic Peace Activities.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote> Functions<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(2) The Assistant Deputy Minister referred to in subsection (1) must carry out those functions of the Department relating to domestic peace activities, including the development of policies that increase awareness of the availability and effectiveness of intervention and counselling in respect of domestic violence and conflict.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Specific responsibilities<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(3) The Assistant Deputy Minister referred to in subsection (1) must</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>a</I>) develop new policies and build on existing programs responsive to the prevention of crime, including the development of community policing strategies and peaceful settlement skills among police and other public safety officers;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>b</I>) develop community-based strategies for celebrating diversity and promoting respect; and</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>c</I>) promote the use of restorative justice practices in the resolution of conflict at the community, regional and national level.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Office of International Peace Activities<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>16.</B> (1) The Assistant Deputy Minister for International Peace Activities is responsible for the establishment and administration of the departmental Office of International Peace Activities.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote> Functions<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(2) The Assistant Deputy Minister referred to in subsection (1) must carry out those functions of the Department relating to international peace activities.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Specific responsibilities<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(3) The Assistant Deputy Minister referred to in subsection (1) must</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>a</I>) provide for the training and deployment of Civilian Peace Service graduates and other non-military conflict-prevention and peacemaking personnel;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>b</I>) sponsor national and regional conflict-prevention and dispute-resolution initiatives in countries experiencing social, political or economic strife;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>c</I>) advocate the creation of a multinational non-violent peace force;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>d</I>) provide training for the administration of post-conflict reconstruction and demobilization in war-torn societies;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>e</I>) provide for personnel exchanges between Canada and other nations who are endeavouring to develop domestic and international peace-based initiatives; and</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>f</I>) create early detection, assessment and response mechanisms to respond to emerging conflicts in order to mitigate or prevent violence.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Office of Arms Control and Disarmament<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>17.</B> (1) The Assistant Deputy Minister for Arms Control and Disarmament is responsible for the establishment and administration of the departmental Office of Arms Control and Disarmament.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote> Functions<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(2) The Assistant Deputy Minister referred to in subsection (1) must carry out those functions of the Department relating to arms control programs and arms limitation agreements.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Specific responsibilities<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(3) The Assistant Deputy Minister referred to in subsection (1) must</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>a</I>) advise the Minister and Deputy Minister on all interagency discussions and all international negotiations regarding the reduction and elimination of weapons of mass destruction throughout the world;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>b</I>) advise the Minister and Deputy Minister on incidents of dismantling of weapons of mass destruction and the safe and secure storage of materials related thereto;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>c</I>) assist nations, international agencies and non-governmental organizations in determining the locations of nuclear weapons build-up; </Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>d</I>) develop non-violent strategies to deter the testing or use of offensive or defensive nuclear weapons, whether based on land, air, sea, or in outer space; </Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>e</I>) facilitate the role of all parties and relevant government departments in <keep>advanc-</keep>ing the development of a nuclear weapons convention for the establishment of national and international legislation and policies on the responsible use, disposal and future elimination of nuclear weapons; and</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>f</I>) provide a depository for copies of all contracts, agreements and treaties that deal with the reduction and elimination of nuclear weapons or the protection of outer space from militarization.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Office of Policies and Programs for Peaceful Engagement<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>18.</B> (1) The Assistant Deputy Minister for Policies and Programs for Peaceful Engagement is responsible for the establishment and administration of the departmental Office of Policies and Programs for Peaceful Engagement.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote> Functions<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(2) The Assistant Deputy Minister referred to in subsection (1) must carry out those functions in the Department relating to research and analysis in respect of creating, initiating, and modelling approaches to peaceful engagement and non-violent conflict resolution.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Specific responsibilities<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(3) The Assistant Deputy Minister referred to in subsection (1)  must</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>a</I>) study the global impact of war, especially on the physical and mental condition of children (using as a guide the ten-point agenda in the 1996 United Nations Children’s Fund report, <I>The State of the World’s Children</I> and the 2004 <I>World Report on Violence and Health</I> of the World Health Organization), as well as the effect of war on the environment and public health; </Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>b</I>) implement United Nations Resolution 1325 to promote the enhanced participation of women in all aspects of peace activities, from conflict prevention to post-conflict reconstruction;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>c</I>) review and implement United Nations deliberations on the Rapid Response Planning Process (R2P2) — Responsibility to Protect, with particular emphasis on the responsibility to prevent; </Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>d</I>) publish a monthly journal of the activities of the Department and encourage scholarly participation; </Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>e</I>) gather information on effective community peace-building activities and disseminate such information to local governments and non-governmental organizations in Canada and abroad; </Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>f</I>) research the effect of reports of violence in the media and make such reports available to Parliament annually; and </Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>g</I>) sponsor conferences throughout Canada to enhance awareness of the work of the Department and non-governmental organizations that work in partnership with the Government. </Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Office of Human, Social and Economic Rights<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>19.</B> (1) The Assistant Deputy Minister for Human, Social and Economic Rights is responsible for the establishment and administration of the departmental Office of Human, Social and Economic Rights.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote> Functions<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(2) The Assistant Deputy Minister referred to in subsection (1) must carry out those functions in the Department that support the principles of the Universal Declaration of Human Rights passed by the General Assembly of the United Nations on December 10, 1948. </Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Specific responsibilities <br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(3) The Assistant Deputy Minister referred to in subsection (1) must</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>a</I>) assist the Minister and Deputy Minister in furthering the incorporation of the principles of human rights, as enunciated in United Nations General Assembly Resolution <keep>217A (III) of</keep> December 10, 1948, into all agreements between Canada and other nations, in order to assist in the reduction of causes of violence; </Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>b</I>) gather information on and document human rights abuses, both domestically and internationally, make such findings available to other agencies in order to facilitate non-violent conflict resolution and recommend to the Minister non-violent responses to correct such abuses; </Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>c</I>) provide trained observers to work with non-governmental organizations for the purposes of creating a climate that is conducive to respect for human rights; </Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>d</I>) conduct economic analyses of the scarcity of human and natural resources as a source of conflict and make recommendations to the Minister regarding the non-violent prevention of such scarcity, non-<keep>violent intervention</keep> in case of such scarcity and the development of programs of assist- ance for people experiencing such scarcity, whether it be due to armed conflict, maldistribution of resources or natural causes; and </Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>e</I>) assist the Minister, in cooperation with the Minister for Foreign Affairs and the Minister of Finance, in developing strategies regarding the sustainability and the management of the distribution of funds from international agencies, the conditions appli- cable to the receipt of such funds and the impact of those conditions on the peace and stability of the recipient nations. </Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Commissioner of Peace<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>20.</B> (1) The Minister must appoint a Commissioner of Peace, who is to monitor the work of the Minister and the Department and report to Parliament every six months on the effectiveness of the Minister and the Department in carrying out their functions and responsibilities under this Act. </Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Additional duties<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(2) The Commissioner must </Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>a</I>) make any recommendations that he or she considers advisable to the Minister regarding the policies of the Department relating to peace and non-violent conflict resolution;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>b</I>) provide a forum for representatives of foreign governments and other entities and federal, provincial, territorial and local governments to discuss peace issues; </Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>c</I>) promote better intergovernmental relations; and </Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>d</I>) report annually to the Minister, the Prime Minister and Parliament on the impact of federal peace activities on provincial, territo­rial and local governments.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Advisory council<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>21.</B> (1) The Minister must appoint an advisory council to assist the Commissioner in carrying out his or her functions under section 20. The council must, in consultation with the Commissioner, also serve as a national and international sounding board on issues relating to peace and non-violent conflict resolution and as a nexus for fostering peace. </Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Members<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(2) The advisory council is to be composed of 10 members, including representatives of peace groups and non-governmental organizations.  The members of the advisory council must serve without remuneration but are to be reimbursed for any reasonable expense incurred in the course of their work.</Para></Block><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="BPT_ImprintE">Published under authority of the Speaker of the House of Commons<br/>Available from:<br/>Publishing and Depository Services<br/>Public Works and Government Services Canada<br/>Ottawa, Ontario K1A 0S5<br/>Telephone: 613-941-5995 or 1-800-635-7943<br/>Fax: 613-954-5779 or 1-800-565-7757<br/>publications@tpsgc-pwgsc.gc.ca<br/>http://publications.gc.ca</Para></Block><Block Align="Yes" LineCnt="N"><Para NoLineBreak="Yes" NoHtml="Yes" Leading="0" Size="0" TopMargin="0" BottomMargin="0"></Para></Block></Bill_Part></Bill>
