<?xml version="1.0"?>
<Bill RHead_reign="60-61 Eliz. II" RHead_ParlYear="2011-2012" DocumentTitle="BILL C-400" Bill_No="C-400" Document_No="411548" xml:lang="EN" Bill_Type="Non-amending" Stage_Name="First-Reading-House" Reprint="No" xml:space="preserve" ChapterNo_E="C. " ChapterNo_F="ch. " Bill-Origin="commons"><Bill_Part Part_Type="Cover" CountLines="No"><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="CovBillNo">C-400</Para></Block><Block><Para TopMargin="24" Size="9" Leading="10" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0" TextAlign="Center">First Session, Forty-first Parliament,</Para></Block><Block><Para Size="9" Leading="10" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0" TextAlign="Center">60-61 Elizabeth II, 2011-2012</Para></Block><Block><Para TopMargin="48" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0" Bold="Yes" TextAlign="Center">HOUSE OF COMMONS OF CANADA</Para></Block><Block><Para TopMargin="42" Size="18" Leading="20" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0" Bold="Yes" TextAlign="Center">BILL C-400</Para></Block><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="CovLongTitle">An Act to ensure secure, adequate, accessible and affordable housing for Canadians</Para></Block><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="COV_StageLine"></Para></Block><Block><Para Size="9" AllCaps="Yes" Hyphenate="OFF">first reading, February 16, 2012</Para></Block><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="COV_StageLine"></Para></Block><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="Cover_Sponsors"><SC SC_PerCent="85">Ms. Morin </SC>(<I>Saint-Hyacinthe—Bagot</I>)</Para></Block><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="Cover_DocNo">411548</Para></Block></Bill_Part><Bill_Part CountLines="No" Part_Type="InsideCover"><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="BPT_InsideCoverE">Also available on the Parliament of Canada Web Site at the following address:<br/><B>http://www.parl.gc.ca</B></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><Para TopMargin="108" BottomMargin="4" Size="10" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">SUMMARY</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" Size="8" Leading="9" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify"> 
 



The purpose of this enactment is to require the Minister responsible for the Canada Mortgage and Housing Corporation to consult with the provincial  ministers of the Crown responsible for municipal affairs and housing and with representatives of municipalities, Aboriginal communities, non-profit and private sector housing providers and civil society organizations in order to establish a national housing strategy.</Para></Block></Bill_Part><Bill_Part Part_Type="MainText" CountLines="Yes" RunningHead_E="Secure, Adequate, Accessible and Affordable Housing"><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="MainText_DocNo">411548</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes"><Para Style="Session_Reign">1st Session, 41st Parliament,</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes"><Para Style="Session_Reign">60-61 Elizabeth II, 2011-2012</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes"><Para Style="MainBillOrigin">house of commons of canada</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes"><Para Bold="Yes" Style="MAIN@BillNo_Title">BILL C-400</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes"><Para Style="MAIN@ti;04">An Act to ensure secure, adequate, accessible and affordable housing for Canadians</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><MarginalNote>Preamble<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">Whereas the  access to adequate housing is a fundamental human right according to paragraph 25(1) of the <I>United Nations Universal Declaration of Human Rights</I>;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">
Whereas, in 1976, Canada acceded to the <I>International Covenant on Economic, Social and Cultural Rights</I>, a legally binding treaty committing Canada to make progress on fully realizing all economic, social and cultural rights, including the right to adequate housing;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify"> 
Whereas the enjoyment of other human rights, such as those to privacy, to respect for the home, to freedom of movement, to freedom from discrimination, to environmental health, to security of the person, to freedom of association and to equality before the law, are indivisible from and indispensable to the realization of the right to adequate housing;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">Whereas Canada’s wealth and national budg- et are more than adequate to ensure that every woman, man and child residing in Canada has secure, adequate, accessible and affordable housing as part of a standard of living that will provide healthy physical, intellectual, emotional, spiritual and social development and a good quality of life;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">Whereas improved housing conditions are best achieved through co-operative partnerships of government and civil society and the meaningful involvement of local communities;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">


And whereas the Parliament of Canada wishes to ensure the establishment of national goals and programs that seek to improve the quality of life for all Canadians as a basic right;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">
Now, therefore, Her Majesty, by and with the advice and consent of the Senate and House of Commons of Canada, enacts as follows:
</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:SHORT TITLE--><Para TopMargin="10" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">SHORT TITLE</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Short title<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>1.</B> This Act may be cited as the <I>Secure, Adequate, Accessible and Affordable Housing Act</I>.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:INTERPRETATION--><Para TopMargin="10" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">INTERPRETATION</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Definitions<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>2.</B> The definitions in this section apply in this Act.
</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><MarginalNote>“Aboriginal community”<br/>« <I>collectivité autochtone</I> »<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0">“Aboriginal community” means a community made up of Métis, Inuit or First Nations peoples, whether or not that community is situated on a reserve.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><MarginalNote>“accessible”<br/>« <I>accessible</I> »<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0">“accessible”, in respect of housing,  means housing that is physically adapted to the individuals who are intended to occupy it, including those who are disadvantaged by age, physical or mental disability or medical condition, and those who are victims of a natural disaster.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><MarginalNote>“adequate”<br/>« <I>adéquat</I> »<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0">“adequate”, in respect of housing, means housing that is habitable and structurally sound,  and that provides sufficient space and protection against cold, damp, heat, rain, wind, noise, pollution and other threats to health.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><MarginalNote>“affordable”<br/>« <I>abordable</I> »<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0">“affordable”, in respect of housing, means housing that is available at a cost that does not compromise an individual’s ability to meet other basic needs, including food, clothing and access to health care services, education and recreational activities.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><MarginalNote>“Minister”<br/>« <I>ministre</I> »<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0">“Minister” means the Minister responsible for the Canada Mortgage and Housing Corporation.
</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:NATIONAL HOUSING STRATEGY--><Para TopMargin="10" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">NATIONAL HOUSING STRATEGY</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>National Housing Strategy to be established<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>3.</B> (1) The Minister must, in consultation with the provincial  ministers of the Crown responsible for municipal affairs and housing and with representatives of municipalities, Aboriginal communities, non-profit and private sector housing providers and civil society organizations, including those that represent groups in need of adequate housing, establish a national housing strategy designed to respect, protect, promote and fulfil the right to adequate housing as guaranteed under international human rights treaties ratified by Canada.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Financial assistance<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(2) The national housing strategy must ensure that the cost of housing in Canada does not compromise an individual’s ability to meet other basic needs, including food, clothing and access to health care services, education and recreational activities, and must provide financial assistance, including financing and credit without discrimination, for those who are otherwise unable to afford rental housing.
</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Requirements<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(3) The national housing strategy must include incentives for affordable rental housing and must have as its objective to make available housing that</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>a</I>) is safe, secure, adequate, affordable, accessible, and not-for-profit in the case of those who cannot otherwise afford it;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>b</I>) reflects the needs of local communities, including Aboriginal communities;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>c</I>) provides access for those with different needs, including, in an appropriate proportion, access for the elderly and persons with disabilities that allows for independent living as a result of housing adaptations;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>d</I>) uses design and equipment standardization where appropriate to accelerate construction	and minimize cost;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>e</I>) uses designs with LEED (Leadership in Energy and Environmental Design) certification;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>f</I>) includes not-for-profit rental housing projects, mixed-income not-for-profit housing cooperatives, special-needs housing and housing that allows senior citizens to remain in their homes as long as possible;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>g</I>) includes housing for the homeless;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>h</I>) includes provision for temporary emergency housing and shelter in the event of disasters and crises; and</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>i</I>) complies with standards for the maintenance of existing housing stock or for the construction and maintenance of new housing and appropriate health, security and safety standards.
</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Priority<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(4) The national housing strategy must give priority to ensuring the availability of secure, adequate, accessible and affordable housing to those without housing and to members of groups particularly vulnerable to homelessness, including</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>a</I>) those who have not had secure, adequate, accessible and affordable housing over an extended period;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>b</I>) those with special housing requirements because of family status or size or because of a mental or physical disability;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>c</I>) those who are at risk of being  denied housing as a result of discrimination on a prohibited ground of discrimination within the meaning of Part 1 of the <I>Canadian Human Rights Act</I>; and</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>d</I>) those who are experiencing violence or who are at risk of experiencing violence.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Benefits — Quebec<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>4.</B> Quebec may, having ratified the <I>International Covenant on Economic, Social and Cultural Rights</I>, use the benefits of this Act with respect to its own choices, its own programs and its own approach related to housing on its territory.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Implementation of national housing strategy<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>5.</B> (1) The Minister, in consultation with the provincial  ministers of the Crown responsible for municipal affairs and housing and with representatives of municipalities and Aboriginal communities, must develop a coordinated approach to the implementation of the national housing strategy and may provide advice and assistance in the development and implementation of programs and practices in support of the strategy.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Measures may be taken<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(2)  The Minister, in cooperation with the provincial ministers of the Crown responsible for housing and  with representatives of municipalities and Aboriginal communities, may take any measures that the Minister considers appropriate to implement the national housing strategy as quickly as possible.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Conference to be held<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>6.</B>  The Minister must, within 180 days after the coming into force of this Act, convene a conference of the provincial ministers of the Crown responsible for municipal affairs and housing and of representatives of municipalities, Aboriginal communities, non-profit and private sector housing providers and civil society organizations, including those that represent groups in need of adequate housing, in order to</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>a</I>) develop standards and set objectives and targets for the national housing strategy referred to in subsection 3(1) — including targets to end homelessness — with clear timelines and accountability mechanisms, and develop programs to carry out the strategy;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>b</I>) set dates for the commencement of the programs referred to in paragraph (<I>a</I>);</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>c</I>) develop the principles of an agreement between the federal and  provincial governments and representatives of  municipalities, Aboriginal communities, non-profit and private sector housing providers and civil society organizations, including those that represent groups in need of adequate housing, for the development, delivery, monitoring and evaluation of the programs referred to in paragraph (<I>a</I>);</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>d</I>) develop a process for the independent review, addressing and reporting of complaints about possible violations of the right to adequate housing; and</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>e</I>) develop a process for review and follow-up on any concerns or recommendations received from United Nations human rights bodies with respect to the right to adequate housing in Canada.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Report<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>7.</B> The Minister must cause a report on the conference, including the matters referred to in paragraphs 6(<I>a</I>) to (<I>e</I>), to be laid before each House of Parliament on any one of the first five days that the House is sitting following the expiration of 180 days after the end of the conference.
</Para></Block><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="BPT_ImprintE">Published under authority of the Speaker of the House of Commons<br/>Available from:<br/>Publishing and Depository Services<br/>Public Works and Government Services Canada<br/>Ottawa, Ontario K1A 0S5<br/>Telephone: 613-941-5995 or 1-800-635-7943<br/>Fax: 613-954-5779 or 1-800-565-7757<br/>publications@tpsgc-pwgsc.gc.ca<br/>http://publications.gc.ca</Para></Block><Block Align="Yes" LineCnt="N"><Para NoLineBreak="Yes" NoHtml="Yes" Leading="0" Size="0" TopMargin="0" BottomMargin="0"></Para></Block></Bill_Part></Bill>
