<?xml version="1.0"?>
<Bill RHead_reign="60-61 Eliz. II" RHead_ParlYear="2011-2012" DocumentTitle="BILL C-410" Bill_No="C-410" Document_No="411578" xml:lang="EN" Bill_Type="Non-amending" Stage_Name="First-Reading-House" Reprint="No" xml:space="preserve" ChapterNo_E="C. " ChapterNo_F="ch. " Bill-Origin="commons"><Bill_Part Part_Type="Cover" CountLines="No"><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="CovBillNo">C-410</Para></Block><Block><Para TopMargin="24" Size="9" Leading="10" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0" TextAlign="Center">First Session, Forty-first Parliament,</Para></Block><Block><Para Size="9" Leading="10" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0" TextAlign="Center">60-61 Elizabeth II, 2011-2012</Para></Block><Block><Para TopMargin="48" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0" Bold="Yes" TextAlign="Center">HOUSE OF COMMONS OF CANADA</Para></Block><Block><Para TopMargin="42" Size="18" Leading="20" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0" Bold="Yes" TextAlign="Center">BILL C-410</Para></Block><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="CovLongTitle">An Act to establish a Pan-Canadian Strategy for Chronic Cerebrospinal Venous Insufficiency (CCSVI)</Para></Block><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="COV_StageLine"></Para></Block><Block><Para Size="9" AllCaps="Yes" Hyphenate="OFF">first reading, March 26, 2012</Para></Block><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="COV_StageLine"></Para></Block><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="Cover_Sponsors"><SC SC_PerCent="85">Ms. Duncan</SC> (<I>Etobicoke North</I>)</Para></Block><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="Cover_DocNo">411578</Para></Block></Bill_Part><Bill_Part CountLines="No" Part_Type="InsideCover"><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="BPT_InsideCoverE">Also available on the Parliament of Canada Web Site at the following address:<br/><B>http://www.parl.gc.ca</B></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><Para TopMargin="108" BottomMargin="4" Size="10" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">SUMMARY</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" Size="8" Leading="9" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">This enactment requires the Minister of Health to convene a conference with the provincial and territorial ministers responsible for health for the purpose of establishing a pan-Canadian strategy to ensure clinical trials are started for the treatment of chronic cerebrospinal venous insufficiency (CCSVI) and to estimate the funding necessary to undertake those clinical trials in Canada and to track individuals who have been treated for CCSVI.</Para></Block></Bill_Part><Bill_Part Part_Type="MainText" CountLines="Yes" RunningHead_E="Pan-Canadian Strategy for Chronic Cerebrospinal Venous Insufficiency (CCSVI)"><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="MainText_DocNo">411578</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes"><Para Style="Session_Reign">1st Session, 41st Parliament,</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes"><Para Style="Session_Reign">60-61 Elizabeth II, 2011-2012</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes"><Para Style="MainBillOrigin">house of commons of canada</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes"><Para Bold="Yes" Style="MAIN@BillNo_Title">BILL C-410</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes"><Para Style="MAIN@ti;04">An Act to establish a Pan-Canadian Strategy for Chronic Cerebrospinal Venous Insufficiency (CCSVI)</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><MarginalNote>Preamble<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">Whereas there is increasing scientific study of chronic cerebrospinal venous insufficiency (CCSVI), as demonstrated by published peer-reviewed articles, as well as presentations <keep>at major</keep> scientific conferences on CCSVI — name­ly those which took place in Hamilton, Canada (February 2010), New York, United States (July 2010), Washington, United States (October 2010), Katowice, Poland (March 2011), Bologna, Italy (March 2011), Chicago, United States (April 2011), San Diego, United States (May 2011) and Orlando, United States (February 2012);</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">Whereas many different groups in countries all over the world (e.g. Greece, Poland, Jordan, United States) have shown, by means of gold standard catheter venography, the presence of CCSVI in more than 90% of individuals who have multiple sclerosis (MS), and an international, multicentre study of more than 705 cases has shown, using echo-colour-Doppler, the presence of CCSVI in 86% of individuals who have MS;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">Whereas over 30,000 individuals with CCSVI have been treated in over 60 countries, and individuals who received treatment for CCSVI have reduced brain fog, reduced fatigue and improved circulation and motor skills, as demonstrated by improved Expanded Disability Status Scale scores, improved MS Quality of Life scores and improved Modified Fatigue Impact Scale scores;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">Whereas clinical trials have demonstrated the safety of using balloon angioplasty in treating CCSVI;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">Whereas every individual with MS is different, with different venous anatomy, a different course of MS and a different length of illness, and some individuals experience an improvement in symptoms after receiving the treatment for CCSVI;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">Whereas multiple clinical trials on the treatment for CCSVI are underway in the United States, including three Phase II clinical trials approved by the U.S. Food and Drug Administration, and in other countries;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">Whereas the cancelling of medical appointments and mandatory tests, the denial of treatment and the threatening of individuals following treatment for CCSVI is continuing;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">And whereas the Parliament of Canada recognizes that every year 400 Canadians who suffer from MS die, many by taking their own life, and that any delay in starting clinical trials on the treatment for CCSVI may mean more damage to individuals suffering from MS, and possibly the difference between walking and not walking, living independently and living in care, or living and dying;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">Now, therefore, Her Majesty, by and with the advice and consent of the Senate and House of Commons of Canada, enacts as follows:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:SHORT TITLE--><Para TopMargin="10" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">SHORT TITLE</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Short title<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>1.</B> This Act may be cited as the <I>Pan-Canadian Strategy for Chronic Cerebrospinal Venous Insufficiency (CCSVI) Act</I>.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:INTERPRETATION--><Para TopMargin="10" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">INTERPRETATION</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Definitions<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>2.</B> The following definitions apply in this Act.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><MarginalNote>“CCSVI”<br/>« <I>IVCC</I> »<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0">“CCSVI” means chronic cerebrospinal venous insufficiency.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><MarginalNote>“Minister”<br/>« <I>ministre</I> »<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0">“Minister” means the Minister of Health.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><MarginalNote>“treatment for CCSVI”<br/>« <I>traitement de l'IVCC</I> »<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0">“treatment for CCSVI” means the medical procedure that uses balloon angioplasty to widen constricted veins in order to improve blood flow from the brain.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:PAN-CANADIAN STRATEGY--><Para TopMargin="10" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">PAN-CANADIAN STRATEGY</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Conference<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>3.</B> The Minister must, within 30 days after this Act comes into force, convene a conference with the provincial and territorial ministers responsible for health for the purpose of establishing a pan-Canadian strategy for CCSVI in order to, among other things,</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>a</I>) ensure that proper health care is not refused to a person on the ground that the person is seeking, or has obtained, the treatment for CCSVI outside Canada, whether or not that treatment is offered in Canada;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>b</I>) identify the most appropriate level of clinical trials for the treatment of CCSVI to undertake in Canada in order to place Canada at the forefront of the international research;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>c</I>) estimate by May 1, 2012 the funding required to</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="4" FirstLineIndent="0">(i) undertake, by July 1, 2012, clinical trials for the treatment for CCSVI in multiple centres across Canada, and</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="4" FirstLineIndent="0">(ii) track individuals who have received the treatment for CCSVI, whether or not that treatment was received in Canada;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>d</I>) establish, by May 1, 2012, an advisory panel, to be composed of experts who have been or are actively engaged in imaging or treating individuals with CCSVI and of an individual who has been treated for CCSVI, to</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="4" FirstLineIndent="0">(i) advise the Minister on the treatment for CCSVI,</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="4" FirstLineIndent="0">(ii) advise on criteria for a call for further research proposals on clinical trials for the treatment for CCSVI,</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="4" FirstLineIndent="0">(iii) advise on the basis for selecting the best research proposals to fund,</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="4" FirstLineIndent="0">(iv) advise on the development of appropriate standards for diagnosing and treating CCSVI,</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="4" FirstLineIndent="0">(v) advise on the appropriate training and expertise required for individuals performing that diagnosis and of those providing that treatment, and</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="4" FirstLineIndent="0">(vi) advise on the most appropriate and efficient mechanisms for tracking individ­uals who undergo the treatment for CCSVI to ensure the accumulation of knowledge relating to the treatment’s efficacy, its effect on the individual’s quality of life, the duration of that effect, the need for any repeat treatment for CCSVI and whether there were any side effects or risks that should be considered in future decisions to provide that treatment; and</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>e</I>) ensure that clinical trials referred to in paragraph (<I>b</I>) begin in Canada by July 1, 2012.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Preparation and publication of report<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>4.</B> The Minister must prepare a report setting out the pan-Canadian strategy and publish it on the departmental website within one year after the conclusion of the conference referred to in section 3.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Report to Parliament<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>5.</B> The Minister must cause a copy of the report referred to in section 4 to be laid before each House of Parliament on any of the first 90 days on which that House is sitting after the report has been published on the departmental website.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:REVIEW AND REPORT--><Para TopMargin="10" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">REVIEW AND REPORT</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Review and report<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>6.</B> The Government of Canada must</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>a</I>) complete a review of the effectiveness of the pan-Canadian strategy no later than five years after the day on which the report referred to in section 4 is published on the departmental website; and</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>b</I>) table a report of its findings before each House of Parliament within the next ten sitting days after the day on which the review is completed.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:REGULATIONS--><Para TopMargin="10" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">REGULATIONS</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Regulations<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>7.</B> The Governor in Council may make regulations for carrying out the purposes and provisions of this Act.</Para></Block><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="BPT_ImprintE">Published under authority of the Speaker of the House of Commons<br/>Available from:<br/>Publishing and Depository Services<br/>Public Works and Government Services Canada<br/>Ottawa, Ontario K1A 0S5<br/>Telephone: 613-941-5995 or 1-800-635-7943<br/>Fax: 613-954-5779 or 1-800-565-7757<br/>publications@tpsgc-pwgsc.gc.ca<br/>http://publications.gc.ca</Para></Block><Block Align="Yes" LineCnt="N"><Para NoLineBreak="Yes" NoHtml="Yes" Leading="0" Size="0" TopMargin="0" BottomMargin="0"></Para></Block></Bill_Part></Bill>
