<?xml version="1.0"?>
<Bill RHead_reign="60-61-62 Eliz. II" RHead_ParlYear="2011-2012-2013" DocumentTitle="BILL C-43" Bill_No="C-43" Document_No="90656" xml:lang="EN" Bill_Type="Non-amending" Stage_Name="Assented-to" Reprint="No" xml:space="preserve" ChapterNo_E="C. 16" ChapterNo_F="ch. 16" Bill-Origin="commons"><Bill_Part Part_Type="Cover" CountLines="No"><Block><Para TopMargin="24" Size="9" Leading="10" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0" TextAlign="Center">First Session, Forty-first Parliament,</Para></Block><Block><Para Size="9" Leading="10" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0" TextAlign="Center">60-61-62 Elizabeth II, 2011-2012-2013</Para></Block><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="COV@StatutesTitle">STATUTES OF CANADA 2013<br/>CHAPTER 16</Para></Block><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="CovLongTitle">An Act to amend the Immigration and Refugee Protection Act</Para></Block><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="COV_StageLine"></Para></Block><Block><Para BottomMargin="14" Size="11" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0" Bold="Yes" TextAlign="Center">ASSENTED TO</Para></Block><Block><Para Size="8" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0" TextAlign="Center">19th JUNE, 2013</Para></Block><Block><Para TopMargin="4" Size="8" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0" TextAlign="Center">BILL C-43</Para></Block><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="COV_StageLine"></Para></Block></Bill_Part><Bill_Part CountLines="No" Part_Type="InsideCover"><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="BPT_InsideCoverE">Available on the Parliament of Canada Web Site at the following address:<br/><B>http://www.parl.gc.ca</B></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><Para TopMargin="108" BottomMargin="4" Size="10" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">SUMMARY</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" Size="8" Leading="9" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">This enactment amends the <I>Immigration and Refugee Protection Act</I> to limit the review mechanisms for certain foreign nationals and permanent residents who are inadmissible on such grounds as serious criminality. It also amends the Act to provide for the denial of temporary resident status to foreign nationals based on public policy considerations and provides for the entry into Canada of certain foreign nationals, including family members, who would otherwise be inadmissible. Finally, this enactment provides for the mandatory imposition of minimum conditions on permanent residents or foreign nationals who are the subject of a report on inadmissibility on grounds of security that is referred to the Immigration Division or a removal order for inadmissibility on grounds of security or who, on grounds of security, are named in a certificate that is referred to the Federal Court.</Para></Block></Bill_Part><Bill_Part Part_Type="MainText" CountLines="No" RunningHead_E="Immigration and Refugee Protection"><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="MAIN@RoyalAssentTitle">60-61-62 ELIZABETH II</Para></Block><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="MAIN@RoyalAssentTitle">——————</Para></Block><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="MAIN@RoyalAssentTitle">CHAPTER 16</Para></Block><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="LongTitleAssent">An Act to amend the Immigration and Refugee Protection Act</Para></Block><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="MAIN@RoyalAssentDate">[<I>Assented to 19th June, 2013</I>]</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">Her Majesty, by and with the advice and consent of the Senate and House of Commons of Canada, enacts as follows:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:SHORT TITLE--><Para TopMargin="10" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">SHORT TITLE</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Short title<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>1.</B> This Act may be cited as the <I>Faster Removal of Foreign Criminals Act</I>.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:IMMIGRATION AND REFUGEE PROTECTION ACT--><MarginalNote>2001, c. 27<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="10" Bold="Yes" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">IMMIGRATION AND REFUGEE PROTECTION ACT</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>2005, c. 38, s.118<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>2.</B> Paragraph 4(2)(<I>d</I>) of the <I>Immigration and Refugee Protection Act</I> is replaced by the following:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>d</I>) declarations referred to in section 42.1.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>3.</B> Subsection 6(3) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Exception<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(3) Despite subsection (2), the Minister may not delegate the power conferred by section 22.1 or subsection 42.1(1) or (2) or 77(1).</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>4.</B> Subsection 14(2) of the Act is amended by striking out “and” at the end of paragraph (<I>f</I>) and by adding the following after paragraph (<I>f</I>):</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>f.1</I>) the power to inspect, including the power to require documents to be provided for inspection, for the purpose of verifying compliance with undertakings; and</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>5.</B> (1) Section 16 of the Act is amended by adding the following after subsection (1):</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Obligation — appear for examination<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(1.1) A person who makes an application must, on request of an officer, appear for an examination.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes">(2) Section 16 of the Act is amended by adding the following after subsection (2):</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Obligation — interview<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(2.1) A foreign national who makes an application must, on request of an officer, appear for an interview for the purpose of an investigation conducted by the Canadian Secu- rity Intelligence Service under section 15 of the <I>Canadian Security Intelligence Service Act</I> for the purpose of providing advice or information to the Minister under section 14 of that Act and must answer truthfully all questions put to them during the interview.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>6.</B> Section 20 of the Act is amended by adding the following after subsection (1):</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Declaration<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(1.1) A foreign national who is the subject of a declaration made under subsection 22.1(1) must not seek to enter or remain in Canada as a temporary resident.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>7.</B> Subsection 22(1) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Temporary resident<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>22.</B> (1) A foreign national becomes a temporary resident if an officer is satisfied that the foreign national has applied for that status, has met the obligations set out in paragraph <keep>20(1)(<I>b</I>),</keep> is not inadmissible and is not the subject of a declaration made under subsection 22.1(1).</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>8.</B> The Act is amended by adding the following after section 22:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Declaration<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>22.1</B> (1) The Minister may, on the Minister’s own initiative, declare that a foreign national, other than a foreign national referred to in section 19, may not become a temporary resident if the Minister is of the opinion that it is justified by public policy considerations.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Effective period<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(2) A declaration has effect for the period specified by the Minister, which is not to exceed 36 months.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Revocation<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(3) The Minister may, at any time, revoke a declaration or shorten its effective period.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Report to Parliament<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(4) The report required under section 94 must include the number of declarations made under subsection (1) and set out the public policy considerations that led to the making of the declarations.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>2010, c. 8, s. 4(1)<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>9.</B> Subsection 25(1) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Humanitarian and compassionate considerations — request of foreign national<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>25.</B> (1) The Minister must, on request of a foreign national in Canada who is inadmissible — other than under section 34, 35 or 37 — or who does not meet the requirements of this Act, and may, on request of a foreign national outside Canada — other than a foreign national who is inadmissible under section 34, 35 or 37 —, examine the circumstances concerning the foreign national and may grant the foreign national permanent resident status or an exemption from any applicable criteria or obligations of this Act if the Minister is of the opinion that it is justified by humanitarian and compassionate considerations relating to the foreign national, taking into account the best interests of a child directly affected.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>2010, c. 8, s. 5<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>10.</B> Subsection 25.1(1) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Humanitarian and compassionate considerations — Minister’s own initiative<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>25.1</B> (1) The Minister may, on the Minister’s own initiative, examine the circumstances concerning a foreign national who is inadmissible — other than under section 34, 35 or 37 — or who does not meet the requirements of this Act and may grant the foreign national permanent resident status or an exemption from any applicable criteria or obligations of this Act if the Minister is of the opinion that it is justified by humanitarian and compassionate considerations relating to the foreign national, taking into account the best interests of a child directly affected.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>11.</B> Section 26 of the Act is amended by adding the following after paragraph (<I>b</I>):</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>b.1</I>) declarations referred to in subsection 22.1(1);</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>12.</B> Section 32 of the Act is amended by adding the following after paragraph (<I>d</I>):</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>d.1</I>) the conditions that must or may be imposed, individually or by class, on individ- uals and entities — including employers and educational institutions — in respect of permanent residents and foreign nationals, or that must or may be varied or cancelled;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>d.2</I>) the power to inspect, including the power to require documents to be provided for inspection, for the purpose of verifying compliance with the conditions imposed under paragraphs (<I>d</I>) and (<I>d.1</I>);</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>d.3</I>) the consequences of a failure to comply with the conditions referred to in paragraphs (<I>d</I>) and (<I>d.1</I>);</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>13.</B> (1) Paragraph 34(1)(<I>a</I>) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>a</I>) engaging in an act of espionage that is against Canada or that is contrary to Canada’s interests;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes">(2) Subsection 34(1) of the Act is amended by adding the following after paragraph (<I>b</I>):</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>b.1</I>) engaging in an act of subversion against a democratic government, institution or process as they are understood in Canada;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes">(2.1) Paragraph 34(1)(<I>f</I>) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>f</I>) being a member of an organization that there are reasonable grounds to believe engages, has engaged or will engage in acts referred to in paragraph (<I>a</I>), (<I>b</I>), (<I>b.1</I>) or (<I>c</I>).</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes">(3) Subsection 34(2) of the Act is repealed.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>14.</B> Subsection 35(2) of the Act is repealed.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>15.</B> Subsection 37(2) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Application<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(2) Paragraph (1)(<I>a</I>) does not lead to a determination of inadmissibility by reason only of the fact that the permanent resident or foreign national entered Canada with the assistance of a person who is involved in organized criminal activity.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>16.</B> (1) Paragraph 40(2)(<I>a</I>) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>a</I>) the permanent resident or the foreign national continues to be inadmissible for misrepresentation for a period of five years following, in the case of a determination outside Canada, a final determination of inadmissibility under subsection (1) or, in the case of a determination in Canada, the date the removal order is enforced; and</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes">(2) Section 40 of the Act is amended by adding the following after subsection (2):</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Inadmissible<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(3) A foreign national who is inadmissible under this section may not apply for permanent resident status during the period referred to in paragraph (2)(<I>a</I>).</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>17.</B> Section 42 of the Act is renumbered as subsection 42(1) and is amended by adding the following:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Exception<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(2) In the case of a foreign national referred to in subsection (1) who is a temporary resident or who has made an application for temporary resident status or an application to remain in Canada as a temporary resident,</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>a</I>) the matters referred to in paragraph (1)(<I>a</I>) constitute inadmissibility only if the family member is inadmissible under section 34, 35 or 37; and</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>b</I>) the matters referred to in paragraph (1)(<I>b</I>) constitute inadmissibility only if the foreign national is an accompanying family member of a person who is inadmissible under section 34, 35 or 37.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>18.</B> The Act is amended by adding the following after section 42:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Exception — application to Minister<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>42.1</B> (1) The Minister may, on application by a foreign national, declare that the matters referred to in section 34, paragraphs 35(1)(<I>b</I>) and (<I>c</I>) and subsection 37(1) do not constitute inadmissibility in respect of the foreign national if they satisfy the Minister that it is not contrary to the national interest.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Exception — Minister’s own initiative<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(2) The Minister may, on the Minister’s own initiative, declare that the matters referred to in section 34, paragraphs 35(1)(<I>b</I>) and (<I>c</I>) and subsection 37(1) do not constitute inadmissibility in respect of a foreign national if the Minister is satisfied that it is not contrary to the national interest.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Considerations<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(3) In determining whether to make a declaration, the Minister may only take into account national security and public safety considerations, but, in his or her analysis, is not limited to considering the danger that the foreign national presents to the public or the security of Canada.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>19.</B> Section 44 of the Act is amended by adding the following after subsection (3):</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Conditions — inadmissibility on grounds of security<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(4) If a report on inadmissibility on grounds of security is referred to the Immigration Division and the permanent resident or the foreign national who is the subject of the report is not detained, an officer shall also impose the prescribed conditions on the person.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Duration of conditions<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(5) The prescribed conditions imposed under subsection (4) cease to apply only when</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>a</I>) the person is detained;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>b</I>) the report on inadmissibility on grounds of security is withdrawn;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>c</I>) a final determination is made not to make a removal order against the person for inadmissibility on grounds of security;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>d</I>) the Minister makes a declaration under subsection 42.1(1) or (2) in relation to the person; or</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>e</I>) a removal order is enforced against the person in accordance with the regulations.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>20.</B> (1) Subsection 46(1) of the Act is amended by striking out “or” at the end of paragraph (<I>c</I>), by adding “or” at the end of paragraph (<I>d</I>) and by adding the following after paragraph (<I>d</I>):</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>e</I>) on approval by an officer of their application to renounce their permanent resident status.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes">(2) Section 46 of the Act is amended by adding the following after subsection (1):</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Effect of renunciation<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(1.1) A person who loses their permanent resident status under paragraph (1)(<I>e</I>) becomes a temporary resident for a period of six months unless they make their application to renounce their permanent resident status at a port of entry or are not physically present in Canada on the day on which their application is approved.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>21.</B> Section 53 of the Act is amended by adding the following after paragraph (<I>a</I>):</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>a.1</I>) the form and manner in which an application to renounce permanent resident status must be made and the conditions that must be met before such an application may be approved;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>22.</B> Section 56 of the Act is renumbered as subsection 56(1) and is amended by adding the following:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Conditions — inadmissibility on grounds of security<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(2) If an officer orders the release of a permanent resident or foreign national who is the subject of either a report on inadmissibility on grounds of security that is referred to the Immigration Division or a removal order for inadmissibility on grounds of security, the officer must also impose the prescribed conditions on the person.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Duration of conditions<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(3) The prescribed conditions imposed under subsection (2) cease to apply only when one of the events described in paragraphs 44(5)(<I>a</I>) to (<I>e</I>) occurs.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>23.</B> Section 58 of the Act is amended by adding the following after subsection (3):</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Conditions — inadmissibility on grounds of security<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(4) If the Immigration Division orders the release of a permanent resident or foreign national who is the subject of either a report on inadmissibility on grounds of security that is referred to the Immigration Division or a removal order for inadmissibility on grounds of security, it shall also impose the prescribed conditions on the person.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Duration of conditions<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(5) The prescribed conditions imposed under subsection (4) cease to apply only when one of the events described in paragraphs 44(5)(<I>a</I>) to (<I>e</I>) occurs.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>24.</B> Subsection 64(2) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Serious criminality<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(2) For the purpose of subsection (1), serious criminality must be with respect to a crime that was punished in Canada by a term of imprisonment of at least six months or that is described in paragraph 36(1)(<I>b</I>) or (<I>c</I>).</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>25.</B> The Act is amended by adding the following after section 77:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Conditions — inadmissibility on grounds of security<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>77.1</B> (1) If a certificate stating that a permanent resident or foreign national is inadmissible on grounds of security is referred to the Federal Court and no warrant for the person’s arrest and detention is issued under section 81, the Minister of Public Safety and Emergency Preparedness shall impose the prescribed conditions on the person who is named in the certificate.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Duration of conditions<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(2) The prescribed conditions imposed under subsection (1) cease to apply only when</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>a</I>) the person is detained;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>b</I>) the certificate stating that the person is inadmissible on grounds of security is withdrawn;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>c</I>) a final determination is made that the certificate is not reasonable;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>d</I>) the Minister makes a declaration under subsection 42.1(1) or (2) in relation to the person; or</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>e</I>) a removal order is enforced against the person in accordance with the regulations.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>26.</B> Section 82 of the Act is amended by adding the following after subsection (5):</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Conditions — inadmissibility on grounds of security<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(6) If the judge orders the release, under paragraph (5)(<I>b</I>), of a person who is named in a certificate stating that they are inadmissible on grounds of security, the judge shall also impose the prescribed conditions on the person.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>No review of conditions<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(7) The prescribed conditions imposed under subsection (6) are not subject to review under subsection (4).</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Variation of conditions<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(8) If a person is subject to the prescribed conditions imposed under subsection (6), any variation of conditions under subsection 82.1(1) or paragraph 82.2(3)(<I>c</I>) is not to result in the person being subject to conditions that do not include those prescribed conditions.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Duration of conditions<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(9) The prescribed conditions imposed under subsection (6) cease to apply only when one of the events described in paragraphs 77.1(2)(<I>a</I>) to (<I>e</I>) occurs.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>2008, c. 3, s. 4<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>27.</B> Subsection 87.2(1) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Regulations<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>87.2</B> (1) The regulations may provide for any matter relating to the application of this Division and may include provisions respecting</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>a</I>) the conditions that must be imposed under subsection 77.1(1) or 82(6); and</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>b</I>) the conditions and qualifications that persons must meet to be included in the list referred to in subsection 85(1) and the additional qualifications that are assets that may be taken into account for that purpose.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:TRANSITIONAL PROVISIONS--><Para TopMargin="10" Bold="Yes" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">TRANSITIONAL PROVISIONS</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Definition of “the Act”<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>28.</B> In sections 29 to 35, “the Act” means the <I>Immigration and Refugee Protection Act</I>.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Humanitarian and compassionate considerations<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>29.</B> Subsection 25(1) of the Act, as it read immediately before the day on which section 9 comes into force, continues to apply in respect of a request made under that subsection 25(1) if, before the day on which section 9 comes into force, no decision has been made in respect of the request.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Imposition of conditions by officer<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>30.</B> (1) When circumstances permit the officer to do so, an officer referred to in subsection 44(4) of the Act must impose the conditions referred to in that subsection on a permanent resident or foreign national who, on the day on which this section comes into force,</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0" Bold="Yes">(<I>a</I>) is the subject of either a report on inadmissibility on grounds of security that was referred to the Immigration Division before the day on which this section comes into force or a removal order for inadmissibility on grounds of security that was made before the day on which this section comes into force;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0" Bold="Yes">(<I>b</I>) is not detained; and</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0" Bold="Yes">(<I>c</I>) is not subject to a release order with conditions that was made under section 58 of the Act.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Deemed imposition<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes">(2) The conditions imposed under subsection (1) are deemed to have been imposed under subsection 44(4) of the Act.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Imposition of conditions by Immigration Division<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>31.</B> (1) On application by the Minister of Public Safety and Emergency Preparedness, the Immigration Division must vary a release order with conditions that was made under section 58 of the Act before the day on which this section comes into force in order to impose the conditions referred to in subsection 58(4) of the Act on a permanent resident or foreign national who is the subject of either a report on inadmissibility on grounds of security or a removal order for inadmissibility on grounds of security.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Deemed imposition<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes">(2) The conditions imposed under subsection (1) are deemed to have been imposed under subsection 58(4) of the Act.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Appeal<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>32.</B> Subsection 64(2) of the Act, as it read immediately before the day on which section 24 comes into force, continues to apply in respect of a person who had a right of appeal under subsection 63(1) of the Act before the day on which section 24 comes into force.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Appeal<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>33.</B> Subsection 64(2) of the Act, as it read immediately before the day on which section 24 comes into force, continues to apply in respect of a person who is the subject of a report that is referred to the Immigration Division under subsection 44(2) of the Act before the day on which section 24 comes into force.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Imposition of conditions by the Minister<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>34.</B> Section 77.1 of the Act applies with respect to a certificate that was referred to the Federal Court before the day on which this section comes into force.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Imposition of conditions by judge<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>35.</B> (1) On application by the Minister of Public Safety and Emergency Preparedness, a judge, as defined in section 76 of the Act, must vary an order that was made under paragraph 82(5)(<I>b</I>) of the Act before the day on which this section comes into force in order to impose the conditions referred to in subsection 82(6) of the Act on a permanent resident or foreign national who is named in a certificate stating that they are inadmissible on grounds of security.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Deemed imposition<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes">(2) The conditions imposed under subsection (1) are deemed to have been imposed under subsection 82(6) of the Act.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:COORDINATING AMENDMENTS--><Para TopMargin="10" Bold="Yes" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">COORDINATING AMENDMENTS</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Bill C-31<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>36.</B> (1) Subsections (2) to (11) apply if Bill C-31, introduced in the 1st session of the 41st Parliament and entitled the <I>Protecting Canada’s Immigration System Act</I> (referred to in this section as the “other Act”), receives royal assent.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes">(2) On the first day on which both section 3 of the other Act and section 3 of this Act are in force, subsection 6(3) of the <I>Immigration and Refugee Protection Act</I> is replaced by the following:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Exception<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(3) Despite subsection (2), the Minister may not delegate the power conferred by subsection 20.1(1), section 22.1 or subsection 42.1(1) or (2) or 77(1).</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes">(3) On the first day on which both section 13 of the other Act and section 9 of this Act are in force, subsection 25(1) of the <I>Immigration and Refugee Protection Act</I> is replaced by the following:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Humanitarian and compassionate considerations — request of foreign national<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>25.</B> (1) Subject to subsection (1.2), the Minister must, on request of a foreign national in Canada who applies for permanent resident status and who is inadmissible — other than under section 34, 35 or 37 — or who does not meet the requirements of this Act, and may, on request of a foreign national outside Canada — other than a foreign national who is inadmissible under section 34, 35 or 37 — who applies for a permanent resident visa, examine the circumstances concerning the foreign national and may grant the foreign national permanent resident status or an exemption from any applicable criteria or obligations of this Act if the Minister is of the opinion that it is justified by humanitarian and compassionate considerations relating to the foreign national, taking into account the best interests of a child directly affected.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes">(4) If section 24 of the other Act comes into force before section 22 of this Act, then that section 22 is replaced by the following:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>22.</B> Section 56 of the Act is amended by adding the following after subsection (2):</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Conditions — inadmissibility on grounds of security<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(3) If an officer orders the release of a permanent resident or foreign national who is the subject of either a report on inadmissibility on grounds of security that is referred to the Immigration Division or a removal order for inadmissibility on grounds of security, the officer must also impose the prescribed conditions on the person.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Duration of conditions<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(4) The prescribed conditions imposed under subsection (3) cease to apply only when one of the events described in paragraphs 44(5)(<I>a</I>) to (<I>e</I>) occurs.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes">(5) If section 22 of this Act comes into force before section 24 of the other Act, then</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0" Bold="Yes">(<I>a</I>) that section 24 is deemed never to have come into force and is repealed; and</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0" Bold="Yes">(<I>b</I>) section 56 of the <I>Immigration and Refugee Protection Act</I> is amended by adding the following after subsection (1):</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Period of detention — designated foreign national<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(1.1) Despite subsection (1), a designated foreign national who is detained under this Division and who was 16 years of age or older on the day of the arrival that is the subject of the designation in question must be detained until</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>a</I>) a final determination is made to allow their claim for refugee protection or application for protection;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>b</I>) they are released as a result of the Immigration Division ordering their release under section 58; or</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>c</I>) they are released as a result of the Minister ordering their release under section 58.1.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes">(6) If section 24 of the other Act comes into force on the same day as section 22 of this Act, then that section 24 is deemed to have come into force before that section 22 and subsection (4) applies as a consequence.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes">(7) If subsection 26(2) of the other Act comes into force before section 23 of this Act,</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0" Bold="Yes">(<I>a</I>) that section 23 is replaced by the following:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>23.</B> Section 58 of the Act is amended by adding the following after subsection (4):</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Conditions — inadmissibility on grounds of security<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(5) If the Immigration Division orders the release of a permanent resident or foreign national who is the subject of either a report on inadmissibility on grounds of security that is referred to the Immigration Division or a removal order for inadmissibility on grounds of security, it shall also impose the prescribed conditions on the person.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Duration of conditions<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(6) The prescribed conditions imposed under subsection (5) cease to apply only when one of the events described in paragraphs 44(5)(<I>a</I>) to (<I>e</I>) occurs.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0" Bold="Yes">(<I>b</I>) every reference to subsection 58(4) in section 31 of this Act is replaced by a reference to subsection 58(5).</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes">(8) If section 23 of this Act comes into force before subsection 26(2) of the other Act, then</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0" Bold="Yes">(<I>a</I>) that subsection 26(2) is deemed never to have come into force and is repealed;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0" Bold="Yes">(<I>b</I>) section 58 of the <I>Immigration and Refugee Protection Act</I> is amended by adding the following after subsection (3):</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Conditions — designated foreign national<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(3.1) If the Immigration Division orders the release of a designated foreign national who was 16 years of age or older on the day of the arrival that is the subject of the designation in question, it shall also impose any condition that is prescribed.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0" Bold="Yes">(<I>c</I>) every reference to subsection 58(4) in the following provisions of the <I>Immigration and Refugee Protection Act</I> is replaced by a reference to subsection 58(3.1):</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="4" FirstLineIndent="0" Bold="Yes">(i) paragraph 11(1.3)(<I>a</I>), as enacted by section 5 of the other Act,</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="4" FirstLineIndent="0" Bold="Yes">(ii) paragraph 20.2(3)(<I>a</I>), as enacted by section 10 of the other Act,</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="4" FirstLineIndent="0" Bold="Yes">(iii) paragraph 24(7)(<I>a</I>), as enacted by section 12 of the other Act, and</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="4" FirstLineIndent="0" Bold="Yes">(iv) paragraph 25(1.03)(<I>a</I>), as enacted by subsection 13(1) of the other Act.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes">(9) If subsection 26(2) of the other Act comes into force on the same day as section 23 of this Act, then that subsection 26(2) is deemed to have come into force before that section 23 and subsection (7) applies as a consequence.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes">(10) On the first day on which both section 27 of the other Act and section 23 of this Act are in force, section 58.1 of the <I>Immigration and Refugee Protection Act</I> is amended by adding the following after subsection (3):</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Conditions — inadmissibility on grounds of security<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(4) If the Minister orders the release of a designated foreign national who is the subject of either a report on inadmissibility on grounds of security that is referred to the Immigration Division or a removal order for inadmissibility on grounds of security, the Minister must also impose the prescribed conditions on the person.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Duration of conditions<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(5) The prescribed conditions imposed under subsection (4) cease to apply only when one of the events described in paragraphs 44(5)(<I>a</I>) to (<I>e</I>) occurs.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes">(11) On the first day on which both section 28 of the other Act and section 23 of this Act are in force, section 61 of the <I>Immigration and Refugee Protection Act</I> is amended by adding the following after paragraph (<I>a.2</I>):</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>a.3</I>) the conditions that an officer, the Immigration Division or the Minister must impose with respect to the release of a permanent resident or foreign national who is the subject of either a report on inadmissibility on grounds of security or a removal order for inadmissibility on grounds of security;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Bill C-38<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>37.</B> (1) Subsections (2) to (4) apply if Bill C-38, introduced in the 1st session of the 41st Parliament and entitled the <I>Jobs, Growth and Long-term Prosperity Act</I> (referred to in this section as the “other Act”), receives royal assent.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes">(2) If section 705 of the other Act comes into force before section 12 of this Act, then</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0" Bold="Yes">(<I>a</I>) that section 12 is deemed never to have come into force and is repealed; and</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0" Bold="Yes">(<I>b</I>) paragraphs 32(<I>d.1</I>) to (<I>d.3</I>) of the <I>Immigration and Refugee Protection Act</I> are replaced by the following:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>d.1</I>) the conditions that must or may be imposed, individually or by class, on individ- uals and entities — including employers and educational institutions — in respect of permanent residents and foreign nationals, or that must or may be varied or cancelled;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>d.2</I>) the power to inspect, including the power to require documents to be provided for inspection, for the purpose of verifying compliance with the conditions imposed under paragraphs (<I>d</I>) and (<I>d.1</I>);</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>d.3</I>) the consequences of a failure to comply with the conditions referred to in paragraphs (<I>d</I>) and (<I>d.1</I>);</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes">(3) If section 12 of this Act comes into force before section 705 of the other Act, that section 705 is deemed never to have come into force and is repealed.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes">(4) If section 705 of the other Act and section 12 of this Act come into force on the same day, then that section 12 is deemed to have come into force before that section 705 and subsection (3) applies as a consequence.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:COMING INTO FORCE--><Para TopMargin="10" Bold="Yes" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">COMING INTO FORCE</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Order in council<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>38.</B> (1) Sections 6 to 8, 16, 17 and 20 come into force on a day or days to be fixed by order of the Governor in Council.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Order in council<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes">(2) Sections 19, 22, 23, 25 to 27, 30, 31, 34 and 35 come into force on a day to be fixed by order of the Governor in Council.</Para></Block><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="BPT_ImprintE"><br/><br/>Published under authority of the Speaker of the House of Commons</Para></Block><Block Align="Yes" LineCnt="N"><Para NoLineBreak="Yes" NoHtml="Yes" Leading="0" Size="0" TopMargin="0" BottomMargin="0"></Para></Block></Bill_Part></Bill>
