<?xml version="1.0"?>
<Bill RHead_reign="60-61-62 Eliz. II" RHead_ParlYear="2011-2012-2013" DocumentTitle="BILL C-51" Bill_No="C-51" Document_No="90682" xml:lang="EN" Bill_Type="Non-amending" Stage_Name="Assented-to" Reprint="No" xml:space="preserve" ChapterNo_E="C. 29" ChapterNo_F="ch. 29" Bill-Origin="commons"><Bill_Part Part_Type="Cover" CountLines="No"><Block><Para TopMargin="24" Size="9" Leading="10" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0" TextAlign="Center">First Session, Forty-first Parliament,</Para></Block><Block><Para Size="9" Leading="10" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0" TextAlign="Center">60-61-62 Elizabeth II, 2011-2012-2013</Para></Block><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="COV@StatutesTitle">STATUTES OF CANADA 2013<br/>CHAPTER 29</Para></Block><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="CovLongTitle">An Act to amend the Witness Protection Program Act and to make a consequential amendment to another Act</Para></Block><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="COV_StageLine"></Para></Block><Block><Para BottomMargin="14" Size="11" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0" Bold="Yes" TextAlign="Center">ASSENTED TO</Para></Block><Block><Para Size="8" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0" TextAlign="Center">26th JUNE, 2013</Para></Block><Block><Para TopMargin="4" Size="8" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0" TextAlign="Center">BILL C-51</Para></Block><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="COV_StageLine"></Para></Block></Bill_Part><Bill_Part CountLines="No" Part_Type="InsideCover"><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="BPT_InsideCoverE">Available on the Parliament of Canada Web Site at the following address:<br/><B>http://www.parl.gc.ca</B></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><Para TopMargin="108" BottomMargin="4" Size="10" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">RECOMMENDATION</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" Size="8" Leading="9" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">His Excellency the Governor General recommends to the House of Commons the appropriation of public revenue under the circumstances, in the manner and for the purposes set out in a measure entitled “<I>An Act to amend the Witness Protection Program Act and to make a consequential amendment to another Act</I>”.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><Para TopMargin="60" BottomMargin="4" Size="10" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">SUMMARY</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" Size="8" Leading="9" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">This enactment amends the <I>Witness Protection Program Act</I> to, among other things,</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" Size="8" Leading="9" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">(<I>a</I>) provide for the designation of a provincial or municipal witness protection program so that certain provisions of that Act apply to such a program;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" Size="8" Leading="9" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">(<I>b</I>) authorize the Commissioner of the Royal Canadian Mounted Police to coordinate, at the request of an official of a designated provincial or municipal program, the activities of federal departments, agencies and services in order to facilitate a change of identity for persons admitted to the designated program;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" Size="8" Leading="9" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">(<I>c</I>) add prohibitions on the disclosure of information relating to persons admitted to designated provincial and municipal programs, to the means and methods by which witnesses are protected and to persons who provide or assist in providing protection;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" Size="8" Leading="9" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">(<I>d</I>) specify the circumstances under which disclosure of protected information is nevertheless permitted;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" Size="8" Leading="9" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">(<I>e</I>) exempt a person from any liability or other punishment for stating that they do not provide or assist in providing protection to witnesses or that they do not know that a person is protected under a witness protection program;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" Size="8" Leading="9" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">(<I>f</I>) expand the categories of witnesses who may be admitted to the federal Witness Protection Program to include persons who assist federal departments, agencies or services that have a national security, national defence or public safety mandate and who may require protection as a result;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" Size="8" Leading="9" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">(<I>g</I>) allow witnesses in the federal Witness Protection Program to end their protection voluntarily;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" Size="8" Leading="9" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">(<I>h</I>) extend the period during which protection may, in an emergency, be provided to a person who has not been admitted to the federal Witness Protection Program; and</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" Size="8" Leading="9" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">(<I>i</I>) make a consequential amendment to another Act.</Para></Block></Bill_Part><Bill_Part Part_Type="MainText" CountLines="No" RunningHead_E="Witness Protection Program"><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="MAIN@RoyalAssentTitle">60-61-62 ELIZABETH II</Para></Block><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="MAIN@RoyalAssentTitle">——————</Para></Block><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="MAIN@RoyalAssentTitle">CHAPTER 29</Para></Block><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="LongTitleAssent">An Act to amend the Witness Protection Program Act and to make a consequential amendment to another Act</Para></Block><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="MAIN@RoyalAssentDate">[<I>Assented to 26th June, 2013</I>]</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">Her Majesty, by and with the advice and consent of the Senate and House of Commons of Canada, enacts as follows:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:SHORT TITLE--><Para TopMargin="10" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">SHORT TITLE</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Short title<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>1.</B> This Act may be cited as the <I>Safer Witnesses Act</I>.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:WITNESS PROTECTION PROGRAM ACT--><MarginalNote>1996, c. 15<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="10" Bold="Yes" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">WITNESS PROTECTION PROGRAM ACT</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>2.</B> The long title of the <I>Witness Protection Program Act</I> is replaced by the following:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="10" LeftMargin="4" FirstLineIndent="-4" Hyphenate="OFF">An Act respecting the establishment and operation of a federal program for the protection of certain persons providing information or assistance and respecting the protection of persons admitted to certain provincial or municipal protection programs</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>3.</B> (1) The definition “protection” in section 2 of the Act is replaced by the following:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>“protection”<br/>« <I>protection</I> »<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0">“protection” may include relocation, accommodation and change of identity as well as counselling and financial support for those or any other purposes in order to ensure the security of a person or to facilitate the person’s re-establishment or becoming self-sufficient;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes">(2) The definitions “<AltLang xml:lang="fr">bénéficiaire</AltLang>” and “<AltLang xml:lang="fr">programme</AltLang>” in section 2 of the French version of the Act are replaced by the following:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>« bénéficiaire »<br/>“<I>protectee</I>”<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0"><AltLang xml:lang="fr">« bénéficiaire » Personne jouissant de la protection du Programme.</AltLang></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><MarginalNote>« Programme »<br/>“<I>Program</I>”<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0"><AltLang xml:lang="fr">« Programme » Le Programme de protection des témoins instauré par l’article 4.</AltLang></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes">(3) The definition “witness” in section 2 of the Act is amended by striking out “or” at the end of paragraph (<I>a</I>) and by replacing paragraph (<I>b</I>) with the following:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>b</I>) a person who has assisted or has agreed to assist a federal security, defence or safety organization and who may require protection because of a risk to his or her security arising in relation to the assistance, or</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>c</I>) a person who, because of their relationship to or association with a person referred to in paragraph (<I>a</I>) or (<I>b</I>), may also require protection for the reasons referred to in that paragraph.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes">(4) Section 2 of the Act is amended by adding the following in alphabetical order:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>“designated program”<br/>« <I>programme désigné</I> »<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0">“designated program” means a provincial or municipal program that is set out in the schedule;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><MarginalNote>“designated program protectee”<br/>« <I>bénéficiaire d’un programme désigné</I> »<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0">“designated program protectee” means a person who is receiving protection under a designated program;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><MarginalNote>“federal security, defence or safety organization”<br/>« <I>organisation fédérale de sécurité ou de défense</I> »<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0">“federal security, defence or safety organization” means a federal department, agency or service that has a mandate relating to national security, national defence or public safety matters;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><MarginalNote>“protected person”<br/>« <I>personne protégée</I> »<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0">“protected person” means a current or former protectee or a current or former designated program protectee;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><MarginalNote>“provincial official”<br/>« <I>fonctionnaire provincial</I> »<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0">“provincial official” means, with respect to a designated program, the official designated under subsection 10.1(2) or (3);</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><MarginalNote>“substantial harm”<br/>« <I>préjudice sérieux</I> »<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0">“substantial harm” means any injury, whether physical or psychological, that interferes in a substantial way with a person’s health or well-being;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>4.</B> The Act is amended by adding the following after section 2:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:HER MAJESTY--><Para TopMargin="10" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">HER MAJESTY</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Binding on Her Majesty<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>2.1</B> This Act is binding on Her Majesty in right of Canada or a province.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>2000, c. 24, s. 71<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>5.</B> Section 3 of the Act is replaced by the following:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Protection of persons<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>3.</B> The purpose of this Act is to promote law enforcement, national security, national defence and public safety by facilitating the protection of persons</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>a</I>) who are involved directly or indirectly in providing assistance in law enforcement matters in relation to</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="4" FirstLineIndent="0">(i) activities conducted by the Force, other than activities arising under an arrangement entered into under section 20 of the <I>Royal Canadian Mounted Police Act</I>, or</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="4" FirstLineIndent="0">(ii) activities conducted by any law enforcement agency or international criminal court or tribunal in respect of which an agreement or arrangement has been entered into under section 14;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>b</I>) who are involved directly or indirectly in providing assistance to a federal security, defence or safety organization; or</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>c</I>) who have been admitted to a designated program.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>2000, c. 24, s. 72<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>6.</B> (1) The portion of subsection 6(1) of the Act before paragraph (<I>b</I>) is replaced by the following:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Admission to Program<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>6.</B> (1)  A witness shall not be admitted to the Program unless</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>a</I>) a recommendation for the admission has been made by a law enforcement agency, a federal security, defence or safety organization or an international criminal court or tribunal;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes">(2) Subsection 6(2) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Emergency situations<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(2) Despite subsection (1), the Commissioner may, in a case of emergency, and for a period of not more than 90 days, provide protection to a person who has not entered into a protection agreement. The Commissioner may, if the emergency persists, provide protection for one additional period of not more than 90 days.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>7.</B> (1) The portion of section 7 of the English version of the Act before paragraph (<I>a</I>) is replaced by the following:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Factors to be considered<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>7.</B> The Commissioner shall consider the following factors in determining whether a witness should be admitted to the Program:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes">(2) Paragraphs 7(<I>c</I>) and (<I>d</I>) of the Act are replaced by the following:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>c</I>) the nature of the inquiry, investigation or prosecution involving the witness — or the nature of the assistance given or agreed to be given by the witness to a federal security, defence or safety organization — and the importance of the witness in the matter;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>d</I>) the value of the witness’s participation or of the information, evidence or assistance given or agreed to be given by the witness;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>8.</B> Subparagraph 8(<I>b</I>)(i) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="4" FirstLineIndent="0">(i) to give the information or evidence or participate as required in relation to the inquiry, investigation or prosecution — or to give to the federal security, defence or safety organization the assistance — in respect of which protection is provided under the agreement,</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>9.</B> The Act is amended by adding the following after section 8:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Request for termination of protection<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>8.1</B> (1) A protectee may request that the Commissioner terminate the protection provided to the protectee.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Termination<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(2) The Commissioner shall meet in person with the protectee to discuss their request and shall terminate the protection provided to them if, either at the meeting or afterwards, they confirm their request in the form and manner that the Commissioner considers appropriate in the circumstances.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Effective day<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(3) The termination takes effect on the day on which the request is confirmed or on a later day that the protectee may specify.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>2000, c. 24, s. 73<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>10.</B> Paragraph 10(<I>a</I>) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>a</I>) to refuse to admit a witness to the Program, the Commissioner shall provide the body that recommended the admission or, in the case of a witness recommended by the Force, the witness, with written reasons to enable the body or witness to understand the basis for the decision; or</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>11.</B> The Act is amended by adding the following after section 10:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:DESIGNATED PROGRAMS--><Para TopMargin="10" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">DESIGNATED PROGRAMS</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Designation — program<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>10.1</B> (1) At the request of a provincial minister who is responsible for a provincial or municipal program that facilitates the protection of witnesses and on the Minister’s recommendation, the Governor in Council may, by regulation, designate the program by adding its name to the schedule.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Designation — provincial official<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(2) In his or her request, the provincial minister shall designate an official of the applicable province or municipality to be the program’s provincial official.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Change of provincial official<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(3) The provincial minister may replace the provincial official by designating another official of the applicable province or municipality and shall notify the Minister without delay of any such replacement.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Deletion from schedule<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>10.2</B> On the Minister’s recommendation, the Governor in Council may, by regulation, delete the name of a program from the schedule.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Coordination — change of identity<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>10.3</B> (1) At a provincial official’s request, the Commissioner shall coordinate the activities of federal departments, agencies and services in order to facilitate a change of identity for a designated program protectee.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Required information<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(2) The provincial official shall provide any information that the Commissioner requires for the purpose of subsection (1).</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>12.</B> Section 11 of the Act and the heading before it are replaced by the following:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:PROTECTION OF INFORMATION--><Para TopMargin="10" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">PROTECTION OF INFORMATION</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Disclosures prohibited<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>11.</B> (1) Subject to sections 11.1 to 11.5, no person shall directly or indirectly disclose</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>a</I>) any information that reveals, or from which may be inferred, the location or a change of identity of a person that they know is a protected person;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>b</I>) any information about the means and methods by which protected persons are protected, knowing that or being reckless as to whether the disclosure could result in substantial harm to any protected person; or</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>c</I>) the identity and role of a person who provides protection or directly or indirectly assists in providing protection, knowing that or being reckless as to whether the disclosure could result in substantial harm to</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="4" FirstLineIndent="0">(i) that person,</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="4" FirstLineIndent="0">(ii) a member of that person’s family, or</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="4" FirstLineIndent="0">(iii) any protected person.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Means and methods of protection<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(2) For the purpose of paragraph (1)(<I>b</I>), information about the means and methods by which protected persons are protected includes information about</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>a</I>) covert operational methods used to provide protection;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>b</I>) covert administrative methods used to support the provision of protection;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>c</I>) any means used to record or exchange confidential information relating to protection or used to gain access to that information; and</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>d</I>) the location of facilities used to provide protection.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Non-application — protected or other person<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>11.1</B> Paragraph 11(1)(<I>a</I>) does not apply to</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>a</I>) a protected person who discloses information about themselves, if the disclosure could not result in substantial harm to any protected person; or</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>b</I>) a person who discloses information that was disclosed to them by a protected person, if the disclosure could not result in substantial harm to any protected person.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Exception — Commissioner<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>11.2</B> (1) The Commissioner may make a disclosure described in paragraph 11(1)(<I>a</I>) that relates to</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>a</I>) a protectee, for the purpose of providing protection to them; or</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>b</I>) a designated program protectee, for the purpose of facilitating a change of identity for them.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Other exceptions<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(2) The Commissioner may make a disclosure described in paragraph 11(1)(<I>a</I>) that relates to a protected person if</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>a</I>) the protected person consents to the disclosure;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>b</I>) the protected person has previously made such a disclosure or acted in a manner that results in such a disclosure;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>c</I>) the Commissioner has reasonable grounds to believe that the disclosure is essential for the purposes of the administration of justice, including</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="4" FirstLineIndent="0">(i) investigating a serious offence if there is reason to believe that the protected person can provide material information or evidence in relation to, or has been involved in the commission of, the offence,</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="4" FirstLineIndent="0">(ii) preventing the commission of a serious offence, or</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="4" FirstLineIndent="0">(iii) establishing the innocence of a person in criminal proceedings;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>d</I>) the Commissioner has reasonable grounds to believe that the disclosure is essential for the purposes of national security or national defence; or</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>e</I>) the disclosure is made in accordance with an agreement or arrangement entered into under subsection 14.1(1).</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Designated program protectee<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(3) The Commissioner is only permitted to make a disclosure under paragraph (2)(<I>c</I>) that relates to a current or former designated program protectee if, in the Commissioner’s opinion, the urgency of the situation requires the disclosure or if the appropriate provincial official consents to it.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Exception — other information<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(4) The Commissioner may make a disclosure described in paragraph 11(1)(<I>b</I>) or (<I>c</I>)</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>a</I>) that relates to the Program or a person associated with it, if the Commissioner has reasonable grounds to believe that the disclosure is essential for the purposes of the administration of justice, <keep>national securi-</keep>ty, national defence or public safety; and</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>b</I>) that relates to a current or former designated program or a person associated with it, if the Commissioner has reasonable grounds to believe that the disclosure is essential for the purposes of national security or national defence.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Prior notification — protected person<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(5) The Commissioner shall, before making a disclosure under paragraph (2)(<I>b</I>), (<I>c</I>) or (<I>e</I>), take reasonable steps to notify the protected person and allow them to make representations concerning the matter.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Non-application<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(6) Subsection (5) does not apply if, in the Commissioner’s opinion, the notification would impede the investigation of an offence, could compromise national security, national defence or public safety or could result in substantial harm to any protected person or to any person providing protection or directly or indirectly assisting in providing protection.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Prior notification — provincial official<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(7) The Commissioner shall notify the appropriate provincial official of a disclosure under paragraph (2)(<I>a</I>) or (<I>b</I>) that relates to a current or former designated program protectee before the disclosure is made.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Notification — provincial official<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(8) The Commissioner shall notify the appropriate provincial official of a disclosure referred to in subsection (3) as soon as feasible after making it, if it was made on the basis of the urgency of the situation.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Exception — provincial official<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>11.3</B> (1) The appropriate provincial official may make a disclosure described in paragraph 11(1)(<I>a</I>) that relates to a designated program protectee for the purpose of providing protection to them.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Other exceptions<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(2) The appropriate provincial official may make a disclosure described in paragraph 11(1)(<I>a</I>) that relates to a current or former designated program protectee if</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>a</I>) the current or former designated program protectee consents to the disclosure;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>b</I>) the current or former designated program protectee has previously made such a disclosure or acted in a manner that results in such a disclosure;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>c</I>) the provincial official has reasonable grounds to believe that the disclosure is essential for the purposes of the administration of justice, including</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="4" FirstLineIndent="0">(i) investigating a serious offence if there is reason to believe that the current or former designated program protectee can provide material information or evidence in relation to, or has been involved in the commission of, the offence,</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="4" FirstLineIndent="0">(ii) preventing the commission of a serious offence, or</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="4" FirstLineIndent="0">(iii) establishing the innocence of a person in criminal proceedings; or</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>d</I>) the disclosure is made in accordance with an agreement or arrangement entered into under subsection 14.1(2).</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Exception — other information<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(3) A provincial official may make a disclosure described in paragraph 11(1)(<I>b</I>) or (<I>c</I>) that relates to their designated program or to a person associated with it if the provincial official has reasonable grounds to believe that the disclosure is essential for the purposes of the administration of justice or public safety.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Prior notification — designated program protectee<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(4) The provincial official shall, before making a disclosure under any of paragraphs (2)(<I>b</I>) to (<I>d</I>), take reasonable steps to notify the current or former designated program protectee and allow them to make representations concerning the matter.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Non-application<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(5) Subsection (4) does not apply if, in the provincial official’s opinion, the notification would impede the investigation of an offence, could compromise public safety or could result in substantial harm to any current or former designated program protectee or to any person providing protection or directly or indirectly assisting in providing protection.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Exception — agreement or arrangement<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>11.4</B> (1) A party, other than the Commissioner or a provincial official, who has entered into an agreement or arrangement under subsection 14.1(1) or (2) may make a disclosure described in paragraph 11(1)(<I>a</I>) in accordance with the agreement or arrangement.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Prior notification<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(2) The party shall, before making a disclosure under subsection (1), take reasonable steps to notify the protected person and allow them to make representations concerning the matter.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Further disclosures prohibited<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>11.5</B> (1) Subject to this section, a person to whom information is disclosed under sections 11.2 to 11.4 is not authorized to disclose that information to anyone else.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Exception — Commissioner’s request<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(2) A person may, for the purpose of providing protection to a protectee or of changing a designated program protectee’s identity, disclose that information to the extent that is necessary to give effect to a Commissioner’s request that is made for that purpose.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Exception — provincial official’s request<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(3) A person may, for the purpose of providing protection to a designated program protectee, disclose that information to the extent that is necessary to give effect to a provincial official’s request that is made for that purpose.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Court — confidentiality<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(4) Once a disclosure described in subsection 11(1) is made to a court, the court shall take any measures that it considers necessary to ensure that the information remains confidential.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Exception — court<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(5) A court may make a disclosure described in subsection 11(1) for the purpose of preventing a miscarriage of justice, but in doing so it shall disclose only the information that it considers necessary for that purpose and shall disclose the information only to persons who require it for that purpose.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>13.</B> (1) The portion of section 12 of the Act before paragraph (<I>a</I>) is replaced by the following:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Factors to be considered<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>12.</B> The Commissioner or a provincial official shall consider the following factors in determining whether to make a disclosure under section 11.2 or 11.3, as the case may be, except for a disclosure under paragraph 11.2(2)(<I>e</I>) or 11.3(2)(<I>d</I>):</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes">(2) Paragraph 12(<I>b</I>) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>b</I>) the danger or adverse consequences of the disclosure in relation to a person and the integrity of the Program or of a designated program, as the case may be;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>14.</B> Section 13 of the Act is replaced by the following:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Informer privilege<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>12.1</B> Informer privilege at common law prevails over any authority to disclose information provided under this Act.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Claim — new identity<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>13.</B> A person shall not be liable or otherwise punished for making a claim that the new identity of a protected person, whose identity has been changed as a consequence of the protection provided under the Program or under a designated program, is and has been the protected person’s only identity.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Claim — providing protection<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>13.1</B> A person who provides protection or directly or indirectly assists in providing protection under the Program or under a designated program shall not be liable or otherwise punished for making a claim that they do not</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>a</I>) provide or assist in providing protection; or</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>b</I>) know a protected person or know that a person is a protected person.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>15.</B> The heading before section 14 of the English version of the Act is replaced by the following:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes"><!--Heading:AGREEMENTS AND ARRANGEMENTS--><Para TopMargin="10" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">AGREEMENTS AND ARRANGEMENTS</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>16.</B> The Act is amended by adding the following after section 14:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Agreement or arrangement — Commissioner<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>14.1</B> (1) The Commissioner may enter into an agreement or arrangement with a federal department, agency or service regarding disclosures — that are described in paragraph 11(1)(<I>a</I>) and that relate to a current or former protectee — to each other or to another federal department, agency or service or any provincial department, agency or service.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Agreement or arrangement — provincial official<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(2) A provincial official may enter into an agreement or arrangement with a provincial department, agency or service of the same province as that official regarding disclosures — that are described in paragraph 11(1)(<I>a</I>) and that relate to a current or former designated program protectee — to each other or to another department, agency or service of the same province or any federal department, agency or service.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Factors to be considered<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(3) The Commissioner or a provincial official shall consider the factors set out in paragraphs 12(<I>a</I>) to (<I>e</I>) in determining whether to enter into an agreement or arrangement and in establishing its terms.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Mandatory terms<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(4) An agreement or arrangement shall include the following terms:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>a</I>) a party is not permitted to make a disclosure unless it is for a purpose that is essential for the administration of justice or public safety and that is specified in the agreement or arrangement; and</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>b</I>) the parties shall take whatever steps are necessary, including any steps specified in the agreement or arrangement, to protect information that is disclosed from being disclosed beyond what is strictly necessary in the circumstances.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Multiple departments, agencies or services<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(5) More than one department, agency or service may be party to a single agreement or arrangement.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>2000, c. 24, s. 75(E)<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>17.</B> Section 15 of the Act is replaced by the following:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Delegation — Commissioner<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>15.</B> (1) The Commissioner may delegate to any member of the Force any of his or her powers, duties and functions under this Act, except the power to delegate under this section and the power to</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>a</I>) determine whether to disclose information under any of paragraphs 11.2(2)(<I>b</I>) to (<I>d</I>) and subsection 11.2(4);</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>b</I>) enter into an agreement or arrangement under subsection 14.1(1);</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>c</I>) designate an Assistant Commissioner to be responsible for the Program; and</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>d</I>) determine whether to admit a witness to the Program, to change the identity of a protectee and to terminate the protection provided to a protectee.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Assistant Commissioner<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(2) The Commissioner may designate an Assistant Commissioner to be responsible for the Program and, despite paragraph (1)(<I>d</I>), may delegate the powers set out in that paragraph to that Assistant Commissioner.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Delegation — provincial official<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>15.1</B> A provincial official may delegate to any official of the same province or municipality any of his or her powers, duties and functions under this Act, except the power to</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>a</I>) determine whether to disclose information under paragraphs 11.3(2)(<I>b</I>) and (<I>c</I>) and subsection 11.3(3); and</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>b</I>) enter into an agreement or arrangement under subsection 14.1(2).</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>18.</B> Section 17 of the Act is replaced by the following:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Policy directions<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>17.</B> The Commissioner shall give effect to any directions that the Minister may make concerning matters of general policy that are related to the administration of the Program and to the coordination of activities under this Act respecting a designated program.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>19.</B> Section 18 of the Act is replaced by the following:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Cooperation<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>18.</B> Subject to the confidentiality requirements imposed by any other Act of Parliament, federal departments, agencies and services shall, to the extent possible, cooperate with the Commissioner and persons acting on his or her behalf in the administration of the Program and of activities under this Act respecting a designated program.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Terminology<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>20.</B> The French version of the Act is amended by replacing “<AltLang xml:lang="fr">programme</AltLang>” with “<AltLang xml:lang="fr">Programme</AltLang>” in the following provisions:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0" Bold="Yes">(<I>a</I>) section 1;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0" Bold="Yes">(<I>b</I>) section 4;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0" Bold="Yes">(<I>c</I>) section 7;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0" Bold="Yes">(<I>d</I>) subparagraph 8(<I>b</I>)(iv);</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0" Bold="Yes">(<I>e</I>) paragraph 9(1)(<I>a</I>);</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0" Bold="Yes">(<I>f</I>) section 14;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0" Bold="Yes">(<I>g</I>) subsection 16(1); and</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0" Bold="Yes">(<I>h</I>) paragraph 20(<I>a</I>).</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>21.</B> The Act is amended by adding, after section 23, the schedule set out in the schedule to this Act.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:CONSEQUENTIAL AMENDMENT TO THE ACCESS TO INFORMATION ACT--><MarginalNote>R.S., c. A-1<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="10" Bold="Yes" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">CONSEQUENTIAL AMENDMENT TO THE ACCESS TO INFORMATION ACT</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>22.</B> Schedule II to the <I>Access to Information Act</I> is amended by adding, <keep>in alphabet-</keep>ical order, a reference to</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><Para TopMargin="2" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="-2">Witness Protection Program Act</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="0" LeftMargin="4" FirstLineIndent="-2" Italic="Yes"><AltLang xml:lang="fr">Loi sur le Programme de protection des témoins</AltLang></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0" Bold="Yes">and a corresponding reference to “section 11”.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:COORDINATING AMENDMENT--><Para TopMargin="10" Bold="Yes" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">COORDINATING AMENDMENT</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Bill C-42<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>23.</B> If Bill C-42, introduced in the 1st session of the 41st Parliament and entitled the <I>Enhancing Royal Canadian Mounted Police Accountability Act</I>, receives royal assent, then, on the first day on which both section 35 of that Act and section 12 of this Act are in force, paragraphs 45.4(1)(<I>b</I>) and (<I>c</I>) of the <I>Royal Canadian Mounted Police Act</I> are replaced by the following:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>b</I>) information the disclosure of which is described in subsection 11(1) of the <I>Witness Protection Program Act</I>;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:COMING INTO FORCE--><Para TopMargin="10" Bold="Yes" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">COMING INTO FORCE</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Order in council<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>24.</B> The provisions of this Act, other than section 23, come into force on a day or days to be fixed by order of the Governor in Council.</Para></Block><Block Align="Yes" LineCnt="N"><Para NoLineBreak="Yes" NoHtml="Yes" Leading="0" Size="0" TopMargin="0" BottomMargin="0"></Para></Block></Bill_Part><Bill_Part Part_Type="Schedule" CountLines="No" RunningHead_E="Witness Protection Program — Schedule"><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><Para TopMargin="10" Size="9" Leading="10" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0" Bold="Yes" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">SCHEDULE </Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><Para Size="9" Leading="10" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0" Bold="Yes" Italic="Yes" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">(Section 21)</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><Para TopMargin="10" Size="9" Leading="10" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">SCHEDULE </Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><Para Size="9" Leading="10" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0" Italic="Yes" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">(Sections 10.1 and 10.2)</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:DESIGNATED PROGRAMS--><Para TopMargin="5" Size="9" Leading="10" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">DESIGNATED PROGRAMS</Para></Block><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="BPT_ImprintE"><br/><br/>Published under authority of the Speaker of the House of Commons</Para></Block><Block Align="Yes" LineCnt="N"><Para NoLineBreak="Yes" NoHtml="Yes" Leading="0" Size="0" TopMargin="0" BottomMargin="0"></Para></Block></Bill_Part></Bill>
