<?xml version="1.0"?>
<Bill RHead_reign="60-61-62 Eliz. II" RHead_ParlYear="2011-2012-2013" DocumentTitle="BILL C-537" Bill_No="C-537" Document_No="411655" xml:lang="EN" Bill_Type="Non-amending" Stage_Name="First-Reading-House" Reprint="No" xml:space="preserve" ChapterNo_E="C. " ChapterNo_F="ch. " Bill-Origin="commons"><Bill_Part Part_Type="Cover" CountLines="No"><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="CovBillNo">C-537</Para></Block><Block><Para TopMargin="24" Size="9" Leading="10" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0" TextAlign="Center">First Session, Forty-first Parliament,</Para></Block><Block><Para Size="9" Leading="10" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0" TextAlign="Center">60-61-62 Elizabeth II, 2011-2012-2013</Para></Block><Block><Para TopMargin="48" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0" Bold="Yes" TextAlign="Center">HOUSE OF COMMONS OF CANADA</Para></Block><Block><Para TopMargin="42" Size="18" Leading="20" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0" Bold="Yes" TextAlign="Center">BILL C-537</Para></Block><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="CovLongTitle">An Act to ensure legislative compliance with the Canadian Bill of Rights and the Constitution Acts, 1867 to 1982, including the Canadian Charter of Rights and Freedoms</Para></Block><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="COV_StageLine"></Para></Block><Block><Para Size="9" AllCaps="Yes" Hyphenate="OFF">first reading, June 17, 2013</Para></Block><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="COV_StageLine"></Para></Block><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="Cover_Sponsors"><SC SC_PerCent="85">Mr. Cotler</SC></Para></Block><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="Cover_DocNo">411655</Para></Block></Bill_Part><Bill_Part CountLines="No" Part_Type="InsideCover"><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="BPT_InsideCoverE">Available on the Parliament of Canada Web Site at the following address:<br/><B>http://www.parl.gc.ca</B></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><Para TopMargin="108" BottomMargin="4" Size="10" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">SUMMARY</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" Size="8" Leading="9" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">This enactment establishes a requirement for the review of all bills introduced in the Senate or the House of Commons to ensure that they are not inconsistent with the purposes and provisions of the <I>Canadian Bill of Rights</I> and the <I>Constitution Acts, 1867 to 1982</I>, including the <I>Canadian Charter of Rights and Freedoms</I>. Inconsistency would be determined by the Law Clerk and Parliamentary Counsel of the relevant House if it is the opinion of the Law Clerk that, were that provision to be challenged in court, it would, on the balance of probabilities, be found to infringe, limit or violate the purposes or provisions of any of those statutes.</Para></Block></Bill_Part><Bill_Part Part_Type="MainText" CountLines="Yes" RunningHead_E="Constitutional Compliance Review"><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="MainText_DocNo">411655</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes"><Para Style="Session_Reign">1st Session, 41st Parliament,</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes"><Para Style="Session_Reign">60-61-62 Elizabeth II, 2011-2012-2013</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes"><Para Style="MainBillOrigin">house of commons of canada</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes"><Para Bold="Yes" Style="MAIN@BillNo_Title">BILL C-537</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes"><Para Style="MAIN@ti;04">An Act to ensure legislative compliance with the Canadian Bill of Rights and the Constitution Acts, 1867 to 1982, including the Canadian Charter of Rights and Freedoms</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">Her Majesty, by and with the advice and consent of the Senate and House of Commons of Canada, enacts as follows:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:SHORT TITLE--><Para TopMargin="10" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">SHORT TITLE</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Short title<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>1.</B> This Act may be cited as the <I>Constitutional Compliance Review Act</I>.  </Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:APPLICATION--><Para TopMargin="10" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">APPLICATION</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Application<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>2.</B> (1) Subject to subsection (2), this Act applies in respect of all bills introduced in the Senate or the House of Commons.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Exemptions<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(2) The following bills are exempt from the application of this Act:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>a</I>) bills made under section 44 of the <I>Constitution Act, 1982</I> to amend the Constitution of Canada;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>b</I>) bills to amend electoral boundaries as a result of a representation order made under section 25 of the <I>Electoral Boundaries Readjustment Act</I> or bills to amend such a representation order to change the name of an electoral district in the order; and</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>c</I>) appropriation bills.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:EXAMINATION OF BILLS--><Para TopMargin="10" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">EXAMINATION OF BILLS</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Examination of bills introduced<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>3.</B> Every bill introduced in the Senate or the House of Commons must, within the period set out in section 4, be examined by the Law Clerk and Parliamentary Counsel of the House in which it is introduced, with the assistance of the Library of Parliament as required, in order to determine whether any of the provisions of the bill is likely to be inconsistent with the purposes and provisions of the <I>Canadian Bill of Rights</I> or the <I>Constitution Acts, 1867 to 1982</I>, including the <I>Canadian Charter of Rights and Freedoms</I>.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Examination period<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>4.</B> The examination referred to in section 3 must be completed,</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>a</I>) in the case of Government Bills introduced in the Senate or the House of Commons, within 20 sitting days after the day on which a bill is introduced; and</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>b</I>) in the case of Senators' Bills introduced in the Senate or Private Members' Bills introduced in the House of Commons, within 45 sitting days after the day on which a bill is introduced and no later than 10 sitting days after the bill is placed in the Order of Precedence for Private Members' Bills.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Inconsistency<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>5.</B> For the purposes of the examination referred to in section 3, a provision of a bill is likely to be inconsistent with any of the purposes and provisions of the statutes referred to in that section if it is the opinion of the Law Clerk and Parliamentary Counsel of the relevant House that, if that provision were to be challenged in court, it would, on the balance of probabilities, be found to infringe, limit or violate the purposes or provisions of any of those statutes.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:REPORT OF EXAMINATION--><Para TopMargin="10" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">REPORT OF EXAMINATION</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Report of examination<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>6.</B> (1) The Law Clerk and Parliamentary Counsel who reviewed the bill must, without delay, notify the Clerk of the relevant House that the bill has been examined under section 3, indicating the number and title of the bill, and whether a report will be submitted under subsection (2).</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Report of inconsistency<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(2) If it is determined that any of the provisions of a bill examined in accordance with section 3 is likely to be inconsistent with the purposes and provisions of the statutes referred to in that section, the Law Clerk and Parliamentary Counsel who reviewed the bill must submit a report, in both official languages, to the Speaker of the Senate or the Speaker of the House of Commons, as the case may be, identifying the provisions of the bill that are likely to be inconsistent with the relevant statute and providing a brief summary of the reasons for the determination.  </Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Tabling of report<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>7.</B> The Speaker of the Senate or the Speaker of the House of Commons, as the case may be, must lay every report submitted in accordance with section 6 before the Senate or the House of Commons forthwith after receiving it or, if that House is not then sitting, on any of the first 15 days on which that House is sitting after the Speaker receives it.</Para></Block><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="BPT_ImprintE"><br/><br/>Published under authority of the Speaker of the House of Commons</Para></Block><Block Align="Yes" LineCnt="N"><Para NoLineBreak="Yes" NoHtml="Yes" Leading="0" Size="0" TopMargin="0" BottomMargin="0"></Para></Block></Bill_Part></Bill>
