<?xml version="1.0"?>
<Bill RHead_reign="60 Eliz. II" RHead_ParlYear="2011" DocumentTitle="BILL S-1001" Bill_No="S-1001" Document_No="1022" xml:lang="EN" Bill_Type="Non-amending" Stage_Name="Assented-to" Reprint="No" xml:space="preserve" ChapterNo_E="C. 27" ChapterNo_F="ch. 27" Bill-Origin="senate"><Bill_Part Part_Type="Cover" CountLines="No"><Block><Para TopMargin="24" Size="9" Leading="10" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0" TextAlign="Center">First Session, Forty-first Parliament,</Para></Block><Block><Para Size="9" Leading="10" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0" TextAlign="Center">60 Elizabeth II, 2011</Para></Block><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="COV@StatutesTitle">STATUTES OF CANADA 2011<br/>CHAPTER 27</Para></Block><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="CovLongTitle">An Act respecting Queen’s University at Kingston</Para></Block><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="COV_StageLine"></Para></Block><Block><Para BottomMargin="14" Size="11" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0" Bold="Yes" TextAlign="Center">ASSENTED TO</Para></Block><Block><Para Size="8" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0" TextAlign="Center">26th JUNE, 2011</Para></Block><Block><Para TopMargin="4" Size="8" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0" TextAlign="Center">BILL S-1001</Para></Block><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="COV_StageLine"></Para></Block></Bill_Part><Bill_Part CountLines="No" Part_Type="InsideCover"><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="BPT_InsideCoverE">Available on the Parliament of Canada Web Site at the following address:<br/><B>http://www.parl.gc.ca</B></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><Para TopMargin="108" BottomMargin="4" Size="10" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">SUMMARY</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" Size="8" Leading="9" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">This enactment amends the constitution of the corporation of Queen’s University at Kingston in order to effect certain changes in the composition and powers of the Board of Trustees and of the University Council and the mode of election of their respective members, and to effect other technical and incidental changes.</Para></Block></Bill_Part><Bill_Part Part_Type="MainText" CountLines="No" RunningHead_E="Queen’s University"><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="MAIN@RoyalAssentTitle">60 ELIZABETH II</Para></Block><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="MAIN@RoyalAssentTitle">——————</Para></Block><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="MAIN@RoyalAssentTitle">CHAPTER 27</Para></Block><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="LongTitleAssent">An Act respecting Queen’s University at Kingston</Para></Block><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="MAIN@RoyalAssentDate">[<I>Assented to 26th June, 2011</I>]</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Preamble<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">Whereas Queen’s University at Kingston was incorporated by Royal Charter on October 16, 1841, under the name Queen’s College at Kingston;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">Whereas the Charter has since been amended and added to by Act of Parliament from time to time;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">Whereas Queen’s University at Kingston has by its petition prayed that the constitution of the corporation of the University be amended in order to effect certain changes in the composition and powers of the Board of Trustees and of the University Council and the mode of election of their respective members, and to effect other technical or incidental changes as may be appropriate;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">And whereas it is expedient to grant the prayer of the petition;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">Now, therefore, Her Majesty, by and with the advice and consent of the Senate and House of Commons of Canada, enacts as follows:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:AN ACT RESPECTING QUEEN’SCOLLEGE AT KINGSTON, AND TO CHANGE ITS NAME TO "QUEEN’S UNIVERSITY AT KINGSTON" --><Para TopMargin="10" Bold="Yes" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">AN ACT RESPECTING QUEEN’SCOLLEGE AT KINGSTON, AND TO CHANGE ITS NAME TO "QUEEN’S UNIVERSITY AT KINGSTON" </Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>1912, ch.138<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>1.</B>  Section 7 of <I>An Act respecting Queen’s College at Kingston, and to change its name to "Queen’s University at Kingston"</I>, chapter 138 of the Statutes of Canada, 1912, is repealed.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>2.</B> Sections 10 and 11 of the Act are replaced by the following:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Board of Trustees<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>10.</B> The Board of Trustees of the University consists of</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>a</I>) the Chancellor, the Rector and the Principal, who are ex officio members;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>b</I>)  two faculty members elected by the faculty, in accordance with the by-laws of the Board of Trustees; </Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>c</I>)  two staff members elected by the staff, in accordance with the by-laws of the Board of Trustees;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>d</I>) two student members elected by students registered in academic programs of the University, in accordance with the by-laws of the Board of Trustees; </Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>e</I>) six individuals elected or appointed by the University Council from time to time, in accordance with the by-laws of the University Council; and</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>f</I>) not more than ten individuals elected or appointed by the Board of Trustees from time to time, in accordance with the by-laws of the Board of Trustees.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>By-laws of Board of Trustees<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>11.</B> The Board of Trustees may make by-laws from time to time, not contrary to the Royal Charter or any Act of Parliament, respecting</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>a</I>) subject to paragraph 10(<I>f</I>), the number of Trustees to be elected or appointed by the Board of Trustees, and their term of office;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>b</I>) the manner of election of the faculty, staff and student members of the Board of Trustees referred to in paragraphs 10(<I>b</I>) to (<I>d</I>), and their term of office;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>c</I>) the retirement and replacement of members of the Board of Trustees, and the filling of vacancies that may occur from time to time by reason of the death, resignation, or disability of a member of the Board of Trustees, or for any other cause;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>d</I>) the establishment and removal of committees of the Board of Trustees, and the membership and powers of such committees;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>e</I>) the manner of holding meetings, provision for quorum, and voting rights;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>f</I>) the making, repeal and amendment of the by-laws of the Board of Trustees; and</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>g</I>) the conduct in all other particulars of the affairs of the Board of Trustees.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>3.</B> Sections 14 and 15 of the Act are repealed.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>4.</B> Section 17 of the Act is replaced by the following:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>University Council<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>17.</B> (1) Subject to the provisions of this Act, the University Council of Queen’s University is hereby continued and shall have and exercise the lawful powers and functions held and exercised by it immediately before the coming into force of this provision.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>By-laws of University Council<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(2) The University Council may make by-laws from time to time, not contrary to the Royal Charter or any Act of Parliament, respecting</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>a</I>) the determination of the membership of the University Council;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>b</I>)  the time for and the manner of election or appointment of the members of the University Council, and their term of office;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>c</I>) the retirement and replacement of the members of the University Council, and the filling of vacancies that may occur from time to time by reason of the death, resignation, or disability of a member of the University Council, or for any other cause;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>d</I>) the appointment and removal of a Secretary and such other officers as the University Council considers necessary or expedient;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>e</I>) the manner of appointment of the Chancellor of Queen’s University;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>f</I>) the manner of election of the Rector;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>g</I>) the time for and the manner of election or appointment of members of the Board of Trustees by the University Council, and their term of office; and</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>h</I>) the conduct in all other particulars of the affairs of the University Council.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Chancellor<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>17.1</B> (1) The University Council shall, in accordance with its by-laws, appoint a Chancellor of Queen’s University as the highest officer of the University.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Term of office<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(2) The Chancellor holds office for three years from the date of appointment or until a successor is appointed, whichever is later.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Role at meetings<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(3) The Chancellor shall preside at all meetings of the University Council, holding both a deliberative and a casting vote on all motions submitted to any meeting of the University Council.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Rector<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>17.2</B> The students registered in academic programs of the University shall, in accordance with the by-laws of the University Council, elect a Rector to hold office for three years from the date of election or until a successor is elected, whichever is later. </Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:TRANSITIONAL PROVISION--><Para TopMargin="10" Bold="Yes" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">TRANSITIONAL PROVISION</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Transitional provision<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>5.</B> The persons who, immediately before the coming into force of this Act, held the office of Chancellor or Rector, or were members of the Board of Trustees or the University Council, continue to hold office for the remainder of the term for which they were elected or appointed.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:INCONSISTENCY--><Para TopMargin="10" Bold="Yes" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">INCONSISTENCY</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Inconsistency or conflict<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>6.</B> Where there is any inconsistency or conflict between this Act and the Royal Charter or the provisions of any law, this Act prevails to the extent of the inconsistency or conflict. </Para></Block><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="BPT_ImprintE">Published under authority of the Senate of Canada<br/>Available from:<br/>Publishing and Depository Services<br/>Public Works and Government Services Canada<br/>Ottawa, Ontario K1A 0S5<br/>Telephone: 613-941-5995 or 1-800-635-7943<br/>Fax: 613-954-5779 or 1-800-565-7757<br/>publications@tpsgc-pwgsc.gc.ca<br/>http://publications.gc.ca</Para></Block><Block Align="Yes" LineCnt="N"><Para NoLineBreak="Yes" NoHtml="Yes" Leading="0" Size="0" TopMargin="0" BottomMargin="0"></Para></Block></Bill_Part></Bill>
