<?xml version="1.0"?>
<Bill RHead_reign="60-61-62 Eliz. II" RHead_ParlYear="2011-2012-2013" DocumentTitle="BILL S-15" Bill_No="S-15" Document_No="90678" xml:lang="EN" Bill_Type="Non-amending" Stage_Name="Assented-to" Reprint="No" xml:space="preserve" ChapterNo_E="C. 28" ChapterNo_F="ch. 28" Bill-Origin="senate"><Bill_Part Part_Type="Cover" CountLines="No"><Block><Para TopMargin="24" Size="9" Leading="10" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0" TextAlign="Center">First Session, Forty-first Parliament,</Para></Block><Block><Para Size="9" Leading="10" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0" TextAlign="Center">60-61-62 Elizabeth II, 2011-2012-2013</Para></Block><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="COV@StatutesTitle">STATUTES OF CANADA 2013<br/>CHAPTER 28</Para></Block><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="CovLongTitle">An Act to amend the Canada National Parks Act and the Canada-Nova Scotia Offshore Petroleum Resources Accord Implementation Act and to make consequential amendments to the Canada Shipping Act, 2001</Para></Block><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="COV_StageLine"></Para></Block><Block><Para BottomMargin="14" Size="11" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0" Bold="Yes" TextAlign="Center">ASSENTED TO</Para></Block><Block><Para Size="8" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0" TextAlign="Center">19th JUNE, 2013</Para></Block><Block><Para TopMargin="4" Size="8" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0" TextAlign="Center">BILL S-15</Para></Block><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="COV_StageLine"></Para></Block></Bill_Part><Bill_Part CountLines="No" Part_Type="InsideCover"><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="BPT_InsideCoverE">Available on the Parliament of Canada Web Site at the following address:<br/><B>http://www.parl.gc.ca</B></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><Para TopMargin="108" BottomMargin="4" Size="10" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">SUMMARY</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" Size="8" Leading="9" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">Part 1 of this enactment amends the <I>Canada National Parks Act</I> to create Sable Island National Park Reserve of Canada.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" Size="8" Leading="9" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">It also amends the <I>Canada-Nova Scotia Offshore Petroleum Resources Accord Implementation Act</I> to prohibit drilling for petroleum in Sable Island National Park Reserve of Canada or within one nautical mile seaward of Sable Island’s low-water mark, to restrict surface access rights provided for under that Act and to provide for the issuance of licences and authorizations with respect to activities that may be carried out in Sable Island National Park Reserve of Canada.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" Size="8" Leading="9" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">Finally, it makes consequential amendments to the <I>Canada Shipping Act, 2001</I>.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" Size="8" Leading="9" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">Part 2 amends the <I>Canada National Parks Act</I> to provide that the dedication of the national parks of Canada to the people of Canada is subject to any Act of Parliament.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" Size="8" Leading="9" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">It also amends the description of the commercial zones for the Community of Field in Yoho National Park of Canada in Schedule 4 to that Act and of the leasehold boundary of the Marmot Basin Ski Area in Jasper National Park of Canada in Schedule 5 to that Act.</Para></Block></Bill_Part><Bill_Part Part_Type="MainText" CountLines="No" RunningHead_E="Canada National Parks and Canada-Nova Scotia Offshore Petroleum Resources Accord Implementation"><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="MAIN@RoyalAssentTitle">60-61-62 ELIZABETH II</Para></Block><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="MAIN@RoyalAssentTitle">——————</Para></Block><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="MAIN@RoyalAssentTitle">CHAPTER 28</Para></Block><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="LongTitleAssent">An Act to amend the Canada National Parks Act and the Canada-Nova Scotia Offshore Petroleum Resources Accord Implementation Act and to make consequential amendments to the Canada Shipping Act, 2001</Para></Block><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="MAIN@RoyalAssentDate">[<I>Assented to 19th June, 2013</I>]</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Preamble<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">Whereas Sable Island is a unique and fragile ecosystem of sand dunes, marram grass and freshwater ponds that support a diverse flora and fauna, including endangered species, as well as remnants of a rich cultural heritage, including shipwrecks and Canada’s first lifesaving station;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">Whereas on October 17, 2011, the Governments of Canada and Nova Scotia signed a Memorandum of Agreement to establish and manage Sable Island as a national park reserve of Canada for the purpose of protecting Sable Island for all time for the benefit, education and enjoyment of the people of Canada;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">Whereas the designation of Sable Island as a national park reserve of Canada takes into consideration Mi’kmaq asserted rights and title in Nova Scotia, which are being addressed through the Made-in-Nova Scotia Process between the Governments of Canada and Nova Scotia and the Mi’kmaq;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">Whereas under section 4 of the <I>Canada-Nova Scotia Offshore Petroleum Resources Accord Implementation Act</I>, in the case of any inconsistency or conflict between that Act, or any regulations made under it, and any other Act that applies to the offshore area (which includes Sable Island), or any regulations made under that other Act, the former Act and the regulations made under it take precedence;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">Whereas the Governments of Canada and Nova Scotia have agreed that Parliament will enact legislation amending the <I>Canada-Nova Scotia Offshore Petroleum Resources Accord Implementation Act</I> to prohibit drilling for petroleum in Sable Island National Park Reserve of Canada, or within one nautical mile seaward of Sable Island’s low-water mark, and to limit the range of surface access rights in respect of petroleum work or activity in Sable Island National Park Reserve of Canada;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">Whereas it is desirable to amend the descriptions in the <I>Canada National Parks Act</I> of the commercial zones for the Community of Field in Yoho National Park of Canada and of the leasehold boundary of the Marmot Basin Ski Area in Jasper National Park of Canada;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">And whereas it is desirable to amend that Act to provide that the dedication of the national parks of Canada to the people of Canada is subject to any Act of Parliament;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Left">Now, therefore, Her Majesty, by and with the advice and consent of the Senate and House of Commons of Canada, enacts as follows:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:SHORT TITLE--><Para TopMargin="10" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">SHORT TITLE</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Short title<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>1.</B> This Act may be cited as the <I>Expansion and Conservation of Canada’s National Parks Act</I>.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><Para TopMargin="10" Bold="Yes" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">PART 1</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:SABLE ISLAND NATIONAL PARK RESERVE OF CANADA--><Para TopMargin="5" Bold="Yes" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">SABLE ISLAND NATIONAL PARK RESERVE OF CANADA</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:Canada National Parks Act--><MarginalNote>2000, c. 32<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" Bold="Yes" SmallCaps="Yes" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">Canada National Parks Act</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>2009, c. 17, s. 6<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>2.</B> Section 39 of the <I>Canada National Parks Act</I> is replaced by the following:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Application of Act to reserves<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>39.</B> Subject to sections 40 to 41.3, this Act applies to a park reserve as if it were a park.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>3.</B> The Act is amended by adding the following after section 41.1:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Continuation — leases, easements and licences of occupation<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>41.2</B> (1) Existing leases, easements and licences of occupation in or on Sable Island National Park Reserve of Canada are continued under this Act in accordance with their terms and conditions, which prevail over this Act to the extent of any inconsistency between them.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Renewals — leases and licences of occupation<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(2) Those leases and licences of occupation may be renewed in accordance with their terms and conditions. If a lease or licence of occupation does not provide for its renewal, then it may be renewed in accordance with this Act.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Canada-Nova Scotia Offshore Petroleum Board<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>41.3</B> Nothing in this Act prevents any activity in Sable Island National Park Reserve of Canada that is authorized by the Canada-Nova Scotia Offshore Petroleum Board under the <I>Canada-Nova Scotia Offshore Petroleum Resources Accord Implementation Act</I>, and no authority under this Act is necessary in order to carry on any activity there that is authorized by that Board under that Act.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>4.</B> Schedule 2 to the Act is amended by adding the following after the description of Gulf Islands National Park Reserve of Canada:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:SABLE ISLAND NATIONAL PARK RESERVE OF CANADA--><Para TopMargin="10" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">SABLE ISLAND NATIONAL PARK RESERVE OF CANADA</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">All that lot, piece or parcel of land, within Nova Scotia, situate, lying and being in the Atlantic Ocean, located southeast of the City of Halifax in Nova Scotia and more particularly described as follows:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">All of Sable Island located near the geographic coordinates 43°56′ north latitude and 59°55′ west longitude including its shore and foreshore;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">Said parcel containing an area of approximately 30 square kilometres.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:Canada-Nova Scotia Offshore Petroleum Resources Accord Implementation Act--><MarginalNote>1988, c. 28<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="10" Bold="Yes" SmallCaps="Yes" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">Canada-Nova Scotia Offshore Petroleum Resources Accord Implementation Act</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>5.</B> Section 2 of the <I>Canada-Nova Scotia Offshore Petroleum Resources Accord Implementation Act</I> is amended by adding the following in alphabetical order:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>“Sable Island National Park Reserve of Canada”<br/>« <I>réserve à vocation de parc national de l’Île-de-Sable du Canada</I> »<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0">“Sable Island National Park Reserve of Canada” means Sable Island National Park Reserve of Canada as described in Schedule 2 to the <I>Canada National Parks Act</I>;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>6.</B> The Act is amended by adding the following after section 140:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Prohibition — Sable Island National Park Reserve of Canada<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>140.1</B> No person shall carry on any work or activity related to the drilling for petroleum, including exploratory drilling for petroleum, in Sable Island National Park Reserve of Canada or within one nautical mile seaward of its low-water mark.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>7.</B> The Act is amended by adding the following after section 142:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Authorizations — Sable Island National Park Reserve of Canada<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>142.01</B> (1) If the Board receives an application for an authorization with respect to a work or activity proposed to be carried on in Sable Island National Park Reserve of Canada, it shall, within 60 days after the day on which it received the application, provide a copy of the application to the Parks Canada Agency.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Parks Canada Agency<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(2) The Parks Canada Agency shall, within 60 days after the day on which it received the copy of the application, advise the Board in writing about any potential impact of the proposed work or activity on the management of the surface of Sable Island National Park Reserve of Canada.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Board to consider advice<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(3) Before deciding whether to issue the authorization, the Board shall consider any advice that it receives under subsection (2). If it issues the authorization, it may include in it terms and conditions, including mitigation or remedial measures, to address the potential impact of the proposed work or activity on the management of the surface of Sable Island National Park Reserve of Canada.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>8.</B> Section 142.1 of the Act is amended by adding the following after subsection (2):</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Sable Island National Park Reserve of Canada<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(3) With respect to Sable Island National Park Reserve of Canada, the surface access rights provided for under this section are limited to the following:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>a</I>) access to existing wellheads for the purposes of safety and environmental protection;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>b</I>) petroleum exploration activities with a low impact on the environment, including seismic, geological or geophysical programs;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>c</I>) emergency evacuation capacity for offshore workers; and</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>d</I>) the operation, maintenance and inspection of emergency facilities, including helicopter landing and fuel storage facilities.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:Consequential Amendments to the Canada Shipping Act, 2001--><MarginalNote>2001, c. 26<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="10" Bold="Yes" SmallCaps="Yes" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">Consequential Amendments to the Canada Shipping Act, 2001</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>9.</B> Section 134 of the <I>Canada Shipping Act, 2001</I> and the heading before it are repealed.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>2005, c. 29, s. 18<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>10.</B> Paragraphs 136(2)(<I>a</I>) and (<I>b</I>) of the Act are repealed.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>11.</B> Section 139 of the Act is repealed.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:Coming into Force--><Para TopMargin="10" Bold="Yes" SmallCaps="Yes" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">Coming into Force</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Order in council<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>12.</B> This Part comes into force on a day to be fixed by order of the Governor in Council.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><Para TopMargin="10" Bold="Yes" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">PART 2</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:OTHER AMENDMENTS TO THE CANADA NATIONAL PARKS ACT--><MarginalNote>2000, c. 32<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" Bold="Yes" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">OTHER AMENDMENTS TO THE CANADA NATIONAL PARKS ACT</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:Amendments--><Para TopMargin="5" Bold="Yes" SmallCaps="Yes" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">Amendments</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>13.</B> (1) Subsection 4(1) of the French version of the <I>Canada National Parks Act</I> is replaced by the following:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Usage public des parcs<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>4.</B> (1) Les parcs sont créés à l’intention du peuple canadien pour son bienfait, son agrément et l’enrichissement de ses connaissances, sous réserve de la présente loi et des règlements; ils doivent être entretenus et utilisés de façon à rester intacts pour les générations futures.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes">(2) Section 4 of the Act is amended by adding the following after subsection (1):</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>For greater certainty<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(1.1) For greater certainty, nothing in this Act limits the authority of the Minister to fix fees under section 23 or 24 of the <I>Parks Canada Agency Act</I>.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>SOR/2004-116, s. 1<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>14.</B> Schedule 4 to the Act is amended by replacing the description of commercial zones in column 3 opposite the reference “1. Field” in column 1 with the following:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><TABLE space-before="12pt" frame="topbot"><tgroup cols="2"><colspec colname="1" colnum="1" colwidth="1.83*"/><colspec colname="3" colnum="2" colwidth="3.48*"/><thead valign="top"><row topdouble="yes" topmarginspacing="4"><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0"><Para BottomMargin="3pt" LeftMargin="0" RightMargin="1.5pt" FirstLineIndent="0" TextAlign="Left"><B>Column 1</B></Para></entry><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0"><Para BottomMargin="3pt" LeftMargin="0" RightMargin="1.5pt" FirstLineIndent="0" TextAlign="Left"><B>Column 3</B></Para></entry></row><row topmarginspacing="4"><entry colsep="0" rowsep="1"><Para BottomMargin="3pt" LeftMargin="0" RightMargin="1.5pt" FirstLineIndent="0" TextAlign="Left"><B>Name of Community</B></Para></entry><entry colsep="0" rowsep="1"><Para BottomMargin="3pt" LeftMargin="0" RightMargin="1.5pt" FirstLineIndent="0" TextAlign="Left"><B>Description of Commercial Zones</B></Para></entry></row></thead><tbody valign="top"><row topmarginspacing="4"><entry colname="1" colsep="0" rowsep="0"><Para BottomMargin="3pt" LeftMargin="0" RightMargin="1.5pt" FirstLineIndent="0" TextAlign="Left"><B>1. Field</B></Para></entry><entry colname="3" colsep="0" rowsep="0"><Para TopMargin="5" BottomMargin="3pt" LeftMargin="0" RightMargin="1.5pt" FirstLineIndent="0" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">Plans 88097, 98121 and 98125 recorded in the Canada Lands Surveys Records at Ottawa and the lands in the Province of British Columbia, in Kootenay District, in the Townsite of Field as shown on a plan 88096 recorded in the Canada Lands Surveys Records at Ottawa, in Yoho National Park of Canada, more particularly described as follows:</Para></entry></row><row topmarginspacing="4"><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0"><br/></entry><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0"><Para TopMargin="5" BottomMargin="3pt" LeftMargin="0" RightMargin="1.5pt" FirstLineIndent="0" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">Firstly;</Para></entry></row><row topmarginspacing="4"><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0"><br/></entry><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0"><Para TopMargin="5" BottomMargin="3pt" LeftMargin="0" RightMargin="1.5pt" FirstLineIndent="0" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">That part of Lot W as shown on the plan recorded in the Canada Lands Surveys Records at Ottawa under number 37572, said part described as follows:</Para></entry></row><row topmarginspacing="4"><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0"><br/></entry><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0"><Para TopMargin="5" BottomMargin="3pt" LeftMargin="0" RightMargin="1.5pt" FirstLineIndent="0" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">Commencing at an iron bar located at a bearing of 225°02′51″ a distance of 50.04 metres from an iron bar located on the west boundary of Second Street East and labelled as Point 52 on a plan recorded in the said Canada Lands Surveys Records under number 52883;</Para></entry></row><row topmarginspacing="4"><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0"><br/></entry><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0"><Para TopMargin="5" BottomMargin="3pt" LeftMargin="0" RightMargin="1.5pt" FirstLineIndent="0" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">Thence continuing on a bearing of 225°02′51″ a distance of 32.46 metres to a capped post;</Para></entry></row><row topmarginspacing="4"><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0"><br/></entry><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0"><Para TopMargin="5" BottomMargin="3pt" LeftMargin="0" RightMargin="1.5pt" FirstLineIndent="0" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">Thence on a bearing of 250°37′12″ a distance of 20.12 metres to an iron post;</Para></entry></row><row topmarginspacing="4"><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0"><br/></entry><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0"><Para TopMargin="5" BottomMargin="3pt" LeftMargin="0" RightMargin="1.5pt" FirstLineIndent="0" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">Thence on a bearing of 333°06′36″ a distance of 26.06 metres to an iron post;</Para></entry></row><row topmarginspacing="4"><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0"><br/></entry><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0"><Para TopMargin="5" BottomMargin="3pt" LeftMargin="0" RightMargin="1.5pt" FirstLineIndent="0" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">Thence on a curve to the right having a radius of 268.10 metres, an arc distance of 9.18 metres, having a chord bearing of 64°05′21″ and a chord distance of 9.18 metres to a capped post;</Para></entry></row><row topmarginspacing="4"><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0"><br/></entry><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0"><Para TopMargin="5" BottomMargin="3pt" LeftMargin="0" RightMargin="1.5pt" FirstLineIndent="0" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">Thence on a bearing of 335°04′20″ a distance of 2.00 metres to an iron post;</Para></entry></row><row topmarginspacing="4"><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0"><br/></entry><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0"><Para TopMargin="5" BottomMargin="3pt" LeftMargin="0" RightMargin="1.5pt" FirstLineIndent="0" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">Thence on a bearing of 65°04′11″ a distance of 42.25 metres to an iron post;</Para></entry></row><row topmarginspacing="4"><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0"><br/></entry><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0"><Para TopMargin="5" BottomMargin="3pt" LeftMargin="0" RightMargin="1.5pt" FirstLineIndent="0" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">Thence on a bearing of 155°04′20″ a distance of 19.03 metres more or less, to the point of commencement.</Para></entry></row><row topmarginspacing="4"><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0"><br/></entry><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0"><Para TopMargin="5" BottomMargin="3pt" LeftMargin="0" RightMargin="1.5pt" FirstLineIndent="0" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">The said parcel being shown as Lot 1 on a plan recorded in the Vancouver office of Legal Surveys Division of Natural Resources Canada under number MPS768;</Para></entry></row><row topmarginspacing="4"><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0"><br/></entry><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0"><Para TopMargin="5" BottomMargin="3pt" LeftMargin="0" RightMargin="1.5pt" FirstLineIndent="0" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">The said parcel containing an area of 1329 square metres more or less.</Para></entry></row><row topmarginspacing="4"><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0"><br/></entry><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0"><Para BottomMargin="3pt" LeftMargin="0" RightMargin="1.5pt" FirstLineIndent="0" TextAlign="Left">Secondly;</Para></entry></row><row topmarginspacing="4"><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0"><br/></entry><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0"><Para BottomMargin="3pt" LeftMargin="0" RightMargin="1.5pt" FirstLineIndent="0" TextAlign="Left">That part of Lot W as shown on a plan recorded in the Canada Lands Surveys Records at Ottawa under number 37572, said part described as follows:</Para></entry></row><row topmarginspacing="4"><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0"><br/></entry><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0"><Para TopMargin="5" BottomMargin="3pt" LeftMargin="0" RightMargin="1.5pt" FirstLineIndent="0" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">Commencing at an iron post located at a bearing of 294°49′39″ a distance of 16.78 metres from an iron post, said iron post being located at a bearing of 198°21′20″ a distance of 29.64 metres from an iron post located on the north west boundary of Stephen Avenue and labelled as Point 329 on a plan recorded in the said Canada Lands Surveys Records under number 52883;</Para></entry></row><row topmarginspacing="4"><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0"><br/></entry><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0"><Para TopMargin="5" BottomMargin="3pt" LeftMargin="0" RightMargin="1.5pt" FirstLineIndent="0" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">Thence on a bearing of 201°30′39″ a distance of 25.27 metres to an iron post;</Para></entry></row><row topmarginspacing="4"><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0"><br/></entry><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0"><Para TopMargin="5" BottomMargin="3pt" LeftMargin="0" RightMargin="1.5pt" FirstLineIndent="0" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">Thence on a bearing of 289°42′06″ a distance of 56.77 metres to an iron post;</Para></entry></row><row topmarginspacing="4"><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0"><br/></entry><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0"><Para TopMargin="5" BottomMargin="3pt" LeftMargin="0" RightMargin="1.5pt" FirstLineIndent="0" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">Thence on a bearing of 19°42′06″ a distance of 25.26 metres to an iron post;</Para></entry></row><row topmarginspacing="4"><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0"><br/></entry><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0"><Para TopMargin="5" BottomMargin="3pt" LeftMargin="0" RightMargin="1.5pt" FirstLineIndent="0" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">Thence on a bearing of 109°42′06″ a distance of 57.57 metres more or less, to the point of commencement.</Para></entry></row><row topmarginspacing="4"><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0"><br/></entry><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0"><Para TopMargin="5" BottomMargin="3pt" LeftMargin="0" RightMargin="1.5pt" FirstLineIndent="0" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">The said parcel being shown as Lot 3 on a plan recorded in the Vancouver office of Legal Surveys Division of Natural Resources Canada under number MPS768;</Para></entry></row><row topmarginspacing="4"><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0"><br/></entry><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0"><Para BottomMargin="3pt" LeftMargin="0" RightMargin="1.5pt" FirstLineIndent="0" TextAlign="Left">The said parcel containing an area of 1444 square metres more or less.</Para></entry></row><row topmarginspacing="4"><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0"><br/></entry><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0"><Para TopMargin="5" BottomMargin="3pt" LeftMargin="0" RightMargin="1.5pt" FirstLineIndent="0" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">Thirdly;</Para></entry></row><row topmarginspacing="4"><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0"><br/></entry><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0"><Para TopMargin="5" BottomMargin="3pt" LeftMargin="0" RightMargin="1.5pt" FirstLineIndent="0" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">That part of Lot W as shown on the plan recorded in the Canada Lands Surveys Records at Ottawa under number 37572, described as follows:</Para></entry></row><row topmarginspacing="4"><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0"><br/></entry><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0"><Para TopMargin="5" BottomMargin="3pt" LeftMargin="0" RightMargin="1.5pt" FirstLineIndent="0" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">Commencing at an iron post located at a bearing of 198°21′20″ a distance of 29.64 metres from an iron post located on the north west boundary of Stephen Avenue and labelled as Point 329 on a plan recorded in the said Canada Lands Surveys Records under number 52883;</Para></entry></row><row topmarginspacing="4"><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0"><br/></entry><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0"><Para TopMargin="5" BottomMargin="3pt" LeftMargin="0" RightMargin="1.5pt" FirstLineIndent="0" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">Thence continuing on a bearing of 198°21′20″ a distance of 18.54 metres to an iron post;</Para></entry></row><row topmarginspacing="4"><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0"><br/></entry><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0"><Para TopMargin="5" BottomMargin="3pt" LeftMargin="0" RightMargin="1.5pt" FirstLineIndent="0" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">Thence on a bearing of 252°10′46″ a distance of 8.58 metres to an iron post;</Para></entry></row><row topmarginspacing="4"><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0"><br/></entry><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0"><Para TopMargin="5" BottomMargin="3pt" LeftMargin="0" RightMargin="1.5pt" FirstLineIndent="0" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">Thence on a bearing of 289°42′06″ a distance of 11.15 metres to an iron post;</Para></entry></row><row topmarginspacing="4"><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0"><br/></entry><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0"><Para TopMargin="5" BottomMargin="3pt" LeftMargin="0" RightMargin="1.5pt" FirstLineIndent="0" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">Thence on a bearing of 21°30′39″ a distance of 25.27 metres to an iron post;</Para></entry></row><row topmarginspacing="4"><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0"><br/></entry><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0"><Para TopMargin="5" BottomMargin="3pt" LeftMargin="0" RightMargin="1.5pt" FirstLineIndent="0" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">Thence on a bearing of 114°49′39″ a distance of 16.78 metres more or less, to the point of commencement.</Para></entry></row><row topmarginspacing="4"><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0"><br/></entry><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0"><Para TopMargin="5" BottomMargin="3pt" LeftMargin="0" RightMargin="1.5pt" FirstLineIndent="0" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">The said parcel being shown as Lot 4 on a plan recorded in the Vancouver office of Legal Surveys Division of Natural Resources Canada under number MPS768;</Para></entry></row><row topmarginspacing="4"><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0"><br/></entry><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0"><Para TopMargin="5" BottomMargin="3pt" LeftMargin="0" RightMargin="1.5pt" FirstLineIndent="0" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">The said parcel containing an area of 408 square metres more or less.</Para></entry></row><row topmarginspacing="4"><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0"><br/></entry><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0"><Para TopMargin="5" BottomMargin="3pt" LeftMargin="0" RightMargin="1.5pt" FirstLineIndent="0" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">All bearings are astronomic and are derived from the bearing between found capped posts on the boundary of the Townsite of Field as shown on a plan recorded in the said Canada Lands Surveys Records under number 83808, said capped posts labelled on this plan as points 33 and 34A and having a bearing between them of 63°15′40″.</Para></entry></row></tbody></tgroup></TABLE></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>15.</B> The description of “MARMOT BASIN SKI AREA” in Schedule 5 to the Act is replaced by the following:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">In Jasper National Park of Canada, the following described area:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">The whole of parcel GS and parcels GT and GU as shown on Plan numbers 98059 and 98067 respectively in the Canada Lands Surveys Records at Ottawa, copies of which have been deposited in the Land Titles Office for the North Alberta Land Registration District at Edmonton under numbers 112 0917 and 112 0921 respectively, said parcels containing 622 hectares, more or less.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:Coming into Force--><Para TopMargin="10" Bold="Yes" SmallCaps="Yes" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">Coming into Force</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Order in council<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>16.</B> Section 15 comes into force on a day to be fixed by order of the Governor in Council.</Para></Block><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="BPT_ImprintE">Published under authority of the Senate of Canada<br/>Available from:<br/>Publishing and Depository Services<br/>Public Works and Government Services Canada<br/>Ottawa, Ontario K1A 0S5<br/>Telephone: 613-941-5995 or 1-800-635-7943<br/>Fax: 613-954-5779 or 1-800-565-7757<br/>publications@tpsgc-pwgsc.gc.ca<br/>http://publications.gc.ca</Para></Block><Block Align="Yes" LineCnt="N"><Para NoLineBreak="Yes" NoHtml="Yes" Leading="0" Size="0" TopMargin="0" BottomMargin="0"></Para></Block></Bill_Part></Bill>
