<!--Arbortext, Inc., 1988-2010, v.4002--><Bill bill-origin="commons" bill-type="govt-public" xml:lang="en"><Identification><BillNumber>C-17</BillNumber><Parliament><Session>1</Session><Number>43</Number><RegnalYear><Year-s>68-69</Year-s><Monarch>Elizabeth II</Monarch></RegnalYear><Year-s>2019-2020</Year-s></Parliament><LongTitle>An Act respecting additional COVID-19 measures</LongTitle><ShortTitle status="unofficial">An Act respecting additional COVID-19 measures</ShortTitle><RunningHead>An Act respecting additional COVID-19 measures</RunningHead><BillHistory><Stages stage="first-reading-house"><Date><YYYY>2020</YYYY><MM>6</MM><DD>10</DD></Date></Stages></BillHistory><BillSponsor>MINISTER OF EMPLOYMENT, WORKFORCE DEVELOPMENT AND DISABILITY INCLUSION</BillSponsor><BillRefNumber date-time="2020-6-10">90930</BillRefNumber></Identification><Introduction><Recommendation><TitleText>RECOMMENDATION</TitleText><Provision format-ref="section"><Text>Her Excellency the Governor General recommends to the House of Commons the appropriation of public revenue under the circumstances, in the manner and for the purposes set out in a measure entitled “<Emphasis style="italic">An Act respecting additional COVID-19 measures</Emphasis>”.</Text></Provision></Recommendation><Summary><TitleText>SUMMARY</TitleText><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>Part 1 amends the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Income Tax Act</XRefExternal> to revise the eligibility criteria for the Canada Emergency Wage Subsidy in order to support those employers hardest hit by the coronavirus disease 2019 (COVID-19).</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>Part 2 enacts the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Time Limits and Other Periods Act (COVID-19)</XRefExternal>, which addresses the need for flexibility in relation to certain time limits and other periods that are established by or under Acts of Parliament and that are difficult or impossible to meet as a result of the exceptional circumstances produced by COVID-19. In particular, the enactment</Text><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>suspends, for a maximum of six months, certain time limits in relation to proceedings before courts;</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>temporarily enables ministers to suspend or extend time limits and to extend other periods in relation to specified Acts and regulations for a maximum of six months; and</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>(c)</Label><Text>provides for the transparent exercise of the powers it confers and for Parliamentary oversight over the exercise of those powers.</Text></Provision></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>Part 3 amends the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Income Tax Act</XRefExternal> to authorize the use by officials, or disclosure to Government of Canada officials, of taxpayer information solely for the purpose of a one-time payment to persons with disabilities for reasons related to COVID-19. It also amends the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Children’s Special Allowances Act</XRefExternal> to authorize the disclosure of information for the purpose of that one-time payment.</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>Part 4 amends the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Canada Emergency Response Benefit Act</XRefExternal> to, among other things, enhance the administration and enforcement of the Act and allow a review of decisions made under the Act. It also provides that a worker is not eligible for an income support payment if they do not return to work when it is reasonable to do so or decline a reasonable job offer.</Text></Provision></Summary><TableOfProvisions label-column-width="2.5"><Heading level="1"><TitleText>TABLE OF PROVISIONS</TitleText></Heading><Heading level="1"><TitleText>An Act respecting additional COVID-19 measures</TitleText></Heading><Heading level="1"><Label>PART 1</Label><TitleText>Income Tax Act</TitleText></Heading><Label><Emphasis style="bold">1</Emphasis></Label><Text /><Heading level="1"><Label>PART 2</Label><TitleText>Time Limits and Other Periods Act (COVID-19)</TitleText></Heading><Label><Emphasis style="bold">4</Emphasis></Label><Text>Enactment of Act</Text><Heading level="1"><TitleText>An Act respecting the suspension or extension of time limits and the extension of other periods as part of the response to the coronavirus disease 2019</TitleText></Heading><Heading level="1"><TitleText>Short Title</TitleText></Heading><Label>1</Label><Text><XRefExternal reference-type="act">Time Limits and Other Periods Act (COVID-19)</XRefExternal></Text><Heading level="1"><TitleText>Interpretation and Application</TitleText></Heading><Label>2</Label><Text>Definition of <DefinitionRef>period</DefinitionRef></Text><Label>3</Label><Text>Effect of suspension or extension</Text><Label>4</Label><Text>Non-application — offences</Text><Heading level="1"><TitleText>Purpose</TitleText></Heading><Label>5</Label><Text>Purpose</Text><Heading level="1"><TitleText>Time Limits Related to Proceedings</TitleText></Heading><Label>6</Label><Text>Suspensions</Text><Heading level="1"><TitleText>Other Time Limits and Periods</TitleText></Heading><Label>7</Label><Text>Ministerial orders — Acts and regulations</Text><Heading level="1"><TitleText>General</TitleText></Heading><Label>8</Label><Text><XRefExternal reference-type="act">Statutory Instruments Act</XRefExternal></Text><Label>9</Label><Text>Sunset provision</Text><Heading level="1"><TitleText>Transparency and Parliamentary Oversight</TitleText></Heading><Label>10</Label><Text>Publication on website</Text><Label>11</Label><Text>Tabling in Parliament</Text><Heading level="1"><Label>PART 3</Label><TitleText>Disclosure of Information for the Purpose of a One-time Payment to Persons with Disabilities</TitleText></Heading><Label><Emphasis style="bold">5</Emphasis></Label><Text /><Heading level="1"><Label>PART 4</Label><TitleText>Canada Emergency Response Benefit Act</TitleText></Heading><Label><Emphasis style="bold">7</Emphasis></Label><Text /><Heading level="5"><Label>SCHEDULE</Label></Heading><Heading level="5"><Label>SCHEDULE</Label></Heading></TableOfProvisions><Enacts><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>Her Majesty, by and with the advice and consent <Keep>of the</Keep> Senate and House of Commons of Canada, <Keep>enacts</Keep> as follows:</Text></Provision></Enacts></Introduction><Body><Heading level="1"><Label>PART 1</Label><MarginalNote><HistoricalNote>R.S., c. 1 (5th Supp.)</HistoricalNote></MarginalNote><TitleText>Income Tax Act</TitleText></Heading><Heading level="2"><TitleText>Amendments to the Act</TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><Label>1</Label><Text>Subsection 87(2) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Income Tax Act</XRefExternal> is amended by adding the following after paragraph (g.5):</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><SectionPiece><Paragraph change="ins"><MarginalNote>COVID-19 – wage subsidy</MarginalNote><Label><Ins>(g.6)</Ins></Label><Text><Ins>for the purposes of section 125.7, the new corporation is deemed to be the same corporation as, and a continuation of, each predecessor corporation unless it is reasonable to consider that one of the main purposes of the amalgamation is to cause the new corporation to qualify for the deemed overpayment under subsection 125.7(2);</Ins></Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>2</Label><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The definition <DefinitionRef>baseline remuneration</DefinitionRef> in subsection 125.7(1) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><SectionPiece><Definition><Text><DefinedTermEn>baseline remuneration</DefinedTermEn>, in respect of an eligible employee of an eligible entity, means the average weekly eligible remuneration, excluding any period of seven or more consecutive days for which the employee was not remunerated, paid to the eligible employee by the eligible entity during the period that</Text><Paragraph><Label><Ins>(a)</Ins></Label><Text>begins on January 1, 2020 and ends on March 15, 2020; or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph change="ins"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>if the eligible entity elects for all qualifying periods,</Text><Subparagraph change="ins"><Label>(i)</Label><Text>begins on March 1, 2019 and ends on May 31, 2019, in respect of a qualifying period described in any of paragraphs (a) to (c) of the definition <DefinitionRef>qualifying period</DefinitionRef>, or</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph><Label>(ii)</Label><Text>is prescribed, in respect of a qualifying period described in paragraph (d) of the definition <DefinitionRef>qualifying period</DefinitionRef>. (<DefinedTermFr>rémunération de base</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Subparagraph></Paragraph></Definition></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Paragraphs (a) and (b) of the definition <DefinitionRef>eligible entity</DefinitionRef> in subsection 125.7(1) of the Act are replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><SectionPiece><Definition><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>a corporation <Ins>or a trust</Ins>, other than a corporation <Ins>or a trust</Ins> that is exempt from tax under this Part or is a public institution;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>an individual <Ins>other than a trust</Ins>;</Text></Paragraph></Definition></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(3)</Label><Text>Paragraph (d) of the definition <DefinitionRef>qualifying entity</DefinitionRef> in subsection 125.7(1) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(d)</Label><Text><Ins>it meets either of the following conditions:</Ins></Text><Subparagraph><Label><Ins>(i)</Ins></Label><Text>it had, on March 15, 2020, a business number in respect of which it is registered with the Minister to make remittances required under section 153, <Ins>or</Ins></Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph change="ins"><Label>(ii)</Label><Text>it is the case that</Text><Clause><Label>(A)</Label><Text>on March 15, 2020,</Text><Subclause><Label>(I)</Label><Text>it employed one or more individuals in Canada,</Text></Subclause><Subclause><Label>(II)</Label><Text>the payroll for its employees was administered by another person or partnership (referred to in this subparagraph as the “payroll service provider”), and</Text></Subclause><Subclause><Label>(III)</Label><Text>the payroll service provider had a business number in respect of which it is registered with the Minister to make remittances required under section 153,</Text></Subclause></Clause><Clause><Label>(B)</Label><Text>the payroll service provider used its business number to make the remittances referred to in subclause (A)(III) in respect of the employees of the eligible entity, and</Text></Clause><Clause change="ins"><Label>(C)</Label><Text>the Minister is satisfied that the conditions in clauses (A) and (B) are met. (<DefinedTermFr>entité admissible</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Clause></Subparagraph></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection></Section><Heading level="2"><TitleText>Coming into Force</TitleText></Heading><Section type="transitional"><MarginalNote>April 11, 2020</MarginalNote><Label>3</Label><Text>Sections <XRefInternal>1</XRefInternal> and <XRefInternal>2</XRefInternal> are deemed to have come into force on April 11, 2020, except that, in respect of the periods described in paragraphs (a) and (b) of the definition <DefinitionRef>qualifying period</DefinitionRef> in subsection 125.7(1) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Income Tax Act</XRefExternal>, paragraphs (a) and (b) of the definition <DefinitionRef>eligible entity</DefinitionRef> in subsection 125.7(1) of that Act, as enacted by subsection <XRefInternal>2</XRefInternal>(2), are to be read as follows:</Text><ReadAsText><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>a corporation, other than a corporation that is exempt from tax under this Part or is a public institution;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>an individual;</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></ReadAsText></Section><Heading level="1"><Label>PART 2</Label><TitleText><XRefExternal reference-type="act">Time Limits and Other Periods Act (COVID-19)</XRefExternal></TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote>Enactment of Act</MarginalNote><Label>4</Label><Text>The <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Time Limits and Other Periods Act (COVID-19)</XRefExternal>, whose text is as follows and whose schedule is set out in the schedule to this Act, is enacted:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="yes"><BillInternal><LongTitle>An Act respecting the suspension or extension of time limits and the extension of other periods as part of the response to the coronavirus disease 2019</LongTitle><Body><Heading level="1"><TitleText>Short Title</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Short title</MarginalNote><Label>1</Label><Text>This Act may be cited as the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Time Limits and Other Periods Act (COVID-19)</XRefExternal>.</Text></Section><Heading level="1"><TitleText>Interpretation and Application</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Definition of <DefinitionRef>period</DefinitionRef></MarginalNote><Label>2</Label><Text>In this Act, <DefinedTermEn>period</DefinedTermEn> includes the time during which a licence, permit or other authorization is valid.</Text></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Effect of suspension or extension</MarginalNote><Label>3</Label><Text>If a time limit is suspended or extended or a period is extended under this Act, then, during the period that the suspension or extension is in effect, every reference in any Act of Parliament or its regulations to that time limit or period is to be read as a reference to the time limit or period as it is suspended or extended.</Text></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Non-application — offences</MarginalNote><Label>4</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>This Act does not apply in respect of the investigation of an offence or in respect of a proceeding respecting an offence.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Non-application — <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Corrections and Conditional Release Act</XRefExternal></MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>This Act does not apply in respect of a time limit or other period that is established by or under the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Corrections and Conditional Release Act</XRefExternal>.</Text></Subsection></Section><Heading level="1"><TitleText>Purpose</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Purpose</MarginalNote><Label>5</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The purpose of this Act is</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>to temporarily suspend certain time limits and to temporarily authorize, in a flexible manner, the suspension or extension of other time limits in order to prevent any exceptional circumstances that may be produced by coronavirus disease 2019 (COVID-19) from making it difficult or impossible to meet those time limits; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>to temporarily authorize, in a flexible manner, the extension of other periods in order to prevent any unfair or undesirable effects that may result from the expiry of those periods due to those exceptional circumstances.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>For greater certainty</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>For greater certainty, this Act is to be interpreted in a manner that provides certainty in relation to proceedings and that respects the rule of law and the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Canadian Charter of Rights and Freedoms</XRefExternal>.</Text></Subsection></Section><Heading level="1"><TitleText>Time Limits Related to Proceedings</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Suspensions</MarginalNote><Label>6</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The following time limits are, if established by or under an Act of Parliament, suspended for the period that starts on March 13, 2020 and that ends on September 13, 2020 or on any earlier day fixed by order of the Governor in Council made on the recommendation of the Minister of Justice:</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>any limitation or prescription period for commencing a proceeding before a court;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>any time limit in relation to something that is to be done in a proceeding before a court; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(c)</Label><Text>any time limit within which an application for leave to commence a proceeding or to do something in relation to a proceeding is to be made to a court.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Court orders — variation</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The court may, by order, vary the suspension of a time limit as long as the commencement date of the suspension remains the same and the duration of the suspension does not exceed six months.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Court orders — effects</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>The court may make orders respecting the effects of a failure to meet a suspended time limit, including orders that cancel or vary those effects.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Orders in council</MarginalNote><Label>(4)</Label><Text>The Governor in Council may, by order made on the recommendation of the Minister of Justice, lift a suspension in circumstances specified in the order.</Text></Subsection></Section><Heading level="1"><TitleText>Other Time Limits and Periods</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Ministerial orders — Acts and regulations</MarginalNote><Label>7</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The minister who is responsible for an Act of Parliament set out in column 1 of the schedule or a relevant portion of the Act may make an order</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>suspending or extending a time limit that is established by or under any provision of the Act that is set out in column 2;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>extending any other period that is established by or under any provision of the Act that is set out in column 2;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(c)</Label><Text>if a regulation is set out in column 2 in respect of the Act,</Text><Subparagraph><Label>(i)</Label><Text>suspending or extending a time limit that is established by or under that regulation, or</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph><Label>(ii)</Label><Text>extending any other period that is established by or under that regulation; or</Text></Subparagraph></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(d)</Label><Text>extending a suspension or extension.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Ministerial orders — regulations</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The minister who is responsible for a regulation set out in column 1 of the schedule or a relevant portion of the regulation may make an order</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>suspending or extending a time limit that is established by or under any provision of the regulation that is set out in column 2;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>extending any other period that is established by or under any provision of the regulation that is set out in column 2; or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(c)</Label><Text>extending a suspension or extension.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Non-application</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>An order under subsection (1) or (2) does not apply in respect of a time limit or other period that ends on or after December 31, 2020.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Duration</MarginalNote><Label>(4)</Label><Text>The total duration of a suspension or extension must not exceed six months. However, a suspension must not have the effect of allowing a time limit to continue after December 31, 2020 and an extended time limit or period must end on or before that day.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Retroactivity</MarginalNote><Label>(5)</Label><Text>An order under subsection (1) or (2) may, if it so provides, have retroactive effect, but not before March 13, 2020, and it may also include provisions respecting the effects of a failure to meet the time limit or of the expiry of the period before the day on which the order was made, including provisions that cancel or vary those effects.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Additional content</MarginalNote><Label>(6)</Label><Text>An order under subsection (1) or (2) may provide that</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>a suspension or extension does not apply in respect of any circumstance specified in the order without the consent of a person, court or body specified in the order;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>a suspension or extension applies in respect of any circumstance specified in the order unless a person, court or body specified in the order decides otherwise; or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(c)</Label><Text>a person, court or body specified in the order may vary the effects of the order in relation to any circumstance specified in the order.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Regulations</MarginalNote><Label>(7)</Label><Text>The Governor in Council may, on the recommendation of the Minister of Justice, make regulations restricting, or imposing conditions on, a power to make an order under subsection (1) or (2).</Text></Subsection></Section><Heading level="1"><TitleText>General</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote><XRefExternal reference-type="act">Statutory Instruments Act</XRefExternal></MarginalNote><Label>8</Label><Text>The <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Statutory Instruments Act</XRefExternal> does not apply to an order made under subsection <XRefInternal>6</XRefInternal>(1), (2), (3) or (4) or <XRefInternal>7</XRefInternal>(1) or (2).</Text></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Sunset provision</MarginalNote><Label>9</Label><Text>A power conferred on the Governor in Council or a minister under this Act is not to be exercised after September 30, 2020.</Text></Section><Heading level="1"><TitleText>Transparency and Parliamentary Oversight</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Publication on website</MarginalNote><Label>10</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>An order made under subsection <XRefInternal>6</XRefInternal>(1) or (4) or <XRefInternal>7</XRefInternal>(1) or (2), together with the reasons for making it, must be published, as soon as feasible after the day on which it is made but no later than five days after the day on which it is made, on a Government of Canada website for a period of at least six months.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Publication in <XRefExternal reference-type="other">Canada Gazette</XRefExternal></MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>An order referred to in subsection (1) must be published in Part I of the <XRefExternal reference-type="other">Canada Gazette</XRefExternal> within 14 days after the day on which it is made.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Tabling in Parliament</MarginalNote><Label>11</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>An order made under subsection <XRefInternal>6</XRefInternal>(1) or (4) or <XRefInternal>7</XRefInternal>(1) or (2) must be tabled in each House of Parliament within three days after the day on which it is made, unless a House is not sitting within those three days, in which case the order is to be tabled in that House at the earliest opportunity.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Referral to committee</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>An order that is tabled in a House of Parliament must be referred to a committee of that House.</Text></Subsection></Section></Body></BillInternal></AmendedText></Section><Heading level="1"><Label>PART 3</Label><TitleText>Disclosure of Information for the Purpose of a One-time Payment to Persons with Disabilities</TitleText></Heading><Heading level="2"><MarginalNote><HistoricalNote>R.S., c. 1 (5th Supp.)</HistoricalNote></MarginalNote><TitleText>Income Tax Act</TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><Label>5</Label><Text>Subsection 241(4) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Income Tax Act</XRefExternal> is amended by adding the following after paragraph (h):</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><SectionPiece><Paragraph change="ins"><Label>(h.1)</Label><Text>use, or provide to an official of a department or agency of the Government of Canada, taxpayer information solely for a purpose relating to the administration or enforcement of a program to provide a one-time payment to persons with disabilities for reasons related to the coronavirus disease 2019 (COVID-19), to the extent that the information is relevant for the purpose;</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Section><Heading level="2"><MarginalNote><HistoricalNote>1992, c. 48, Sch.</HistoricalNote></MarginalNote><TitleText>Children’s Special Allowances Act</TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><Label>6</Label><Text>Subsection 10(2) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Children’s Special Allowances Act</XRefExternal> is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Subsection><MarginalNote>Release of information</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Any information obtained by or on behalf of the Minister in the course of the administration or enforcement of this Act or the regulations or the carrying out of an agreement entered into under section 11 may be communicated</Text><Paragraph><Label><Ins>(a)</Ins></Label><Text>to any person if it can reasonably be regarded as necessary for the purposes of the administration or enforcement of this Act, the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Income Tax Act</XRefExternal>, the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Canada Disability Savings Act</XRefExternal> or the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Canada Education Savings Act</XRefExternal> or a program administered under an agreement entered into under section 12 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Canada Education Savings Act</XRefExternal>; <Ins>and</Ins></Text></Paragraph><Paragraph change="ins"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>to the Department of Employment and Social Development, to the extent that the communication is required for the administration of a program to provide a one-time payment to persons with disabilities for reasons related to the coronavirus disease 2019 (COVID-19).</Text></Paragraph></Subsection></AmendedText></Section><Heading level="1"><Label>PART 4</Label><MarginalNote><HistoricalNote>2020, c. 5, s. 8</HistoricalNote></MarginalNote><TitleText>Canada Emergency Response Benefit Act</TitleText></Heading><Heading level="2"><TitleText>Amendments to the Act</TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><Label>7</Label><Text>Subsection 5(1) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Canada Emergency Response Benefit Act</XRefExternal> is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Section><MarginalNote>Application</MarginalNote><Label>5</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>A worker may, in the form and manner established by the Minister, apply for an income support payment</Text><Paragraph><Label><Ins>(a)</Ins></Label><Text>for any period <Ins>of</Ins> four <Ins>weeks</Ins> falling within the period beginning on March 15, 2020 and ending on <Ins>July 4</Ins>, 2020; <Ins>and</Ins></Text></Paragraph><Paragraph change="ins"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>for any period of two weeks falling within the period beginning on July 5, 2020 and ending on October 3, 2020.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>8</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Paragraph 6(1)(a) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>for reasons related to COVID-19 and whether <Ins>as an employee</Ins> or <Ins>in</Ins> self-<Ins>employment,</Ins></Text><Subparagraph><Label><Ins>(i)</Ins></Label><Text><Ins>in the case of the first application made under paragraph 5(1)(a)</Ins>, the worker ceases working for <Ins>a</Ins> period <Ins>of</Ins> at least 14 consecutive days within the period in respect of which they apply for the payment, <Ins>or</Ins></Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph change="ins"><Label>(ii)</Label><Text>in the case of any other application made under paragraph 5(1)(a) or any application made under paragraph 5(1)(b), the worker ceases working for the period in respect of which they apply for the payment; and</Text></Subparagraph></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The portion of paragraph 6(1)(b) of the Act before subparagraph (i) is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text><Ins>the worker</Ins> does not receive, in respect of the <Ins>period for which</Ins> they have ceased working,</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(3)</Label><Text>The portion of subsection 6(1) of the Act before paragraph (a) is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Section><MarginalNote>Eligibility</MarginalNote><Label>6</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Subject to subsection (2.1), a worker is eligible for an income support payment if</Text></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(4)</Label><Text>Section 6 of the Act is amended by adding the following after subsection (2):</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Subsection change="ins"><MarginalNote>Exception — return to work</MarginalNote><Label>(2.1)</Label><Text>A worker is not eligible for an income support payment if they</Text><Paragraph change="ins"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>fail to return to work when it is reasonable to do so and the employer makes a request for their return;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph change="ins"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>fail to resume self-employment when it is reasonable to do so; or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph change="ins"><Label>(c)</Label><Text>decline a reasonable job offer when they are able to work.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection></AmendedText></Subsection></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>9</Label><Text>The Act is amended by adding the following after section 8:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Section change="ins"><MarginalNote>Request for review</MarginalNote><Label>8.1</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>A person who is the subject of a decision of the Minister in respect of an application made by that person under section 5 may make a request, in the form and manner established by the Minister, to the Minister for a review of that decision at any time within 30 days after the day on which they are informed of the decision or any further time that the Minister may allow.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Review</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The Minister must review the decision if a request for its review is made under subsection (1). On completion of the review, the Minister must confirm, vary or rescind the decision.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Notification</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>The Minister must inform the person who made the request of the Minister’s decision under subsection (2).</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Review is final</MarginalNote><Label>(4)</Label><Text>The Minister’s confirmation, variation or rescission, as the case may be, is final and is not to be questioned or reviewed in any court.</Text></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>10</Label><Text>The Act is amended by adding the following after section 12:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Section change="ins"><MarginalNote>Penalties</MarginalNote><Label>12.1</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The Minister may impose on a person who made an application for an income support payment under section 5, or on another person acting for that person, a penalty for each of the following acts or omissions if the Minister becomes aware of facts that in the Minister’s opinion establish that the person or other person has</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>in relation to the application, made a representation that they knew was false or misleading;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>being required under this Act to provide information, provided information or made a representation that they knew was false or misleading;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(c)</Label><Text>knowingly failed to declare to the Minister all or some of the person’s income for the period in respect of which they applied for the payment;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(d)</Label><Text>made an application or declaration under this Act that they knew was false or misleading because of the non-disclosure of facts;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(e)</Label><Text>knowingly, in any manner, received an income support payment that they were not eligible to receive under this Act; or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(f)</Label><Text>participated in, assented to or acquiesced in an act or omission mentioned in paragraphs (a) to (e).</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Amount</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The Minister may set the amount of the penalty for each act or omission at not more than three times the amount of an income support payment for a week that falls within the period in respect of which the application was made.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section change="ins"><MarginalNote>Limitation of imposition of penalties</MarginalNote><Label>12.2</Label><Text>A penalty must not be imposed under section 12.1 if</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>a prosecution for the act or omission has been initiated against the person who made an application for an income support payment under section 5 or another person who acted for that person; or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>36 months have passed since the day on which the act or omission occurred.</Text></Paragraph></Section><Section change="ins"><MarginalNote>Rescission, etc., of penalty</MarginalNote><Label>12.3</Label><Text>The Minister may rescind the imposition of a penalty under section 12.1, or reduce the penalty, on the presentation of new facts or on being satisfied that the penalty was imposed without knowledge of, or on the basis of a mistake as to, some material fact.</Text></Section><Section change="ins"><MarginalNote>Warning</MarginalNote><Label>12.4</Label><Text>The Minister may issue a warning instead of setting the amount of a penalty for an act or omission under subsection 12.1.</Text></Section><Section change="ins"><MarginalNote>Recovery as debt due to Her Majesty</MarginalNote><Label>12.5</Label><Subsection change="ins"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>A penalty imposed under section 12.1 constitutes a debt due to Her Majesty in right of Canada that may be recovered by the Minister.</Text></Subsection><Subsection change="ins"><MarginalNote>Certificate of default</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The amount of any debt referred to in subsection (1) may be certified by the Minister and registration of the certificate in the Federal Court has the same effect as a judgment of that Court for the amount specified in the certificate and all related registration costs.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section change="ins"><MarginalNote>Garnishment</MarginalNote><Label>12.6</Label><Text>If the Minister is of the opinion that a person is or is about to become liable to pay an amount to another person who is indebted to Her Majesty under subsection 12(2) or 12.5(1), the Minister may, by written notice, order the person to pay to the Receiver General on account of the other person’s liability all or part of the amount otherwise payable to the other person.</Text></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>11</Label><Text>Subsection 13(6) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Subsection><MarginalNote>Limitation or prescription period suspended</MarginalNote><Label>(6)</Label><Text>The running of a limitation or prescription period in respect of money owing under this Act is suspended</Text><Paragraph><Label><Ins>(a)</Ins></Label><Text>during any period in which it is prohibited to commence or continue an action or other proceedings against the person to recover money owing under this Act; <Ins>or</Ins></Text></Paragraph><Paragraph change="ins"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>during any period in which any review of a decision establishing the liability in respect of money owing under this Act is pending.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>12</Label><Text>Section 14 of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Section><MarginalNote>No interest payable</MarginalNote><Label>14</Label><Text>No interest is payable on any amount owing to Her Majesty in right of Canada under this Act as a result of an erroneous payment, overpayment or <Ins>a penalty imposed under this Act</Ins>.</Text></Section><Section change="ins"><MarginalNote>Offences</MarginalNote><Label>14.1</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Every person is guilty of an offence who</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>in relation to an application for an income support payment made under section 5, makes a representation that they know to be false or misleading;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>being required under this Act to provide information, provides information or makes a representation that the person knows to be false or misleading;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(c)</Label><Text>knowingly fails to declare to the Minister all or some of the person’s income for the period in respect of which the person applied for the payment;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(d)</Label><Text>makes an application or declaration under this Act that the person knows is false or misleading because of the non-disclosure of facts;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(e)</Label><Text>knowingly, in any manner, receives an income support payment that the person is not eligible to receive under this Act; or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(f)</Label><Text>participates in, assents to or acquiesces in an act or omission mentioned in paragraphs (a) to (e).</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Prosecution</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>No prosecution for an offence under this section may be instituted if a penalty for that conduct has been imposed under section 12.1.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Punishment</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>Every person who is guilty of an offence under subsection (1) is liable on summary conviction to, as the case may be,</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>a fine of not more than $5,000, plus an amount of not more than double the amount of the income support payment that was or would have been paid as a result of committing the offence; or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>both the fine and imprisonment for a term of not more than six months.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection></Section><Section change="ins"><MarginalNote>Contravention of Act or regulations</MarginalNote><Label>14.2</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Every person who contravenes a provision of this Act or of the regulations is guilty of an offence.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Obstruction</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Every person who delays or obstructs an investigator designated under subsection 14.3(1) or under an authorization issued under subsection 14.3(2) in the investigator’s exercise of the Minister’s powers or in their performance of the Minister’s duties and functions under this Act is guilty of an offence.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Punishment</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>Every person who is guilty of an offence under subsection (1) or (2) for which no penalty is provided is liable on summary conviction to a fine of not more than $2,000 or to imprisonment for a term of not more than six months, or to both.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section change="ins"><MarginalNote>Designation — investigators</MarginalNote><Label>14.3</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The Minister may designate as an investigator any person or class of persons for the purpose of enforcing sections 14.1 and 14.2.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Authorization</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The Minister may authorize the <DefinitionRef>Commissioner</DefinitionRef>, as defined in section 2 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Canada Revenue Agency Act</XRefExternal>, to designate as an investigator any employee or class of employees of the <DefinitionRef>Agency</DefinitionRef>, as defined in that section 2, for the purpose of enforcing sections 14.1 and 14.2.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Territorial jurisdiction</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>An information or complaint about an offence under this Act may be heard, tried or determined by any <DefinitionRef>provincial court judge</DefinitionRef>, as defined in section 2 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Criminal Code</XRefExternal>, if the accused is resident, carrying on business, found, apprehended or in custody in the judge’s territorial jurisdiction regardless of whether or not the matter of the information or complaint arose in that jurisdiction.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Limitation period</MarginalNote><Label>(4)</Label><Text>Proceedings in respect of an offence under this Act may be commenced at any time within, but not later than, five years after the day on which the Minister became aware of the subject matter of the prosecution.</Text></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Section><Heading level="2"><TitleText>Transitional Provisions</TitleText></Heading><Section type="transitional"><MarginalNote>Section 8.1</MarginalNote><Label>13</Label><Text>Section 8.1 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Canada Emergency Response Benefit Act</XRefExternal> applies regardless of the date on which the decision was made.</Text></Section><Section type="transitional"><MarginalNote>Sections 12.1 and 12.4</MarginalNote><Label>14</Label><Text>Sections 12.1 and 12.4 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Canada Emergency Response Benefit Act</XRefExternal> apply regardless of the date on which the act or omission occurred.</Text></Section><Section type="transitional"><MarginalNote>Section 12.6</MarginalNote><Label>15</Label><Text>Section 12.6 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Canada Emergency Response Benefit Act</XRefExternal> applies regardless of the date on which the debt arose.</Text></Section><Heading level="2"><TitleText>Coming into Force</TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote>March 25, 2020</MarginalNote><Label>16</Label><Text>Section <XRefInternal>7</XRefInternal> and subsections <XRefInternal>8</XRefInternal>(1) and (2) are deemed to have come into force on March 25, 2020.</Text></Section></Body><Schedule bilingual="no" spanlanguages="yes"><ScheduleFormHeading type="amending"><Label>SCHEDULE</Label><OriginatingRef><Emphasis style="bold">(Section 4)</Emphasis></OriginatingRef></ScheduleFormHeading><Schedule bilingual="no" spanlanguages="yes"><ScheduleFormHeading><Label>SCHEDULE</Label><OriginatingRef>(Subsections 7(1) and (2))</OriginatingRef><TitleText>Acts, Regulations and Provisions</TitleText></ScheduleFormHeading><TableGroup bilingual="no" pointsize="9" rowbreak="no" spanlanguages="no" spanmarginalnotecol="no" topmarginspacing="10"><table colsep="0" frame="topbot" rowsep="0"><tgroup cols="2"><colspec colname="1" colnum="1" colwidth="5.32*" /><colspec colname="2" colnum="2" colwidth="3.98*" /><thead valign="bottom"><row topdouble="yes" topmarginspacing="2"><entry rowsep="1" valign="top">Column 1</entry><entry rowsep="1" valign="top">Column 2</entry></row><row topmarginspacing="2"><entry valign="top" /><entry valign="top" /></row></thead><tbody valign="top"><row topmarginspacing="2"><entry><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="no" list-item="no" topmarginspacing="1pc"><Text><Emphasis style="bold">Acts</Emphasis></Text></Provision></entry><entry><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="no" list-item="no" topmarginspacing="1pc"><Text><Emphasis style="bold">Provisions and Regulations</Emphasis></Text></Provision></entry></row><row topmarginspacing="2"><entry colname="1"><BilingualGroup><BilingualItemEn>Bankruptcy and Insolvency Act</BilingualItemEn><BilingualItemFr>Loi sur la faillite et l’insolvabilité </BilingualItemFr></BilingualGroup></entry><entry colname="2"><Provision language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text>subsections 50.4(2), (6), (8) and (9), section 51, subsection 66.12(5), section 66.15, subsection 66.31(1), section 102 and subsection 170.1(3) of the Act</Text></Provision><BilingualGroup><BilingualItemEn>Bankruptcy and Insolvency General Rules</BilingualItemEn><BilingualItemFr>Règles générales sur la faillite et l’insolvabilité</BilingualItemFr></BilingualGroup></entry></row><row topmarginspacing="2"><entry><BilingualGroup><BilingualItemEn>Boards of Trade Act</BilingualItemEn><BilingualItemFr>Loi sur les chambres de commerce</BilingualItemFr></BilingualGroup></entry><entry><Provision language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text>subsections 17(1) and 42(1) and (2) of the Act</Text></Provision></entry></row><row topmarginspacing="2"><entry><BilingualGroup><BilingualItemEn>Canada Business Corporations Act</BilingualItemEn><BilingualItemFr>Loi canadienne sur les sociétés par actions </BilingualItemFr></BilingualGroup></entry><entry><Provision language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text>subsections 133(1), 135(1), 155(1), 159(1) and 160(1) of the Act</Text></Provision></entry></row><row topmarginspacing="2"><entry><BilingualGroup><BilingualItemEn>Canada Cooperatives Act</BilingualItemEn><BilingualItemFr>Loi canadienne sur les coopératives </BilingualItemFr></BilingualGroup></entry><entry><Provision language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text>subsections 50(1), 52(1) and 247(1), section 251 and subsection 252(1) of the Act</Text></Provision></entry></row><row topmarginspacing="2"><entry><BilingualGroup><BilingualItemEn>Canada–Newfoundland and Labrador Atlantic Accord Implementation Act</BilingualItemEn><BilingualItemFr>Loi de mise en oeuvre de l’Accord atlantique Canada — Terre-Neuve-et-Labrador </BilingualItemFr></BilingualGroup></entry><entry><Provision language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text>subsections 31(2), 35(3), 39(1), 69(2) and 188(1) and (2), section 202.1, paragraphs 205.013(q) and 205.019(1)(p) and subsections 205.04(1), 205.041(3), 205.042(1) and (2), 205.044(3), 205.046(4), 205.059(5), 205.06(2) and (9), 205.063(2), 205.071(1), 205.098(3) and 205.1(2) of the Act</Text></Provision></entry></row><row topmarginspacing="2"><entry colname="1"><BilingualGroup><BilingualItemEn>Canada Not-for-profit Corporations Act</BilingualItemEn><BilingualItemFr>Loi canadienne sur les organisations à but non lucratif </BilingualItemFr></BilingualGroup></entry><entry colname="2"><Provision language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text>subsections 160(1), 162(1), 172(1), 175(1) and 176(1) of the Act</Text></Provision></entry></row><row topmarginspacing="2"><entry colname="1"><BilingualGroup><BilingualItemEn>Canadian Forces Superannuation Act</BilingualItemEn><BilingualItemFr>Loi sur la pension de retraite des Forces canadiennes </BilingualItemFr></BilingualGroup></entry><entry colname="2"><Provision language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text>paragraph 6(b), subsections 6.1(1), 8(1), 23(1) and (2), 29(1) and (5), 41(1), (3) and (4), 42(1) and (1.2) and 43(1), sections 46, 57, 59.6 and 59.7, subsections 62(1) and (2) and 69(2), sections 71, 72 and 92 and subsection 93(1) of the Act</Text></Provision><BilingualGroup><BilingualItemEn>Canadian Forces Superannuation Regulations</BilingualItemEn><BilingualItemFr>Règlement sur la pension de retraite des Forces canadiennes</BilingualItemFr></BilingualGroup><BilingualGroup><BilingualItemEn>Reserve Force Pension Plan Regulations</BilingualItemEn><BilingualItemFr>Règlement sur le régime de pension de la force de réserve</BilingualItemFr></BilingualGroup></entry></row><row topmarginspacing="2"><entry><BilingualGroup><BilingualItemEn>Companies’ Creditors Arrangement Act</BilingualItemEn><BilingualItemFr>Loi sur les arrangements avec les créanciers des compagnies </BilingualItemFr></BilingualGroup></entry><entry><Provision language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text>section 11.001 and subsections 11.02(1) and 11.2(5) of the Act</Text></Provision></entry></row><row topmarginspacing="2"><entry colname="1"><BilingualGroup><BilingualItemEn>Diplomatic Service (Special) Superannuation Act</BilingualItemEn><BilingualItemFr>Loi sur la pension spéciale du service diplomatique</BilingualItemFr></BilingualGroup></entry><entry colname="2"><Provision language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text>section 7 and subsection 11(1) of the Act</Text></Provision></entry></row><row topmarginspacing="2"><entry colname="1"><BilingualGroup><BilingualItemEn>Excise Tax Act</BilingualItemEn><BilingualItemFr>Loi sur la taxe d’accise </BilingualItemFr></BilingualGroup></entry><entry colname="2"><Provision language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text>subsections 298(1) and (2), 303(7) and 304(5) of the Act</Text></Provision></entry></row><row topmarginspacing="2"><entry colname="1"><BilingualGroup><BilingualItemEn>Firearms Act</BilingualItemEn><BilingualItemFr>Loi sur les armes à feu </BilingualItemFr></BilingualGroup></entry><entry colname="2"><Provision language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text>section 64 of the Act</Text></Provision></entry></row><row topmarginspacing="2"><entry colname="1"><BilingualGroup><BilingualItemEn>Garnishment, Attachment and Pension Diversion Act</BilingualItemEn><BilingualItemFr>Loi sur la saisie-arrêt et la distraction de pensions</BilingualItemFr></BilingualGroup></entry><entry colname="2"><Provision language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text>subsection 39(2) of the Act</Text></Provision></entry></row><row topmarginspacing="2"><entry colname="1"><BilingualGroup><BilingualItemEn>Income Tax Act</BilingualItemEn><BilingualItemFr>Loi de l’impôt sur le revenu</BilingualItemFr></BilingualGroup></entry><entry colname="2"><Provision language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text>subsection 37(11), paragraph (m) of the definition <DefinitionRef>investment tax credit</DefinitionRef> in subsection 127(9) and subsections 152(3.1) and (4), 166.1(7) and 166.2(5) of the Act</Text></Provision></entry></row><row topmarginspacing="2"><entry><BilingualGroup><BilingualItemEn>Investment Canada Act</BilingualItemEn><BilingualItemFr>Loi sur Investissement Canada </BilingualItemFr></BilingualGroup></entry><entry><Provision language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text>sections 25.2 and 25.3 of the Act</Text></Provision><BilingualGroup><BilingualItemEn>National Security Review of Investments Regulations</BilingualItemEn><BilingualItemFr>Règlement sur les investissements susceptibles de porter atteinte à la sécurité nationale (examen)</BilingualItemFr></BilingualGroup></entry></row><row topmarginspacing="2"><entry colname="1"><BilingualGroup><BilingualItemEn>Lieutenant Governors Superannuation Act</BilingualItemEn><BilingualItemFr>Loi sur la pension de retraite des lieutenants-gouverneurs </BilingualItemFr></BilingualGroup></entry><entry colname="2"><Provision language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text>subsections 3(3) and 5(1) of the Act</Text></Provision><BilingualGroup><BilingualItemEn>Lieutenant Governors Superannuation Regulations</BilingualItemEn><BilingualItemFr>Règlement sur la pension de retraite des lieutenants-gouverneurs</BilingualItemFr></BilingualGroup></entry></row><row topmarginspacing="2"><entry colname="1"><BilingualGroup><BilingualItemEn>Members of Parliament Retiring Allowances Act</BilingualItemEn><BilingualItemFr>Loi sur les allocations de retraite des parlementaires </BilingualItemFr></BilingualGroup></entry><entry colname="2"><Provision language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text>subsections 10(1) and 32(1) of the Act</Text></Provision><BilingualGroup><BilingualItemEn>Former Members of Parliament Elections for Joint and Survivor Benefits Regulations</BilingualItemEn><BilingualItemFr>Règlement sur les choix relatifs à la pension de réversion des anciens parlementaires</BilingualItemFr></BilingualGroup><BilingualGroup><BilingualItemEn>Recovery of Overpayments Made to Former Members of Parliament Regulations</BilingualItemEn><BilingualItemFr>Règlement sur le recouvrement des versements payés en trop aux anciens parlementaires</BilingualItemFr></BilingualGroup></entry></row><row topmarginspacing="2"><entry colname="1"><BilingualGroup><BilingualItemEn>Pension Benefits Division Act</BilingualItemEn><BilingualItemFr>Loi sur le partage des prestations de retraite</BilingualItemFr></BilingualGroup></entry><entry colname="2"><Provision language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text>subsection 6(1) of the Act</Text></Provision></entry></row><row topmarginspacing="2"><entry colname="1"><BilingualGroup><BilingualItemEn>Public Service Superannuation Act</BilingualItemEn><BilingualItemFr>Loi sur la pension de la fonction publique </BilingualItemFr></BilingualGroup></entry><entry colname="2"><Provision language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text>sections 6 and 9, subsections 10(4) and (5) and 25(7), section 39, subsection 40(11), section 51 and subsection 57(2) of the Act</Text></Provision><BilingualGroup><BilingualItemEn>Counting of Service by Former Members of the Senate or House of Commons Regulations</BilingualItemEn><BilingualItemFr>Règlement du calcul du service des anciens membres du Sénat ou de la Chambre des communes</BilingualItemFr></BilingualGroup><BilingualGroup><BilingualItemEn>Portions of the Public Service General Divestiture Regulations</BilingualItemEn><BilingualItemFr>Règlement général sur la cession de secteurs de la fonction publique</BilingualItemFr></BilingualGroup><BilingualGroup><BilingualItemEn>Public Service Superannuation Regulations</BilingualItemEn><BilingualItemFr>Règlement sur la pension de la fonction publique</BilingualItemFr></BilingualGroup><BilingualGroup><BilingualItemEn>Public Service Superannuation Special Election Regulations</BilingualItemEn><BilingualItemFr>Règlement sur l’exercice d’un choix spécial aux fins de la pension de la fonction publique</BilingualItemFr></BilingualGroup><BilingualGroup><BilingualItemEn>Supplementary Death Benefit Regulations</BilingualItemEn><BilingualItemFr>Règlement sur les prestations supplémentaires de décès</BilingualItemFr></BilingualGroup></entry></row><row topmarginspacing="2"><entry><BilingualGroup><BilingualItemEn>Royal Canadian Mounted Police Superannuation Act</BilingualItemEn><BilingualItemFr>Loi sur la pension de retraite la Gendarmerie royale du Canada</BilingualItemFr></BilingualGroup></entry><entry><Provision language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text>sections 6, 6.1 and 8, subsections 9(4) and 18(4) and section 24 of the Act</Text></Provision><BilingualGroup><BilingualItemEn>Former Members of Parliament Counting of Service Regulations</BilingualItemEn><BilingualItemFr>Règlement sur l’inclusion du service des anciens parlementaires</BilingualItemFr></BilingualGroup><BilingualGroup><BilingualItemEn>Royal Canadian Mounted Police Superannuation Regulations</BilingualItemEn><BilingualItemFr>Règlement sur la pension de retraite de la Gendarmerie royale du Canada</BilingualItemFr></BilingualGroup></entry></row><row topmarginspacing="2"><entry><BilingualGroup><BilingualItemEn>Special Import Measures Act</BilingualItemEn><BilingualItemFr>Loi sur les mesures spéciales d’importation </BilingualItemFr></BilingualGroup></entry><entry><Provision language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text>subsections 41(1) and 41.1(3), paragraph 41.1(4)(d), subsections 42(1) and 43(1) and (2) and sections 55, 55.1, 56, 57, 59, 66, 76.01, 76.02 and 76.03 of the Act</Text></Provision></entry></row><row topmarginspacing="2"><entry><BilingualGroup><BilingualItemEn>Wage Earner Protection Program Act</BilingualItemEn><BilingualItemFr>Loi sur le Programme de protection des salariés</BilingualItemFr></BilingualGroup></entry><entry><Provision language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text>subparagraph (a)(i) of the definition <DefinitionRef>eligible wages</DefinitionRef> in subsection 2(1) of the Act</Text></Provision></entry></row><row topmarginspacing="2"><entry><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="no" list-item="no" topmarginspacing="2pc"><Text><Emphasis style="bold">Regulations</Emphasis></Text></Provision></entry><entry><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="no" list-item="no" topmarginspacing="2pc"><Text><Emphasis style="bold">Provisions</Emphasis></Text></Provision></entry></row><row topmarginspacing="2"><entry><BilingualGroup><BilingualItemEn>Aviation Occupational Health and Safety Regulations</BilingualItemEn><BilingualItemFr>Règlement sur la santé et la sécurité au travail (aéronefs)</BilingualItemFr></BilingualGroup></entry><entry><Provision language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text>section 9.1 and subsection 9.5(5) of the Regulations</Text></Provision></entry></row><row topmarginspacing="2"><entry><BilingualGroup><BilingualItemEn>Canada Labour Standards Regulations</BilingualItemEn><BilingualItemFr>Règlement du Canada sur les normes du travail</BilingualItemFr></BilingualGroup></entry><entry><Provision language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text>section 30 of the Regulations</Text></Provision></entry></row><row topmarginspacing="2"><entry><BilingualGroup><BilingualItemEn>Canada Occupational Health and Safety Regulations</BilingualItemEn><BilingualItemFr>Règlement canadien sur la santé et la sécurité au travail</BilingualItemFr></BilingualGroup></entry><entry><Provision language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text>subsection 16.12(5) of the Regulations</Text></Provision></entry></row><row topmarginspacing="2"><entry><BilingualGroup><BilingualItemEn>Food and Drug Regulations</BilingualItemEn><BilingualItemFr>Règlement sur les aliments et drogues</BilingualItemFr></BilingualGroup></entry><entry><Provision language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text>paragraphs C.05.006(1)(b) and C.05.008(1)(b) of the Regulations</Text></Provision></entry></row><row topmarginspacing="2"><entry><BilingualGroup><BilingualItemEn>Maritime Occupational Health and Safety Regulations</BilingualItemEn><BilingualItemFr>Règlement sur la santé et la sécurité au travail en milieu maritime</BilingualItemFr></BilingualGroup></entry><entry><Provision language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text>paragraph 111(1)(b) of the Regulations</Text></Provision></entry></row><row topmarginspacing="2"><entry><BilingualGroup><BilingualItemEn>Nunavut Mining Regulations</BilingualItemEn><BilingualItemFr>Règlement sur l’exploitation minière au Nunavut</BilingualItemFr></BilingualGroup></entry><entry><Provision language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text>sections 33, 60, 61, 62, 63 and 64 of the Regulations</Text></Provision></entry></row><row topmarginspacing="2"><entry><BilingualGroup><BilingualItemEn>On Board Trains Occupational Health and Safety Regulations</BilingualItemEn><BilingualItemFr>Règlement sur la santé et la sécurité au travail (trains)</BilingualItemFr></BilingualGroup></entry><entry><Provision language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text>subsection 12.7(3) of the Regulations</Text></Provision></entry></row><row topmarginspacing="2"><entry><BilingualGroup><BilingualItemEn>Royal Canadian Mounted Police Pension Continuation Regulations</BilingualItemEn><BilingualItemFr>Règlement sur la continuation des pensions de la Gendarmerie royale du Canada</BilingualItemFr></BilingualGroup></entry><entry><Provision language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text>paragraph 9(b), subsection 10(2), sections 13 and 16 and subsection 21(3) of the Regulations</Text></Provision></entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table></TableGroup></Schedule></Schedule></Bill>