<Bill bill-origin="commons" bill-type="private-public" xml:lang="en" date-time="2020-01-27 16:22:11"><Identification><BillNumber>C-211</BillNumber><Parliament><Session>1</Session><Number>43</Number><RegnalYear><Year-s>68-69</Year-s><Monarch>Elizabeth II</Monarch></RegnalYear><Year-s>2019-2020</Year-s></Parliament><LongTitle>An Act to amend the Criminal Code (assaults against health care professionals and first responders)</LongTitle><ShortTitle status="unofficial" /><RunningHead /><BillHistory><Stages stage="first-reading-house"><Date><YYYY>2020</YYYY><MM>2</MM><DD>20</DD></Date></Stages></BillHistory><BillSponsor><Emphasis style="smallcaps">Mr. Doherty</Emphasis></BillSponsor><BillRefNumber date-time="2020-01-27">431013</BillRefNumber></Identification><Introduction><Summary><TitleText>SUMMARY</TitleText><Provision><Text>This enactment amends the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Criminal Code</XRefExternal> to require a court to consider the fact that the victim of an assault is a health care professional or a first responder to be an aggravating circumstance for the purposes of sentencing.</Text></Provision></Summary><Preamble><Provision pointsize="10"><MarginalNote>Preamble</MarginalNote><Text>Whereas there is an increasing number of incidents involving violence against health care professionals and first responders;</Text></Provision><Provision><Text>Whereas assaults on health care professionals and first responders have both a physical and a psychological impact;</Text></Provision><Provision><Text>And whereas health care professionals and first responders, who care for and protect others, deserve to feel protected and valued by the justice system;</Text></Provision></Preamble><Enacts><Provision><Text>Her Majesty, by and with the advice and consent <Keep>of the</Keep> Senate and House of Commons of Canada, <Keep>enacts</Keep> as follows:</Text></Provision></Enacts></Introduction><Body><Heading level="1"><MarginalNote><HistoricalNote>R.S., c. C-46</HistoricalNote></MarginalNote><TitleText>Criminal Code</TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><Label>1</Label><Text>The <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Criminal Code</XRefExternal> is amended by adding the following after section 269.01:</Text><AmendedText><Section change="ins"><MarginalNote>Aggravating circumstance — assault against health care professionals and first responders</MarginalNote><Label>269.02</Label><Text>When a court imposes a sentence for an offence referred to in paragraph 264.1(1)(a) or any of sections 266 to 269, it shall consider as an aggravating circumstance the fact that the victim of the offence was, at the time of the commission of the offence, a health care professional or a first responder engaged in the performance of their duty. </Text></Section></AmendedText></Section></Body></Bill>