<Bill bill-origin="commons" bill-type="private-public" xml:lang="en" date-time="2018-01-18 14:35:25"><Identification><BillNumber>C-225</BillNumber><Parliament><Session>1</Session><Number>43</Number><RegnalYear><Year-s>68-69</Year-s><Monarch>Elizabeth II</Monarch></RegnalYear><Year-s>2019-2020</Year-s></Parliament><LongTitle>An Act to amend the Aeronautics Act, the Fishing and Recreational Harbours Act and other Acts (application of provincial law)</LongTitle><ShortTitle status="unofficial" /><RunningHead>An Act to amend the Aeronautics Act, the Fishing and Recreational Harbours Act and other Acts (application of provincial law)</RunningHead><BillHistory><Stages stage="first-reading-house"><Date><YYYY>2020</YYYY><MM>2</MM><DD>25</DD></Date></Stages></BillHistory><BillSponsor><Emphasis style="smallcaps">Mr. Simard</Emphasis></BillSponsor><BillRefNumber date-time="2018-01-18">431085</BillRefNumber></Identification><Introduction><Summary><TitleText>SUMMARY</TitleText><Provision><Text>This enactment amends certain acts to subordinate the exercise of certain powers to the applicable provincial laws concerning land use and development and environmental protection.</Text></Provision></Summary><Enacts><Provision><Text>Her Majesty, by and with the advice and consent <Keep>of the</Keep> Senate and House of Commons of Canada, <Keep>enacts</Keep> as follows:</Text></Provision></Enacts></Introduction><Body><Heading level="1" type="amending"><MarginalNote><HistoricalNote>R.S., c. A-2</HistoricalNote></MarginalNote><TitleText><XRefExternal reference-type="act">Aeronautics Act</XRefExternal></TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><Label>1</Label><Text>Subsection 3(2) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Aeronautics Act</XRefExternal> is replaced by the following: </Text><AmendedText><Subsection><MarginalNote><DefinedTermEn>Minister</DefinedTermEn> for certain purposes</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Despite the definition <DefinitionRef>Minister</DefinitionRef> in subsection (1), <DefinedTermEn>Minister</DefinedTermEn>, in relation to any matter referred to in paragraph 4.2(1)(n), 4.9<Ins>(1)</Ins>(p), (q) or (r) or 8.7(1)(b), means the Minister of National Defence.</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>2</Label><Text>Subsection 4(1) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><Section><MarginalNote>Application of Part</MarginalNote><Label>4</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Subject to any regulations made pursuant to paragraph 4.9<Ins>(1)</Ins>(w), this Part applies in respect of aeronautics to all persons and to all aeronautical products and other things in Canada, to all persons outside Canada who hold Canadian aviation documents and to all Canadian aircraft and passengers and crew members thereon outside Canada.</Text></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>3</Label><Text>Subsection 4.3(3) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><Subsection><MarginalNote>Deputy may be authorized to make orders</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>The Minister may authorize his deputy to make orders with respect to the matters referred to in paragraph 4.9<Ins>(1)</Ins>(l).</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>4</Label><Text>Section 4.9 of the Act is renumbered as subsection 4.9(1) and is amended by adding the following:</Text><AmendedText><Subsection change="ins"><MarginalNote>Application of provincial law — aerodrome</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Despite any regulation made under subsection (1), an aerodrome may operate in a province only if its operation complies with that province’s laws concerning land use and development and environmental protection.</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>5</Label><Text>Paragraph 6.2(1)(a) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>a regulation made under paragraph 4.9<Ins>(1)</Ins>(l), or a notice issued under section 5.1, that prohibits or restricts the use of any airspace or aerodrome;</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Section><Heading level="1" type="amending"><MarginalNote><HistoricalNote>R.S., c. F-24</HistoricalNote></MarginalNote><TitleText>Fishing and Recreational Harbours Act</TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><Label>6</Label><Text>Section 9 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Fishing and Recreational Harbours Act</XRefExternal> is renumbered as subsection 9(1) and is amended by adding the following:</Text><AmendedText><Subsection change="ins"><MarginalNote>Application of provincial law — projects</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Despite any regulation made under subsection (1), no project shall be undertaken in a province under subsection 5(1) unless it complies with that province’s laws concerning land use and development and environment­al protection.</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Section><Heading level="1" type="amending"><MarginalNote><HistoricalNote>R.S., c. N-4</HistoricalNote></MarginalNote><TitleText>National Capital Act</TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><Label>7</Label><Text>Section 10 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">National Capital Act</XRefExternal> is amended by adding the following after subsection (2):</Text><AmendedText><Subsection change="ins"><MarginalNote>Application of provincial law</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>In the exercise of its powers under subsection (2), the Commission shall not establish development, conservation or improvement plans for the National Capital Region unless the Commission is of the opinion that those plans comply with the laws of Ontario and Quebec concerning land use and development and environmental protection.</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Section><Heading level="1" type="amending"><MarginalNote><HistoricalNote>R.S., c. R-2</HistoricalNote></MarginalNote><TitleText>Radiocommunication Act</TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><Label>8</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The portion of subsection 5(1) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Radiocommunication Act</XRefExternal> before paragraph (a) is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><Section><MarginalNote>Minister's powers</MarginalNote><Label>5</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Subject to <Ins>subsection (1.6) and</Ins> any regulations made under section 6, the Minister may, taking into account all matters that the Minister considers relevant for ensuring the orderly establishment or modification of <Keep>radio</Keep> stations and the orderly development and efficient operation of radiocommunication in Canada,</Text></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Section 5 of the Act is amended by adding the following after subsection (1.5):</Text><AmendedText><Subsection change="ins"><MarginalNote>Application of provincial law</MarginalNote><Label>(1.6)</Label><Text>In exercising the power conferred under paragraph (1)(f), the Minister shall not approve the site on which radio apparatus may be located or the erection of masts, towers or other antenna-supporting structures unless the Minister is satisfied that the laws concerning land use and development and environmental protection of the province in which the site or the construction is located are complied with.</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Subsection></Section><Heading level="1" type="amending"><MarginalNote><HistoricalNote>1991, c. 50; 2001, c. 4, s. 10</HistoricalNote></MarginalNote><TitleText>Federal Real Property and Federal Immovables Act</TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><Label>9</Label><Text>Section 18 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Federal Real Property and Federal Immovables Act</XRefExternal> is amended by adding the following after subsection (6):</Text><AmendedText><Subsection change="ins"><MarginalNote>Application of provincial law</MarginalNote><Label>(7)</Label><Text>A Minister or corporation shall use any federal real property or federal immovable under their administration in a manner that complies with the laws concerning land use and development and environmental protection of the province in which the property is situated.</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Section><Heading level="1" type="amending"><MarginalNote><HistoricalNote>1998, c. 10</HistoricalNote></MarginalNote><TitleText>Canada Marine Act</TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><Label>10</Label><Text>Section 28 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Canada Marine Act</XRefExternal> is amended by adding the following after subsection (4):</Text><AmendedText><Subsection change="ins"><MarginalNote>Application of provincial law</MarginalNote><Label>(4.1)</Label><Text>A port authority shall exercise the powers and engage in the activities set out in its letters patent in compliance with the laws concerning land use and de­velopment and environmental protection of the province in which the port that it operates is situated.</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Section><Heading level="1" type="amending"><MarginalNote><HistoricalNote>2017, c. 20, s. 403</HistoricalNote></MarginalNote><TitleText>Canada Infrastructure Bank Act</TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><Label>11</Label><Text>Section 7 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Canada Infrastructure Bank Act</XRefExternal> is amended by adding the following after subsection (2):</Text><AmendedText><Subsection change="ins"><MarginalNote>Application of provincial law</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>The Bank must not undertake any of the functions referred to in subsection (1) with respect to infrastructure projects unless the Bank is satisfied that those projects comply with the laws concerning land use and development and environmental protection of the provinces involved.</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Section></Body></Bill>