


<Bill bill-origin="commons" bill-type="private-public" xml:lang="en" date-time="2006-03-08 08:43:10"><Identification><BillNumber>C-241</BillNumber><Parliament><Session>1</Session><Number>43</Number><RegnalYear><Year-s>68-69</Year-s><Monarch>Elizabeth II</Monarch></RegnalYear><Year-s>2019-2020</Year-s></Parliament><LongTitle>An Act to amend the Parliament of Canada Act (change of political affiliation)</LongTitle><ShortTitle status="unofficial" /><RunningHead>An Act to amend the Parliament of Canada Act (change of political affiliation)</RunningHead><BillHistory><Stages stage="first-reading-house"><Date><YYYY>2020</YYYY><MM>3</MM><DD>12</DD></Date></Stages></BillHistory><BillSponsor><Emphasis style="smallcaps">Mr. Davies</Emphasis></BillSponsor><BillRefNumber date-time="2006-03-08">431052</BillRefNumber></Identification><Introduction><Summary><TitleText>SUMMARY</TitleText><Provision first-line-indent="0" subsequent-line-indent="0"><Text>This enactment amends the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Parliament of Canada Act</XRefExternal> to provide that a member’s seat in the House of Commons is vacated and a by-election called for that seat if the member, having been elected to the House as a member of a registered party or as an independent, changes parties or becomes a member of a party, as the case may be.</Text></Provision></Summary><Enacts><Provision first-line-indent="0" subsequent-line-indent="0"><Text>Her Majesty, by and with the advice and consent of the Senate and House of Commons of Canada, <Keep>enacts as</Keep> follows:</Text></Provision></Enacts></Introduction><Body><Heading level="1"><MarginalNote><HistoricalNote>R.S., c. P-1</HistoricalNote></MarginalNote><TitleText>Parliament of Canada Act</TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><Label>1</Label><Text>The <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Parliament of Canada Act</XRefExternal> is amended by adding the following after section 27:</Text><AmendedText><Heading level="3" change="ins"><TitleText>Change of Political Affiliation</TitleText></Heading><Section change="ins"><MarginalNote>Seat deemed vacated</MarginalNote><Label>27.1</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Any person holding a seat in the House of Commons who becomes a member of a registered party as defined in subsection 2(1) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Canada Elections Act</XRefExternal> is deemed to have vacated the seat and ceases to be a member of the House if, in the last election, the person was endorsed by another registered party or was not endorsed by a registered party.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Notice</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The leader of the registered party of which the person referred to in subsection (1) has become a member shall, without delay, notify the Speaker of the House of Commons in writing that the person is now a member of that party.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Speaker to address a warrant</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>The Speaker of the House shall, on receipt of the notice referred to in subsection (2), address a warrant of the Speaker to the Chief Electoral Officer for the issue of a writ for the election of a member to fill the vacancy.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Proceedings when Speaker absent</MarginalNote><Label>(4)</Label><Text>If there is no Speaker of the House, if the Speaker is absent from Canada or if the member whose seat is vacated is the Speaker, the leader referred to in subsection (2) shall address the warrant, under their hand and seal, to the Chief Electoral Officer for the issue of a writ for the election of a member to fill the vacancy.</Text></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Section></Body></Bill>