<!--Arbortext, Inc., 1988-2010, v.4002--><Bill bill-origin="commons" bill-type="govt-public" xml:lang="en"><Identification><BillNumber>C-3</BillNumber><Parliament><Session>1</Session><Number>43</Number><RegnalYear><Year-s>68</Year-s><Monarch>Elizabeth II</Monarch></RegnalYear><Year-s>2019-2020</Year-s></Parliament><LongTitle>An Act to amend the Royal Canadian Mounted Police Act and the Canada Border Services Agency Act and to make consequential amendments to other Acts</LongTitle><ShortTitle status="unofficial">An Act to amend the Royal Canadian Mounted Police Act and the Canada Border Services Agency Act and to make consequential amendments to other Acts</ShortTitle><RunningHead>An Act to amend the Royal Canadian Mounted Police Act and the Canada Border Services Agency Act and to make consequential amendments ...</RunningHead><BillHistory><Stages stage="first-reading-house"><Date><YYYY>2020</YYYY><MM>1</MM><DD>27</DD></Date></Stages></BillHistory><BillSponsor>MINISTER OF PUBLIC SAFETY AND EMERGENCY PREPAREDNESS</BillSponsor><BillRefNumber date-time="2020-1-24">90907</BillRefNumber></Identification><Introduction><Recommendation><TitleText>RECOMMENDATION</TitleText><Provision format-ref="section"><Text>Her Excellency the Governor General recommends to the House of Commons the appropriation of public revenue under the circumstances, in the manner and for the purposes set out in a measure entitled “<Emphasis style="italic">An Act to amend the Royal Canadian Mounted Police Act and the Canada Border Services Agency Act and to make consequential amendments to other Acts</Emphasis>”.</Text></Provision></Recommendation><Summary><TitleText>SUMMARY</TitleText><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>This enactment amends the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Royal Canadian Mounted Police Act</XRefExternal> to, among other things, rename the Civilian Review and Complaints Commission for the Royal Canadian Mounted Police as the Public Complaints and Review Commission. It also amends the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Canada Border Services Agency Act</XRefExternal> to, among other things, grant to that Commission powers, duties and functions in relation to the Canada Border Services Agency, including the power to conduct a review of the activities of that Agency and to investigate complaints concerning the conduct of any of that Agency’s officers or employees. It also makes consequential amendments to other Acts.</Text></Provision></Summary><TableOfProvisions label-column-width="2.5"><Heading level="1"><TitleText>TABLE OF PROVISIONS</TitleText></Heading><Heading level="1"><TitleText>An Act to amend the Royal Canadian Mounted Police Act and the Canada Border Services Agency Act and to make consequential amendments to other Acts</TitleText></Heading><Label><Emphasis style="bold">1</Emphasis></Label><Text><XRefExternal reference-type="act">Royal Canadian Mounted Police Act</XRefExternal></Text><Label><Emphasis style="bold">12</Emphasis></Label><Text><XRefExternal reference-type="act">Canada Border Services Agency Act</XRefExternal></Text><Heading level="1"><TitleText>Consequential Amendments</TitleText></Heading><Label><Emphasis style="bold">16</Emphasis></Label><Text><XRefExternal reference-type="act">Access to Information Act</XRefExternal></Text><Label><Emphasis style="bold">18</Emphasis></Label><Text><XRefExternal reference-type="act">Canada Evidence Act</XRefExternal></Text><Label><Emphasis style="bold">19</Emphasis></Label><Text><XRefExternal reference-type="act">Financial Administration Act</XRefExternal></Text><Label><Emphasis style="bold">25</Emphasis></Label><Text><XRefExternal reference-type="act">Security of Information Act</XRefExternal></Text><Label><Emphasis style="bold">27</Emphasis></Label><Text><XRefExternal reference-type="act">Privacy Act</XRefExternal></Text><Label><Emphasis style="bold">29</Emphasis></Label><Text><XRefExternal reference-type="act">Public Sector Compensation Act</XRefExternal></Text><Label><Emphasis style="bold">31</Emphasis></Label><Text><XRefExternal reference-type="act">National Security and Intelligence Committee of Parliamentarians Act</XRefExternal></Text><Label><Emphasis style="bold">34</Emphasis></Label><Text><XRefExternal reference-type="act">National Security and Intelligence Review Agency Act</XRefExternal></Text><Label><Emphasis style="bold">40</Emphasis></Label><Text><XRefExternal reference-type="act">Avoiding Complicity in Mistreatment by Foreign Entities Act</XRefExternal></Text><Heading level="1"><TitleText>Coming into Force</TitleText></Heading><Label><Emphasis style="bold">42</Emphasis></Label><Text>Order in council</Text></TableOfProvisions><Enacts><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>Her Majesty, by and with the advice and consent of the Senate and House of Commons of Canada, enacts as follows:</Text></Provision></Enacts></Introduction><Body><Heading level="1"><MarginalNote><HistoricalNote>R.S., c. R-10</HistoricalNote></MarginalNote><TitleText><XRefExternal reference-type="act">Royal Canadian Mounted Police Act</XRefExternal></TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote><HistoricalNote>2013, c. 18, s. 2(3)</HistoricalNote></MarginalNote><Label>1</Label><Text>The definition <DefinedTermEn>Commission</DefinedTermEn> in subsection 2(1) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Royal Canadian Mounted Police Act</XRefExternal> is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><SectionPiece><Definition><Text><DefinedTermEn>Commission</DefinedTermEn> means the <Ins>Public</Ins> Complaints and Review Commission established by subsection 45.29(1); (<DefinedTermFr>Commission</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Definition></SectionPiece></AmendedText><ExplanatoryNote><TitleText>Royal Canadian Mounted Police Act</TitleText><Label><Emphasis style="italic">Clause 1</Emphasis>:</Label><ExplanatoryText>Existing text of the definition:</ExplanatoryText><ExistingText><SectionPiece><Definition><Text><DefinedTermEn>Commission</DefinedTermEn> means the Civilian Review and Complaints Commission for the Royal Canadian Mounted Police established by subsection 45.29(1); (<DefinedTermFr>Commission</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Definition></SectionPiece></ExistingText></ExplanatoryNote></Section><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote><HistoricalNote>2013, c. 18, s. 35</HistoricalNote></MarginalNote><Label>2</Label><Text>The heading to Part VI of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Heading level="1"><TitleText><Ins>Public</Ins> Complaints and Review Commission</TitleText></Heading></AmendedText><ExplanatoryNote><Label><Emphasis style="italic">Clause 2</Emphasis>:</Label><ExplanatoryText>Existing text of the heading:</ExplanatoryText><ExistingText><Heading level="1"><TitleText>Civilian Review and Complaints Commission For the Royal Canadian Mounted Police</TitleText></Heading></ExistingText></ExplanatoryNote></Section><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote><HistoricalNote>2013, c. 18, s. 35</HistoricalNote></MarginalNote><Label>3</Label><Text>Subsection 45.29(1) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Section><MarginalNote>Establishment</MarginalNote><Label>45.29</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The <Ins>Public</Ins> Complaints and Review Commission is established, consisting of a Chairperson, a Vice-chairperson and not more than <Ins>three</Ins> other members, appointed by the Governor in Council.</Text></Subsection></Section></AmendedText><ExplanatoryNote><Label><Emphasis style="italic">Clause 3</Emphasis>:</Label><ExplanatoryText>Existing text of subsection 45.29(1):</ExplanatoryText><ExistingText><Section><Label>45.29</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The Civilian Review and Complaints Commission for the Royal Canadian Mounted Police is established, consisting of a Chairperson and not more than four other members, one of whom may be a Vice-chairperson, appointed by the Governor in Council.</Text></Subsection></Section></ExistingText></ExplanatoryNote></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>4</Label><Text>Section 45.33 of the Act is renumbered as subsection 45.33(1) and is amended by adding the following:</Text><AmendedText change="ins" include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Subsection><MarginalNote>Royal Canadian Mounted Police Unit</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The officers and employees of the Commission that support the Commission in the exercise of its powers and the performance of its duties and functions under this Part and Parts VII to VII.2 may be referred to as the “Royal Canadian Mounted Police Unit”.</Text></Subsection></AmendedText><ExplanatoryNote><Label><Emphasis style="italic">Clause 4</Emphasis>:</Label><ExplanatoryText>New.</ExplanatoryText></ExplanatoryNote></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>5</Label><Text>Section 45.34 of the Act is amended by adding the following after subsection (5):</Text><AmendedText change="ins" include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Subsection><MarginalNote>Summary of report</MarginalNote><Label>(6)</Label><Text>The Commission shall make public a summary of the report.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Opportunity to make comments</MarginalNote><Label>(7)</Label><Text>Before making the summary public, the Commission shall give the Commissioner an opportunity to submit comments on the findings and recommendations included in the report. The Commission shall make any comments that the Commissioner submits public at the same time as it makes the summary public.</Text></Subsection></AmendedText><ExplanatoryNote><Label><Emphasis style="italic">Clause 5</Emphasis>:</Label><ExplanatoryText>New.</ExplanatoryText></ExplanatoryNote></Section><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote><HistoricalNote>2013, c. 18, s. 35</HistoricalNote></MarginalNote><Label>6</Label><Text>Section 45.37 of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Section><MarginalNote>Service standards respecting time limits</MarginalNote><Label>45.37</Label><Subsection><Label><Ins>(1)</Ins></Label><Text>The Commission <Ins>and the Force</Ins> shall <Ins>jointly</Ins> establish service standards respecting the time limits within which <Ins>reviews under section 45.34 or 45.35 are to be conducted and the time limits within which each of them</Ins> is to deal with complaints <Ins>made under this Act</Ins> and specifying the circumstances under which those time limits do not apply or the circumstances under which they may be extended. <Ins>The Commission shall publish on its Internet site those service standards that are related to communications with complainants</Ins>.</Text></Subsection><Subsection change="ins"><MarginalNote>Regulations</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The Governor in Council may make regulations respecting the establishing of the service standards.</Text></Subsection></Section></AmendedText><ExplanatoryNote><Label><Emphasis style="italic">Clause 6</Emphasis>:</Label><ExplanatoryText>Existing text of section 45.37:</ExplanatoryText><ExistingText><Section><Label>45.37</Label><Text>The Commission shall establish, and make public, service standards respecting the time limits within which it is to deal with complaints and specifying the circumstances under which those time limits do not apply or the circumstances under which they may be extended.</Text></Section></ExistingText></ExplanatoryNote></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>7</Label><Text>The Act is amended by adding the following after section 45.48:</Text><AmendedText change="ins" include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Section><MarginalNote>Use of information</MarginalNote><Label>45.481</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Despite any provision in this Act or the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Canada Border Services Agency Act</XRefExternal>, but subject to subsection (2), a member, officer or employee of the <Keep svc="1">Commission,</Keep> with the approval of the Chairperson, may, in the exercise of their powers or the performance of their duties and functions under that Act,</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>use information obtained by the Commission under this Act relating to a complaint if</Text><Subparagraph><Label>(i)</Label><Text>the information relates to a particular event or series of events that involved one or more members and one or more officers or <DefinitionRef>employees</DefinitionRef>, as defined in subsection 16(1) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Canada Border Services Agency Act</XRefExternal>, of the Canada Border Services Agency,</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph><Label>(ii)</Label><Text>the information is relevant and necessary to deal with a complaint made under section 33 or 39 of that Act that relates to the event or series of events or to initiate a complaint under section 39 of that Act that relates to the event or series of events, and</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph><Label>(iii)</Label><Text>the information is used solely for the purpose of dealing with the complaint or initiating the complaint; and</Text></Subparagraph></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>use information obtained by the Commission under a review conducted under section 45.34 or 45.35 of any activity that was, is or may be performed by the Force if</Text><Subparagraph><Label>(i)</Label><Text>the information is relevant and necessary to the conduct of a review under section 18 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Canada Border Services Agency Act</XRefExternal> of any similar activity that was, is or may be performed by the Canada Border Services Agency, and</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph><Label>(ii)</Label><Text>the information is used solely for the purposes of the review referred to in subparagraph (i).</Text></Subparagraph></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Opportunity to make representations</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>If the information is privileged information that was obtained from the Force, no member, officer or employee of the Commission may use the information without having first given the Commissioner an opportunity to make representations.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Regulations</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>The Governor in Council may make regulations respecting the use of information under subsection (1).</Text></Subsection></Section></AmendedText><ExplanatoryNote><Label><Emphasis style="italic">Clause 7</Emphasis>:</Label><ExplanatoryText>New.</ExplanatoryText></ExplanatoryNote></Section><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote><HistoricalNote>2013, c. 18, s. 35</HistoricalNote></MarginalNote><Label>8</Label><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Paragraph 45.49(1)(b) of the French version of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no" xml:lang="fr"><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>b)</Label><Text>la fixation du quorum pour l’exercice <Ins>de ses</Ins> fonctions;</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText><ExplanatoryNote><Label><Emphasis style="italic">Clause 8</Emphasis>: (1) and (2)</Label><ExplanatoryText>Relevant portion of subsection 45.49(1):</ExplanatoryText><ExistingText><Section><Label>45.49</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Subject to the provisions of this Act and the regulations, the Commission may make rules respecting</Text><Paragraph><Label>...</Label><Text> </Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>the fixing of the quorum for the performance of its duties and functions;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>...</Label><Text> </Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(e)</Label><Text>the performance of the duties and functions of the Commission under this Act generally.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection></Section></ExistingText></ExplanatoryNote></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><MarginalNote><HistoricalNote>2013, c. 18, s. 35</HistoricalNote></MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Paragraph 45.49(1)(e) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(e)</Label><Text>the performance of the duties and functions of the Commission generally.</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection></Section><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote><HistoricalNote>2013, c. 18, s. 35</HistoricalNote></MarginalNote><Label>9</Label><Text>Subsection 45.51(1) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Section><MarginalNote>Special reports</MarginalNote><Label>45.51</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The Commission may, on the request of the Minister or on its own initiative, provide the Minister <Ins>and the Commissioner</Ins> with a special report concerning any matter that relates to its powers, duties and functions under this Act. <Ins>If it does so, it shall also provide them with a summary of the special report</Ins>.</Text></Subsection><Subsection change="ins"><MarginalNote>Summary to be made public</MarginalNote><Label>(1.1)</Label><Text>The Commission shall make the summary of the special report public after at least 15 days have elapsed after the later of the day the summary was provided to the Minister and to the Commissioner.</Text></Subsection></Section></AmendedText><ExplanatoryNote><Label><Emphasis style="italic">Clause 9</Emphasis>:</Label><ExplanatoryText>Existing text of subsection 45.51(1):</ExplanatoryText><ExistingText><Section><Label>45.51</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The Commission may, on the request of the Minister or on its own initiative, provide the Minister with a special report concerning any matter that relates to its powers, duties and functions under this Act.</Text></Subsection></Section></ExistingText></ExplanatoryNote></Section><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote><HistoricalNote>2013, c. 18, s. 35</HistoricalNote></MarginalNote><Label>10</Label><Text>Subsection 45.52(1) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Section><MarginalNote>Annual report</MarginalNote><Label>45.52</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The Chairperson shall, within three months after the end of each fiscal year, submit to the Minister a report of the activities of the Commission <Ins>under this Act and the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Canada Border Services Agency Act</XRefExternal></Ins> during that year, and its recommendations, if any. The Minister shall cause a copy of the report to be tabled in each House of Parliament on any of the first 15 days on which that House is sitting after the day on which the Minister receives the report.</Text></Subsection><Subsection change="ins"><MarginalNote>Contents — <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Canada Border Services Agency Act</XRefExternal></MarginalNote><Label>(1.1)</Label><Text>The report referred to in subsection (1) must</Text><Paragraph change="ins"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>contain information respecting the Commission’s performance in relation to the service standards established under section 21 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Canada Border Services Agency Act</XRefExternal>;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph change="ins"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>set out the number of complaints made under that Act by persons detained by the Canada Border Services Agency and a summary of the nature, status and disposition of those complaints;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph change="ins"><Label>(c)</Label><Text>to the extent known by the Chairperson, set out the number of complaints made by persons who are or have been detained on behalf of the Agency under an agreement or arrangement referred to in subsection 13(3) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Canada Border Services Agency Act</XRefExternal> and who have made a complaint respecting their treatment during detention — or their conditions of detention — and a summary of the nature, status and disposition of those complaints; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph change="ins"><Label>(d)</Label><Text>set out the number of <DefinitionRef>serious incidents</DefinitionRef>, as defined in subsection 58(1) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Canada Border Services Agency Act</XRefExternal>, that the Commission was notified of under section 59 of that Act and contain information concerning their type, the provinces in which they are alleged to have occurred and whether charges were laid in respect of them.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection></Section></AmendedText><ExplanatoryNote><Label><Emphasis style="italic">Clause 10</Emphasis>:</Label><ExplanatoryText>Existing text of subsection 45.52(1):</ExplanatoryText><ExistingText><Section><Label>45.52</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The Chairperson shall, within three months after the end of each fiscal year, submit to the Minister a report of the activities of the Commission during that year and its recommendations, if any. The Minister shall cause a copy of the report to be tabled in each House of Parliament on any of the first 15 days on which that House is sitting after the day on which the Minister receives the report.</Text></Subsection></Section></ExistingText></ExplanatoryNote></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>11</Label><Text>The Act is amended by adding the following after section 45.57:</Text><AmendedText change="ins" include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Heading level="2"><TitleText>Records of Complaints</TitleText></Heading></AmendedText><ExplanatoryNote><Label><Emphasis style="italic">Clause 11</Emphasis>:</Label><ExplanatoryText>New.</ExplanatoryText></ExplanatoryNote></Section><Heading level="1"><MarginalNote><HistoricalNote>2005, c. 38</HistoricalNote></MarginalNote><TitleText><XRefExternal reference-type="act">Canada Border Services Agency Act</XRefExternal></TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><Label>12</Label><Text>The <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Canada Border Services Agency Act</XRefExternal> is amended by adding the following after section 1:</Text><AmendedText change="ins" include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Heading level="1"><Label>PART 1</Label><TitleText>Canada Border Services Agency</TitleText></Heading></AmendedText><ExplanatoryNote><TitleText>Canada Border Services Agency Act</TitleText><Label><Emphasis style="italic">Clause 12</Emphasis>:</Label><ExplanatoryText>New.</ExplanatoryText></ExplanatoryNote></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>13</Label><Text>The portion of section 2 of the Act before the definition <DefinitionRef>Agency</DefinitionRef> is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Section><MarginalNote>Definitions</MarginalNote><Label>2</Label><Text>The following definitions apply in this <Ins>Part</Ins>.</Text></Section></AmendedText><ExplanatoryNote><Label><Emphasis style="italic">Clause 13</Emphasis>:</Label><ExplanatoryText>Relevant portion of section 2:</ExplanatoryText><ExistingText><Section><Label>2</Label><Text>The following definitions apply in this Act.</Text></Section></ExistingText></ExplanatoryNote></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>14</Label><Text>Section 13 of the Act is amended by adding the following after subsection (2):</Text><AmendedText change="ins" include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Subsection><MarginalNote>Restriction</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>The Agency may enter into an agreement or arrangement with the government of a province respecting the detention of persons on behalf of the Agency only if the Minister is of the opinion that there is in the province an independent individual or body that is empowered to receive and deal with complaints about the treatment and conditions of detention of detained persons.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Exception</MarginalNote><Label>(4)</Label><Text>If the Minister is of the opinion that there is an urgent need to provide for the detention of persons on a temporary basis, the Agency may, with the approval of the Minister, enter into an agreement or arrangement referred to in subsection (3) with the government of a province even if the Minister is of the opinion that there is no independent individual or body referred to in that subsection in the province.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Duty to provide information</MarginalNote><Label>(5)</Label><Text>If the Agency is notified that a person who is or has been detained on behalf of the Agency under an agreement or arrangement referred to in subsection (3) has made a complaint respecting their treatment during detention — or their conditions of detention — to any competent authority in the province where they are or were detained, the Agency shall, as soon as feasible, provide the <DefinitionRef>Commission</DefinitionRef>, as defined in subsection 16(1), with all of the information that the Agency has received or receives in relation to the complaint.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Duty to provide copy</MarginalNote><Label>(6)</Label><Text>If the Agency enters into an agreement or arrangement respecting the monitoring of the treatment and of the conditions of detention of persons detained by or on behalf of the Agency or the inspection of any facility where persons are detained by or on behalf of the Agency, the Agency shall, as soon as feasible, provide the <DefinitionRef>Commission</DefinitionRef>, as defined in subsection 16(1), with a copy of every document containing findings or recommendations that it receives under that agreement or arrangement.</Text></Subsection></AmendedText><ExplanatoryNote><Label><Emphasis style="italic">Clause 14</Emphasis>:</Label><ExplanatoryText>New.</ExplanatoryText></ExplanatoryNote></Section><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote><HistoricalNote>2005, c. 38, ss. 144(1) to (3), par. (8)(a)(E) and (b)(E)</HistoricalNote></MarginalNote><Label>15</Label><Text>The headings before section 16 and sections 16 to 147 of the Act are replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Heading change="ins" level="1"><Label>PART 2</Label><TitleText>Public Complaints and Review Commission</TitleText></Heading><Heading change="ins" level="2"><TitleText>Interpretation</TitleText></Heading><Section change="ins"><MarginalNote>Definitions</MarginalNote><Label>16</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The following definitions apply in this Part.</Text><Definition><Text><DefinedTermEn>Agency</DefinedTermEn> has the same meaning as in section 2. (<DefinedTermFr>Agence</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Definition><Definition><Text><DefinedTermEn>Commission</DefinedTermEn> means the Public Complaints and Review Commission established by subsection 45.29(1) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Royal Canadian Mounted Police Act</XRefExternal>. (<DefinedTermFr>Commission</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Definition><Definition><Text><DefinedTermEn>employee</DefinedTermEn>, in relation to the Agency, includes any person who assists the Agency in the exercise of any of its powers or the performance of any of its duties and functions under Part 1, other than a person who assists the Agency by reason only of an agreement or arrangement referred to in subsection 13(3). (<DefinedTermFr>employé</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Definition><Definition><Text><DefinedTermEn>Minister</DefinedTermEn> has the same meaning as in section 2. (<DefinedTermFr>ministre</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Definition><Definition><Text><DefinedTermEn>program legislation</DefinedTermEn> has the same meaning as in section 2. (<DefinedTermFr>législation frontalière</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Definition></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Designation under subsection 9(2)</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Every person designated under subsection 9(2) is an officer or employee of the Agency for the purposes of this Part and, when that person is exercising any power or performing any duty or function by reason of the designation, that person is deemed to be exercising a power or performing a duty or function under Part 1.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Complaints regarding level of service</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>For the purposes of section <XRefInternal>33</XRefInternal> and <XRefInternal>39</XRefInternal>, the taking of, or the failure to take, a decision in relation to the level of any service provided by the Agency by a person who, at the time the decision was taken, or not taken, as the case may be, was an officer or employee of the Agency is deemed to be conduct by the person in the exercise of a power or the performance of a duty or function under Part 1.</Text></Subsection></Section><Heading change="ins" level="2"><TitleText>Powers, Duties and Functions</TitleText></Heading><Section change="ins"><MarginalNote>Powers, duties and functions of Commission</MarginalNote><Label>17</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The Commission shall exercise the powers and perform the duties and functions that are assigned to it under this Part.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Canada Border Services Agency Unit</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The officers and employees of the Commission that support the Commission in the exercise of its powers and the performance of its duties and functions under this Part may be referred to as the “Canada Border Services Agency Unit”.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section change="ins"><MarginalNote>Review and report</MarginalNote><Label>18</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>For the purpose of ensuring that the activities of the Agency are carried out in accordance with Part 1, with any ministerial directions made under that Part and with any policy, procedure or guideline relating to the operation of the Agency, the Commission may, on the request of the Minister or on its own initiative, conduct a review of specified activities of the Agency and provide a report to the Minister and the President of the Agency on the review.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Conditions</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>In order to conduct a review on its own initiative, the Commission</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>must be satisfied that sufficient resources exist for conducting the review and that the handling of complaints under this Part will not be compromised; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>must have taken reasonable steps to verify that no other review or inquiry has been undertaken on substantially the same issue by a federal or provincial entity.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Notice</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>Before conducting a review on its own initiative, the Commission shall give a notice to the Minister indicating that it is satisfied that the conditions referred to in subsection (2) have been met and setting out the rationale for conducting the review.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Policies, procedures and guidelines</MarginalNote><Label>(4)</Label><Text>The Commission shall include in the report any findings and recommendations that it sees fit regarding the adequacy, appropriateness, sufficiency or clarity of any policy, procedure or guideline relating to the operation of the Agency.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Summary of report</MarginalNote><Label>(5)</Label><Text>The Commission shall make public a summary of the report.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Opportunity to make comments</MarginalNote><Label>(6)</Label><Text>Before making the summary public, the Commission shall give the President of the Agency an opportunity to submit comments on the findings and recommendations included in the report. The Commission shall make any comments that the President submits public at the same time as it makes the summary public.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section change="ins"><MarginalNote>National security</MarginalNote><Label>19</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The Commission does not have jurisdiction to conduct a review of an activity that is related to national security.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Referral</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The Commission shall refer to the National Security and Intelligence Review Agency any matter related to national security arising from a request for a review under section <XRefInternal>18</XRefInternal>.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section change="ins"><MarginalNote>Powers</MarginalNote><Label>20</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The Commission has, when conducting a review under section <XRefInternal>18</XRefInternal>, all of the powers of the Commission under paragraphs <XRefInternal>45</XRefInternal>(1)(a) to (d).</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Application</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Subsections <XRefInternal>45</XRefInternal>(2) to (5) apply, with any necessary modifications, to the exercise of the powers by the Commission under subsection (1).</Text></Subsection></Section><Section change="ins"><MarginalNote>Service standards respecting time limits</MarginalNote><Label>21</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The Commission and the Agency shall jointly establish service standards respecting the time limits within which reviews under section <XRefInternal>18</XRefInternal> are to be conducted and the time limits within which each of them is to deal with complaints made under this Part, and specifying the circumstances under which those time limits do not apply or the circumstances under which they may be extended. The Commission shall publish on its Internet site those service standards that are related to communications with complainants.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Regulations</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The Governor in Council may make regulations respecting the establishment of the service standards.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section change="ins"><MarginalNote>Education and information</MarginalNote><Label>22</Label><Text>The Commission shall implement education and information programs to make its mandate under this Part better known to persons who interact with officers or <Keep svc="1">employees</Keep> of the Agency, including those who are detained by or on behalf of the Agency.</Text></Section><Heading change="ins" level="2"><TitleText>Information Provisions</TitleText></Heading><Section change="ins"><MarginalNote>Right of access — reviews</MarginalNote><Label>23</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Despite any other Act of Parliament and subject to section <XRefInternal>26</XRefInternal>, the Commission is entitled, in relation to a review conducted under section <XRefInternal>18</XRefInternal>, to have access in a timely manner to any information in the possession or under the control of the Agency that the Commission considers relevant to the review.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Protected information</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Under subsection (1), the Commission is entitled to have access to information that is subject to any privilege under the law of evidence, to solicitor-client privilege or the professional secrecy of advocates and notaries or to litigation privilege.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>For greater certainty</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>For greater certainty, the disclosure to the Commission under this section of any information that is subject to solicitor-client privilege or the professional secrecy of advocates and notaries or to litigation privilege does not constitute a waiver of those privileges or that secrecy.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section change="ins"><MarginalNote>Right of access — complaints</MarginalNote><Label>24</Label><Text>Despite any other Act of Parliament and any privilege under the law of evidence and subject to section <XRefInternal>26</XRefInternal>, the Commission is entitled, in relation to a complaint made under section <XRefInternal>33</XRefInternal> or <XRefInternal>39</XRefInternal>, to have access in a timely manner to any information in the possession or under the control of the Agency that the Commission considers relevant to the complaint.</Text></Section><Section change="ins"><MarginalNote>Documents and explanations</MarginalNote><Label>25</Label><Text>Under sections <XRefInternal>23</XRefInternal> and <XRefInternal>24</XRefInternal>, the Commission is entitled to receive from the officers and employees of the Agency any documents and explanations that the Commission considers necessary for the exercise of its powers and the performance of its duties and functions under this Part.</Text></Section><Section change="ins"><MarginalNote>Exception</MarginalNote><Label>26</Label><Text>The Commission is not entitled to have access to</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>a confidence of the Queen’s Privy Council for Canada the disclosure of which could be refused under section 39 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Canada Evidence Act</XRefExternal>; or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>commercial information that Canada has committed under an international agreement to keeping confidential.</Text></Paragraph></Section><Section change="ins"><MarginalNote>Disclosure prohibited</MarginalNote><Label>27</Label><Text>A current or former member, officer or employee of the Commission, or any person who is acting or has acted on the Commission’s behalf, may disclose information that they obtained or to which they had access in the course of exercising their powers or performing their duties and functions under this Part only for the purpose of exercising their powers or performing their duties and functions under this Part or as authorized or required by any other law.</Text></Section><Section change="ins"><MarginalNote>Protection of confidential information</MarginalNote><Label>28</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The Commission shall, when preparing an annual report referred to in section 45.52 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Royal Canadian Mounted Police Act</XRefExternal>, a summary referred to in subsection <XRefInternal>18</XRefInternal>(5) or <XRefInternal>32</XRefInternal>(1) or a report referred to in subsection <XRefInternal>51</XRefInternal>(2), <XRefInternal>52</XRefInternal>(2) or <XRefInternal>55</XRefInternal>(3), take the steps that it considers necessary to ensure that the report or summary does not contain</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>information referred to in subsection (2) the disclosure of which would be injurious to national security, national defence or international relations or would compromise or seriously hinder the administration or enforcement of program legislation or the investigation or prosecution of any offence; or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>information referred to in subsection (2) that is subject to solicitor-client privilege or the professional secrecy of advocates and notaries or to litigation privilege.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Description of information</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The information described in subsection (1) is any information that the Commission obtained — or is created from information that it obtained — under this Part.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section change="ins"><MarginalNote>Safeguards — third party</MarginalNote><Label>29</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The Commission shall not disclose information that it has received from the Agency under this Part to any person or entity other than a member, employee or officer of the Commission or a person acting on its behalf unless the Chairperson of the Commission is satisfied that</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>the person or entity will take reasonable measures to protect that information;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>the person or entity will require all of its members, employees, officers and other persons acting on its behalf to meet requirements that are equivalent to the requirements referred to in section 45.45 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Royal Canadian Mounted Police Act</XRefExternal>; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(c)</Label><Text>the person or entity has agreed to any measures that would assist the Commission to verify compliance with the obligations described in paragraphs (a) and (b), which may include agreeing to permit the Commission to enter and inspect the premises of the person or entity and any information storage facilities and to provide any information or documents requested by the Commission.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Regulations</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The Governor in Council may make regulations respecting the disclosure by the Commission of information that it has received from the Agency under this Part to persons or entities other than a member, employee or officer of the Commission or a person acting on its behalf and the measures that the persons or entities receiving the information are to take to protect the information.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Duty to comply</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>Every person who has received information under this section shall comply with the regulations made under subsection (2).</Text></Subsection></Section><Section change="ins"><MarginalNote>Use of information</MarginalNote><Label>30</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Despite any provision in this Act or the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Royal Canadian Mounted Police Act</XRefExternal>, a member, officer or employee of the Commission, with the approval of the Chairperson of the Commission, may, in the exercise of their powers or the performance of their duties and functions under that Act,</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>use information obtained by the Commission under this Act relating to a complaint if</Text><Subparagraph><Label>(i)</Label><Text>the information relates to a particular event or series of events that involved one or more officers or employees of the Agency and one or more <DefinitionRef>members</DefinitionRef>, as defined in subsection 2(1) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Royal Canadian Mounted Police Act</XRefExternal>,</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph><Label>(ii)</Label><Text>the information is relevant and necessary to deal with a complaint made under section 45.53 or 45.59 of that Act that relates to the event or series of events or to initiate a complaint under section 45.59 of that Act that relates to the event or series of events, and</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph><Label>(iii)</Label><Text>the information is used solely for the purpose of dealing with the complaint or initiating the complaint; and</Text></Subparagraph></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>use information obtained by the Commission under a review conducted under section <XRefInternal>18</XRefInternal> of any activity that was, is or may be performed by the Agency if</Text><Subparagraph><Label>(i)</Label><Text>the information is relevant and necessary to the conduct of a review under section 45.34 or 45.35 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Royal Canadian Mounted Police Act</XRefExternal> of any similar activity that was, is or may be performed by the <DefinitionRef>Force</DefinitionRef>, as defined in subsection 2(1) of that Act; and</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph><Label>(ii)</Label><Text>the information is used solely for the purposes of the review referred to in subparagraph (i).</Text></Subparagraph></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Regulations</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The Governor in Council may make regulations respecting the use of information under subsection (1).</Text></Subsection></Section><Heading change="ins" level="2"><TitleText>Immunity</TitleText></Heading><Section change="ins"><MarginalNote>Immunity from criminal, civil or administrative actions or proceedings</MarginalNote><Label>31</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>No criminal, civil or administrative action or proceeding lies against the members, officers or employees of the Commission, or any person acting on behalf or under the direction of the Commission, for anything done, reported or said in good faith in the exercise or purported exercise of any of their powers, or the performance or purported performance of any of their duties or functions, under this Part.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>No summons</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>A member, officer or employee of the Commission, or any person acting on behalf or under the direction of the Commission, is not a competent or compellable witness, in respect of any matter coming to the knowledge of the Commission or that person as a result of the exercise of any of their powers or the performance of any of their duties or functions under this Part, in any proceeding other than a prosecution for an offence under this Part, a prosecution for an offence under the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Security of Information Act</XRefExternal> or a prosecution for an offence under section 132 or 136 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Criminal Code</XRefExternal>.</Text></Subsection></Section><Heading change="ins" level="2"><TitleText>Reporting</TitleText></Heading><Section change="ins"><MarginalNote>Special report and summary</MarginalNote><Label>32</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The Commission may, on the request of the Minister or on its own initiative, provide the Minister and the President of the Agency with a special report concerning any matter that relates to the Commission’s powers, <Keep svc="1">duties</Keep> and functions under this Part. If it does so, it shall also provide them with a summary of the special report.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Summary to be made public</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The Commission shall make the summary of the special report public after at least 15 days have elapsed after the later of the day the summary was provided to the Minister and to the President of the Agency.</Text></Subsection></Section><Heading change="ins" level="2"><TitleText>Complaints</TitleText></Heading><Section change="ins"><MarginalNote>Complaints</MarginalNote><Label>33</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Any individual may make a complaint concerning the conduct, in the exercise of any power or the performance of any duty or function under Part 1, of any person who, at the time that the conduct is alleged to have occurred, was an officer or employee of the Agency.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Right to refuse to deal with complaint</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The Commission may refuse to deal with the complaint if, in its opinion,</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>the complaint is trivial, frivolous, vexatious or made in bad faith; or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>the complaint is from an individual who</Text><Subparagraph><Label>(i)</Label><Text>is not the individual at whom the conduct was directed,</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph><Label>(ii)</Label><Text>is neither the guardian, tutor, curator or mandatary — under a protection mandate — of the individual at whom the conduct was directed nor a person who is appointed to act in a similar capacity on behalf of the individual,</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph><Label>(iii)</Label><Text>did not see or hear the conduct or its effects as a result of not being physically present at the time and place that the conduct or its effects occurred,</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph><Label>(iv)</Label><Text>has not been given written permission to make the complaint from the individual at whom the conduct was directed, or</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph><Label>(v)</Label><Text>has not suffered loss, damage, distress, danger or inconvenience as a result of the conduct.</Text></Subparagraph></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Duty to refuse to deal with complaints</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>The Commission shall refuse to deal with the complaint if, in its opinion,</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>the complaint has been or could have been adequately dealt with, or could more appropriately be dealt with, according to a procedure provided for <Keep svc="1">under</Keep> any Act of Parliament — other than this Act — or any Act of the legislature of a province;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>the complaint relates to a disciplinary measure taken, or not taken, by the President of the Agency; or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(c)</Label><Text>dealing with the complaint would compromise or seriously hinder the administration or enforcement of program legislation or the investigation or prosecution of any offence.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>National security</MarginalNote><Label>(4)</Label><Text>The Commission shall refuse to deal with a complaint concerning an activity that is closely related to national security and shall refer such a complaint to the National Security and Intelligence Review Agency.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Notice to complainant and President</MarginalNote><Label>(5)</Label><Text>Subject to subsection (6), if the Commission refuses to deal with a complaint, it shall give notice in writing of the refusal and the reasons for it to the complainant and the President of the Agency. If the reason for the refusal is that the complaint could more appropriately be dealt with according to a procedure provided for under any Act of Parliament — other than this Act — or any Act of the legislature of a province, the notice given to the complainant shall identify that procedure.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Notice — application of subsection (4)</MarginalNote><Label>(6)</Label><Text>If the Commission refuses to deal with a complaint under subsection (4), it shall give to the President of the Agency, and then to the complainant, notice in writing of the refusal to deal with the complaint and of the referral made under that subsection.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Notice to officer or employee</MarginalNote><Label>(7)</Label><Text>After receiving the notice, the President of the Agency shall notify the officer or employee whose conduct is the subject matter of the complaint of the refusal to deal with the complaint and, if applicable, of the referral made under subsection (4).</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Time limit</MarginalNote><Label>(8)</Label><Text>The complaint must be made within one year after the day on which the conduct is alleged to have occurred or any longer period permitted under subsection (9).</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Extension of time limit</MarginalNote><Label>(9)</Label><Text>The Commission or the President of the Agency may extend the time limit for making the complaint if the Commission or the President, as the case may be, is of the opinion that there are good reasons for doing so and that it is not contrary to the public interest.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Notice</MarginalNote><Label>(10)</Label><Text>If the complaint is made more than one year after the day on which the conduct is alleged to have occurred and the President of the Agency does not extend the time limit for the making of the complaint, he or she shall so notify the complainant and the Commission.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Reception of complaint</MarginalNote><Label>(11)</Label><Text>The complaint must be made to the Commission or any officer or employee of the Agency.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Assistance</MarginalNote><Label>(12)</Label><Text>The Commission shall, on the request of an individual who wishes to make a complaint, arrange for the provision of assistance to that individual in making the complaint.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Acknowledgement and notification</MarginalNote><Label>(13)</Label><Text>As soon as feasible after the Commission or an officer or employee of the Agency receives a complaint, the Commission or an officer or employee of the Agency, as the case may be, shall acknowledge the complaint in writing to the complainant and shall provide written notice of the complaint to the President of the Agency. If the complaint is received by an officer or employee of the Agency, an officer or employee of the Agency shall also provide written notice of the complaint to the Commission.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section change="ins"><MarginalNote>Notice to officer or employee</MarginalNote><Label>34</Label><Text>As soon as feasible after being notified of a complaint, the President of the Agency shall notify in writing the officer or employee whose conduct is the subject matter of the complaint of the substance of the complaint unless, in the President’s opinion, to do so might compromise or hinder any investigation that is being or may be carried out in respect of the complaint.</Text></Section><Heading change="ins" level="2"><TitleText>Withdrawal of Complaints</TitleText></Heading><Section change="ins"><MarginalNote>Withdrawal</MarginalNote><Label>35</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>A complainant may withdraw a complaint at any time by sending a written notice to the Commission or the President of the Agency.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Assistance</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The Commission shall, on the request of an individual who wishes to withdraw a complaint, arrange for the provision of assistance to that individual in withdrawing the complaint.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Notice of withdrawal</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>As soon as feasible after the Commission or the President of the Agency receives a notice that a complaint has been withdrawn, they shall give written notice of the withdrawal to the other.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Notice to officer or employee or other person</MarginalNote><Label>(4)</Label><Text>When the President of the Agency receives a notice referred to in subsection (1) or (3), he or she shall notify in writing the officer or employee whose conduct is the subject matter of the complaint that the complaint has been withdrawn.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Investigation or hearing into withdrawn complaint</MarginalNote><Label>(5)</Label><Text>Despite the withdrawal of the complaint, the complaint may be the subject of an investigation, review or hearing conducted under this Part.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Preservation of evidence</MarginalNote><Label>(6)</Label><Text>The President of the Agency shall ensure the protection and preservation of any evidence relating to a withdrawn complaint.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Regulations</MarginalNote><Label>(7)</Label><Text>The Governor in Council may make regulations respecting the period during which the evidence is to be protected and preserved.</Text></Subsection></Section><Heading change="ins" level="2"><TitleText>Informal Resolution of Complaints</TitleText></Heading><Section change="ins"><MarginalNote>Informal resolution</MarginalNote><Label>36</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>As soon as feasible after receiving or being notified of a complaint, the President of the Agency shall consider whether the complaint can be resolved informally and, with the consent of the complainant and the officer or employee whose conduct is the subject matter of the complaint, may attempt to resolve it informally.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Inadmissibility</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>An answer or statement made in the course of attempting to resolve a complaint informally, by the complainant or the officer or employee whose conduct is the subject matter of the complaint, may be used or received against that person only in</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>a prosecution under section 132 or 136 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Criminal Code</XRefExternal>; or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>a civil or administrative proceeding regarding an allegation that, with intent to mislead, the person gave the answer or statement knowing it to be false.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Agreement to informal resolution in writing</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>The terms of every informal resolution of a complaint, as well as the agreement of the complainant and the officer or employee whose conduct is the subject matter of the complaint to those terms, must be signified in writing. A copy of everything so signified in writing is to be provided to the Commission.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Regulations</MarginalNote><Label>(4)</Label><Text>The Governor in Council may make regulations prescribing categories of complaints that are not to be resolved informally by the President of the Agency.</Text></Subsection><Subsection change="ins"><MarginalNote>Clarification</MarginalNote><Label>(5)</Label><Text>For greater certainty, nothing in this section prevents the Commission from informally resolving a complaint of which it is seized under this Part and, if the Commission attempts to informally resolve such a complaint, subsection (2) applies.</Text></Subsection></Section><Heading change="ins" level="2"><TitleText>Representations</TitleText></Heading><Section change="ins"><MarginalNote>Right to make representations</MarginalNote><Label>37</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>If a complaint is made under this Part with respect to the conduct of an officer or employee, the following persons shall be given an opportunity to make representations with respect to that conduct’s impact on them or the individual at whom the conduct was directed:</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>the complainant;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>the guardian, tutor, curator or mandatary — under a protection mandate — of the individual at whom the conduct was directed or a person who is appointed to act in a similar capacity on behalf of the individual; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(c)</Label><Text>an individual who has written permission to make the representations from the individual at whom the conduct was directed.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Disclosure</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Representations, including any personal information contained in them, received by the Commission in relation to the complaint must be disclosed as soon as feasible to the Agency.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Regulations</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>The Governor in Council may make regulations respecting the making of representations under subsection (1).</Text></Subsection></Section><Heading change="ins" level="2"><TitleText>Records of Complaints</TitleText></Heading><Section change="ins"><MarginalNote>Duty to establish and maintain</MarginalNote><Label>38</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The President of the Agency and the Commission shall establish and maintain a record of all complaints they receive or for which they are provided notice under this Part, including those that are resolved informally and those that are withdrawn by the complainant.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Making record available</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The President of the Agency shall, on request, make available to the Commission any information contained in a record maintained by the President under subsection (1), other than information described in paragraph <XRefInternal>26</XRefInternal>(a) or (b) and information that is subject to solicitor-client privilege or the professional secrecy of advocates and notaries or to litigation privilege.</Text></Subsection></Section><Heading change="ins" level="2"><TitleText>Chairperson-initiated Complaints</TitleText></Heading><Section change="ins"><MarginalNote>Complaints initiated by Chairperson</MarginalNote><Label>39</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>If the Chairperson of the Commission is satisfied that there are reasonable grounds to investigate the conduct, in the exercise of any power or the performance of any duty or function under Part 1, of any person who, at the time that the conduct is alleged to have occurred, was an officer or employee of the Agency, the Chairperson may initiate a complaint in relation to that conduct.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Chairperson is complainant</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Unless the context otherwise requires, a reference in this Part to a complainant is, in relation to a complaint initiated under subsection (1), a reference to the Chairperson of the Commission.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Notice to Minister and President</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>The Chairperson of the Commission shall notify the Minister and the President of the Agency of any complaint initiated under subsection (1).</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Notice to officer or employee</MarginalNote><Label>(4)</Label><Text>Immediately after being notified of a complaint under subsection (3), the President of the Agency shall notify in writing the officer or employee whose conduct is the subject matter of the complaint of the substance of the complaint unless, in the President’s opinion, to do so might compromise or hinder any investigation that is being or may be carried out in respect of the complaint.</Text></Subsection></Section><Heading change="ins" level="2"><TitleText>Investigation of Complaints by the Agency</TitleText></Heading><Section change="ins"><MarginalNote>Investigation by the Agency</MarginalNote><Label>40</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Subject to subsection (2) and section <XRefInternal>41</XRefInternal>, the Agency shall investigate any complaint made under this Part.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Restriction on power to investigate</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The Agency shall not commence or continue an investigation of a complaint if</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>in the Agency’s opinion, doing so would compromise or seriously hinder the administration or enforcement of program legislation or the investigation or prosecution of any offence; or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>the Commission has notified the President of the Agency that the Commission will investigate the complaint or institute a hearing to inquire into the complaint.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection></Section><Section change="ins"><MarginalNote>Right to refuse or terminate investigation</MarginalNote><Label>41</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The President of the Agency may direct the Agency to not commence or continue an investigation of a complaint, other than a complaint initiated under subsection <XRefInternal>39</XRefInternal>(1), if, in the President’s opinion,</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>any of the reasons referred to in paragraph <XRefInternal>33</XRefInternal>(2)(a) or (b) or (3)(b) applies; or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>having regard to all the circumstances, it is not necessary or reasonably practicable to commence or continue an investigation of the complaint.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Duty to refuse or terminate investigation</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The President of the Agency shall direct the Agency to not commence or continue an investigation of a complaint by an officer or employee of the Agency if the complaint has been or could have been adequately dealt with, or could more appropriately be dealt with, according to a procedure provided for under any Act of Parliament — other than this Act — or any Act of the legislature of a province.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Notice to complainant and officer or employee</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>If the President of the Agency directs the Agency to not commence or continue an investigation of a complaint, he or she shall give notice in writing to the complainant and the officer or employee whose conduct is the subject matter of the complaint of the decision and the reasons for it and the complainant’s right to refer the complaint to the Commission for review, within 60 days after the day on which the complainant is notified of the decision, if the complainant is not satisfied with the decision.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Additional information in notice to complainant</MarginalNote><Label>(4)</Label><Text>If the President of the Agency directs the Agency to not commence or continue an investigation of a complaint because the complaint could more appropriately be dealt with according to a procedure provided for under any Act of Parliament — other than this Act — or any Act of the legislature of a province, the notice given to the complainant under subsection (3) must identify that procedure.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Notice to Commission</MarginalNote><Label>(5)</Label><Text>The President of the Agency shall notify the Commission of any action he or she takes under this section.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section change="ins"><MarginalNote>Rules</MarginalNote><Label>42</Label><Text>The President of the Agency may make rules governing the procedures to be followed by the Agency in notifying persons under this Part and in investigating, disposing of or otherwise dealing with complaints under this Part.</Text></Section><Section change="ins"><MarginalNote>Updates with respect to the investigation</MarginalNote><Label>43</Label><Text>The President of the Agency shall, on the regular basis provided for in service standards established under section <XRefInternal>21</XRefInternal>, notify in writing the complainant and the officer or employee whose conduct is the subject matter of the complaint of the status of the investigation unless, in the President’s opinion, to do so might compromise or hinder any investigation that is being or may be carried out in respect of the complaint.</Text></Section><Section change="ins"><MarginalNote>Report</MarginalNote><Label>44</Label><Text>As soon as feasible after the investigation of a complaint is completed, the President of the Agency shall prepare and send to the complainant, the officer or employee whose conduct is the subject matter of the complaint and the Commission a report setting out</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>a summary of the complaint;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>the findings of the investigation;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(c)</Label><Text>a summary of any action that has been or will be taken with respect to the disposition of the complaint; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(d)</Label><Text>the complainant’s right to refer the complaint to the Commission for review, within 60 days after the day on which the complainant receives the report, if the complainant is not satisfied with the disposition of the complaint.</Text></Paragraph></Section><Heading change="ins" level="2"><TitleText>Powers of Commission in Relation to Complaints</TitleText></Heading><Section change="ins"><MarginalNote>Powers</MarginalNote><Label>45</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The Commission may, in relation to a complaint before it,</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>in the same manner and to the same extent as a superior court of record, summon and enforce the attendance of witnesses before the Commission and compel them to give oral or written evidence on oath or solemn affirmation and to produce any documents and things that the Commission considers relevant for the full investigation, hearing and consideration of the complaint;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>administer oaths and solemn affirmations;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(c)</Label><Text>receive and accept any evidence and other information, whether on oath or solemn affirmation or by affidavit or otherwise, that the Commission sees fit, whether or not that evidence or information is or would be admissible in a court of law; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(d)</Label><Text>make any examination of records and any inquiries that the Commission considers necessary.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>No excuse</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>No witness shall be excused from answering any question or producing any document or thing, when compelled to do so by the Commission, on the grounds that the answer or statement made in response to the question, or the document or thing given by the witness, may tend to criminate the witness or subject the witness to any criminal, civil or administrative action or proceeding.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Inadmissibility</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>Evidence given, or a document or thing produced, by a witness who is compelled by the Commission to give or produce it, and any evidence derived from it, may be used or received against the witness only in</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>a prosecution under section 132 or 136 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Criminal Code</XRefExternal>; or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>a civil or administrative proceeding in respect of an allegation that, with intent to mislead, the witness gave an answer or statement knowing it to be false.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection change="ins"><MarginalNote>Use of evidence</MarginalNote><Label>(4)</Label><Text>Despite subsection (1), the Commission shall not receive or accept any answer or statement made in response to a question described in subsection (2) in any investigation or hearing with respect to any other complaint.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Witness fees</MarginalNote><Label>(5)</Label><Text>Any witness, other than an officer or employee of the Agency, who is summoned is entitled, at the discretion of the Commission, to receive the same fees and allowances as those paid to witnesses summoned to attend before the Federal Court.</Text></Subsection></Section><Heading change="ins" level="2"><TitleText>Investigation by Commission</TitleText></Heading><Section change="ins"><MarginalNote>Complaints</MarginalNote><Label>46</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>After receiving or being notified of a complaint made under this Part, the Commission shall investigate the complaint or institute a hearing to inquire into it if the Chairperson of the Commission is of the opinion that it would be in the public interest for the Commission to do so.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Notice to President and Minister</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The Commission shall notify the Minister and the President of the Agency of any investigation or hearing initiated under this section.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section change="ins"><MarginalNote>Right to discontinue investigation</MarginalNote><Label>47</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The Commission may decide to discontinue an investigation of a complaint if, in its opinion,</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>any of the reasons for which it may refuse to deal with a complaint under paragraph <XRefInternal>33</XRefInternal>(2)(a) or (b) applies; or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>having regard to all the circumstances, it is not necessary or reasonably practicable to continue to investigate the complaint.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Duty to discontinue investigation</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The Commission shall discontinue an investigation of a complaint if, in its opinion, any of the reasons for which it shall refuse to deal with a complaint under paragraph <XRefInternal>33</XRefInternal>(3)(a), (b) or (c) applies.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Referral — national security</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>The Commission shall discontinue an investigation of a complaint if subsection <XRefInternal>33</XRefInternal>(4) applies and shall refer the complaint to the National Security and Intelligence Review Agency.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Notice to complainant and President</MarginalNote><Label>(4)</Label><Text>Subject to subsection (5), if the Commission discontinues an investigation of a complaint, it shall give notice in writing of the discontinuance and the reasons for it to the complainant and the President of the Agency. If the reason for the discontinuance is that the complaint could more appropriately be dealt with according to a procedure provided for under any Act of Parliament — other than this Act — or any Act of the legislature of a province, the notice given to the complainant shall identify that procedure.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Notice — application of subsection (3)</MarginalNote><Label>(5)</Label><Text>If the investigation of a complaint is discontinued under subsection (3), the Commission shall give to the President of the Agency, and then to the complainant, notice in writing of the investigation’s discontinuance and of the referral made under that subsection.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Notice to officer or employee</MarginalNote><Label>(6)</Label><Text>After receiving the notice, the President of the Agency shall notify the officer or employee whose conduct is the subject matter of the complaint of the discontinuance of the investigation of the complaint and, if applicable, of the referral made under subsection (3).</Text></Subsection></Section><Section change="ins"><MarginalNote>Consolidation of complaints</MarginalNote><Label>48</Label><Text>The Commission may, if in its opinion it is appropriate to do so, merge two or more complaints for the purposes of an investigation, review or hearing.</Text></Section><Section change="ins"><MarginalNote>Updates with respect to investigation</MarginalNote><Label>49</Label><Text>The Commission shall, on the regular basis provided for in the service standards established under section <XRefInternal>21</XRefInternal>, notify in writing the complainant and the officer or employee whose conduct is the subject matter of the complaint of the status of the investigation unless, in the Commission’s opinion, to do so might compromise or hinder any investigation that is being or may be carried out in respect of the complaint.</Text></Section><Heading change="ins" level="2"><TitleText>Referral of Complaints to Commission</TitleText></Heading><Section change="ins"><MarginalNote>Referral to Commission</MarginalNote><Label>50</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>A complainant who is not satisfied with a decision under section <XRefInternal>41</XRefInternal> or a report under section <XRefInternal>44</XRefInternal> may, within 60 days after the day on which they are notified of the decision or receive the report, refer the complaint in writing to the Commission for review.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Extension of time limit</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The Commission may extend the time limit for referring a complaint to the Commission for review if it is of the opinion that there are good reasons for doing so and that it is not contrary to the public interest.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Material to be provided</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>If a complainant refers a complaint to the Commission under subsection (1),</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>the Commission shall notify the President of the Agency that the complaint has been referred to the Commission; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>the President of the Agency shall, as soon as feasible, provide the Commission with a copy of the notice given under subsection <XRefInternal>41</XRefInternal>(3) or the report sent under section <XRefInternal>44</XRefInternal> and a copy of every other document relating to the complaint that the Agency provided to the complainant.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection></Section><Section change="ins"><MarginalNote>Review by Commission</MarginalNote><Label>51</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The Commission shall review any complaint referred to it under section <XRefInternal>50</XRefInternal>.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Commission satisfied</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>If, after reviewing the complaint, the Commission is satisfied with the President of the Agency’s decision or report, the Commission shall prepare and send a report in writing to that effect to the President, the complainant and the officer or employee whose conduct is the subject matter of the complaint.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Commission not satisfied</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>If, after reviewing the complaint, the Commission is not satisfied with the President of the Agency’s decision or report or considers that further inquiry is warranted, the Commission may</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>prepare and send to the President a report in writing setting out any findings it sees fit with respect to the decision or report and any recommendations it sees fit with respect to the complaint;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>request that the President direct the Agency to investigate or further investigate the complaint; or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(c)</Label><Text>investigate or further investigate the complaint or institute a hearing to inquire into the complaint.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection></Section><Section change="ins"><MarginalNote>President’s response</MarginalNote><Label>52</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The President of the Agency shall, as soon as feasible after receiving a report referred to in paragraph <XRefInternal>51</XRefInternal>(3)(a), provide the Commission with a written response indicating any further action that has been or will be taken with respect to the complaint. If the President decides not to act on any findings or recommendations set out in the report, he or she shall include in the response the reasons for not so acting.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Commission’s final report</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>After considering the response, the Commission shall prepare a final report in writing setting out any findings and recommendations with respect to the complaint that it sees fit and shall send a copy of the report and a copy of the response to the President of the Agency, the complainant and the officer or employee whose conduct is the subject matter of the complaint.</Text></Subsection></Section><Heading change="ins" level="2"><TitleText>Hearings</TitleText></Heading><Section change="ins"><MarginalNote>Hearing</MarginalNote><Label>53</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>If the Commission decides, under section <XRefInternal>46</XRefInternal> or paragraph <XRefInternal>51</XRefInternal>(3)(c), to institute a hearing to inquire into a complaint, the Chairperson of the Commission shall assign one or more members of the Commission to conduct the hearing and shall send a notice in writing of the decision to the Minister, the President of the Agency, the complainant and the officer or employee whose conduct is the subject matter of the complaint.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Commission</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>For the purposes of subsections (3) to (11), the member or members of the Commission who are conducting the hearing are deemed to be the Commission.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Meaning of <DefinitionRef>party</DefinitionRef></MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>In this section, <DefinedTermEn>party</DefinedTermEn> means the officer or employee designated by the President of the Agency for the purposes of this Part, the officer or employee whose conduct is the subject matter of the complaint or the complainant.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Notice</MarginalNote><Label>(4)</Label><Text>The Commission shall serve on the parties a notice in writing of the time and place set for the hearing.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Sittings of Commission</MarginalNote><Label>(5)</Label><Text>The Commission may sit at any place in Canada and at any time that it may fix, taking into account the convenience of the parties who wish to appear before it.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Hearings in public</MarginalNote><Label>(6)</Label><Text>A hearing to inquire into a complaint shall be held in public but the Commission, on its own initiative or at the request of any party or witness, may order a hearing or any part of a hearing to be held <Language xml:lang="la">in camera</Language> or <Language xml:lang="la">ex parte</Language> if it is of the opinion</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>that information that could reasonably be expected to be injurious to national security, national defence or international relations will likely be disclosed during the course of the hearing;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph change="ins"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>that information that could reasonably be expected to compromise or seriously hinder the administration or enforcement of program legislation or the investigation or prosecution of any offence will likely be disclosed during the course of the hearing;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(c)</Label><Text>that information respecting a person’s financial or personal affairs, if that person’s interest or security outweighs the public’s interest in the information, will likely be disclosed during the course of the hearing;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(d)</Label><Text>that information that could reasonably be expected to reveal information that is subject to solicitor-client privilege or the professional secrecy of advocates and notaries or to litigation privilege, or information that is described in paragraph <XRefInternal>26</XRefInternal>(b), will likely be disclosed during the course of the hearing; or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(e)</Label><Text>that it is otherwise required by the circumstances of the case.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Rights of persons interested</MarginalNote><Label>(7)</Label><Text>The parties and any other person who satisfies the Commission that the person has a substantial and direct interest in a complaint before the Commission shall be allowed an opportunity, in person or by legal counsel, to present evidence, cross-examine witnesses and make representations at the hearing.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Representation of witnesses</MarginalNote><Label>(8)</Label><Text>The Commission shall permit any person who gives evidence at a hearing to be represented by legal counsel.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Designated officer or employee</MarginalNote><Label>(9)</Label><Text>The officer or employee designated by the President of the Agency for the purposes of this Part may be represented or assisted at a hearing by any other person.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Confidential communications</MarginalNote><Label>(10)</Label><Text>If the officer or employee referred to in subsection (9) is represented or assisted by another person, communications passing in confidence between them in relation to the hearing are, for the purposes of this Part, privileged as if they were communications passing in professional confidence between the officer or employee and their legal counsel.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Expenses</MarginalNote><Label>(11)</Label><Text>If the Commission sits at a place in Canada that is not the ordinary place of residence of the complainant, of the officer or employee whose conduct is the subject matter of the complaint or of the legal counsel of any of those persons, then that person or their legal counsel is entitled, at the discretion of the Commission, to receive, in accordance with Treasury Board directives, the travel and living expenses incurred by that person or their legal counsel in appearing before the Commission.</Text></Subsection></Section><Heading change="ins" level="2"><TitleText>Suspension</TitleText></Heading><Section change="ins"><MarginalNote>Duty to suspend</MarginalNote><Label>54</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The Commission shall suspend an investigation, review or hearing with respect to a complaint if, in its opinion, continuing it would compromise or seriously hinder the administration or enforcement of program legislation or the investigation or prosecution of any offence.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Power to suspend</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The Commission may suspend an investigation, review or hearing with respect to a complaint if, in its opinion, continuing it would compromise or seriously hinder an ongoing civil or administrative proceeding.</Text></Subsection></Section><Heading change="ins" level="2"><TitleText>Reports Following Investigation or Hearing</TitleText></Heading><Section change="ins"><MarginalNote>Interim report</MarginalNote><Label>55</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>On completion of an investigation or a hearing, the Commission shall prepare and send to the President of the Agency a report in writing setting out any findings and recommendations with respect to the complaint that it sees fit.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>President’s response</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The President of the Agency shall, as soon as feasible, provide the Chairperson of the Commission with a written response indicating any further action that has been or will be taken with respect to the complaint. If the President decides not to act on any findings or <Keep svc="1">recommendations</Keep> set out in the report, he or she shall include in the response the reasons for not so acting.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Commission’s final report</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>After considering the response, the Commission shall prepare a final report in writing setting out any findings and recommendations with respect to the complaint that it sees fit and shall send a copy of the report and a copy of the response to the President of the Agency, the complainant and the officer or employee whose conduct is the subject matter of the complaint.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section change="ins"><MarginalNote>Final and conclusive</MarginalNote><Label>56</Label><Text>All of the findings and recommendations that are contained in the Commission’s final report under subsection <XRefInternal>52</XRefInternal>(2) or <XRefInternal>55</XRefInternal>(3) are final and are not subject to appeal to or review by any court.</Text></Section><Section change="ins"><MarginalNote>Return of documents and things</MarginalNote><Label>57</Label><Text>Any document or thing that a person produced to the Agency or the Commission shall, on the request of the person, be released to that person within a reasonable time after the completion of the Commission’s final report.</Text></Section><Heading change="ins" level="2"><TitleText>Serious Incidents</TitleText></Heading><Section change="ins"><MarginalNote>Definitions</MarginalNote><Label>58</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The following definitions apply in this section and sections <XRefInternal>59</XRefInternal> to <XRefInternal>61</XRefInternal>.</Text><Definition change="ins"><Text><DefinedTermEn>employee</DefinedTermEn>, in relation to the Agency, includes any person who assists the Agency in the exercise of any of its powers or the performance of any of its duties and functions under Part 1. (<DefinedTermFr>employé</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Definition><Definition><Text><DefinedTermEn>serious incident</DefinedTermEn> means an incident in which the actions of an officer or employee of the Agency in the exercise of their powers or the performance of their duties and functions under Part 1</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>may have resulted in serious injury to, or the death of, any person; or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>may have constituted an offence under federal or provincial law that the Minister or the President of the Agency decides would be in the public interest to be investigated by the Agency. (<DefinedTermFr>incident grave</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Paragraph></Definition><Definition><Text><DefinedTermEn>serious injury</DefinedTermEn> means a prescribed physical or psychological injury. (<DefinedTermFr>blessure grave</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Definition></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Regulations</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The Governor in Council may make regulations prescribing physical or psychological injuries for the purposes of the definition <DefinitionRef>serious injury</DefinitionRef> in subsection (1).</Text></Subsection></Section><Section change="ins"><MarginalNote>Notification</MarginalNote><Label>59</Label><Text>As soon as feasible after becoming aware that a serious incident is alleged to have occurred, the President of the Agency shall notify the police force that has jurisdiction at the location where it is alleged to have occurred — and the Commission — of the alleged serious incident.</Text></Section><Section change="ins"><MarginalNote>Investigation</MarginalNote><Label>60</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Subject to subsection (2), after the President of the Agency becomes aware that a serious incident is alleged to have occurred, the Agency shall investigate the alleged serious incident.</Text></Subsection><Subsection change="ins"><MarginalNote>Limit on investigation</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>If the alleged serious incident involves the actions of one or more persons, the Agency shall not, in the investigation, investigate the actions of any person who assists the Agency in the exercise of any of its powers or the performance of any of its duties and functions under Part 1 by reason only of an agreement or arrangement referred to in subsection 13(3).</Text></Subsection></Section><Section change="ins"><MarginalNote>Copy of records</MarginalNote><Label>61</Label><Text>As soon as feasible after completing the investigation, the President of the Agency shall provide the Commission with a copy of any records in its possession relating to the investigation. The President shall also provide the Commission with a copy of any record in respect of every other lawfully authorized investigation conducted into the alleged serious incident that the Agency receives after the completion of its own investigation.</Text></Section><Heading change="ins" level="2"><TitleText>General</TitleText></Heading><Section change="ins"><MarginalNote>Delegation</MarginalNote><Label>62</Label><Text>The Chairperson of the Commission may delegate to the Vice-chairperson of the Commission or, if the office of Vice-chairperson is vacant, to any other member of the Commission any of the Chairperson’s powers, duties and functions under this Part, except the power to delegate under this section.</Text></Section><Section change="ins"><MarginalNote>Technical assistance</MarginalNote><Label>63</Label><Text>The Commission may, with the approval of the Treasury Board,</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>engage, on a temporary basis, the services of persons having technical or specialized knowledge of any matter relating to the work of the Commission to advise and assist it in the exercise of its powers and the performance of its duties and functions under this Part; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>fix and pay the remuneration and expenses of persons engaged under paragraph (a).</Text></Paragraph></Section><Section change="ins"><MarginalNote>No effect</MarginalNote><Label>64</Label><Text>The making of a complaint under section <XRefInternal>33</XRefInternal> or <XRefInternal>39</XRefInternal>, the investigation into a complaint made under either of those sections or the review of a complaint under section <XRefInternal>51</XRefInternal> is not to</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>delay any investigation of an offence under an Act of Parliament or of the legislature of a province or prevent any such investigation from commencing;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>delay an action taken under any program legislation or prevent any such action from being taken;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(c)</Label><Text>delay any removal proceedings or prevent the enforcement of any removal order;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(d)</Label><Text>delay any extradition proceedings or prevent the extradition of any individual to or from Canada; or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(e)</Label><Text>permit any individual to enter Canada or to remain in Canada beyond the end of the period for which they are authorized to so remain.</Text></Paragraph></Section><Section change="ins"><MarginalNote>Right to be informed</MarginalNote><Label>65</Label><Text>Every person who is arrested or detained by an officer or employee of the Agency has a right to be informed, as soon as feasible, of their right to make a complaint under this Part and of how the complaint may be made and, if the person is subsequently detained on behalf of the Agency under an agreement or arrangement referred to in subsection 13(3), a right to be informed, as soon as feasible, of their right to make a complaint to the competent authority in the province where they are detained about their treatment while under detention and their conditions of detention, and of how the complaint may be made.</Text></Section><Section change="ins"><MarginalNote>Joint reviews or joint investigations, reviews or hearings</MarginalNote><Label>66</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>If a review conducted under section <XRefInternal>18</XRefInternal> or a complaint made under this Part concerns the detention of persons on behalf of the Agency under an agreement or arrangement referred to in subsection 13(3), the Commission may conduct that review, or an investigation, review or hearing of that complaint, as the case may be, jointly with any competent authority in the province where the persons are or were detained.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Regulations</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The Governor in Council may make regulations respecting reviews, or investigations, reviews or hearings, conducted jointly under subsection (1), including regulations respecting the entering into of agreements or arrangements — and the sharing of information — between the Commission and any competent authority referred to in that subsection for the purpose of the joint reviews or the joint investigations, reviews or hearings.</Text></Subsection></Section><Heading change="ins" level="2"><TitleText>Offences</TitleText></Heading><Section change="ins"><MarginalNote>Attendance of witnesses, etc.</MarginalNote><Label>67</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Every person commits an offence punishable on summary conviction who</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>on being duly summoned as a witness or otherwise under this Part, fails to attend;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>being in attendance as a witness in any proceeding,</Text><Subparagraph><Label>(i)</Label><Text>refuses to take an oath or solemn affirmation required of them,</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph><Label>(ii)</Label><Text>refuses to produce any document or thing in their possession or under their control that is required to be produced by them, or</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph><Label>(iii)</Label><Text>refuses to answer any question;</Text></Subparagraph></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(c)</Label><Text>at any proceeding uses insulting or threatening language or causes any interference or disturbance; or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(d)</Label><Text>without lawful justification or excuse, prints or publishes observations or uses words in relation to an ongoing proceeding with intent to dissuade a witness in any proceeding from testifying.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Definition of <DefinedTermEn>proceeding</DefinedTermEn></MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>In subsection (1), <DefinedTermEn>proceeding</DefinedTermEn> means any investigation or hearing conducted by the Commission with respect to a complaint made under this Part. </Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Punishment</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>Every person who is convicted of an offence under subsection (1) is liable to a fine of not more than $5,000 or to imprisonment for a term of not more than six months, or to both.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section change="ins"><MarginalNote>Offences — harassment, obstruction, destroying documents etc.</MarginalNote><Label>68</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>No person shall</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>harass, intimidate or threaten any person with the intent to compel that other person to abstain from making a complaint under this Part;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>harass, intimidate or threaten</Text><Subparagraph><Label>(i)</Label><Text>an individual who makes a complaint under this Part,</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph><Label>(ii)</Label><Text>an individual at whom the conduct that is the subject of a complaint made under this Part was directed,</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph><Label>(iii)</Label><Text>a person who they have reasonable grounds to believe will be questioned or summoned by the Commission when it deals with a complaint made under this Part, or</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph><Label>(iv)</Label><Text>a person who is exercising any power or performing any duty or function under this Part;</Text></Subparagraph></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(c)</Label><Text>wilfully obstruct a person who is exercising any power or performing any duty or function under this Part, or knowingly make any false or misleading statement or knowingly provide false or misleading information to such a person;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(d)</Label><Text>destroy, mutilate, alter, falsify or conceal a document or thing, or make a false document or thing, knowing that the document or thing is likely to be relevant to an investigation of, or hearing to inquire into, a complaint made under this Part or to a review under this Part; or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(e)</Label><Text>direct, counsel or cause, in any manner, any person to do anything mentioned in any of paragraphs (a) to (d), or propose, in any manner, to any person that they do anything mentioned in any of those paragraphs.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Punishment</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Every person who contravenes subsection (1) is guilty of an offence and liable</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>on conviction on indictment, to imprisonment for a term of not more than five years; or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>on summary conviction, to a fine of not more than $5,000 or to imprisonment for a term of not more than six months, or to both.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection></Section><Section change="ins"><MarginalNote>Offence — section <XRefInternal>27</XRefInternal> and subsection <XRefInternal>29</XRefInternal>(3)</MarginalNote><Label>69</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Every person who contravenes section <XRefInternal>27</XRefInternal> or subsection <XRefInternal>29</XRefInternal>(3) is guilty of an offence punishable on summary conviction and liable to a fine of not more than $5,000 or to imprisonment for a term of not more than six months, or to both.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Defence</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>A person shall not be found guilty of an offence under subsection (1) if they establish that they exercised all due diligence to prevent the commission of the offence.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section change="ins"><MarginalNote>Limitation period</MarginalNote><Label>70</Label><Text>Summary conviction proceedings in respect of an offence under this Part may be instituted at any time within but not later than two years after the time when the subject matter of the proceedings arose.</Text></Section></AmendedText><ExplanatoryNote><Label><Emphasis style="italic">Clause 15</Emphasis>:</Label><ExplanatoryText>New.</ExplanatoryText></ExplanatoryNote></Section><Heading level="1"><TitleText>Consequential Amendments</TitleText></Heading><Heading level="2"><MarginalNote><HistoricalNote>R.S., c. A-1</HistoricalNote></MarginalNote><TitleText><XRefExternal reference-type="act">Access to Information Act</XRefExternal></TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote><HistoricalNote>2013, c. 18, s. 43</HistoricalNote></MarginalNote><Label>16</Label><Text>Schedule I to the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Access to Information Act</XRefExternal> is amended by striking out the following under the heading “Other Government Institutions”:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><BilingualGroup><BilingualItemEn>Civilian Review and Complaints Commission for the Royal Canadian Mounted Police</BilingualItemEn><BilingualItemFr>Commission civile d’examen et de traitement des plaintes relatives à la Gendarmerie royale du Canada</BilingualItemFr></BilingualGroup></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>17</Label><Text>Schedule I to the Act is amended by adding the following in alphabetical order under the heading “Other Government Institutions”:</Text><AmendedText change="ins" include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><BilingualGroup><BilingualItemEn>Public Complaints and Review Commission</BilingualItemEn><BilingualItemFr>Commission d’examen et de traitement des plaintes du public</BilingualItemFr></BilingualGroup></AmendedText></Section><Heading level="2"><MarginalNote><HistoricalNote>R.S., c. C-5</HistoricalNote></MarginalNote><TitleText><XRefExternal reference-type="act">Canada Evidence Act</XRefExternal></TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote><HistoricalNote>2013, c. 18, s. 85</HistoricalNote></MarginalNote><Label>18</Label><Text>Item 22 of the schedule to the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Canada Evidence Act</XRefExternal> is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Label>22</Label><Text>The <Ins>Public</Ins> Complaints and Review Commission, for the purposes of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Royal Canadian Mounted Police Act</XRefExternal> <Ins>and the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Canada Border Services Agency Act</XRefExternal></Ins>, but only in relation to information that is under the control, or in the possession, of the Royal Canadian Mounted Police, <Ins>the Canada Border Services Agency</Ins> or the Central Authority, as the case may be.</Text></Provision></AmendedText></Section><Heading level="2"><MarginalNote><HistoricalNote>R.S., c. F-11</HistoricalNote></MarginalNote><TitleText><XRefExternal reference-type="act">Financial Administration Act</XRefExternal></TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote><HistoricalNote>2013, c. 18, s. 48</HistoricalNote></MarginalNote><Label>19</Label><Text>Schedule I.1 to the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Financial Administration Act</XRefExternal> is amended by striking out, in column I, the reference to</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><BilingualGroup><BilingualItemEn>Civilian Review and Complaints Commission for the Royal Canadian Mounted Police</BilingualItemEn><BilingualItemFr>Commission civile d’examen et de traitement des plaintes relatives à la Gendarmerie royale du Canada</BilingualItemFr></BilingualGroup></AmendedText><ContinuedSectionSubsection type="amending"><Text>and the corresponding reference in column II to ‘‘Minister of Public Safety and Emergency Preparedness’’.</Text></ContinuedSectionSubsection></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>20</Label><Text>Schedule I.1 to the Act is amended by adding, in alphabetical order in column I, a reference to</Text><AmendedText change="ins" include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><BilingualGroup><BilingualItemEn>Public Complaints and Review Commission</BilingualItemEn><BilingualItemFr>Commission d’examen et de traitement des plaintes du public</BilingualItemFr></BilingualGroup></AmendedText><ContinuedSectionSubsection type="amending"><Text>and a corresponding reference in column II to ‘‘Minister of Public Safety and Emergency Preparedness’’.</Text></ContinuedSectionSubsection></Section><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote><HistoricalNote>2013, c. 18, s. 50</HistoricalNote></MarginalNote><Label>21</Label><Text>Schedule IV to the Act is amended by striking out the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><BilingualGroup><BilingualItemEn>Civilian Review and Complaints Commission for the Royal Canadian Mounted Police</BilingualItemEn><BilingualItemFr>Commission civile d’examen et de traitement des plaintes relatives à la Gendarmerie royale du Canada</BilingualItemFr></BilingualGroup></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>22</Label><Text>Schedule IV to the Act is amended by adding the following in alphabetical order:</Text><AmendedText change="ins" include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><BilingualGroup><BilingualItemEn>Public Complaints and Review Commission</BilingualItemEn><BilingualItemFr>Commission d’examen et de traitement des plaintes du public</BilingualItemFr></BilingualGroup></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote><HistoricalNote>2013, c. 18, s. 53</HistoricalNote></MarginalNote><Label>23</Label><Text>Part III of Schedule VI to the Act is amended by striking out, in column I, the reference to</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><BilingualGroup><BilingualItemEn>Civilian Review and Complaints Commission for the Royal Canadian Mounted Police</BilingualItemEn><BilingualItemFr>Commission civile d’examen et de traitement des plaintes relatives à la Gendarmerie royale du Canada</BilingualItemFr></BilingualGroup></AmendedText><ContinuedSectionSubsection type="amending"><Text>and the corresponding reference in column II to ‘‘Chairperson’’.</Text></ContinuedSectionSubsection></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>24</Label><Text>Part III of Schedule VI to the Act is amended by adding, in alphabetical order in column I, a reference to</Text><AmendedText change="ins" include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><BilingualGroup><BilingualItemEn>Public Complaints and Review Commission</BilingualItemEn><BilingualItemFr>Commission d’examen et de traitement des plaintes du public</BilingualItemFr></BilingualGroup></AmendedText><ContinuedSectionSubsection type="amending"><Text>and a corresponding reference in column II to ‘‘Chairperson’’.</Text></ContinuedSectionSubsection></Section><Heading level="2"><MarginalNote><HistoricalNote>R.S., c. O-5; 2001, c. 41, s. 25</HistoricalNote></MarginalNote><TitleText><XRefExternal reference-type="act">Security of Information Act</XRefExternal></TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote><HistoricalNote>2013, c. 18, s. 54</HistoricalNote></MarginalNote><Label>25</Label><Text>The schedule to the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Security of Information Act</XRefExternal> is amended by striking out the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><BilingualGroup><BilingualItemEn>Civilian Review and Complaints Commission for the Royal Canadian Mounted Police</BilingualItemEn><BilingualItemFr>Commission civile d’examen et de traitement des plaintes relatives à la Gendarmerie royale du Canada</BilingualItemFr></BilingualGroup></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>26</Label><Text>The schedule to the Act is amended by adding the following in alphabetical order:</Text><AmendedText change="ins" include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><BilingualGroup><BilingualItemEn>Public Complaints and Review Commission</BilingualItemEn><BilingualItemFr>Commission d’examen et de traitement des plaintes du public</BilingualItemFr></BilingualGroup></AmendedText></Section><Heading level="2"><MarginalNote><HistoricalNote>R.S., c. P-21</HistoricalNote></MarginalNote><TitleText><XRefExternal reference-type="act">Privacy Act</XRefExternal></TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote><HistoricalNote>2013, c. 18, s. 56</HistoricalNote></MarginalNote><Label>27</Label><Text>The schedule to the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Privacy Act</XRefExternal> is amended by striking out the following under the heading “Other Government Institutions”:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><BilingualGroup><BilingualItemEn>Civilian Review and Complaints Commission for the Royal Canadian Mounted Police</BilingualItemEn><BilingualItemFr>Commission civile d’examen et de traitement des plaintes relatives à la Gendarmerie royale du Canada</BilingualItemFr></BilingualGroup></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>28</Label><Text>The schedule to the Act is amended by adding the following in alphabetical order under the heading “Other Government Institutions”:</Text><AmendedText change="ins" include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><BilingualGroup><BilingualItemEn>Public Complaints and Review Commission</BilingualItemEn><BilingualItemFr>Commission d’examen et de traitement des plaintes du public</BilingualItemFr></BilingualGroup></AmendedText></Section><Heading level="2"><MarginalNote><HistoricalNote>1991, c. 30</HistoricalNote></MarginalNote><TitleText><XRefExternal reference-type="act">Public Sector Compensation Act</XRefExternal></TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote><HistoricalNote>2013, c. 18, s. 58</HistoricalNote></MarginalNote><Label>29</Label><Text>Schedule I to the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Public Sector Compensation Act</XRefExternal> is amended by striking out the following under the heading “Other Portions of the Public Service”:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><BilingualGroup><BilingualItemEn>Civilian Review and Complaints Commission for the Royal Canadian Mounted Police</BilingualItemEn><BilingualItemFr>Commission civile d’examen et de traitement des plaintes relatives à la Gendarmerie royale du Canada</BilingualItemFr></BilingualGroup></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>30</Label><Text>Schedule I to the Act is amended by adding the following in alphabetical order under the heading “Other Portions of the Public Service”:</Text><AmendedText change="ins" include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><BilingualGroup><BilingualItemEn>Public Complaints and Review Commission</BilingualItemEn><BilingualItemFr>Commission d’examen et de traitement des plaintes du public</BilingualItemFr></BilingualGroup></AmendedText></Section><Heading level="2"><MarginalNote><HistoricalNote>2017, c. 15</HistoricalNote></MarginalNote><TitleText><XRefExternal reference-type="act">National Security and Intelligence Committee of Parliamentarians Act</XRefExternal></TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><Label>31</Label><Text>Paragraph (a) of the definition <DefinitionRef>review body</DefinitionRef> in section 2 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">National Security and Intelligence Committee of Parliamentarians Act</XRefExternal> is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>the <Ins>Public</Ins> Complaints and Review Commission established by subsection 45.29(1) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Royal Canadian Mounted Police Act</XRefExternal>; or</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText><ExplanatoryNote><TitleText>National Security and Intelligence Committee of Parliamentarians Act</TitleText><Label><Emphasis style="italic">Clause 31</Emphasis>:</Label><ExplanatoryText>Relevant portion of the definition:</ExplanatoryText><ExistingText><SectionPiece><Definition><Text><DefinedTermEn>review body</DefinedTermEn> means</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>the Civilian Review and Complaints Commission for the Royal Canadian Mounted Police established by subsection 45.29(1) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Royal Canadian Mounted Police Act</XRefExternal>; or</Text></Paragraph></Definition></SectionPiece></ExistingText></ExplanatoryNote></Section><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote><HistoricalNote>2019, c. 13, s. 49(3)</HistoricalNote></MarginalNote><Label>32</Label><Text>Subsection 16(3) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Subsection><MarginalNote>Review bodies informed of decision</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>The appropriate Minister must provide the decision and reasons to the National Security and Intelligence <Keep svc="1">Review</Keep> Agency and, in the case of information under the control of the Royal Canadian Mounted Police <Ins>or the Canada Border Services Agency</Ins>, to the <Ins>Public</Ins> Complaints and Review Commission.</Text></Subsection></AmendedText><ExplanatoryNote><Label><Emphasis style="italic">Clause 32</Emphasis>:</Label><ExplanatoryText>Existing text of subsection 16(3):</ExplanatoryText><ExistingText><Subsection><Label>(3)</Label><Text>The appropriate Minister must provide the decision and reasons to the National Security and Intelligence Review Agency and, in the case of information under the control of the Royal Canadian Mounted Police, the Civilian Review and Complaints Commission for the Royal Canadian Mounted Police.</Text></Subsection></ExistingText></ExplanatoryNote></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>33</Label><Text>Paragraph 23(a) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>to the <Ins>Public</Ins> Complaints and Review Commission, information that is obtained from — or that is created by the Committee from information obtained from — the Royal Canadian Mounted Police <Ins>or the Canada Border Services Agency</Ins> and that is related to the fulfilment of that <Ins>Commission’s</Ins> mandate; or</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText><ExplanatoryNote><Label><Emphasis style="italic">Clause 33</Emphasis>:</Label><ExplanatoryText>Relevant portion of section 23:</ExplanatoryText><ExistingText><Section><Label>23</Label><Text>The Committee may provide,</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>to the Civilian Review and Complaints Commission for the Royal Canadian Mounted Police, information that is obtained from — or that is created by the Committee from information obtained from — the Royal Canadian Mounted Police and that is related to the fulfilment of that review body’s mandate; or</Text></Paragraph></Section></ExistingText></ExplanatoryNote></Section><Heading level="2"><MarginalNote><HistoricalNote>2019, c. 13, s. 2</HistoricalNote></MarginalNote><TitleText><XRefExternal reference-type="act">National Security and Intelligence Review Agency Act</XRefExternal></TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><Label>34</Label><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The definition <DefinitionRef>deputy head</DefinitionRef> in section 2 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">National Security and Intelligence Review Agency Act</XRefExternal> is amended by adding the following after paragraph (c):</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><SectionPiece><Paragraph change="ins"><Label>(c.1)</Label><Text>with respect to the Canada Border Services Agency, the President;</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText><ExplanatoryNote><TitleText>National Security and Intelligence Review Agency Act</TitleText><Label><Emphasis style="italic">Clause 34</Emphasis>: (1)</Label><ExplanatoryText>Relevant portion of the definition</ExplanatoryText><ExistingText><SectionPiece><Definition><Text><DefinedTermEn>deputy head</DefinedTermEn> means, except in section 42,</Text></Definition></SectionPiece></ExistingText></ExplanatoryNote></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Paragraph (a) of the definition <DefinitionRef>review body</DefinitionRef> in section 2 of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>the <Ins>Public</Ins> Complaints and Review Commission established by subsection 45.29(1) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Royal Canadian Mounted Police Act</XRefExternal>; or</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText><ExplanatoryNote><Label>(2)</Label><ExplanatoryText>Relevant portion of the definition:</ExplanatoryText><ExistingText><SectionPiece><Definition><Text><DefinedTermEn>review body</DefinedTermEn> means</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>the Civilian Review and Complaints Commission for the Royal Canadian Mounted Police established by subsection 45.29(1) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Royal Canadian Mounted Police Act</XRefExternal>; or</Text></Paragraph></Definition></SectionPiece></ExistingText></ExplanatoryNote></Subsection></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>35</Label><Text>Paragraph 8(1)(d) of the Act is amended by adding the following after subparagraph (ii):</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><SectionPiece><Subparagraph change="ins"><Label>(ii.1)</Label><Text>any complaint referred to the Agency under subsection 33(4) or 47(3) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Canada Border Services Agency Act</XRefExternal>,</Text></Subparagraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText><ExplanatoryNote><Label><Emphasis style="italic">Clause 35</Emphasis>:</Label><ExplanatoryText>Relevant portion of subsection 8(1):</ExplanatoryText><ExistingText><Section><Label>8</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The mandate of the Review Agency is to</Text><Paragraph><Label>...</Label><Text> </Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(d)</Label><Text>investigate</Text></Paragraph></Subsection></Section></ExistingText></ExplanatoryNote></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>36</Label><Text>Paragraph 10(d) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(d)</Label><Text>in relation to a complaint referred to it under subsection 45.53(4.1) or 45.67(2.1) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Royal Canadian Mounted Police Act</XRefExternal> <Ins>or subsection 33(4) or 47(3) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Canada Border Services Agency Act</XRefExternal></Ins>, any information that relates to the complaint and that is in the <Keep svc="1">possession</Keep> or under the control of the <Ins>Public</Ins> Complaints and Review Commission, the Royal Canadian Mounted Police, the Canadian Security Intelligence Service, the Communications Security Establishment or <Ins>the Canada Border Services Agency</Ins>.</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText><ExplanatoryNote><Label><Emphasis style="italic">Clause 36</Emphasis>:</Label><ExplanatoryText>Relevant portion of section 10:</ExplanatoryText><ExistingText><Section><Label>10</Label><Text>Despite any other Act of Parliament and any privilege under the law of evidence and subject to section 12, the Review Agency is entitled to have access in a timely manner to the following information:</Text><Paragraph><Label>...</Label><Text> </Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(d)</Label><Text>in relation to a complaint referred to it under subsection 45.53(4.1) or 45.67(2.1) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Royal Canadian Mounted Police Act</XRefExternal>, any information that relates to the complaint and that is in the possession or under the control of the Civilian Review and Complaints Commission for the Royal Canadian Mounted Police established by subsection 45.29(1) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Royal Canadian Mounted Police Act</XRefExternal>, the Royal Canadian Mounted Police, the Canadian Security Intelligence Service or the Communications Security Establishment.</Text></Paragraph></Section></ExistingText></ExplanatoryNote></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>37</Label><Text>Section 15 of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Section><MarginalNote>Public Complaints and Review Commission</MarginalNote><Label>15</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The Review Agency may provide to the <Ins>Public</Ins> Complaints and Review Commission</Text><Paragraph><Label><Ins>(a)</Ins></Label><Text>information that is obtained from — or that is created by the Agency from information obtained from — the Royal Canadian Mounted Police and that is related, in the Agency’s opinion, to the fulfilment of that <Ins>Commission’s</Ins> mandate under subsection 45.34(1) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Royal Canadian Mounted Police Act</XRefExternal>; <Ins>or</Ins></Text></Paragraph><Paragraph change="ins"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>information that is obtained from — or that is created by the Agency from information obtained from — the Canada Border Services Agency and that is related, in the Agency’s opinion, to the fulfilment of that Commission’s mandate under subsection 18(1) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Canada Border Services Agency Act</XRefExternal>.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Exception</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The Review Agency must not provide to the <Ins>Public Complaints and</Ins> Review <Ins>Commission</Ins> information that is referred to in subsection 45.42(1) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Royal Canadian Mounted Police Act</XRefExternal> <Ins>or paragraph 26(b) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Canada Border Services Agency Act</XRefExternal>.</Ins></Text></Subsection></Section></AmendedText><ExplanatoryNote><Label><Emphasis style="italic">Clause 37</Emphasis>:</Label><ExplanatoryText>Existing text of section 15:</ExplanatoryText><ExistingText><Section><Label>15</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The Review Agency may provide to the Civilian Review and Complaints Commission for the Royal Canadian Mounted Police information that is obtained from — or that is created by the Agency from information obtained from — the Royal Canadian Mounted Police and that is related, in the Agency’s opinion, to the fulfilment of that review body’s mandate under subsection 45.34(1) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Royal Canadian Mounted Police Act</XRefExternal>.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The Review Agency must not provide to the review body information that is referred to in subsection 45.42(1) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Royal Canadian Mounted Police Act</XRefExternal>.</Text></Subsection></Section></ExistingText></ExplanatoryNote></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>38</Label><Text>Section 19 of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Section><MarginalNote>Complaints referred by review body</MarginalNote><Label>19</Label><Text>The Review Agency must receive and investigate a complaint referred to it under subsection 45.53(4.1) or 45.67(2.1) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Royal Canadian Mounted Police Act</XRefExternal> <Ins>or subsection 33(4) or 47(3) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Canada Border Services Agency Act</XRefExternal></Ins> if it is satisfied that the complaint is not trivial, frivolous or vexatious or made in bad faith.</Text></Section></AmendedText><ExplanatoryNote><Label><Emphasis style="italic">Clause 38</Emphasis>:</Label><ExplanatoryText>Existing text of section 19:</ExplanatoryText><ExistingText><Section><Label>19</Label><Text>The Review Agency must receive and investigate a complaint referred to it under subsection 45.53(4.1) or 45.67(2.1) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Royal Canadian Mounted Police Act</XRefExternal> if the Agency is satisfied that the complaint is not trivial, frivolous or vexatious or made in bad faith.</Text></Section></ExistingText></ExplanatoryNote></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>39</Label><Text>Subsection 29(1) of the Act is amended by striking out “and” at the end of paragraph (b), by adding “and” at the end of paragraph (c) and by adding the following after paragraph (c):</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><SectionPiece><Paragraph change="ins"><Label>(d)</Label><Text>on completion of an investigation in relation to a complaint referred to it under subsection 33(4) or 47(3) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Canada Border Services Agency Act</XRefExternal>, provide the appropriate Minister and the President of the Canada Border Services Agency with a report containing the findings of the investigation and any recommendations that the Agency considers appropriate.</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText><ExplanatoryNote><Label><Emphasis style="italic">Clause 39</Emphasis>:</Label><ExplanatoryText>Relevant portion of subsection 29(1):</ExplanatoryText><ExistingText><Section><Label>29</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The Review Agency must,</Text></Subsection></Section></ExistingText></ExplanatoryNote></Section><Heading level="2"><MarginalNote><HistoricalNote>2019, c. 13, s. 49.1</HistoricalNote></MarginalNote><TitleText><XRefExternal reference-type="act">Avoiding Complicity in Mistreatment by Foreign Entities Act</XRefExternal></TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote><HistoricalNote>2019, c. 13, s. 49.2</HistoricalNote></MarginalNote><Label>40</Label><Text>Section 6 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Avoiding Complicity in Mistreatment by Foreign Entities Act</XRefExternal> is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Section><MarginalNote>Copy to be provided</MarginalNote><Label>6</Label><Text>Every deputy head to whom directions have been issued under section 3 must, as soon as feasible after receiving them, provide a copy of the directions to the National Security and Intelligence Committee of Parliamentarians, the National Security and Intelligence Review Agency and, if applicable, the <Ins>Public</Ins> Complaints and Review Commission.</Text></Section></AmendedText><ExplanatoryNote><TitleText>Avoiding Complicity in Mistreatment by Foreign Entities Act</TitleText><Label><Emphasis style="italic">Clause 40</Emphasis>:</Label><ExplanatoryText>Existing text of section 6:</ExplanatoryText><ExistingText><Section><Label>6</Label><Text>Every deputy head to whom directions have been issued under section 3 must, as soon as feasible after receiving them, provide a copy of the directions to the National Security and Intelligence Committee of Parliamentarians, the National Security and Intelligence Review Agency and, if applicable, the Civilian Review and Complaints Commission for the Royal Canadian Mounted Police.</Text></Section></ExistingText></ExplanatoryNote></Section><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote><HistoricalNote>2019, c. 13, s. 49.2</HistoricalNote></MarginalNote><Label>41</Label><Text>Subsection 8(1) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Section><MarginalNote>Obligation to provide copy</MarginalNote><Label>8</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>As soon as feasible after receiving a report under section 7, the appropriate Minister must provide a copy of it to the National Security and Intelligence Committee of Parliamentarians, the National Security and Intelligence Review Agency and, if applicable, the <Ins>Public</Ins> Complaints and Review Commission.</Text></Subsection></Section></AmendedText><ExplanatoryNote><Label><Emphasis style="italic">Clause 41</Emphasis>:</Label><ExplanatoryText>Existing text of subsection 8(1):</ExplanatoryText><ExistingText><Section><Label>8</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>As soon as feasible after receiving a report under section 7, the appropriate Minister must provide a copy of it to the National Security and Intelligence Committee of Parliamentarians, the National Security and Intelligence Review Agency and, if applicable, the Civilian Review and Complaints Commission for the Royal Canadian Mounted Police.</Text></Subsection></Section></ExistingText></ExplanatoryNote></Section><Heading level="1"><TitleText>Coming into Force</TitleText></Heading><Section type="transitional"><MarginalNote>Order in council</MarginalNote><Label>42</Label><Text>The provisions of this Act come into force on a day or days to be fixed by order of the Governor in Council.</Text></Section></Body></Bill>