<Bill bill-origin="senate" bill-type="private-public" xml:lang="en" date-time="2019-12-03 10:47:35"><Identification><BillNumber>S-203</BillNumber><Parliament><Session>1</Session><Number>43</Number><RegnalYear><Year-s>68</Year-s><Monarch>Elizabeth II</Monarch></RegnalYear><Year-s>2019</Year-s></Parliament><LongTitle>An Act to amend the National Capital Act (buildings or works of national significance)</LongTitle><ShortTitle status="unofficial" /><RunningHead>An Act to amend the National Capital Act (buildings or works of national significance)</RunningHead><BillHistory><Stages stage="first-reading-senate"><Date><YYYY>2019</YYYY><MM>12</MM><DD>10</DD></Date></Stages></BillHistory><BillSponsor>Joyal, P.C.</BillSponsor><BillRefNumber date-time="">4311914</BillRefNumber></Identification><Introduction><Summary><TitleText>SUMMARY</TitleText><Provision><Text>This enactment amends the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">National Capital Act</XRefExternal> to establish certain requirements related to the erection, alteration, extension or demolition of certain buildings or other works within the National Capital Region.</Text></Provision></Summary><Enacts><Provision><Text>Her Majesty, by and with the advice and consent of the Senate and House of Commons of Canada, <Keep>enacts</Keep> as follows:</Text></Provision></Enacts></Introduction><Body><Heading level="1"><MarginalNote><HistoricalNote>R.S., c. N-4</HistoricalNote></MarginalNote><TitleText><XRefExternal reference-type="act">National Capital Act</XRefExternal></TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><Label>1</Label><Text>Section 2 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">National Capital Act</XRefExternal> is amended by adding the following in alphabetical order:</Text><AmendedText change="ins"><SectionPiece><Definition><Text><DefinedTermEn>building or work of national significance</DefinedTermEn> means</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>the grounds in the City of Ottawa bounded by Wellington Street, the Rideau Canal, the Ottawa River and Kent Street, known as Parliament Hill, and any buildings or works located on those grounds;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>the Senate of Canada Building, located at 2 Rideau Street in the City of Ottawa;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(c)</Label><Text>the building located at 1 Wellington Street in the City of Ottawa;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(d)</Label><Text>the Victoria Building, located at 140 Wellington Street in the City of Ottawa;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(e)</Label><Text>the Sir John A. Macdonald Building, located at 144 Wellington Street in the City of Ottawa;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(f)</Label><Text>the Wellington Building, located at 180 Wellington Street in the City of Ottawa;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(g)</Label><Text>the Confederation Building, located at 229 Wellington Street in the City of Ottawa;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(h)</Label><Text>the Justice Building, located at 249 Wellington Street in the City of Ottawa;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(i)</Label><Text>the Supreme Court of Canada Building, located at 301 Wellington Street in the City of Ottawa;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(j)</Label><Text>any place that has been commemorated as a historic place under paragraph 3(a) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Historic Sites and Monuments Act</XRefExternal>;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(k)</Label><Text>a national historic site as defined in subsection 2(1) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Parks Canada Agency Act</XRefExternal>; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(l)</Label><Text>any prescribed building or work. (<DefinedTermFr><Language xml:lang="fr">Version anglaise seulement</Language></DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Paragraph></Definition><Definition><Text><DefinedTermEn>prescribed</DefinedTermEn> means prescribed by regulation. (<DefinitionEnOnly>English version only</DefinitionEnOnly>)</Text></Definition></SectionPiece></AmendedText><ExplanatoryNote><TitleText><XRefExternal reference-type="act">National Capital Act</XRefExternal></TitleText><Label><Emphasis style="italic">Clause 1</Emphasis>:</Label><ExplanatoryText>New.</ExplanatoryText></ExplanatoryNote></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>2</Label><Text>Subsection 12(1) of the Act is amended by striking out “or” at the end of paragraph (b) and adding the following after that paragraph:</Text><AmendedText change="ins"><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(b.1)</Label><Text>any department or person proposes to erect, alter, extend or demolish a building or other work on a parcel of land in the National Capital Region that is within 500 m of another parcel of land on which a building or work of national significance is situated; or</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText><ExplanatoryNote><Label><Emphasis style="italic">Clause 2</Emphasis>:</Label><ExplanatoryText>Existing text of relevant portions of subsection 12(1):</ExplanatoryText><ExistingText><Section><Label>12</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Where</Text><Paragraph><Label>. . .</Label><Text><?xm-replace_text Text?></Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>any person proposes to erect, alter, extend or demolish a building or other work on public lands in the National Capital Region, or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>. . .</Label><Text><?xm-replace_text Type new Text here ?></Text></Paragraph><ContinuedSectionSubsection><Text>the department or person shall, prior to the commencement of the project, submit a proposal therefor to the Commission for approval.</Text></ContinuedSectionSubsection></Subsection></Section></ExistingText></ExplanatoryNote></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>3</Label><Text>The Act is amended by adding the following after section 12.2:</Text><AmendedText change="ins"><Section><MarginalNote>Application of standards</MarginalNote><Label>12.3</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Any erection, alteration or extension of a building or work of national significance located in the National Capital Region must be carried out in a manner consistent with the <XRefExternal reference-type="standard">Standards and Guidelines for the Conservation of Historic Places in Canada</XRefExternal>, published by Parks Canada, as amended from time to time.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>National historic sites</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>If an alteration or extension of a building or work referred to in subsection (1) relates to a national historic site as defined in subsection 2(1) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Parks Canada Agency Act</XRefExternal>, that alteration or extension must be carried out in a manner that preserves the commemorative integrity of the national historic site.</Text></Subsection></Section></AmendedText><ExplanatoryNote><Label><Emphasis style="italic">Clause 3</Emphasis>:</Label><ExplanatoryText>New.</ExplanatoryText></ExplanatoryNote></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>4</Label><Text>Section 20 of the Act is amended by adding the following after subsection (2):</Text><AmendedText change="ins"><Subsection><MarginalNote>Regulations</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>The Governor in Council may make regulations prescribing anything that, by this Act, is to be prescribed.</Text></Subsection></AmendedText><ExplanatoryNote><Label><Emphasis style="italic">Clause 4</Emphasis>:</Label><ExplanatoryText>New.</ExplanatoryText></ExplanatoryNote></Section></Body></Bill>