<Bill bill-origin="senate" bill-type="private-public" xml:lang="en" date-time="2017-10-19 13:04:37"><Identification><BillNumber>S-204</BillNumber><Parliament><Session>1</Session><Number>43</Number><RegnalYear><Year-s>68</Year-s><Monarch>Elizabeth II</Monarch></RegnalYear><Year-s>2019</Year-s></Parliament><LongTitle>An Act to amend the Criminal Code and the Immigration and Refugee Protection Act (trafficking in human organs)</LongTitle><ShortTitle status="unofficial" /><RunningHead>An Act to amend the Criminal Code and the Immigration and Refugee Protection Act (trafficking in human organs)</RunningHead><BillHistory><Stages stage="first-reading-senate"><Date><YYYY>2019</YYYY><MM>12</MM><DD>10</DD></Date></Stages></BillHistory><BillSponsor>Senator Ataullahjan</BillSponsor><BillRefNumber date-time="">4211721</BillRefNumber></Identification><Introduction><Summary><TitleText>SUMMARY</TitleText><Provision><Text>This enactment amends the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Criminal Code</XRefExternal> to create new offences in relation to trafficking in human organs. It also amends the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Immigratiand Refugee Protection Act </XRefExternal>to provide that a permanent resident or foreign national is inadmissible to Canada if the Minister of Citizenship and Immigration is of the opinion that they have engaged in any activities relating to trafficking in human organs.</Text></Provision></Summary><Enacts><Provision><Text>Her Majesty, by and with the advice and consent of the Senate and House of Commons of Canada, <Keep>enacts</Keep> as follows:</Text></Provision></Enacts></Introduction><Body><Heading level="1"> <MarginalNote><HistoricalNote>R.S., c. C-46</HistoricalNote></MarginalNote><TitleText><XRefExternal reference-type="act">Criminal Code</XRefExternal></TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><Label>1</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Section 7 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Criminal Code</XRefExternal> is amended by adding the following after subsection (4.11):</Text><AmendedText change="ins"><Subsection><MarginalNote>Offence outside Canada</MarginalNote><Label>(4.2)</Label><Text>Despite anything in this Act or any other Act, a person who commits an act or omission outside Canada that, if committed in Canada, would be an offence under section 240.1 is deemed to commit that act or omission in Canada if the person is a Canadian citizen or a permanent resident within the meaning of subsection 2(1) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Immigration and Refugee Protection Act.</XRefExternal></Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Subsection 7(4.3) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><Subsection><MarginalNote>Consent of Attorney General</MarginalNote><Label>(4.3)</Label><Text>Proceedings with respect to an act or omission deemed to have been committed in Canada under subsection (4.1) <Ins>or (4.2)</Ins> may only be instituted with the consent of the Attorney General.</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Subsection><ExplanatoryNote><TitleText><XRefExternal reference-type="act">Criminal Code</XRefExternal></TitleText><Label><Emphasis style="italic">Clause 1</Emphasis>:</Label><ExplanatoryText>Existing text of subsections 7(4.2) and (4.3):</ExplanatoryText><ExistingText><Subsection><Label>(4.2)</Label><Text>[Repealed, 2002, c. 13, s. 3]</Text></Subsection><Subsection><Label>(4.3)</Label><Text>Proceedings with respect to an act or omission deemed to have been committed in Canada under subsection (4.1) may only be instituted with the consent of the Attorney General.</Text></Subsection></ExistingText></ExplanatoryNote></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>2</Label><Text>The Act is amended by adding the following after section 240:</Text><AmendedText change="ins"><Heading level="1"><TitleText>Trafficking in Human Organs</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Removal without informed consent</MarginalNote><Label>240.1</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Everyone commits an offence who</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>obtains an organ to be transplanted into their body or into the body of another person, knowing that the person from whom it was removed or a person lawfully authorized to consent on behalf of the person from whom it was removed did not give informed consent to the removal, or being reckless as to whether or not such consent was given;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>carries out, participates in or facilitates the removal of an organ from the body of another person, knowing that the person from whom it was removed or a person lawfully authorized to consent on behalf of the person from whom it was removed did not give informed consent to the removal, or being reckless as to whether or not such consent was given; or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(c)</Label><Text>does anything in connection with the removal of an organ from the body of another person on behalf of, at the direction of or in association with the person who removes the organ, knowing that the person from whom it was removed or a person lawfully authorized to consent on behalf of the person from whom it was removed did not give informed consent to the removal, or being reckless as to whether or not such consent was given.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Financial transaction</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Everyone commits an offence who obtains or participates in or facilitates the obtaining of an organ from the body of another person for the purposes of having that organ transplanted into their body or the body of another person, knowing that it was obtained for consideration or being reckless as to whether or not it was obtained for consideration.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Punishment</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>Everyone who commits an offence under subsection (1) or (2) is guilty of an indictable offence and liable to imprisonment for a term of not more than 14 years.</Text></Subsection></Section></AmendedText><ExplanatoryNote><Label><Emphasis style="italic">Clause 2</Emphasis>:</Label><ExplanatoryText>New.</ExplanatoryText></ExplanatoryNote></Section><Heading level="1"> <MarginalNote><HistoricalNote>2001, c. 27</HistoricalNote></MarginalNote><TitleText><XRefExternal reference-type="act">Immigration and Refugee Protection Act</XRefExternal></TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><Label>3</Label><Text>Subsection 35(1) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Immigration and Refugee Protection Act</XRefExternal> is amended by adding the following after paragraph (c):</Text><AmendedText change="ins"><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(c.1)</Label><Text>having engaged in conduct that would, in the opinion of the Minister, constitute an offence under section 240.1 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Criminal Code</XRefExternal>;</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText><ExplanatoryNote><TitleText><XRefExternal reference-type="act">Immigration and Refugee Protection Act</XRefExternal></TitleText><Label><Emphasis style="italic">Clause 3</Emphasis>:</Label><ExplanatoryText>Text of relevant portion of subsection 35(1):</ExplanatoryText><ExistingText><Section><Label>35</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>A permanent resident or a foreign national is inadmissible on grounds of violating human or international rights for</Text><Paragraph><Label>. . .</Label><Text><?xm-replace_text Text?></Text></Paragraph></Subsection></Section></ExistingText></ExplanatoryNote></Section></Body></Bill>