<Bill bill-origin="senate" bill-type="private-public" xml:lang="en" date-time="2016-11-03 11:42:05"><Identification><BillNumber>S-210</BillNumber><Parliament><Session>1</Session><Number>43</Number><RegnalYear><Year-s>68</Year-s><Monarch>Elizabeth II</Monarch></RegnalYear><Year-s>2019-2020</Year-s></Parliament><LongTitle>An Act to amend the Parliament of Canada Act (Parliamentary Visual Artist Laureate)</LongTitle><ShortTitle status="unofficial" /><RunningHead>An Act to amend the Parliament of Canada Act (Parliamentary Visual Artist Laureate)</RunningHead><BillHistory><Stages stage="first-reading-senate"><Date><YYYY>2020</YYYY><MM>2</MM><DD>4</DD></Date></Stages></BillHistory><BillSponsor>Senator Bovey</BillSponsor><BillRefNumber date-time="">4211618</BillRefNumber></Identification><Introduction><Summary><TitleText>SUMMARY</TitleText><Provision><Text>This enactment creates the position of Parliamentary Visual Artist Laureate. It also corrects a reference to the Canada Council for the Arts in the English version of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Parliament of Canada Act</XRefExternal>.</Text></Provision></Summary><Enacts><Provision><Text>Her Majesty, by and with the advice and consent of the Senate and House of Commons of Canada, <Keep>enacts</Keep> as follows:</Text></Provision></Enacts></Introduction><Body><Heading level="1"><MarginalNote><HistoricalNote>R.S., c. P-1</HistoricalNote></MarginalNote><TitleText>Parliament of Canada Act</TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><Label>1</Label><Text>The <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Parliament of Canada Act</XRefExternal> is amended by adding the following after section 75:</Text><AmendedText><Section><MarginalNote>Parliamentary Visual Artist Laureate</MarginalNote><Label>75.01</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>There is hereby established the position of Parliamentary Visual Artist Laureate, the holder of which is an officer of the Library of Parliament.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Selection</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The Speaker of the Senate and the Speaker of the House of Commons, acting together, shall select the Parliamentary Visual Artist Laureate from a list of three names, reflecting Canada’s diversity, submitted in confidence by a committee chaired by the Parliamentary Librarian, and also composed of the Director of the National Gallery of Canada, the Commissioner of Official Languages for Canada, the Chairperson of the Canada Council for the Arts and the President of the Royal Canadian Academy of Arts, or their designates.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Tenure of office</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>The Parliamentary Visual Artist Laureate holds office for a term not exceeding two years, at the pleasure of the Speaker of the Senate and the Speaker of the House of Commons acting together.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Mandate</MarginalNote><Label>(4)</Label><Text>The mandate of the Parliamentary Visual Artist Laureate is to promote the arts in Canada, through <Keep svc="1">Parliament,</Keep> including by fostering knowledge, enjoyment, awareness and development of the arts.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Powers</MarginalNote><Label>(5)</Label><Text>In carrying out his or her mandate, the Parliamentary Visual Artist Laureate may</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>produce or cause to be produced artistic creations, at the request of either Speaker, especially for use in Parliament on occasions of state;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>sponsor artistic events, including art exhibitions;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(c)</Label><Text>give advice to the Parliamentary Librarian regarding the collection of the Library and acquisitions to enrich its cultural holdings; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(d)</Label><Text>perform such other related duties as are requested by either Speaker or the Parliamentary Librarian.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Definition of <DefinedTermEn>arts</DefinedTermEn></MarginalNote><Label>(6)</Label><Text>In this section, <DefinedTermEn>arts</DefinedTermEn> means drawing, painting, sculpture, printmaking, design, crafts, photography, videography and filmmaking.</Text></Subsection></Section></AmendedText><ExplanatoryNote><TitleText><XRefExternal reference-type="act">Parliament of Canada Act</XRefExternal></TitleText><Label><Emphasis style="italic">Clause 1</Emphasis>:</Label><ExplanatoryText>New.</ExplanatoryText></ExplanatoryNote></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>2</Label><Text>Subsection 75.1(2) of the English version of the Act is replaced by the following : </Text><AmendedText><Subsection><MarginalNote>Selection</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The Speaker of the Senate and the Speaker of the House of Commons, acting together, shall select the Parliamentary Poet Laureate from a list of three names submitted in confidence by a committee chaired by the Parliamentary Librarian and also composed of the Librarian and Archivist of Canada, the Commissioner of Official Languages for Canada and the Chair of the Canada Council <Ins>for the Arts</Ins>.</Text></Subsection></AmendedText><ExplanatoryNote><Label><Emphasis style="italic">Clause 2</Emphasis>:</Label><ExplanatoryText>Existing text of subsection 75.1(2):</ExplanatoryText><ExistingText><Subsection><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The Speaker of the Senate and the Speaker of the House of Commons, acting together, shall select the Parliamentary Poet Laureate from a list of three names submitted in confidence by a committee chaired by the Parliamentary Librarian and also composed of the Librarian and Archivist of Canada, the Commissioner of Official Languages for Canada and the Chair of the Canada Council.</Text></Subsection></ExistingText></ExplanatoryNote></Section></Body></Bill>