<?xml version="1.0"?>
<Bill RHead_reign="55-56 Eliz. II" RHead_ParlYear="2006-2007" DocumentTitle="BILL C-18" Bill_No="C-18" Document_No="90347" xml:lang="EN" Bill_Type="Non-amending" Stage_Name="Assented-to" Reprint="No" xml:space="preserve" ChapterNo_E="C. 22" ChapterNo_F="ch. 22" Bill-Origin="commons"><Bill_Part Part_Type="Cover" CountLines="No"><Block><Para TopMargin="24" Size="9" Leading="10" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0" TextAlign="Center">First Session, Thirty-ninth Parliament,</Para></Block><Block><Para Size="9" Leading="10" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0" TextAlign="Center">55-56 Elizabeth II, 2006-2007</Para></Block><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="COV@StatutesTitle">STATUTES OF CANADA 2007<br/>CHAPTER 22</Para></Block><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="CovLongTitle">An Act to amend certain Acts in relation to DNA identification</Para></Block><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="COV_StageLine"></Para></Block><Block><Para BottomMargin="14" Size="11" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0" Bold="Yes" TextAlign="Center">ASSENTED TO</Para></Block><Block><Para Size="8" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0" TextAlign="Center">22nd JUNE, 2007</Para></Block><Block><Para TopMargin="4" Size="8" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0" TextAlign="Center">BILL C-18</Para></Block><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="COV_StageLine"></Para></Block></Bill_Part><Bill_Part CountLines="No" Part_Type="InsideCover"><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="BPT_InsideCoverE">Also available on the Parliament of Canada Web Site at the following address:<br/><B>http://www.parl.gc.ca</B></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><Para TopMargin="108" BottomMargin="4" Size="10" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">SUMMARY</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" Size="8" Leading="9" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">This enactment amends the <I>Criminal Code</I>, the <I>DNA Identification Act</I> and the <I>National Defence Act</I> to facilitate the implementation of <I>An Act to amend the Criminal Code, the DNA Identification Act and the National Defence Act</I>, chapter 25 of the Statutes of Canada, 2005. The enactment makes certain technical changes to those Acts. It also</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" Size="8" Leading="9" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">(<I>a</I>) specifies that the provisions in section 487.051 of the <I>Criminal Code</I> relating to orders for the taking of samples of bodily substances for forensic DNA analysis apply to persons who are sentenced or are discharged under section 730 of, or are found not criminally responsible on account of mental disorder for, designated offences committed at any time, including before June 30, 2000, and makes similar amendments to the <I>National Defence Act</I>;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" Size="8" Leading="9" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">(<I>b</I>) allows an order to be made under section 487.051 of the <I>Criminal Code</I> at a hearing whose date is set within 90 days after the day on which a person is sentenced, discharged under section 730 or found not criminally responsible on account of mental disorder, and makes similar amendments to the <I>National Defence Act</I>;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" Size="8" Leading="9" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">(<I>c</I>) adds attempted murder and conspiracy to commit murder or to cause another person to be murdered to the offences covered by section 487.055 of the <I>Criminal Code</I>;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" Size="8" Leading="9" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">(<I>d</I>) permits an application to be made under section 487.055 of the <I>Criminal Code</I> when a person is still serving a sentence of imprisonment for one of the specified offences, rather than requiring that they be serving a sentence of imprisonment of two years or more for that offence;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" Size="8" Leading="9" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">(<I>e</I>) in certain circumstances, allows a court to require a person who wishes to participate in a hearing relating to an order or authorization under the <I>Criminal Code</I> for the taking of samples of bodily substances for forensic DNA analysis to appear by closed-circuit television or a similar means of communication;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" Size="8" Leading="9" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">(<I>f</I>) allows samples of bodily substances to be taken under the <I>Criminal Code</I> and the <I>National Defence Act</I> at the place, day and time set by an order or a summons or as soon as feasible afterwards;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" Size="8" Leading="9" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">(<I>g</I>) specifies that it is an offence under the <I>Criminal Code</I> and the <I>National Defence Act</I> to fail to comply with such an order or summons;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" Size="8" Leading="9" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">(<I>h</I>) requires the Commissioner of the Royal Canadian Mounted Police to destroy the bodily substances collected under an order or authorization and the information transmitted with them if, in the opinion of the Attorney General or the Director of Military Prosecutions, as the case may be, the offence to which the order or authorization relates is not a designated offence;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" Size="8" Leading="9" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">(<I>i</I>) enables the Commissioner to communicate internationally the information that may be communicated within Canada under subsection 6(1) of the <I>DNA Identification Act</I>; and<PageBreak></PageBreak></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" Size="8" Leading="9" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">(<I>j</I>) allows the Commissioner to communicate information for the purpose of the investigation of criminal offences, and allows the subsequent communication of that information for the purpose of the investigation and prosecution of criminal offences.</Para></Block></Bill_Part><Bill_Part Part_Type="MainText" CountLines="No" RunningHead_E="DNA Identification"><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="MAIN@RoyalAssentTitle">55-56 ELIZABETH II</Para></Block><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="MAIN@RoyalAssentTitle">——————</Para></Block><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="MAIN@RoyalAssentTitle">CHAPTER 22</Para></Block><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="LongTitleAssent">An Act to amend certain Acts in relation to DNA identification</Para></Block><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="MAIN@RoyalAssentDate">[<I>Assented to 22nd June, 2007</I>]</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">Her Majesty, by and with the advice and consent of the Senate and House of Commons of Canada, enacts as follows:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:INTERPRETATION--><Para TopMargin="10" Bold="Yes" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">INTERPRETATION</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Definition of “other Act”<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>1.</B> In this Act, “other Act” means <I>An Act to amend the Criminal Code, the DNA Identification Act and the National Defence Act</I>, chapter 25 of the Statutes of Canada, 2005.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:AMENDMENTS TO THE OTHER ACT--><MarginalNote>2005, c. 25<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="10" Bold="Yes" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">AMENDMENTS TO THE OTHER ACT</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>2.</B> (1) Subsection 1(5.1) of the other Act is repealed.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes">(2) Subsection 1(6.1) of the other Act is repealed.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>3.</B> Section 4 of the other Act is replaced by the following:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>1998, c. 37, s. 17; 2000, c. 10, s. 14; 2002, c. 1, s. 177<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>4.</B> Sections 487.052 and 487.053 of the Act are replaced by the following:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Timing of order<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>487.053</B> (1) The court may make an order under section 487.051 authorizing the taking of samples of bodily substances when it imposes a sentence on a person, finds the person not criminally responsible on account of mental disorder or directs that they be discharged under section 730.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Hearing<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(2) If the court does not consider the matter at that time, it</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>a</I>) shall, within 90 days after the day on which it imposes the sentence, makes the finding or directs that the person be discharged, set a date for a hearing to do so;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>b</I>) retains jurisdiction over the matter; and</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>c</I>) may require the person to appear by closed-circuit television or any other means that allows the court and the person to engage in simultaneous visual and oral communication, as long as the person is given the opportunity to communicate privately with counsel if they are represented by counsel.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>4.</B> Section 7 of the other Act is repealed.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>5.</B> Section 25 of the other Act is replaced by the following:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>2000, c. 10, s. 1<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>25.</B> Sections 196.15 and 196.16 of the Act are replaced by the following:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Timing of order<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>196.16</B> (1) The court martial may make an order under section 196.14 authorizing the taking of samples of bodily substances either when it imposes a sentence on a person or finds them not responsible on account of mental disorder or at a later date if it adjourns the proceedings after it imposes the sentence or makes the finding.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Hearing by new court martial<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(2) If the court martial does not consider the matter at that time,</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>a</I>) the Chief Military Judge shall cause the Court Martial Administrator to convene a court martial to do so;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>b</I>) the Court Martial Administrator shall, within 90 days after the day on which the sentence was imposed or the person was found not responsible on account of mental disorder, convene the court martial; and</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>c</I>) for greater certainty, the person who may be made subject to the order continues to be liable to be dealt with under the Code of Service Discipline for the purpose of the hearing.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Failure to appear<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>196.161</B> (1) If a person fails to appear at the place, day and time set out in an order made under subsection 196.14(4) or 196.24(4), a military judge may issue a warrant in the prescribed form for their arrest to allow samples of bodily substances to be taken.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Warrant in force<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(2) The warrant may be executed anywhere in or outside Canada by a peace officer who has jurisdiction in that place or over the person. The warrant remains in force until it is executed.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>6.</B> Section 30.1 of the other Act is repealed.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:CRIMINAL CODE--><MarginalNote>R.S., c. C-46<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="10" Bold="Yes" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">CRIMINAL CODE</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>2000, c. 10, s. 13<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>7.</B> Subsection 487.03(2) of the <I>Criminal Code</I> is repealed.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>1998, c. 37, s. 15(1)<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>8.</B> (1) Paragraph (<I>b</I>) of the definition “forensic DNA analysis” in section 487.04 of the Act is replaced by the following:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>b</I>) in relation to a bodily substance that is provided voluntarily in the course of an investigation of a designated offence or is taken from a person under an order made under section 487.051 or an authorization granted under section 487.055 or 487.091, or to a bodily substance referred to in paragraph 487.05(1)(<I>b</I>), means forensic DNA analysis of the bodily substance;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes">(2) Paragraph (<I>a</I>) of the definition “primary designated offence” in section 487.04 of the Act, as enacted by subsection 1(4) of the other Act, is amended by striking out the word “and” at the end of subparagraph (xii) and by replacing subparagraph (xiii) with the following:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="4" FirstLineIndent="0">(xiii) subsection 431.2(2) (explosive or other lethal device),</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="4" FirstLineIndent="0">(xiv) section 467.11 (participation in activities of criminal organization),</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="4" FirstLineIndent="0">(xv) section 467.12 (commission of offence for criminal organization), and</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="4" FirstLineIndent="0">(xvi) section 467.13 (instructing commission of offence for criminal organization),</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes">(3) Paragraphs (<I>a</I>) and (<I>b</I>) of the definition “secondary designated offence” in section 487.04 of the Act, as enacted by subsection 1(7) of the other Act, are replaced by the following:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>a</I>) an offence under this Act that may be prosecuted by indictment — or, for section 487.051 to apply, is prosecuted by indictment — for which the maximum punishment is imprisonment for five years or more,</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>b</I>) an offence under any of the following provisions of the <I>Controlled Drugs and Substances Act</I> that may be prosecuted by indictment — or, for section 487.051 to apply, is prosecuted by indictment — for which the maximum punishment is imprisonment for five years or more:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="4" FirstLineIndent="0">(i) section 5 (trafficking in substance and possession for purpose of trafficking),</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="4" FirstLineIndent="0">(ii) section 6 (importing and exporting), and</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="4" FirstLineIndent="0">(iii) section 7 (production of substance),</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes">(4) Subparagraph (<I>c</I>)(i) of the definition “secondary designated offence” in section 487.04 of the Act, as enacted by subsection 1(7) of the other Act, is replaced by the following:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="4" FirstLineIndent="0">(i) section 145 (escape and being at large without excuse),</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="4" FirstLineIndent="0">(i.1) section 146 (permitting or assisting escape),</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="4" FirstLineIndent="0">(i.2) section 147 (rescue or permitting escape),</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="4" FirstLineIndent="0">(i.3) section 148 (assisting prisoner of war to escape),</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="4" FirstLineIndent="0">(i.4) subsection 160(3) (bestiality in pres­ence of or by child),</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes">(5) Paragraph (<I>e</I>) of the definition “secondary designated offence” in section 487.04 of the Act, as enacted by subsection 1(7) of the other Act, is replaced by the following:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>e</I>) an attempt to commit or, other than for the purposes of subsection 487.05(1), a conspiracy to commit</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="4" FirstLineIndent="0">(i) an offence referred to in paragraph (<I>a</I>) or (<I>b</I>) — which, for section 487.051 to apply, is prosecuted by indictment, or</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="4" FirstLineIndent="0">(ii) an offence referred to in paragraph (<I>c</I>) or (<I>d</I>);</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>9.</B> Section 487.051 of the Act, as enacted by section 3 of the other Act, is replaced by the following:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Order — primary designated offences<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>487.051</B> (1) The court shall make an order in Form 5.03 authorizing the taking of the number of samples of bodily substances that is reasonably required for the purpose of forensic DNA analysis from a person who is convicted, discharged under section 730 or found guilty under the <I>Youth Criminal Justice Act</I> or the <I>Young Offenders Act</I>, of an offence committed at any time, including before June 30, 2000, if that offence is a primary designated offence within the meaning of paragraph (<I>a.1</I>) of the definition “primary designated offence” in section 487.04 when the person is sentenced or discharged.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Order — primary designated offences<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(2) The court shall make such an order in Form 5.03 in relation to a person who is convicted, discharged under section 730 or found guilty under the <I>Youth Criminal Justice Act</I> or the <I>Young Offenders Act</I>, of an offence committed at any time, including before June 30, 2000, if that offence is a primary designated offence within the meaning of paragraph (<I>a</I>) or any of paragraphs (<I>b</I>) to (<I>d</I>) of the definition “primary designated offence” in section 487.04 when the person is sentenced or discharged. However, the court is not required to make the order if it is satisfied that the person has established that the impact of such an order on their privacy and security of the person would be grossly disproportionate to the public interest in the protection of society and the proper administration of justice, to be achieved through the early detection, arrest and conviction of offenders.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Order — persons found not criminally responsible and secondary designated offences<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(3) The court may, on application by the prosecutor and if it is satisfied that it is in the best interests of the administration of justice to do so, make such an order in Form 5.04 in relation to</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>a</I>) a person who is found not criminally responsible on account of mental disorder for an offence committed at any time, including before June 30, 2000, if that offence is a designated offence when the finding is made; or</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>b</I>) a person who is convicted, discharged under section 730 or found guilty under the <I>Youth Criminal Justice Act</I> or the <I>Young Offenders Act</I>, of an offence committed at any time, including before June 30, 2000, if that offence is a secondary designated offence when the person is sentenced or discharged.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0">In deciding whether to make the order, the court shall consider the person’s criminal record, whether they were previously found not criminally responsible on account of mental disorder for a designated offence, the nature of the offence, the circumstances surrounding its commission and the impact such an order would have on the person’s privacy and security of the person and shall give reasons for its decision.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Order to offender<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(4) When the court makes an order authorizing the taking of samples of bodily substances, it may make an order in Form 5.041 to require the person to report at the place, day and time set out in the order and submit to the taking of the samples.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>1998, c. 37, s. 17<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>10.</B> Section 487.054 of the Act is replaced by the following:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Appeal<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>487.054</B> The offender or the prosecutor may appeal from a decision of the court under any of subsections 487.051(1) to (3).</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>2005, c. 25, s. 5(1)<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>11.</B> (1) Paragraphs 487.055(1)(<I>d</I>) and (<I>e</I>) of the Act are replaced by the following:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>c.1</I>) had been convicted of attempted murder or conspiracy to commit murder or to cause another person to be murdered and, on the date of the application, is serving a sentence of imprisonment for that offence;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>d</I>) had been convicted of a sexual offence within the meaning of subsection (3) and, on the date of the application, is serving a sentence of imprisonment for that offence; or</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>e</I>) had been convicted of manslaughter and, on the date of the application, is serving a sentence of imprisonment for that offence.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes">(2) Section 487.055 of the Act is amended by adding the following after subsection (3):</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Manner of appearance<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(3.01) The court may require a person who is given notice of an application under subsection (1) and who wishes to appear at the hearing to appear by closed-circuit television or any other means that allows the court and the person to engage in simultaneous visual and oral communication, as long as the person is given the opportunity to communicate privately with counsel if they are represented by counsel.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>1998, c. 37, s. 17<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes">(3) Subsection 487.055(4) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Order<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(3.11) If the court authorizes the taking of samples of bodily substances from a person who is on conditional release and who has appeared at the hearing, it shall make an order in Form 5.041 to require the person to report at the place, day and time set out in the order and submit to the taking of the samples.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Summons<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(4) However, if a person who is on conditional release has not appeared at the hearing, a summons in Form 5.061 setting out the information referred to in paragraphs 487.07(1)(<I>b</I>) to (<I>d</I>) shall be directed to them requiring them to report at the place, day and time set out in the summons and submit to the taking of the samples.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>1998, c. 37, s. 17<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes">(4) Subsections 487.055(7) to (10) of the Act are repealed.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>12.</B> The Act is amended by adding the following after section 487.055:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Failure to appear<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>487.0551</B> (1) If a person fails to appear at the place, day and time set out in an order made under subsection 487.051(4) or 487.055(3.11) or in a summons referred to in subsection 487.055(4) or 487.091(3), a justice of the peace may issue a warrant for their arrest in Form 5.062 to allow samples of bodily substances to be taken.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Execution of warrant<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(2) The warrant may be executed anywhere in Canada by a peace officer who has jurisdiction in that place or over the person. The warrant remains in force until it is executed.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Failure to comply with order or summons<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>487.0552</B> (1) Every person who, without reasonable excuse, fails to comply with an order made under subsection 487.051(4) or 487.055(3.11) of this Act or under subsection 196.14(4) or 196.24(4) of the <I>National Defence Act</I>, or with a summons referred to in subsection 487.055(4) or 487.091(3) of this Act, is guilty of</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>a</I>) an indictable offence and liable to imprisonment for a term of not more than two years; or</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>b</I>) an offence punishable on summary conviction.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>For greater certainty<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(2) For greater certainty, a lawful command that prevents a person from complying with an order or summons is a reasonable excuse if, at the time, the person is subject to the Code of Service Discipline within the meaning of subsection 2(1) of the <I>National Defence Act</I>.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>13.</B> (1) Subsection 487.056(1) of the Act, as enacted by section 6 of the other Act, is replaced by the following:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>When collection to take place<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>487.056</B> (1) Samples of bodily substances shall be taken as authorized under section 487.051</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>a</I>) at the place, day and time set out in an order made under subsection 487.051(4) or as soon as feasible afterwards; or</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>b</I>) in any other case, on the day on which the order authorizing the taking of the samples is made or as soon as feasible afterwards.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>1998, c. 37, s. 17; 2000, c. 10, s. 16(1)<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes">(2) Subsections 487.056(2) and (3) of the Act are replaced by the following:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>When collection to take place<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(2) Samples of bodily substances shall be taken as authorized under section 487.055 or 487.091</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>a</I>) at the place, day and time set out in an order made under subsection 487.055(3.11) or a summons referred to in subsection 487.055(4) or 487.091(3) or as soon as feasible afterwards; or</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>b</I>) in any other case, as soon as feasible after the authorization is granted.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>When collection to take place<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(3) If a person fails to appear as required by an order made under subsection 487.051(4) or 487.055(3.11) or a summons referred to in subsection 487.055(4) or 487.091(3), samples of bodily substances shall be taken</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>a</I>) when the person is arrested under a warrant issued under subsection 487.0551(1) or as soon as feasible afterwards; or</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>b</I>) as soon as feasible after the person appears at the place set out in the order or summons if no warrant is issued.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Appeal<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(4) Subsections (1) to (3) apply even if the order or authorization to take the samples of bodily substances is appealed.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Collection of samples<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(5) A peace officer who is authorized under section 487.051, 487.055 or 487.091 to take samples of bodily substances may cause the samples to be taken in any place in Canada in which the person who is subject to the order or authorization is located.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Who collects samples<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(6) The samples shall be taken by a peace officer who has jurisdiction over the person or in the place in which the samples are taken — or a person acting under their direction — who is able, by virtue of training or experience, to take them.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>2000, c. 10, s. 17<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>14.</B> (1) Subsection 487.057(1) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Report of peace officer<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>487.057</B> (1) A peace officer who takes samples of bodily substances from a person or who causes a person who is not a peace officer to take samples under their direction shall, as soon as feasible after the samples are taken, make a written report in Form 5.07 and cause the report to be filed with</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>a</I>) the provincial court judge who issued the warrant under section 487.05 or granted the authorization under section 487.055 or 487.091 or another judge of that provincial court; or</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>b</I>) the court that made the order under section 487.051.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes">(2) Section 487.057 of the Act is amended by adding the following after subsection (2):</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Copy of report<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(3) A peace officer who takes the samples or causes the samples to be taken under their direction at the request of another peace officer shall send a copy of the report to the other peace officer unless that other peace officer had jurisdiction to take the samples.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>2000, c. 10, s. 18<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>15.</B> Section 487.058 of the Act is replaced by the following:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>No criminal or civil liability<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>487.058</B> No peace officer, and no person acting under a peace officer’s direction, incurs any criminal or civil liability for anything necessarily done with reasonable care and skill in the taking of samples of bodily substances from a person under a warrant issued under section 487.05, an order made under section 487.051 or an authorization granted under section 487.055 or 487.091.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>2000, c. 10, s. 19(1)<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>16.</B> (1) The portion of subsection 487.06(1) of the Act before paragraph (<I>a</I>) is replaced by the following:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Investigative procedures<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>487.06</B> (1) A peace officer or a person acting under a peace officer’s direction is authorized by a warrant issued under section 487.05, an order made under section 487.051 or an authorization granted under section 487.055 or 487.091 to take samples of bodily substances by any of the following means:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>2000, c. 10, s. 19(2)<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes">(2) Subsection 487.06(3) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Fingerprints<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(3) A peace officer who is authorized to take samples of bodily substances from a person by an order made under section 487.051 or an authorization granted under section 487.055 or 487.091, or a person acting under their direction, may take fingerprints from the person for the purpose of the <I>DNA Identification Act</I>.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>2000, c. 10, s. 20(1)<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>17.</B> The portion of subsection 487.07(1) of the Act before paragraph (<I>a</I>) is replaced by the following:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Duty to inform<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>487.07</B> (1) Before taking samples of bodily substances from a person, or causing samples to be taken under their direction, in execution of a warrant issued under section 487.05 or an order made under section 487.051 or under an authorization granted under section 487.055 or 487.091, a peace officer shall inform the person of</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>18.</B> (1) Subsection 487.071(1) of the Act, as enacted by section 8 of the other Act, is replaced by the following:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Verification<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>487.071</B> (1) Before taking samples of bodily substances from a person under an order made under section 487.051 or an authorization granted under section 487.055 or 487.091, a peace officer, or a person acting under their direction, shall verify whether the convicted offenders index of the national DNA data bank, established under the <I>DNA Identification Act</I>, contains the person’s DNA profile.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes">(2) Paragraph 487.071(2)(<I>b</I>) of the English version of the Act, as enacted by section 8 of the other Act, is replaced by the following:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>b</I>) transmit a copy of the order or authorization containing that confirmation and any other information prescribed by regulations made under the <I>DNA Identification Act</I> to the Commissioner of the Royal Canadian Mounted Police.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>19.</B> Subsection 487.08(1.1) of the Act, as enacted by subsection 9(1) of the other Act, is replaced by the following:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Use of bodily substances — order, authorization<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(1.1) No person shall use bodily substances that are taken in execution of an order made under section 487.051 of this Act or section 196.14 of the <I>National Defence Act</I>, or under an authorization granted under section 487.055 or 487.091 of this Act or section 196.24 of the <I>National Defence Act</I>, except to transmit them to the Commissioner of the Royal Canadian Mounted Police for the purpose of forensic DNA analysis in accordance with the <I>DNA Identification Act</I>.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>20.</B> (1) Paragraph 487.091(1)(<I>a</I>) of the Act, as enacted by section 10 of the other Act, is replaced by the following:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>a</I>) a DNA profile cannot be derived from the bodily substances that were taken from that person under an order made under section 487.051 or an authorization granted under section 487.055; or</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes">(2) Paragraph 487.091(1)(<I>b</I>) of the English version of the Act, as enacted by section 10 of the other Act, is replaced by the following:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>b</I>) the information or bodily substances required by regulations made under the <I>DNA Identification Act</I> were not transmitted in accordance with the requirements of the regulations or were lost.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes">(3) Subsection 487.091(2) of the English version of the Act, as enacted by section 10 of the other Act, is replaced by the following:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Reasons<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(2) The application shall state the reasons why a DNA profile cannot be derived from the bodily substances or why the information or bodily substances were not transmitted in accordance with the regulations or were lost.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>2000, c. 10, s. 23<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes">(4) Subsection 487.091(3) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Persons not in custody<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(3) If the court authorizes the taking of samples of bodily substances from a person who is not in custody, a summons in Form 5.061 setting out the information referred to in paragraphs 487.07(1)(<I>b</I>) to (<I>d</I>) shall be directed to the person requiring them to report at the place, day and time set out in the summons and submit to the taking of the samples. Subsections 487.055(5) and (6) apply, with any modifications that the circumstances require.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>21.</B> (1) Subsection 487.0911(1) of the Act, as enacted by section 11 of the other Act, is replaced by the following:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Review by Attorney General<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>487.0911</B> (1) On receipt of a notice from the Commissioner of the Royal Canadian Mounted Police under subsection 5.2(1) of the <I>DNA Identification Act</I> that an order made under section 487.051 or an authorization granted under section 487.091 appears to be defective, the Attorney General shall review the order or authorization and the court record.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes">(2) The portion of subsection 487.0911(2) of the English version of the Act before paragraph (<I>a</I>), as enacted by section 11 of the other Act, is replaced by the following:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Clerical error<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(2) If the Attorney General is of the opinion that the defect is due to a clerical error, the Attorney General shall</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes">(3) Subsection 487.0911(3) of the Act, as enacted by section 11 of the other Act, is replaced by the following:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Substantive defect<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(3) If the Attorney General is of the opinion that the offence referred to in the order or authorization is not a designated offence, the Attorney General shall inform the Commissioner of that opinion.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>R.S., c. 27 (1st Supp.), s. 149<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>22.</B> Subsection 703(2) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Warrant effective in a province<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(2) Despite any other provision of this Act but subject to subsections 487.0551(2) and 705(3), a warrant of arrest or committal that is issued by a justice or provincial court judge may be executed anywhere in the province in which it is issued.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>23.</B> Forms 5.03 to 5.06 in Part XXVIII of the Act, as enacted by section 12 of the other Act, are replaced by the following:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><Para TopMargin="10" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">FORM 5.03 </Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><Para LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0" Italic="Yes" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">(Subsections 487.051(1) and (2))</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:ORDER AUTHORIZING THE TAKING OF BODILY SUBSTANCES FOR FORENSIC DNA ANALYSIS--><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">ORDER AUTHORIZING THE TAKING OF BODILY SUBSTANCES FOR FORENSIC DNA ANALYSIS</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">Canada</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">Province of ................</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">(<I>territorial division</I>)</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">To the peace officers in (<I>territorial division</I>):</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">Whereas (<I>name of offender</I>) has been convicted under the <I>Criminal Code</I>, discharged under section 730 of that Act or, in the case of a young person, found guilty under the <I>Young Offenders Act</I>, chapter Y-1 of the Revised Statutes of Canada, 1985, or the <I>Youth Criminal Justice Act</I> of (<I>offence</I>), which, on the day on which the offender was sentenced or discharged, was a primary designated offence within the meaning of section 487.04 of the <I>Criminal Code</I>;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">Therefore, you are authorized to take or cause to be taken from (<I>name of offender</I>) the number of samples of bodily substances that is reasonably required for forensic DNA analysis, provided that the person taking the samples is able, by virtue of training or experience, to take them by means of the investigative procedures described in subsection 487.06(1) of the <I>Criminal Code</I> and that, if the person taking the samples is not a peace officer, they take them under the direction of a peace officer.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">This order is subject to the following terms and conditions that I consider advisable to ensure that the taking of the samples is reasonable in the circumstances:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">Dated this ................ day of ................ ,</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify"><keep>A.D. ........ ,</keep> at ................ .</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No" KeepWith="Next"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Center">............................................</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="0" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Center">(<I>Signature of judge of the court</I>)</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><Para TopMargin="10" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">FORM 5.04 </Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><Para LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0" Italic="Yes" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">(Subsection 487.051(3))</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:ORDER AUTHORIZING THE TAKING OF BODILY SUBSTANCES FOR FORENSIC DNA ANALYSIS--><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">ORDER AUTHORIZING THE TAKING OF BODILY SUBSTANCES FOR FORENSIC DNA ANALYSIS</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">Canada</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">Province of .................</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">(<I>territorial division</I>)</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">To the peace officers in (<I>territorial division</I>):</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">Whereas (<I>name of offender</I>), in this order called the “offender”,</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">(<I>a</I>) has been found not criminally responsible on account of mental disorder for (<I>offence</I>), which, on the day on which the finding was made, was a primary designated offence within the meaning of section 487.04 of the <I>Criminal Code</I>, or</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">(<I>b</I>) has been convicted under the <I>Criminal Code</I>, discharged under section 730 of that Act or, in the case of a young person, found guilty under the <I>Young Offenders Act</I>, chapter Y-1 of the Revised Statutes of Canada, 1985, or the <I>Youth Criminal Justice Act</I>, of, or has been found not criminally responsible on account of mental disorder for, (<I>offence</I>), which, on the day on which the offender was sentenced or discharged or the finding was made, was one of the following secondary designated offences within the meaning of section 487.04 of the <I>Criminal Code</I> (<I>check applicable box</I>):</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="5" FirstLineIndent="-3" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">[ ] <Tab/>(i) an offence under the <I>Criminal Code</I> for which the maximum punishment is imprisonment for five years or more and that was prosecuted by indictment,</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="5" FirstLineIndent="-3" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">[ ] <Tab/>(ii) an offence under any of sections 5 to 7 of the <I>Controlled Drugs and Substances Act</I> for which the maximum punishment is imprisonment for five years or more and that was prosecuted by indictment,</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="5" FirstLineIndent="-3" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">[ ] <Tab/>(iii) an offence under any of sections 145 to 148, subsection 160(3), sections 170, 173, 252, 264, 264.1, 266 and 270, paragraph 348(1)(<I>e</I>) and sections 349 and 423 of the <I>Criminal Code</I>,</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="5" FirstLineIndent="-3" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">[ ] <Tab/>(iv) an offence under section 433 or 434 of the <I>Criminal Code</I> as that section read from time to time before July 1, 1990, or</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="5" FirstLineIndent="-3" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">[ ] <Tab/>(v) an attempt or a conspiracy to commit an offence referred to in subparagraph (i) or (ii) that was prosecuted by indictment (<I>or, if applicable,</I> an attempt or a conspiracy to commit an offence referred to in subparagraph (iii) or (iv));</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">Whereas I have considered the offender’s criminal record, the nature of the offence, the circumstances surrounding its commission, whether the offender was previously found not criminally responsible on account of mental disorder for a designated offence, and the impact that this order would have on the offender’s privacy and security of the person;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">And whereas I am satisfied that it is in the best interests of the administration of justice to make this order;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">Therefore, you are authorized to take or cause to be taken from (<I>name of offender</I>) the number of samples of bodily substances that is reasonably required for forensic DNA analysis, provided that the person taking the samples is able, by virtue of training or experience, to take them by means of the investigative procedures described in subsection 487.06(1) of the <I>Criminal Code</I> and that, if the person taking the samples is not a peace officer, they take them under the direction of a peace officer.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">This order is subject to the following terms and conditions that I consider advisable to ensure that the taking of the samples is reasonable in the circumstances:<PageBreak></PageBreak></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">Dated this ................ day of ................, <keep>A.D. ........ ,</keep> at ................ .</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No" KeepWith="Next"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Center">........................................</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="0" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Center">(<I>Signature of judge of the court</I>)</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><Para TopMargin="10" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">FORM 5.041 </Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><Para LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0" Italic="Yes" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">(Subsections 487.051(4) and 487.055(3.11))</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:ORDER TO A PERSON TO HAVE BODILY SUBSTANCES TAKEN FOR FORENSIC DNA ANALYSIS--><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">ORDER TO A PERSON TO HAVE BODILY SUBSTANCES TAKEN FOR FORENSIC DNA ANALYSIS</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">Canada</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">Province of ................</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">(<I>territorial division</I>)</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">To A.B., of ................ ,</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">Whereas an order has been made under section 487.051, or an authorization has been granted under section 487.055, of the <I>Criminal Code</I>, to take from you the number of samples of bodily substances that is reasonably required for forensic DNA analysis;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">This is therefore to command you, in Her Majesty’s name, to appear on ................ , the ................ day of ................ , A.D. ........ , at ............ o’clock, at ................ , for the purpose of the taking of bodily substances by means of the investigative procedures set out in subsection 487.06(1) of the <I>Criminal Code</I>.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">You are warned that failure to appear in accordance with this order may result in a warrant being issued for your arrest under subsection 487.0551(1) of the <I>Criminal Code</I>. You are also warned that failure to appear, without reasonable excuse, is an offence under subsection 487.0552(1) of that Act.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">Subsection 487.0551(1) of the <I>Criminal Code</I> states as follows:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify"><B>487.0551</B> (1) If a person fails to appear at the place, day and time set out in an order made under subsection 487.051(4) or 487.055(3.11) or in a summons referred to in subsection 487.055(4) or 487.091(3), a justice of the peace may issue a warrant for their arrest in Form 5.062 to allow samples of bodily substances to be taken.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">Subsection 487.0552(1) of the <I>Criminal Code</I> states as follows:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify"><B>487.0552</B> (1) Every person who, without reasonable excuse, fails to comply with an order made under subsection 487.051(4) or 487.055(3.11) of this Act or under subsection 196.14(4) or 196.24(4) of the <I>National Defence Act</I>, or with a summons referred to in subsection 487.055(4) or 487.091(3) of this Act, is guilty of</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">(<I>a</I>) an indictable offence and liable to imprisonment for a term of not more than two years; or</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">(<I>b</I>) an offence punishable on summary conviction.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">Dated this ................ day of ................ , <keep>A.D. ........ ,</keep> at ................ .</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No" KeepWith="Next"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Center">...........................................</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="0" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Center">(<I>Signature of judge of the court</I>)</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><Para TopMargin="10" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">FORM 5.05 </Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><Para LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0" Italic="Yes" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">(Subsection 487.055(1))</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:APPLICATION FOR AN AUTHORIZATION TO TAKE BODILY SUBSTANCES FOR FORENSIC DNA ANALYSIS--><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">APPLICATION FOR AN AUTHORIZATION TO TAKE BODILY SUBSTANCES FOR FORENSIC DNA ANALYSIS</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">Canada</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">Province of ................</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">(<I>territorial division</I>)</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">I (<I>name of peace officer</I>), (<I>occupation</I>), <keep>of ..........</keep> in (<I>territorial division</I>), apply for an authorization to take bodily substances for forensic DNA analysis. A certificate referred to in paragraph 667(1)(<I>a</I>) of the <I>Criminal Code</I> is filed with this application.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">Whereas (<I>name of offender</I>), before June 30, 2000,</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">(<I>a</I>) had been declared a dangerous offender under Part XXIV of the <I>Criminal Code</I>,</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">(<I>b</I>) had been declared a dangerous offender or a dangerous sexual offender under Part XXI of the <I>Criminal Code</I>, chapter C-34 of the Revised Statutes of Canada, 1970, as it read from time to time before January 1, 1988,</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">(<I>c</I>) had been convicted of murder,</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">(<I>c.1</I>) had been convicted of attempted murder or conspiracy to commit murder or to cause another person to be murdered and is currently serving a sentence of imprisonment for that offence,</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">(<I>d</I>) had been convicted of a sexual offence within the meaning of subsection 487.055(3) of the <I>Criminal Code</I> and is currently serving a sentence of imprisonment for that offence, or</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">(<I>e</I>) had been convicted of manslaughter and is currently serving a sentence of imprisonment for that offence;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">Therefore, I request that an authorization be granted under subsection 487.055(1) of the <I>Criminal Code</I> to take from (<I>name of offender</I>) the number of samples of bodily substances that is reasonably required for forensic DNA analysis, provided that the person taking the samples is able, by virtue of training or experience, to take them by means of the investigative procedures described in subsection 487.06(1) of the <I>Criminal Code</I> and that, if the person taking the samples is not a peace officer, they take them under the direction of a peace officer.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">Dated this ................ day of ................ , <keep>A.D. ......</keep> , at ............... .</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No" KeepWith="Next"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Center">.........................................</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="0" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Center">(<I>Signature of applicant</I>)</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><Para TopMargin="10" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">FORM 5.06 </Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><Para LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0" Italic="Yes" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">(Subsection 487.055(1))</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:AUTHORIZATION TO TAKE BODILY SUBSTANCES FOR FORENSIC DNA ANALYSIS--><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">AUTHORIZATION TO TAKE BODILY SUBSTANCES FOR FORENSIC DNA ANALYSIS</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">Canada</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">Province of ................</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">(<I>territorial division</I>)</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">To the peace officers in (<I>territorial division</I>):</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">Whereas (<I>name of peace officer</I>), a peace officer in (<I>territorial division</I>), has applied for an authorization to take the number of samples of bodily substances from (<I>name of offender</I>) that is reasonably required for forensic DNA analysis by means of the investigative procedures described in subsection 487.06(1) of the <I>Criminal Code</I>;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">Whereas (<I>name of offender</I>), before June 30, 2000,</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">(<I>a</I>) had been declared a dangerous offender under Part XXIV of the <I>Criminal Code</I>,</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">(<I>b</I>) had been declared a dangerous offender or a dangerous sexual offender under Part XXI of the <I>Criminal Code</I>, chapter C-34 of the Revised Statutes of Canada, 1970, as it read from time to time before January 1, 1988,</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">(<I>c</I>) had been convicted of murder,</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">(<I>c.1</I>) had been convicted of attempted murder or conspiracy to commit murder or to cause another person to be murdered and, on the date of the application, was serving a sentence of imprisonment for that offence,</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">(<I>d</I>) had been convicted of a sexual offence within the meaning of subsection 487.055(3) of the <I>Criminal Code</I> and, on the date of the application, was serving a sentence of imprisonment for that offence, or</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">(<I>e</I>) had been convicted of manslaughter and, on the date of the application, was serving a sentence of imprisonment for that offence;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">And whereas I have considered the offender’s criminal record, the nature of the offence, the circumstances surrounding its commission and the impact that this authorization would have on the offender’s privacy and security of the person;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">Therefore, you are authorized to take those samples or cause them to be taken from (<I>name of offender</I>), provided that the person taking the samples is able, by virtue of training or experience, to take them by means of the investigative procedures described in subsection 487.06(1) of the <I>Criminal Code</I> and that, if the person taking the samples is not a peace officer, they take them under the direction of a peace officer.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">This authorization is subject to the following terms and conditions that I consider advisable to ensure that the taking of the samples is reasonable in the circumstances:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">Dated this ................ day of ................ , A.D., at ................ .</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No" KeepWith="Next"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Center">........................................</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="0" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Center">(<I>Signature of provincial court judge</I>)</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><Para TopMargin="10" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">FORM 5.061 </Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><Para LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0" Italic="Yes" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">(Subsections 487.055(4) and 487.091(3))</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:SUMMONS TO A PERSON TO HAVE BODILY SUBSTANCES TAKEN FOR FORENSIC DNA ANALYSIS--><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">SUMMONS TO A PERSON TO HAVE BODILY SUBSTANCES TAKEN FOR FORENSIC DNA ANALYSIS</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">Canada</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">Province of ................</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">(<I>territorial division</I>)</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">To A.B., of ................ ,</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">Whereas an authorization has been granted under section 487.055 or 487.091 of the <I>Criminal Code</I> to take from you the number of samples of bodily substances that is reasonably required for forensic DNA analysis;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">This is therefore to command you, in Her Majesty’s name, to appear on ................ , <keep>the ................</keep> day of ................ , A.D. ........ , <keep>at ............</keep> o’clock, at ................ , for the purpose of the taking of bodily substances by means of the investigative procedures set out in subsection 487.06(1) of the <I>Criminal Code</I>. A peace officer, or a person who is acting under a peace officer’s direction, who takes the samples of bodily substances may use as much force as necessary to do so.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">You are warned that failure to appear in accordance with this summons may result in a warrant being issued for your arrest under subsection 487.0551(1) of the <I>Criminal Code</I>. You are also warned that failure to appear, without reasonable excuse, is an offence under subsection 487.0552(1) of that Act.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">Subsection 487.0551(1) of the <I>Criminal Code</I> states as follows:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify"><B>487.0551</B> (1) If a person fails to appear at the place, day and time set out in an order made under subsection 487.051(4) or 487.055(3.11) or in a summons referred to in subsection 487.055(4) or 487.091(3), a justice of the peace may issue a warrant for their arrest in Form 5.062 to allow samples of bodily substances to be taken.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">Subsection 487.0552(1) of the <I>Criminal Code</I> states as follows:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify"><B>487.0552</B> (1) Every person who, without reasonable excuse, fails to comply with an order made under subsection 487.051(4) or 487.055(3.11) of this Act or under subsection 196.14(4) or 196.24(4) of the <I>National Defence Act</I>, or with a summons referred to in subsection 487.055(4) or 487.091(3) of this Act, is guilty of</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">(<I>a</I>) an indictable offence and liable to imprisonment for a term of not more than two years; or</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">(<I>b</I>) an offence punishable on summary conviction.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">Dated this ................ day of ................ , <keep>A.D. ........ ,</keep> at ................ .</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No" KeepWith="Next"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Center">...........................................</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="0" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Center">(<I>Signature of judge of the court</I>)</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><Para TopMargin="10" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">FORM 5.062 </Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><Para LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0" Italic="Yes" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">(Subsection 487.0551(1))</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:WARRANT FOR ARREST--><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">WARRANT FOR ARREST</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">Canada</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">Province of ................</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">(<I>territorial division</I>)</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">To the peace officers in (<I>territorial division</I>):</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">This warrant is issued for the arrest of A.B., of ................, (<I>occupation</I>), in this warrant called the “offender”.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">Whereas the offender failed to appear at the place, day and time set out in an order made under subsection 487.051(4) or 487.055(3.11), or in a summons referred to in subsection 487.055(4) or 487.091(3), of the <I>Criminal Code</I> to submit to the taking of samples of bodily substances;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">This is, therefore, to command you, in Her Majesty’s name, to arrest the offender without delay in order to allow the samples of bodily substances to be taken.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">Dated this ................ day of ................ <keep>A.D. ........,</keep> at ................ .</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No" KeepWith="Next"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Center">........................................</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No" KeepWith="Next"><Para TopMargin="0" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Center">A Justice of the Peace in</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No" KeepWith="Next"><Para TopMargin="0" LeftMargin="4" FirstLineIndent="0" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Center">and for .............................</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>1998, c. 37, s. 24<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>24.</B> Form 5.07 in Part XXVIII of the Act is replaced by the following:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><Para TopMargin="10" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">FORM 5.07 </Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><Para LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0" Italic="Yes" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">(Subsection 487.057(1))</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:REPORT TO A PROVINCIAL COURT JUDGE OR THE COURT--><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">REPORT TO A PROVINCIAL COURT JUDGE OR THE COURT</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">Canada</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">Province of ................</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">(<I>territorial division</I>)</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">[ ] To (<I>name of judge</I>), a judge of the provincial court who issued a warrant under section 487.05 or granted an authorization under section 487.055 or 487.091 of the <I>Criminal Code</I> or to another judge of that court:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">[ ] To the court that made an order under section 487.051 of the <I>Criminal Code</I>:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">I (<I>name of peace officer</I>), declare that (<I>state here whether the samples were taken under a warrant issued under section 487.05, an order made under section 487.051 or an authorization granted under section 487.055 or 487.091</I> <I>of the</I> <I>Criminal Code</I>).</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">I have (<I><I>state here whether you took the samples yourself or caused them to be taken</I> under your direction</I>) from (<I>name of offender</I>) the number of samples of bodily substances that I believe is reasonably required for forensic DNA analysis, in accordance with (<I>state whether the samples were taken under a warrant issued or an authorization granted by the judge or another judge of the court or an order made by the court</I>).</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">The samples were taken on the ... day <keep>of ...........,</keep> A.D. ......, at .......... o’clock.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">I (<I>or state the name of the person who took the samples</I>) took the following samples from (<I>name of offender</I>) in accordance with subsection 487.06(1) of the <I>Criminal Code</I> and was able, by virtue of training or experience, to do so (<I>check applicable box</I>):</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="5" FirstLineIndent="-3" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">[ ] <Tab/>individual hairs, including the root sheath</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="5" FirstLineIndent="-3" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">[ ] <Tab/>epithelial cells taken by swabbing the lips, tongue or inside cheeks of the mouth</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="5" FirstLineIndent="-3" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">[ ] <Tab/>blood taken by pricking the skin surface with a sterile lancet</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">Any terms or conditions in the (<I>warrant, order or authorization</I>) have been complied with.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">Dated this ................ day of ................ <keep>A.D. ........,</keep> at ................ .</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No" KeepWith="Next"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Center">........................................</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="0" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Center">(<I>Signature of peace officer</I>)</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>25.</B> Forms 5.08 and 5.09 in Part XXVIII of the Act, as enacted by section 13 of the other Act, are replaced by the following:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><Para TopMargin="10" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">FORM 5.08 </Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><Para LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0" Italic="Yes" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">(Subsection 487.091(1))</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:APPLICATION FOR AN AUTHORIZATION TO TAKE ADDITIONAL SAMPLES OF BODILY SUBSTANCES FOR FORENSIC DNA ANALYSIS--><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">APPLICATION FOR AN AUTHORIZATION TO TAKE ADDITIONAL SAMPLES OF BODILY SUBSTANCES FOR FORENSIC DNA ANALYSIS</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">Canada</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">Province of ................</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">(<I>territorial division</I>)</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">I (<I>name of peace officer</I>), (<I>occupation</I>), <keep>of ..........</keep> in (<I>territorial division</I>), apply for an authorization to take additional samples of bodily substances for forensic DNA analysis.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">Whereas samples of bodily substances were taken from (<I>name of offender</I>) for the purpose of forensic DNA analysis under an order made under section 487.051, or an authorization granted under section 487.055, of the <I>Criminal Code</I> (<I>attach a copy of the order or authorization</I>);</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">And whereas on (<I>day/month/year</I>) it was determined that</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">(<I>a</I>) a DNA profile could not be derived from the samples for the following reasons:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">(<I>b</I>) the information or bodily substances required by regulations made under the <I>DNA Identification Act</I> were not transmitted in accordance with the requirements of the regulations or were lost for the following reasons:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">Therefore, I request that an authorization be granted under subsection 487.091(1) of the <I>Criminal Code</I> to take from (<I>name of offender</I>) the number of additional samples of bodily substances that is reasonably required for forensic DNA analysis, provided that the person taking the samples is able, by virtue of training or experience, to take them by means of the investigative procedures described in subsection 487.06(1) of the <I>Criminal Code</I> and that, if the person taking the samples is not a peace officer, they take them under the direction of a peace officer.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">Dated this .... day of ........ , A.D. ........ , at ............... .</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No" KeepWith="Next"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Center">.........................................</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="0" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Center">(<I>Signature of applicant</I>)</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><Para TopMargin="10" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">FORM 5.09 </Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><Para LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0" Italic="Yes" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">(Subsection 487.091(1))</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:AUTHORIZATION TO TAKE ADDITIONAL SAMPLES OF BODILY SUBSTANCES FOR FORENSIC DNA ANALYSIS--><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">AUTHORIZATION TO TAKE ADDITIONAL SAMPLES OF BODILY SUBSTANCES FOR FORENSIC DNA ANALYSIS</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">Canada</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">Province of ................</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">(<I>territorial division</I>)</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">To the peace officers in (<I>territorial division</I>):</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">Whereas samples of bodily substances were taken from (<I>name of offender</I>) for the purpose of forensic DNA analysis under an order made under section 487.051 or an authorization granted under section 487.055, of the <I>Criminal Code</I>;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">Whereas on (<I>day/month/year</I>) it was determined that</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">(<I>a</I>) a DNA profile could not be derived from the samples for the following reasons:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">(<I>b</I>) the information or bodily substances required by regulations made under the <I>DNA Identification Act</I> were not transmitted in accordance with the requirements of the regulations or were lost for the following reasons:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">And whereas (<I>name of peace officer</I>), a peace officer in (<I>territorial division</I>), has applied for an authorization to take the number of additional samples of bodily substances from (<I>name of offender</I>) that is reasonably required for forensic DNA analysis by means of the investigative procedures described in subsection 487.06(1) of the <I>Criminal Code</I>;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">Therefore, you are authorized to take those additional samples, or cause them to be taken, from (<I>name of offender</I>), provided that the person taking the samples is able, by virtue of training or experience, to take them by means of the investigative procedures described in subsection 487.06(1) of the <I>Criminal Code</I> and that, if the person taking the samples is not a peace officer, they take them under the direction of a peace officer.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">This authorization is subject to the following terms and conditions that I consider advisable to ensure that the taking of the samples is reasonable in the circumstances:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">Dated this ................ day of ................ , <keep>A.D. ........ ,</keep> at ................ .</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No" KeepWith="Next"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Center">........................................</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="0" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Center">(<I>Signature of provincial court judge</I>)</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>2000, c. 10, s. 24<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>26.</B> Form 28.1 in Part XXVIII of the Act is repealed.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:DNA IDENTIFICATION ACT--><MarginalNote>1998, c. 37<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="10" Bold="Yes" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">DNA IDENTIFICATION ACT</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>27.</B> The definition “order” in section 2 of the <I>DNA Identification Act</I>, as enacted by subsection 14(2) of the other Act, is replaced by the following:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>“order”<br/>« <I>ordonnance</I> »<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0">“order” means an order made under section 487.051 of the <I>Criminal Code</I> or section 196.14 of the <I>National Defence Act</I>.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>28.</B> Subsection 5(4) of the Act, as enacted by section 15 of the other Act, is replaced by the following:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Convicted offenders index<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(4) The convicted offenders index shall contain DNA profiles derived from bodily substances that are taken under orders and authorizations.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>2005, c. 25, s. 16<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>29.</B> Subsection 5.1(3) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Retention of order or authorization<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(3) The Commissioner shall retain the copy of the order or authorization transmitted under subsection 487.071(2) of the <I>Criminal Code</I> or subsection 196.22(2) of the <I>National Defence Act</I>.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>2005, c. 25, s. 16<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>30.</B> Subsection 5.2(3) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Substantive defect<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(3) If the Attorney General or the Director of Military Prosecutions, as the case may be, informs the Commissioner that the offence referred to in the order or authorization is not a designated offence, the Commissioner shall, without delay, destroy the bodily substances collected under the order or authorization and the information transmitted with it.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>2005, c. 25, s. 17(1)<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>31.</B> (1) The portion of subsection 6(1) of the Act before paragraph (<I>a</I>) is replaced by the following:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Communication of information<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>6.</B> (1) The Commissioner shall compare any DNA profile that is entered in the convicted offenders index or the crime scene index with those DNA profiles that are already contained in the data bank and may then, for the purpose of the investigation of a criminal offence, communicate the following information to any Canadian law enforcement agency or laboratory that the Commissioner considers appropriate:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>2005, c. 25, s. 17(1)<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes">(2) Paragraph 6(1)(<I>b</I>) of the English version of the Act is replaced by the following:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>b</I>) if the DNA profile is already contained in the data bank, the information contained in the data bank in relation to that DNA profile;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>2005, c. 25, s. 17(1)<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes">(3) Paragraph 6(1)(<I>d</I>) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>d</I>) if a law enforcement agency or laboratory advises the Commissioner that their comparison of a DNA profile communicated under paragraph (<I>c</I>) with one that is connected to the commission of a criminal offence has not excluded the former as a possible match, the information contained in the data bank in relation to that profile.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>2005, c. 25, s. 17(2)<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes">(4) Subsection 6(3) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Foreign law enforcement agencies<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(3) On receipt of a DNA profile from the government of a foreign state, an international organization established by the governments of states or an institution of such a government or international organization, the Commissioner may compare the profile with those in the DNA data bank to determine whether it is already contained in the data bank and may then communicate to the government, organization or institution</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>a</I>) the information referred to in any of paragraphs (1)(<I>a</I>) to (<I>c</I>) in the circumstances referred to in that paragraph; and</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>b</I>) the information contained in the data bank in relation to a DNA profile communicated to the government, organization or institution in the circumstances set out in paragraph (1)(<I>c</I>) if the government, organization or institution advises the Commissioner that their comparison of that DNA profile with one that is connected to the commission of a criminal offence has not excluded the former as a possible match.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>2005, c. 25, s. 17(3)<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes">(5) Subsection 6(6.1) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Subsequent communication<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(6.1) Information that is communicated under subsection (1) may be communicated subsequently to a person to whom the communication is necessary for the purpose of the investigation or prosecution of a criminal offence.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>32.</B> Subsection 9(2) of the Act, as enacted by section 18 of the other Act, is replaced by the following:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Information to be permanently removed<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(2) Access to information in the convicted offenders index shall be permanently removed</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>a</I>) without delay after every order or authorization for the collection of bodily substances from the person to whom the information relates is finally set aside;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>b</I>) without delay after the person is finally acquitted of every designated offence in connection with which an order was made or an authorization was granted; or</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>c</I>) one year after the day on which the person is discharged absolutely, or three years after the day on which they are discharged conditionally, of a designated offence under section 730 of the <I>Criminal Code</I> if they are not subject to an order or authorization that relates to another designated offence and are neither convicted of, nor found not criminally responsible on account of mental disorder for, a designated offence during that period.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>33.</B> Subsection 10(7) of the Act, as enacted by subsection 20(3) of the other Act, is replaced by the following:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Mandatory destruction in certain cases<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(7) The Commissioner shall destroy the stored bodily substances of a person</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>a</I>) without delay after every order or authorization for the collection of bodily substances from the person is finally set aside;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>b</I>) without delay after the person is finally acquitted of every designated offence in connection with which an order was made or an authorization was granted; or</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>c</I>) one year after the day on which the person is discharged absolutely, or three years after the day on which they are discharged conditionally, of a designated offence under section 730 of the <I>Criminal Code</I> if they are not subject to an order or authorization that relates to another designated offence and are neither convicted of, nor found not criminally responsible on account of mental disorder for, a designated offence during that period.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:NATIONAL DEFENCE ACT--><MarginalNote>R.S., c. N-5<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="10" Bold="Yes" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">NATIONAL DEFENCE ACT</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>34.</B> The <I>National Defence Act</I> is amended by adding the following after section 119:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:Offence in Relation to DNA Identification--><Para TopMargin="10" Italic="Yes" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">Offence in Relation to DNA Identification</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Failure to comply with order or summons<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>119.1</B> (1) Every person who, without reasonable excuse, fails to comply with an order made under subsection 196.14(4) or 196.24(4) of this Act or subsection 487.051(4) or 487.055(3.11) of the <I>Criminal Code</I>, or with a summons referred to in subsection 487.055(4) or 487.091(3) of the <I>Criminal Code</I>, is guilty of an offence and on conviction is liable to imprisonment for less than two years or to less punishment.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>For greater certainty<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(2) For greater certainty, a lawful command that prevents a person from complying with an order or summons is a reasonable excuse.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>2000, c. 10, s. 1<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>35.</B> Paragraph (<I>b</I>) of the definition “forensic DNA analysis” in section 196.11 of the Act is replaced by the following:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>b</I>) in relation to a bodily substance that is provided voluntarily in the course of an investigation of a designated offence or is taken from a person in execution of an order made under section 196.14 or under an authorization granted under section 196.24, or to a bodily substance referred to in paragraph 196.12(1)(<I>b</I>), means forensic DNA analysis of the bodily substance.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>36.</B> Section 196.14 of the Act, as enacted by section 24 of the other Act, is replaced by the following:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Order — primary designated offences<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>196.14</B> (1) A court martial shall make an order in the prescribed form authorizing the taking of the number of samples of bodily substances that is reasonably required for the purpose of forensic DNA analysis from a person who is found guilty of an offence committed at any time, including before June 30, 2000, if that offence is a primary designated offence within the meaning of paragraph (<I>a.1</I>) of the definition “primary designated offence” in section 196.11 when the person is sentenced.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Order — primary designated offences<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(2) A court martial shall make such an order in the prescribed form in relation to a person who is found guilty of an offence committed at any time, including before June 30, 2000, if that offence is a primary designated offence within the meaning of paragraph (<I>a</I>) or (<I>b</I>) of the definition “primary designated offence” in section 196.11 when the person is sentenced. However, the court martial is not required to make the order if it is satisfied that the person has established that the impact of such an order on their privacy and security of the person would be grossly disproportionate to the public interest in the protection of society and the proper administration of military justice, to be achieved through the early detection, arrest and conviction of offenders.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Order — persons found not responsible and secondary designated offences<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(3) A court martial may, on application by the prosecutor and if it is satisfied that it is in the best interests of the administration of military justice to do so, make such an order in the prescribed form in relation to</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>a</I>) a person who is found not responsible on account of mental disorder for an offence committed at any time, including before June 30, 2000, if that offence is a designated offence when the finding is made; or</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>b</I>) a person who is found guilty of an offence committed at any time, including before June 30, 2000, if that offence is a secondary designated offence when the person is sentenced.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0">In deciding whether to make the order, the court martial shall consider the nature of the offence and the circumstances surrounding its commission, any previous convictions by a service tribunal or civil court, any previous finding of not responsible on account of mental disorder for a designated offence and the impact such an order would have on the person’s privacy and security of the person and shall give reasons for the decision.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Order to offender<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(4) When a court martial makes an order authorizing the taking of samples of bodily substances, it may make an order in the prescribed form to require the person to report at the place, day and time set out in the order and submit to the taking of the samples.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>37.</B> (1) Subsection 196.17(1) of the Act, as enacted by subsection 26(1) of the other Act, is replaced by the following:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>When collection to take place<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>196.17</B> (1) Samples of bodily substances shall be taken as authorized under section 196.14</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>a</I>) at the place, day and time set out in an order made under subsection 196.14(4) or as soon as feasible afterwards; or</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>b</I>) in any other case, on the day on which the order authorizing the taking of the samples is made or as soon as feasible afterwards.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>When collection to take place<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(1.1) Samples of bodily substances shall be taken as authorized under section 196.24</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>a</I>) at the place, day and time set out in an order made under subsection 196.24(4) or as soon as feasible afterwards; or</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>b</I>) in any other case, as soon as feasible after the authorization is granted.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>When collection to take place<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(1.2) If a person fails to appear as required by an order made under subsection 196.14(4) or 196.24(4), samples of bodily substances shall be taken</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>a</I>) when the person is arrested under a warrant issued under subsection 196.161(1) or as soon as feasible afterwards; or</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>b</I>) as soon as feasible after the person appears at the place set out in the order if no warrant is issued.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Appeal<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(1.3) Subsections (1) to (1.2) apply even if the order or authorization to take the samples of bodily substances is appealed.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>2000, c. 10, s. 1<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes">(2) Subsection 196.17(2) of the Act is repealed.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes">(3) Subsections 196.17(3) to (5) of the Act, as enacted by subsection 26(2) of the other Act, are replaced by the following:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Collection of samples<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(2) A peace officer who is authorized under section 196.14 or 196.24 to take samples of bodily substances may cause the samples to be taken in any place in or outside Canada in which the person who is subject to the order or authorization is located.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Who collects samples<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(3) The samples shall be taken by a peace officer who has jurisdiction over the person or in the place in which the samples are taken — or a person acting under their direction — who is able, by virtue of training or experience, to take them.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>2000, c. 10, s. 1<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>38.</B> (1) Subsection 196.18(1) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Report of peace officer<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>196.18</B> (1) A peace officer who takes samples of bodily substances from a person or who causes a person who is not a peace officer to take samples under their direction shall, as soon as feasible after the samples are taken, make a written report in the prescribed form and cause the report to be filed with</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>a</I>) the military judge who issued the warrant under section 196.12 or 196.13 or who granted the authorization under section 196.24, or another military judge; or</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>b</I>) the Court Martial Administrator, in the case of an order made by a court martial under section 196.14.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes">(2) Section 196.18 of the Act is amended by adding the following after subsection (2):</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Copy of report<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(2.1) The peace officer who takes the samples or causes the samples to be taken under their direction at the request of another peace officer shall send a copy of the report to the other peace officer unless that other peace officer had jurisdiction to take the samples.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>2000, c. 10, s. 1<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>39.</B> Section 196.19 of the Act is replaced by the following:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>No criminal or civil liability<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>196.19</B> No peace officer, and no person acting under a peace officer’s direction, incurs any disciplinary, criminal or civil liability for anything necessarily done with reasonable care and skill in the taking of samples of bodily substances in execution of a warrant issued under section 196.12 or 196.13 or an order made under section 196.14 or under an authorization granted under section 196.24.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>2000, c. 10, s. 1<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>40.</B> (1) The portion of subsection 196.2(1) of the Act before paragraph (<I>a</I>) is replaced by the following:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Investigative procedures<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>196.2</B> (1) A peace officer, or a person acting under a peace officer’s direction, is authorized by a warrant issued under section 196.12 or 196.13, an order made under section 196.14 or an authorization granted under section 196.24 to take samples of bodily substances by any of the following means:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>2000, c. 10, s. 1<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes">(2) Subsections 196.2(2) and (3) of the Act are replaced by the following:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Terms and conditions<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(2) The warrant or order shall include any terms and conditions that the military judge or court martial considers advisable to ensure that the taking of the samples is reasonable in the circumstances.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Fingerprints<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(3) A peace officer who is authorized to take samples of bodily substances from a person by an order made under section 196.14 or an authorization granted under section 196.24, or a person acting under their direction, may take fingerprints from the person for the purpose of the <I>DNA Identification Act</I>.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>2000, c. 10, s. 1<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>41.</B> The portion of subsection 196.21(1) of the Act before paragraph (<I>a</I>) is replaced by the following:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Duty to inform<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>196.21</B> (1) Before taking samples of bodily substances from a person, or causing samples to be taken under their direction, in execution of a warrant issued under section 196.12 or 196.13 or an order made under section 196.14 or under an authorization granted under section 196.24, a peace officer shall inform the person of</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>42.</B> Section 196.22 of the Act, as enacted by section 27 of the other Act, is replaced by the following:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Verification<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>196.22</B> (1) Before taking samples of bodily substances from a person under an order made under section 196.14 or an authorization granted under section 196.24, a peace officer, or a person acting under their direction, shall verify whether the convicted offenders index of the national DNA data bank, established under the <I>DNA Identification Act</I>, contains the person’s DNA profile.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>DNA profile in data bank<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(2) If the person’s DNA profile is in the convicted offenders index of the national DNA data bank, the peace officer or person acting under their direction shall not take any bodily substances from the person but shall</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>a</I>) confirm in writing on the order or authorization that they have been advised that the person’s DNA profile is in the national DNA data bank; and</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>b</I>) transmit a copy of the order or authorization containing that confirmation and any other information prescribed by regulations made under the <I>DNA Identification Act</I> to the Commissioner.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>DNA profile not in data bank<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(3) If the person’s DNA profile is not in the convicted offenders index of the national DNA data bank, the peace officer or person acting under their direction shall execute the order or authorization and transmit to the Commissioner</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>a</I>) any bodily substances taken; and</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>b</I>) a copy of the order or authorization and any other information prescribed by regulations made under the <I>DNA Identification Act</I>.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>43.</B> (1) Paragraph 196.24(1)(<I>a</I>) of the Act, as enacted by section 28 of the other Act, is replaced by the following:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>a</I>) a DNA profile cannot be derived from the bodily substances that were taken from that person under an order made under section 196.14; or</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes">(2) Paragraph 196.24(1)(<I>b</I>) of the English version of the Act, as enacted by section 28 of the other Act, is replaced by the following:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>b</I>) the information or bodily substances required by regulations made under the <I>DNA Identification Act</I> were not transmitted in accordance with the requirements of the regulations or were lost.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes">(3) Subsection 196.24(2) of the English version of the Act, as enacted by section 28 of the other Act, is replaced by the following:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Reasons<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(2) The application shall state the reasons why a DNA profile cannot be derived from the bodily substances or why the information or bodily substances were not transmitted in accordance with the regulations or were lost.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>2000, c. 10, s. 1<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes">(4) Subsection 196.24(3) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>For greater certainty<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(3) For greater certainty, the person who may be made subject to the authorization continues to be liable to be dealt with under the Code of Service Discipline for that purpose.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Persons not in custody<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(4) If the military judge authorizes the taking of samples of bodily substances from a person who is not in custody, an order in the prescribed form shall be directed to the person requiring them to report at the place, day and time set out in the order and submit to the taking of the samples.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>44.</B> (1) Subsection 196.241(1) of the Act, as enacted by section 29 of the other Act, is replaced by the following:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Review by Director of Military Prosecutions<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>196.241</B> (1) On receipt of a notice from the Commissioner under subsection 5.2(1) of the <I>DNA Identification Act</I> that an order made under section 196.14 or an authorization granted under section 196.24 appears to be defective, the Director of Military Prosecutions shall review the order or authorization and the court record.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes">(2) The portion of subsection 196.241(2) of the English version of the Act before paragraph (<I>a</I>), as enacted by section 29 of the other Act, is replaced by the following:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Clerical error<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(2) If the Director of Military Prosecutions is of the opinion that the defect is due to a clerical error, the Director shall</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes">(3) Subsection 196.241(3) of the Act, as enacted by section 29 of the other Act, is replaced by the following:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Substantive defect<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(3) If the Director of Military Prosecutions is of the opinion that the offence referred to in the order or authorization is not a designated offence, the Director shall inform the Commissioner of that opinion.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>2000, c. 10, s. 2<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>45.</B> Paragraph 230(<I>f</I>) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>f</I>) the legality of a decision made under any of subsections 196.14(1) to (3).</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>2000, c. 10, s. 3<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>46.</B> Paragraph 230.1(<I>g</I>) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>g</I>) the legality of a decision made under any of subsections 196.14(1) to (3).</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:COORDINATING AMENDMENTS--><Para TopMargin="10" Bold="Yes" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">COORDINATING AMENDMENTS</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>2005, c. 25<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>47.</B> (1) On the day on which subsections 1(2) to (5) of the other Act come into force, paragraphs (<I>a</I>) and (<I>a.1</I>) of the definition “primary designated offence” in section 487.04 of the <I>Criminal Code</I> are renumbered respectively as paragraphs (<I>a.1</I>) and (<I>a</I>) of that definition and are repositioned accordingly.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes">(2) On the later of the day on which section 3 of the other Act comes into force and the day on which subsection (1) produces its effects — or, if those days are the same day, then on that day — subsections 487.051(1) and (2) of the <I>Criminal Code</I> are replaced by the following:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Order — primary designated offences<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>487.051</B> (1) The court shall make an order in Form 5.03 authorizing the taking of the number of samples of bodily substances that is reasonably required for the purpose of forensic DNA analysis from a person who is convicted, discharged under section 730 or found guilty under the <I>Youth Criminal Justice Act</I> or the <I>Young Offenders Act</I>, of an offence committed at any time, including before June 30, 2000, if that offence is a primary designated offence within the meaning of paragraph (<I>a</I>) of the definition “primary designated offence” in section 487.04 when the person is sentenced or discharged.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Order — primary designated offences<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(2) The court shall make such an order in Form 5.03 in relation to a person who is convicted, discharged under section 730 or found guilty under the <I>Youth Criminal Justice Act</I> or the <I>Young Offenders Act</I>, of an offence committed at any time, including before June 30, 2000, if that offence is a primary designated offence within the meaning of any of paragraphs (<I>a.1</I>) to (<I>d</I>) of the definition “primary designated offence” in section 487.04 when the person is sentenced or discharged. However, the court is not required to make the order if it is satisfied that the person has established that the impact of such an order on their privacy and security of the person would be grossly disproportionate to the public interest in the protection of society and the proper administration of justice, to be achieved through the early detection, arrest and conviction of offenders.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>2005, c. 25<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>48.</B> (1) On the day on which subsection 23(1) of the other Act comes into force, paragraphs (<I>a</I>) and (<I>a.1</I>) of the definition “primary designated offence” in section 196.11 of the <I>National Defence Act</I> are replaced by the following:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>a</I>) an offence within the meaning of paragraph (<I>a</I>) of the definition “primary designated offence” in section 487.04 of the <I>Criminal Code</I> that is punishable under section 130;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>a.1</I>) an offence within the meaning of any of paragraphs (<I>a.1</I>) to (<I>c.1</I>) of the definition “primary designated offence” in section 487.04 of the <I>Criminal Code</I> that is punishable under section 130; and</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes">(2) On the later of the day on which section 24 of the other Act comes into force and the day on which subsection (1) produces its effects — or, if those days are the same day, then on that day — subsections 196.14(1) and (2) of the <I>National Defence Act</I> are replaced by the following:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Order — primary designated offences<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>196.14</B> (1) A court martial shall make an order in the prescribed form authorizing the taking of the number of samples of bodily substances that is reasonably required for the purpose of forensic DNA analysis from a person who is found guilty of an offence committed at any time, including before June 30, 2000, if that offence is a primary designated offence within the meaning of paragraph (<I>a</I>) of the definition “primary designated offence” in section 196.11 when the person is sentenced.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Order — primary designated offences<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(2) A court martial shall make such an order in the prescribed form in relation to a person who is found guilty of an offence committed at any time, including before June 30, 2000, if that offence is a primary designated offence within the meaning of paragraph (<I>a.1</I>) or (<I>b</I>) of the definition “primary designated offence” in section 196.11 when the person is sentenced. However, the court martial is not required to make the order if it is satisfied that the person has established that the impact of such an order on their privacy and security of the person would be grossly disproportionate to the public interest in the protection of society and the proper administration of military justice, to be achieved through the early detection, arrest and conviction of offenders.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Bill S-3<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>49.</B> If Bill S-3, introduced in the 1st session of the 39th Parliament and entitled <I>An Act to amend the National Defence Act, the Criminal Code, the Sex Offender Information Registration Act and the Criminal Records Act</I>, receives royal assent, then, on the later of the day on which section 2 of that Act comes into force and the day on which section 34 of this Act comes into force — or, if those days are the same day, then on that day — section 119.1 of the <I>National Defence Act</I>, as enacted by that section 34, is renumbered as section 119.2. If necessary, that section 119.2 and the heading before it are repositioned accordingly.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Bill C-7<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>50.</B> Paragraphs (<I>a</I>) to (<I>c</I>) apply as follows if Bill C-7, introduced in the 1st session of the 39th Parliament and entitled <I>An Act to amend the National Defence Act</I> (“C-7”), receives royal assent:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0" Bold="Yes">(<I>a</I>) if sections 57 and 58 of C-7 come into force before section 36 of this Act, section 126 of C-7 is repealed;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0" Bold="Yes">(<I>b</I>) if section 36 of this Act comes into force before sections 57 and 58 of C-7, sections 57, 58 and 126 of C-7 are repealed; and</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0" Bold="Yes">(<I>c</I>) if section 36 of this Act comes into force on the same day as sections 57 and 58 of C-7, sections 57 and 58 of C-7 are deemed to have come into force before section 36 of this Act and paragraph (<I>a</I>) applies.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Bill C-10<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>51.</B> If Bill C-10, introduced in the 1st session of the 39th Parliament and entitled <I>An Act to amend the Criminal Code (minimum penalties for offences involving firearms) and to make a consequential amendment to another Act</I> (“C-10”), receives royal assent and if subsection 47(1) of this Act produces its effects before the coming into force of section 26 of C-10, then section 26 of C-10, as enacted by subsection 30(1) of C-10, is replaced by the following:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>26.</B> Subparagraph (<I>a</I>)(v) of the definition “primary designated offence” in section 487.04 of the Act is replaced by the following:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="4" FirstLineIndent="0">(v) section 244 (discharging firearm with intent),</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:COMING INTO FORCE--><Para TopMargin="10" Bold="Yes" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">COMING INTO FORCE</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Order in council<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>52.</B> Section 7, subsection 8(1), section 10, subsections 11(2) to (4), section 12, subsection 13(2), sections 14 to 17, subsection 20(4), sections 22, 24, 26, 29, 30, 34 and 35, subsection 37(2), sections 38 to 41, subsection 43(4) and sections 45 and 46 of this Act come into force on a day to be fixed by order of the Governor in Council as long as that day is the same day as that fixed for the coming into force of section 1 of the other Act.</Para></Block><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="BPT_ImprintE">Published under authority of the Speaker of the House of Commons<br/>Available from:<br/>Publishing and Depository Services<br/>Public Works and Government Services Canada<br/>Ottawa, Ontario K1A 0S5<br/>Telephone: 613-941-5995 or 1-800-635-7943<br/>Fax: 613-954-5779 or 1-800-565-7757<br/>publications@tpsgc-pwgsc.gc.ca<br/>http://publications.gc.ca</Para></Block><Block Align="Yes" LineCnt="N"><Para NoLineBreak="Yes" NoHtml="Yes" Leading="0" Size="0" TopMargin="0" BottomMargin="0"></Para></Block></Bill_Part></Bill>
