<?xml version="1.0"?>
<Bill RHead_reign="55 Eliz. II" RHead_ParlYear="2006" DocumentTitle="BILL C-261" Bill_No="C-261" Document_No="391065" xml:lang="EN" Bill_Type="Non-amending" Stage_Name="First-Reading-House" Reprint="No" xml:space="preserve" ChapterNo_E="C. " ChapterNo_F="ch. " Bill-Origin="commons"><Bill_Part Part_Type="Cover" CountLines="No"><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="CovBillNo">C-261</Para></Block><Block><Para TopMargin="24" Size="9" Leading="10" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0" TextAlign="Center">First Session, Thirty-ninth Parliament,</Para></Block><Block><Para Size="9" Leading="10" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0" TextAlign="Center">55 Elizabeth II, 2006</Para></Block><Block><Para TopMargin="48" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0" Bold="Yes" TextAlign="Center">HOUSE OF COMMONS OF CANADA</Para></Block><Block><Para TopMargin="42" Size="18" Leading="20" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0" Bold="Yes" TextAlign="Center">BILL C-261</Para></Block><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="CovLongTitle">An Act to establish the office of Pension Ombudsman to investigate administrative difficulties encountered by persons in their dealings with the Government of Canada in respect of benefits under the Canada Pension Plan or the Old Age Security Act or tax liability on such benefits and to review the policies and practices applied in the administration and adjudication of such benefits and liabilities</Para></Block><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="COV_StageLine"></Para></Block><Block><Para Size="9" AllCaps="Yes" Hyphenate="OFF">first reading, May 5, 2006</Para></Block><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="COV_StageLine"></Para></Block><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="Cover_Sponsors"><SC SC_PerCent="85">Mr. Martin</SC> (<I>Winnipeg Centre</I>)</Para></Block><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="Cover_DocNo">391065</Para></Block></Bill_Part><Bill_Part CountLines="No" Part_Type="InsideCover"><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="BPT_InsideCoverE">Also available on the Parliament of Canada Web Site at the following address:<br/><B>http://www.parl.gc.ca</B></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><Para TopMargin="108" BottomMargin="4" Size="10" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">SUMMARY</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" Size="8" Leading="9" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">The purpose of this enactment is to establish the office of Pension Ombudsman, whose function is to assist persons dealing with the Government of Canada in respect of benefits under the <I>Canada Pension Plan</I> or the <I>Old Age Security Act</I> or tax liabilities thereon in cases where they are dealt with unfairly or unreasonably or with unreasonable delay. The Ombudsman may investigate complaints and report on complaints that are not satisfactorily resolved. The reports may be to the relevant minister as to the specific details of complaints, or in general terms to a standing committee of the House of Commons.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" Size="8" Leading="9" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">The Ombudsman may propose changes in the way the public is served in these matters with respect to fairness, reasonableness and promptness.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" Size="8" Leading="9" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">If the relevant department fails to improve its policies and practices at the suggestion of the Ombudsman, the Ombudsman may make a report to the Minister of Human Resources and Skills Development or to the Minister of National Revenue, and the report must then be laid before Parliament.</Para></Block></Bill_Part><Bill_Part Part_Type="MainText" CountLines="Yes" RunningHead_E="Pension Ombudsman"><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="MainText_DocNo">391065</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes"><Para Style="Session_Reign">1st Session, 39th Parliament,</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes"><Para Style="Session_Reign">55 Elizabeth II, 2006</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes"><Para Style="MainBillOrigin">house of commons of canada</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes"><Para Bold="Yes" Style="MAIN@BillNo_Title">BILL C-261</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes"><Para Style="MAIN@ti;04">An Act to establish the office of Pension Ombudsman to investigate administrative difficulties encountered by persons in their dealings with the Government of Canada in respect of benefits under the Canada Pension Plan or the Old Age Security Act or tax liability on such benefits and to review the policies and practices applied in the administration and adjudication of such benefits and liabilities</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">Her Majesty, by and with the advice and consent of the Senate and House of Commons of Canada, enacts as follows:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:SHORT TITLE--><Para TopMargin="10" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">SHORT TITLE</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Short title<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>1.</B> This Act may be cited as the <I>Pension Ombudsman Act</I>.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:INTERPRETATION--><Para TopMargin="10" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">INTERPRETATION</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Definitions<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>2.</B> The definitions in this section apply in this Act.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><MarginalNote>“Department”<br/>« <I>ministère</I> »<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0">“Department” means the Department of Human Resources and Skills Development. </Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><MarginalNote>“Minister”<br/>« <I>ministre</I> »<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0">“Minister” means the Minister of Human Resources and Skills Development.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><MarginalNote>“Ombudsman”<br/>« <I>ombudsman</I> »<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0">“Ombudsman” means the person holding the office of Pension Ombudsman established under section 3.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><MarginalNote>“relevant department”<br/>« <I>ministère
visé</I> »<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0">“relevant department” means the Department or the Canada Revenue Agency,  as the case may be. </Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><MarginalNote>“Standing Committee”<br/>« <I>comité permanent</I> »<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0">“Standing Committee” means the Standing Committee of the House of Commons appointed by the House to deal with matters related to pensions and other benefits for senior citizens.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:PENSION OMBUDSMAN--><Para TopMargin="10" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">PENSION OMBUDSMAN</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Office established<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>3.</B> (1) There is hereby established the office of Pension Ombudsman.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Function of office<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(2) The function of the Pension Ombudsman is</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>a</I>) to investigate administrative difficulties as to fairness, reasonableness and promptness encountered by persons in their dealings with the Government of Canada in respect of benefits under the <I>Canada Pension Plan</I> or the<I> Old Age Security Act</I> or tax liability on such benefits;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>b</I>) to review the policies and practices applied in the administration and adjudication of such benefits and liabilities with respect to fairness, reasonableness and promptness; and</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>c</I>) to make reports on cases where difficulties are not satisfactorily resolved or where policies and practices are not adequately adjusted on the Ombudsman’s request.  </Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Appointment<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>4.</B> (1) The Governor in Council shall appoint a Pension Ombudsman recommended by the Minister from a list of persons nominated by the Standing Committee. </Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Term and removal<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(2) The Ombudsman holds office during good behaviour for a term of five years, but may be</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>a</I>) removed by the Governor in Council at any time on a resolution of the House of Commons following a report recommending removal by the Standing Committee; or</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>b</I>) suspended by the Governor in Council on the recommendation of the Minister, made at any time when the House is adjourned for a period of four weeks or more, or is dissolved, for a period expiring thirty days after the day the House next sits.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Acting Ombudsman<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(3) In the event of the absence, incapacity or suspension of the Ombudsman, the Governor in Council may, on the recommendation of the Minister, appoint another person to act as Ombudsman until the Ombudsman returns, the suspension is terminated or another Ombudsman is appointed, as the case may be.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>No more than two terms<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(4) No person may serve more than two terms as Ombudsman.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Remuneration<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(5) The Ombudsman shall receive such remuneration, benefits and reimbursement of expenses as is ordered by the Governor in Council.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Part of the federal public administration<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(6) The Office of the Ombudsman is deemed to be a part of the federal public administration.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Staff<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(7) The Ombudsman may hire, under the <I>Public Service Employment Act</I>, such officers and staff as are necessary to carry out the purposes of this Act.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:COMPLAINTS AND INVESTIGATIONS--><Para TopMargin="10" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">COMPLAINTS AND INVESTIGATIONS</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Complaints<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>5.</B> (1) Any person who claims to have encountered administrative difficulties as to fairness, reasonableness and promptness in their dealings with the relevant department in respect of benefits under the <I>Canada Pension Plan</I> or the <I>Old Age Security Act</I> or tax liability on such benefits may make a complaint to the Ombudsman.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Investigations<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(2) The Ombudsman shall investigate those complaints received under subsection (1) that show reasonable grounds to believe that there has been unfair or unreasonable treatment or unreasonable delay by the Department respecting a benefit or by the Canada Revenue Agency respecting tax liability on a benefit.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Departmental information<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(3) For the purposes of an investigation, the Ombudsman may request, from the relevant department,  information that is relevant to the complaint being investigated, and the relevant department shall provide the information requested.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Confidential information<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(4) The Ombudsman may, with the information requested under subsection (3), and with the written consent of the complainant, include a request for information respecting the complainant that is confidential, and the relevant department shall, notwithstanding any other Act of Parliament, provide the information covered by the consent.  </Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Information kept confidential<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(5) The Ombudsman shall keep confidential all information provided by the relevant department under subsection (4), except as necessary for a report under subsection (7) that contains such information without identifying the complainant.  </Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Report<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(6) If, after investigation, the Ombudsman is not satisfied that the relevant department has dealt fairly, reasonably and with due dispatch with the complainant, either before or after the complaint or investigation, the Ombudsman,</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>a</I>) having given written notice to the relevant department that a report will be made to the minister in charge of the relevant department, including a draft of the proposed report,</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>b</I>) having considered any representation sent to the Ombudsman by the relevant department respecting the proposed report, and made such changes in the proposed report as appear in the opinion of the Ombudsman to be warranted on the basis of such representations, and</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>c</I>) having received the prior written consent of the complainant,</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0">may report the matter in detail to the minister in charge of the relevant department, and the minister shall reveal the report only to the officials of the relevant department.  </Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"/><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Reports to the Standing Committee<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(7) The Ombudsman may make reports from time to time to the Standing Committee on matters that the Ombudsman has investigated and reported on to the relevant department under subsection (6) if the Ombudsman is not satisfied with the action taken by the relevant department in the matter.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Complainant not identified<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(8) A report under subsection (7) shall be in general terms and not identify a complainant.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:ADMINISTRATIVE POLICIES AND PRACTICES--><Para TopMargin="10" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">ADMINISTRATIVE POLICIES AND PRACTICES</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Notice re unfair policies<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>6.</B> (1) If the Ombudsman is of the opinion, based on complaints that have been investigated under section 5, that the relevant department’s policies and practices result in unfair or unreasonable treatment or unreasonable delays in dealing with persons in respect of benefits under the <I>Canada Pension Plan</I> or the <I>Old Age Security Act</I> or tax liabilities thereon, the Ombudsman may give notice to the relevant department of the changes that the Ombudsman considers should be made.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Changes to be made<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(2) Within ninety days after receiving a notice under subsection (1), the relevant department shall advise the Ombudsman of the changes that will be made in the relevant department’s policies and practices.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Changes unsatisfactory or not made<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(3) If the Ombudsman is not satisfied with the changes proposed by the relevant department under subsection (2), or if on investigation the Ombudsman finds that the proposed changes have not been made, the Ombudsman shall submit a report on the matter to the minister responsible for the administration of the relevant department.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Report referred to the Standing Committee<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(4) The minister responsible for the administration of the relevant department shall forthwith cause every report received under subsection (3) to be laid before both Houses of Parliament, and it shall be deemed to have been referred to the Standing Committee for review and report to the House of Commons.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Notice of Ombudsman’s services<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>7.</B> The Department and the Canada Revenue Agency shall post, at every place where it regularly receives persons to deal with benefits under the <I>Canada Pension Plan</I> or the <I>Old Age Security Act </I>or tax liabilities thereon, a notice in the form prescribed by the Ombudsman, describing the function of the office of the Ombudsman and the means of contacting the office.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Annual report<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>8.</B> The Ombudsman shall submit to the Minister by April 1 of every year a report on the functions of the office of the Pension Ombudsman during the previous year, and the Minister shall forthwith cause the report to be laid before both Houses of Parliament.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:OFFENCES AND PENALTIES--><Para TopMargin="10" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">OFFENCES AND PENALTIES</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>False information<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>9.</B> (1) Every complainant, member of a relevant department or other person who knowingly provides false information to the Ombudsman in connection with this Act is guilty of an offence.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Refusal to provide information<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(2) Every person who refuses or fails to provide information requested by the Ombudsman under the authority of this Act is guilty of an offence.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Punishment<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(3) Every person who commits an offence under this Act is liable, on summary conviction, to a fine not exceeding $1,000 for a first offence, and to a fine not exceeding $5,000 or imprisonment for not more than six months, or to both, in the case of a second or subsequent offence. </Para></Block><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="BPT_ImprintE">Published under authority of the Speaker of the House of Commons<br/>Available from:<br/>Publishing and Depository Services<br/>Public Works and Government Services Canada<br/>Ottawa, Ontario K1A 0S5<br/>Telephone: 613-941-5995 or 1-800-635-7943<br/>Fax: 613-954-5779 or 1-800-565-7757<br/>publications@tpsgc-pwgsc.gc.ca<br/>http://publications.gc.ca</Para></Block><Block Align="Yes" LineCnt="N"><Para NoLineBreak="Yes" NoHtml="Yes" Leading="0" Size="0" TopMargin="0" BottomMargin="0"></Para></Block></Bill_Part></Bill>
