<?xml version="1.0"?>
<Bill RHead_reign="55 Eliz. II" RHead_ParlYear="2006" DocumentTitle="BILL C-316" Bill_No="C-316" Document_No="391125" xml:lang="EN" Bill_Type="Non-amending" Stage_Name="First-Reading-House" Reprint="No" xml:space="preserve" ChapterNo_E="C. " ChapterNo_F="ch. " Bill-Origin="commons"><Bill_Part Part_Type="Cover" CountLines="No"><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="CovBillNo">C-316</Para></Block><Block><Para TopMargin="24" Size="9" Leading="10" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0" TextAlign="Center">First Session, Thirty-ninth Parliament,</Para></Block><Block><Para Size="9" Leading="10" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0" TextAlign="Center">55 Elizabeth II, 2006</Para></Block><Block><Para TopMargin="48" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0" Bold="Yes" TextAlign="Center">HOUSE OF COMMONS OF CANADA</Para></Block><Block><Para TopMargin="42" Size="18" Leading="20" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0" Bold="Yes" TextAlign="Center">BILL C-316</Para></Block><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="CovLongTitle">An Act to establish a national literacy policy</Para></Block><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="COV_StageLine"></Para></Block><Block><Para Size="9" AllCaps="Yes" Hyphenate="OFF">first reading, June 5, 2006</Para></Block><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="COV_StageLine"></Para></Block><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="Cover_Sponsors"><SC SC_PerCent="85">Mr. Silva</SC></Para></Block><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="Cover_DocNo">391125</Para></Block></Bill_Part><Bill_Part CountLines="No" Part_Type="InsideCover"><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="BPT_InsideCoverE">Also available on the Parliament of Canada Web Site at the following address:<br/><B>http://www.parl.gc.ca</B></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><Para TopMargin="108" BottomMargin="4" Size="10" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">SUMMARY</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" Size="8" Leading="9" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">The purpose of this enactment is to require the Minister of Canadian Heritage to consult with the provincial ministers of the Crown responsible for education and literacy, experts in education and literacy, representatives of business and labour, and representatives of the media in order to establish a national literacy policy.</Para></Block></Bill_Part><Bill_Part Part_Type="MainText" CountLines="Yes" RunningHead_E="National Literacy Policy"><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="MainText_DocNo">391125</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes"><Para Style="Session_Reign">1st Session, 39th Parliament,</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes"><Para Style="Session_Reign">55 Elizabeth II, 2006</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes"><Para Style="MainBillOrigin">house of commons of canada</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes"><Para Bold="Yes" Style="MAIN@BillNo_Title">BILL C-316</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes"><Para Style="MAIN@ti;04">An Act to establish a national literacy policy</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Preamble<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">WHEREAS literacy is a prerequisite for social and economic development and should be recognized as a basic human right;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">WHEREAS approximately thirty-eight per cent of Canadians have difficulty reading and writing;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">WHEREAS  illiteracy costs Canadian society approximately ten billion dollars annually;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">WHEREAS literacy programs in Canada generally lack the funding, coordination with other programs, and accessibility necessary for long-term success;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">WHEREAS the number of unskilled workers in Canada is increasing, while employment opportunities for these workers are decreasing;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">WHEREAS illiteracy facilitates and <keep>perpetuates</keep> the economic stagnation of those whom it affects, which will in turn severely impede Canada’s ability to maintain its position as an innovative and competitive world leader;

</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">AND WHEREAS the Parliament of Canada is committed to facilitating the cooperation of all levels of government in order to reduce illiteracy;

</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">NOW, THEREFORE, Her Majesty, by and with the advice and consent of the Senate and House of Commons of Canada, enacts as follows:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:SHORT TITLE--><Para TopMargin="10" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">SHORT TITLE</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Short title<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>1.</B> This Act may be cited as the <I>National Literacy Policy Act</I>.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:INTERPRETATION--><Para TopMargin="10" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">INTERPRETATION</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Definitions<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>2.</B> The definitions in this section apply in this Act.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><MarginalNote>“Canadian”<br/>« <I>Canadien</I> »<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0">“Canadian” means a citizen or a resident of Canada.

</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><MarginalNote>“Committee”<br/>« <I>Comité</I> »<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0">“Committee” means the Literacy Policy Advisory Committee established under section 8.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><MarginalNote>“literacy”<br/>« <I>alphabétisa-tion</I> »<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0">“literacy” means the ability to read, write, speak, understand and calculate in a language at the level necessary to function in the community, the workplace and the home.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><MarginalNote>“Minister”<br/>« <I>ministre</I> »<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0">“Minister” means the Minister of Canadian Heritage.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><MarginalNote>“national literacy policy”<br/>« <I>politique nationale d'alphabétisation</I> »<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0">“national literacy policy” means a uniform set of initiatives to be implemented throughout Canada to help Canadians achieve basic literacy.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:PURPOSE--><Para TopMargin="10" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">PURPOSE</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Purpose<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>3.</B> The purpose of this Act is to initiate a process to establish a national literacy policy.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:NATIONAL LITERACY POLICY--><Para TopMargin="10" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">NATIONAL LITERACY POLICY</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Establishment of national literacy policy<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>4.</B> The Minister shall,  in consultation with the provincial ministers of the Crown responsible for education and literacy, experts in education and literacy, representatives of business and labour, and representatives of the media, establish a national literacy policy designed to</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>a</I>) monitor students’ basic reading and writing skills and encourage them to value literacy;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>b</I>) encourage literacy in the workplace through various measures, including the provision of literacy incentives at work and the availability of seminars, training and resource offices in the workplace to identify illiteracy and enable those with literacy problems to seek help in confidence;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>c</I>) encourage literacy in the community through various measures, including the promotion of literacy awareness and the availability of seminars, training and resource offices in the community to enable those with literacy problems to seek help in confidence; and</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>d</I>) encourage the media to take initiatives to promote literacy awareness and to take a leading role in devising a national advertising campaign aimed at fighting illiteracy.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Implementation of the national literacy policy<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>5.</B> The Minister, in consultation with the provincial ministers of the Crown responsible for education and literacy, shall encourage and promote a coordinated approach to the implementation of the national literacy policy and may provide advice and assistance in the development and implementation of programs and practices in support of the policy.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Specific mandate<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>6.</B> (1) The Minister shall take any measures that the Minister considers appropriate to implement the national literacy policy and, without limiting the generality of the foregoing, may</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>a</I>) assist the business community, labour organizations, voluntary and other private organizations, as well as public institutions, to adopt the national literacy policy;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>b</I>) provide support to individuals, groups and organizations for the purpose of promoting the national literacy policy and ensuring its adoption; </Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>c</I>) establish and maintain a register of resources that are available to literacy students, literacy teachers and literacy programs administrators; and</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>d</I>) undertake any other projects or programs, not by law assigned to any other federal institution that are designed to promote the national literacy policy.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Provincial agreements<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(2) The Minister may enter into an agreement or arrangement with any province respecting the implementation of the national literacy policy.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Responsibilities of other ministers<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>7.</B> (1) The provincial ministers of the Crown shall, in the execution of their respective mandates, take any measures that they consider appropriate to implement the national literacy policy.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Provincial agreements<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(2) A provincial minister of the Crown may enter into an agreement or arrangement with any province respecting the implementation of the national literacy policy.

</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:LITERACY POLICY ADVISORY COMMITTEE--><Para TopMargin="10" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">LITERACY POLICY ADVISORY COMMITTEE</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Advisory Committee<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>8.</B>  (1) The Minister may establish a committee, to be known as the Literacy Policy Advisory Committee, to advise and assist the Minister with respect to the implementation of this Act and any other matter relating to literacy and, in consultation with any  organizations representing literacy interests that the Minister deems appropriate, may appoint the members and designate the chairperson and other officers of the Committee.

</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Composition of Committee<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(2) The Minister shall make all reasonable efforts to ensure that the Committee’s membership consists of experts in education and literacy, representatives of business and labour, and representatives of the media.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:REPORT--><Para TopMargin="10" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">REPORT</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Annual report<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>9.</B> The chairperson of the Committee shall, within four months after the end of each fiscal year, submit to the Minister a report on the activities of the Committee for that year and on any other matter relating to the implementation of the national literacy policy that the chairperson considers appropriate.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Annual report<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>10.</B> The Minister shall cause a copy of the report to be laid before each House of Parliament on any of the first ten days on which that House is sitting after the Minister receives the report.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Permanent review by a Parliamentary committee<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>11.</B> A committee of the House of Commons, of the Senate or of both Houses of Parliament that may be designated or established for the purpose shall review on a permanent basis the operation of the Act and shall review each year the report made under section 9. </Para></Block><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="BPT_ImprintE">Published under authority of the Speaker of the House of Commons<br/>Available from:<br/>Publishing and Depository Services<br/>Public Works and Government Services Canada<br/>Ottawa, Ontario K1A 0S5<br/>Telephone: 613-941-5995 or 1-800-635-7943<br/>Fax: 613-954-5779 or 1-800-565-7757<br/>publications@tpsgc-pwgsc.gc.ca<br/>http://publications.gc.ca</Para></Block><Block Align="Yes" LineCnt="N"><Para NoLineBreak="Yes" NoHtml="Yes" Leading="0" Size="0" TopMargin="0" BottomMargin="0"></Para></Block></Bill_Part></Bill>
