<?xml version="1.0"?>
<Bill RHead_reign="55 Eliz. II" RHead_ParlYear="2006" DocumentTitle="BILL C-357" Bill_No="C-357" Document_No="391409" xml:lang="EN" Bill_Type="Non-amending" Stage_Name="First-Reading-House" Reprint="No" xml:space="preserve" ChapterNo_E="C. " ChapterNo_F="ch. " Bill-Origin="commons"><Bill_Part Part_Type="Cover" CountLines="No"><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="CovBillNo">C-357</Para></Block><Block><Para TopMargin="24" Size="9" Leading="10" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0" TextAlign="Center">First Session, Thirty-ninth Parliament,</Para></Block><Block><Para Size="9" Leading="10" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0" TextAlign="Center">55 Elizabeth II, 2006</Para></Block><Block><Para TopMargin="48" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0" Bold="Yes" TextAlign="Center">HOUSE OF COMMONS OF CANADA</Para></Block><Block><Para TopMargin="42" Size="18" Leading="20" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0" Bold="Yes" TextAlign="Center">BILL C-357</Para></Block><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="CovLongTitle">An Act to amend the Employment Insurance Act (Employment Insurance Account and premium rate setting) and another Act in consequence</Para></Block><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="COV_StageLine"></Para></Block><Block><Para Size="9" AllCaps="Yes" Hyphenate="OFF">first reading, October 18, 2006</Para></Block><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="COV_StageLine"></Para></Block><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="Cover_Sponsors"><SC SC_PerCent="85">Mr. Blais</SC></Para></Block><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="Cover_DocNo">391409</Para></Block></Bill_Part><Bill_Part CountLines="No" Part_Type="InsideCover"><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="BPT_InsideCoverE">Also available on the Parliament of Canada Web Site at the following address:<br/><B>http://www.parl.gc.ca</B></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><Para TopMargin="108" BottomMargin="4" Size="10" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">SUMMARY</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" Size="8" Leading="9" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">This enactment amends the method for setting the premium rate in the <I>Employment Insurance Act</I>. It also amends a number of provisions in that Act with respect to the Employment Insurance Account.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" Size="8" Leading="9" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">This enactment provides that every year the Canada Employment Insurance Commission will set the premium rate and cause a report to be sent to the Minister of Human Resources and Skills Development who will cause a copy of the report to be laid before each House of Parliament.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" Size="8" Leading="9" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">This enactment provides also that the Employment Insurance Account will no longer form part of the accounts of Canada. The amounts paid into the Employment Insurance Account will become part of the assets of the Canada Employment Insurance Commission, and the Commission will manage them in the best interests of the contributors and beneficiaries under the employment insurance system.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" Size="8" Leading="9" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">At the request of the Minister of Finance, the Canada Employment Insurance Commission may extend a loan to Her Majesty in right of Canada and establish the interest rate and other terms and conditions for its repayment. Conversely, that Minister must extend a loan to the Commission if the Commission is unable to pay the amounts that it is liable to pay.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" Size="8" Leading="9" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">Under the enactment, the Canada Employment Insurance Commission is composed of 17 commissioners, including a Chairperson, two Vice-Chairpersons, seven representatives of employees and seven representatives of employers. The representatives of employees and employers are appointed by the Governor in Council from lists of nominees provided by representative associations. The Chairperson is appointed by the House of Commons and the Vice-Chairpersons are selected from among the Deputy Ministers or the Associate Deputy Ministers of the Department of Human Resources Development.</Para></Block></Bill_Part><Bill_Part Part_Type="MainText" CountLines="Yes" RunningHead_E="Employment Insurance (Employment Insurance Account and premium rate setting)"><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="MainText_DocNo">391409</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes"><Para Style="Session_Reign">1st Session, 39th Parliament,</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes"><Para Style="Session_Reign">55 Elizabeth II, 2006</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes"><Para Style="MainBillOrigin">house of commons of canada</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes"><Para Bold="Yes" Style="MAIN@BillNo_Title">BILL C-357</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes"><Para Style="MAIN@ti;04">An Act to amend the Employment Insurance Act (Employment Insurance Account and premium rate setting) and another Act in consequence</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">Her Majesty, by and with the advice and consent of the Senate and House of Commons of Canada, enacts as follows:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:EMPLOYMENT INSURANCE ACT--><MarginalNote>1996, c. 23<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="10" Bold="Yes" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">EMPLOYMENT INSURANCE ACT</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>1.</B> Sections 65.3 to 67 of the <I>Employment Insurance Act</I> are replaced by the following:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Premium rate setting<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>66.</B> (1) <change>Not later than November 30 in each year, the</change> Commission shall set the premium rate <change>that the Commission considers will, to the extent possible, over a business cycle,</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0"><change>(<I>a</I>) serve the best interests of the contributors and beneficiaries under the employment insurance system;</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0"><change>(<I>b</I>) ensure that there is enough revenue to pay the expenses authorized to be charged to the Employment Insurance Account;</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0"><change>(<I>c</I>) maintain stable rate levels; and</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0"><change>(<I>d</I>) ensure that the difference between the assets of the Employment Insurance Account and its liabilities does not exceed fifteen billion dollars.</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Report to Minister<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(2) <change>On the first day of October in each year, the Commission shall cause a report to be sent to the Minister containing</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0"><change>(<I>a</I>) the reasons for setting the premium rate for the year;</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0"><change>(<I>b</I>) any change to the amount of benefits that the Commission considers will, to the extent possible, over a business cycle,</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="4" FirstLineIndent="0"><change>(i) ensure that there is enough revenue to pay the expenses authorized to be charged to the Employment Insurance Account, and</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="4" FirstLineIndent="0"><change>(ii) maintain stable rate levels;</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0"><change>(<I>c</I>) a detailed description of the assets of the Commission on the first day of September in each year;</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0"><change>(<I>d</I>) a detailed description of the amounts that have been paid into or paid out of the Employment Insurance Account since the previous report;</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0"><change>(<I>e</I>) an estimate of the amounts to be paid into the Employment Insurance Account under this Act for the following year, calculated on the basis of the premium rate set by the Commission in the report;</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0"><change>(<I>f</I>) an estimate of the amounts to be paid out of the Employment Insurance Account under this Act for the following year, calculated on the basis of the amount of benefits to be paid set by the Commission in the report;</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0"><change>(<I>g</I>) any recommendations that the Commission considers necessary for the improvement of the employment insurance system, including amendments to Acts, regulations and policies with respect to employment insurance; and</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0"><change>(<I>h</I>) any other information that the Commission considers necessary.</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Tabling in Parliament<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(3) <change>The Minister shall cause a copy of the report to be laid before each House of Parliament on any of the first five days on which that House is sitting after the Minister receives it.</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Employee's premium<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>67.</B> Subject to section 70, a person employed in insurable employment shall pay, by deduction as provided in subsection 82(1), a premium equal to their insurable earnings multiplied by the premium rate set under section 66.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>2.</B> Sections 71 to 76 of the Act are replaced by the following:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Employment Insurance
Account established
<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>71.</B> There shall be established in the <change>name of the Commission</change> an account to be known as the Employment Insurance Account.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Payment 
into the Employment
Insurance Account
<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>72.</B> <change>(1)</change> There shall be paid into the <change>Employment Insurance Account</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>a</I>) all amounts <change>credited to the Employment Insurance Account — as that Account exist-ed immediately prior to the day on which this section comes into force — and not charged to that Account for the purposes of this Act on the coming into force of this section</change>;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>b</I>) all amounts received under Parts I and III to IX, as or on account of premiums, fines, penalties, interest, repayment of overpaid benefits and benefit repayment;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>c</I>) all amounts collected by the Commission for services rendered to other government departments or agencies or to the public;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0"><change>(<I>d</I>)</change> all amounts received on account of principal or interest on loans made by the Commission under Part II or as repayment of overpayments made by the Commission under that Part<change>;</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0"><change>(<I>e</I>)</change> <change>all</change> premiums required to be paid by Her Majesty in right of Canada as employer’s premiums for persons employed in insurable employment by Her Majesty in right of Canada<change>;</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0"><change>(<I>f</I>)</change> all amounts paid into the Consolidated Revenue Fund that are</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="4" FirstLineIndent="0"><change>(i)</change> received as or on account of penalties imposed under section 38, 39 or 65.1 and repayments of overpaid benefits, except interest and penalties on benefit repayment<change>,</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="4" FirstLineIndent="0"><change>(ii)</change> received on account of principal or interest on loans made by the Commission under Part II<change>,</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="4" FirstLineIndent="0"><change>(iii)</change> received as repayments of overpayments by the Commission under section 61 for employment benefits and support measures authorized by Part II<change>,</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="4" FirstLineIndent="0"><change>(iv)</change> received as repayments of overpayments by the Commission under agreements entered into under section 63<change>,</change> or</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="4" FirstLineIndent="0"><change>(v)</change> received as interest under section 80.1<change>;</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0"><change>(<I>g</I>) any amount provided out of the Consolidated Revenue Fund to the Commission by the Minister of Finance under section 74;</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0"><change>(<I>h</I>)</change> any <change>amount</change> provided out of the Consolidated Revenue Fund appropriated by Parliament <change>intended</change> for any purpose related to employment insurance and administered by the Commission<change>; and</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0"><change>(<I>i</I>) any other amounts paid into the Consolidated Revenue Fund or to the Commission under this Act for any purpose related to employment insurance and administered by the Commission.</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Annual payments<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><change>(2) The Minister shall pay the amounts referred to in paragraph (1)(<I>a</I>) into the Employment Insurance Account over a period of time that the Minister considers appropriate, having regard to the fiscal position and expected outlook of the Government of Canada.</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Minimum payment<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><change>(3) The amounts paid in the course of a year shall not be less than one half of the amount remaining at the end of that year in the Contingency Reserve provided for in the budget for that year.</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Maximum payment<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><change>(4) Despite subsection (3), the amounts paid in the course of a year shall not exceed the amounts referred to in paragraph 1(<I>a</I>).</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Assets of the Commission<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><change>(5) All amounts paid into the Employment Insurance Account</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0"><change>(<I>a</I>) shall become part of the assets of the Commission; and</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0"><change>(<I>b</I>) shall, as they are paid into the Account, be deposited with a financial institution within the meaning of the <I>Financial Consumer Agency of Canada Act</I>, a body corporate to which the <I>Trust and Loan Companies Act</I> applies, or an association to which the <I>Cooperative Credit Associations Act</I> applies.</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Duties of the Commission<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><change>(6) The Commission shall</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0"><change>(<I>a</I>) manage the amounts paid into the Employment Insurance Account in the best interests of the contributors and beneficiaries under the employment insurance system; and</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0"><change>(<I>b</I>) subject to section 73, invest its assets with a financial institution, body corporate or association referred to in paragraph (5)(<I>b</I>) with a view to achieving a maximum rate of return without undue risk of loss, having regard to the factors that may affect the funding of the employment insurance system provided for in this Act and the ability of the Commission to meet its financial obligations.</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Loans to Her Majesty
in right of Canada
<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>73.</B> <change>At the request of the Minister of Finance, the Commission may extend a loan to Her Majesty in right of Canada to be repaid on such terms and conditions, including interest, as the Commission may establish</change>.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Loan to the Commission<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>74.</B> <change>(1)</change> <change>Where the assets of the Employment Insurance Account are not sufficient for the payment of the amounts that the Commission is liable to pay under this Act, the Minister of Finance shall, at the request of the Commission, extend a loan from the Consolidated Revenue Fund to the Commission in an amount sufficient to meet the payments</change>.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Repayment<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><change>(2) The Minister of Finance shall set an interest rate and terms and conditions for the repayment of the loan that are more advantageous to the Commission then those that the Commission can obtain from a financial institution.</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>3.</B> Sections 77 and 78 of the Act are replaced by the following:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Amounts paid out of the
Employment Insurance Account
<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>77.</B> (1) There shall be paid out of the Employment Insurance Account</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>a</I>) all amounts paid as or on account of benefits under this Act;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>b</I>) all amounts paid under section 61 for employment benefits and support measures authorized by Part II;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>c</I>) all amounts paid under paragraph 63(<I>a</I>);</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>d</I>) the costs of administering this Act, including administration costs paid under section 62 or paragraph 63(<I>b</I>)<change>;</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0"><change>(<I>e</I>) any amount loaned by the Commission to Her Majesty in right of Canada under section 73; and</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0"><change>(<I>f</I>) any other amount to be paid by the Commission under this Act, including all amounts paid by the Commission under an agreement with the government of a prov­ince.</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Payment by 
special
warrants
<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(2) <change>Despite any other Act of Parliament</change>, amounts mentioned in paragraph (1)(<I>a</I>) shall be paid by special warrants drawn on and issued by the Commission by electronic means or bearing the printed signature of the Chairperson and Vice-Chairperson of the Commission, and amounts mentioned in paragraphs (1)(<I>b</I>) and (<I>c</I>) may be paid by the special warrants.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>No charge for negotiation<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(3) The special warrants are negotiable without charge at any financial institution in Canada.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>4.</B> Section 80 of the Act is repealed.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:DEPARTMENT OF HUMAN RESOURCES AND SKILLS DEVELOPMENT ACT--><MarginalNote>2005, c. 34<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="10" Bold="Yes" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">DEPARTMENT OF HUMAN RESOURCES AND SKILLS DEVELOPMENT ACT</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>5.</B> Subsections 20(1) and (2) of the <I>Department of Human Resources and Skills Development Act</I> are replaced by the following:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Establishment of Commission<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>20.</B> (1) <change>There is hereby established a Commission to be known as the</change> Canada Employment Insurance Commission.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Commissioners<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(2) The <change>Commission shall be composed of 17</change>  commissioners, <change>as follows</change>:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>a</I>) <change>a</change> Chairperson;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>b</I>) <change>two Vice-Chairpersons</change>;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>c</I>) <change>seven representatives</change> of <change>employees</change> and <change>seven representatives</change> of employers.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>6.</B> The Act is amended by adding the following after section 21:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Appointment of commissioners<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><change><B>21.1</B> (1) The Governor in Council shall appoint the commissioners who will represent employees and employers from a list of nominees provided by associations represen-ting employees and employers in Canada.</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Appointment of Vice-Chairpersons<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><change>(2) The Governor in Council appoints the Vice-Chairpersons from among the Deputy Ministers or the Associate Deputy Ministers of the Department of Human Resources and Skills Development.</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Appointment of Chairperson<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><change><B>21.2</B> (1) The Chairperson shall be appointed by the House of Commons on the recom-mendation of the Minister following consultation of the commissioners representing employees and employers.</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Deciding vote<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><change>(2) The Chairperson shall not vote, but shall cast a deciding vote in case of an equal division.</change></Para></Block><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="BPT_ImprintE">Published under authority of the Speaker of the House of Commons<br/>Available from:<br/>Publishing and Depository Services<br/>Public Works and Government Services Canada<br/>Ottawa, Ontario K1A 0S5<br/>Telephone: 613-941-5995 or 1-800-635-7943<br/>Fax: 613-954-5779 or 1-800-565-7757<br/>publications@tpsgc-pwgsc.gc.ca<br/>http://publications.gc.ca</Para></Block><Block Align="Yes" LineCnt="N"><Para NoLineBreak="Yes" NoHtml="Yes" Leading="0" Size="0" TopMargin="0" BottomMargin="0"></Para></Block></Bill_Part></Bill>
