<?xml version="1.0"?>
<Bill RHead_reign="55 Eliz. II" RHead_ParlYear="2006" DocumentTitle="BILL C-350" Bill_No="C-350" Document_No="391342" xml:lang="EN" Bill_Type="Non-amending" Stage_Name="First-Reading-House" Reprint="No" xml:space="preserve" ChapterNo_E="C. " ChapterNo_F="ch. " Bill-Origin="commons"><Bill_Part Part_Type="Cover" CountLines="No"><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="CovBillNo">C-350</Para></Block><Block><Para TopMargin="24" Size="9" Leading="10" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0" TextAlign="Center">First Session, Thirty-ninth Parliament,</Para></Block><Block><Para Size="9" Leading="10" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0" TextAlign="Center">55 Elizabeth II, 2006</Para></Block><Block><Para TopMargin="48" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0" Bold="Yes" TextAlign="Center">HOUSE OF COMMONS OF CANADA</Para></Block><Block><Para TopMargin="42" Size="18" Leading="20" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0" Bold="Yes" TextAlign="Center">BILL C-350</Para></Block><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="CovLongTitle">An Act to amend the Criminal Code (bail for persons charged with violent offences), the Extradition Act and the Youth Criminal Justice Act</Para></Block><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="COV_StageLine"></Para></Block><Block><Para Size="9" AllCaps="Yes" Hyphenate="OFF">first reading, September 18, 2006</Para></Block><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="COV_StageLine"></Para></Block><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="Cover_Sponsors"><SC SC_PerCent="85">Mr. Thompson</SC> (<I>Wild Rose</I>)</Para></Block><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="Cover_DocNo">391342</Para></Block></Bill_Part><Bill_Part CountLines="No" Part_Type="InsideCover"><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="BPT_InsideCoverE">Also available on the Parliament of Canada Web Site at the following address:<br/><B>http://www.parl.gc.ca</B></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><Para TopMargin="108" BottomMargin="4" Size="10" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">SUMMARY</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" Size="8" Leading="9" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">This enactment repeals section 522 of the <I>Criminal Code</I> to remove the power of a judge of a superior court of criminal jurisdiction to grant interim release to a person accused of one of the very serious offences listed in section 469. These offences are</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" Size="8" Leading="9" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">(<I>a</I>) an offence under any of the following sections:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" Size="8" Leading="9" LeftMargin="4" FirstLineIndent="0" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">(i) section 47 (treason),</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" Size="8" Leading="9" LeftMargin="4" FirstLineIndent="0" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">(ii) section 49 (alarming Her Majesty),</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" Size="8" Leading="9" LeftMargin="4" FirstLineIndent="0" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">(iii) section 51 (intimidating Parliament or a legislature),</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" Size="8" Leading="9" LeftMargin="4" FirstLineIndent="0" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">(iv) section 53 (inciting to mutiny),</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" Size="8" Leading="9" LeftMargin="4" FirstLineIndent="0" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">(v) section 61 (seditious offences),</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" Size="8" Leading="9" LeftMargin="4" FirstLineIndent="0" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">(vi) section 74 (piracy),</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" Size="8" Leading="9" LeftMargin="4" FirstLineIndent="0" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">(vii) section 75 (piratical acts), or</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" Size="8" Leading="9" LeftMargin="4" FirstLineIndent="0" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">(viii) section 235 (murder);</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" Size="8" Leading="9" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">(<I>b</I>) the offence of being an accessory after the fact to high treason or treason or murder;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" Size="8" Leading="9" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">(<I>c</I>) an offence under section 119 (bribery of  judicial officers);</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" Size="8" Leading="9" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">(<I>c.1</I>) an offence under any of sections 4 to 7 of the <I>Crimes Against Humanity and War Crimes Act</I>;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" Size="8" Leading="9" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">(<I>d</I>) the offence of attempting to commit any offence mentioned in any of subparagraphs (<I>a</I>)(i) to (vii); and</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" Size="8" Leading="9" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">(<I>e</I>) the offence of conspiring to commit any offence mentioned in paragraph (<I>a</I>).</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" Size="8" Leading="9" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">The enactment also prohibits the interim release of a person accused of an offence under section 264 (criminal harassment), 272 (sexual assault with a weapon, threats to a third party or causing bodily harm) or 273 (aggravated sexual assault), if there is direct evidence of identification. It provides that, if an application for the interim release of such a person is brought before a justice, and the justice is satisfied that there is credible or trustworthy evidence of identification of the accused by a victim or witness, the application must be refused.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" Size="8" Leading="9" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">The enactment also makes related amendments to the <I>Extradition Act</I> and the <I>Youth Criminal Justice Act</I>.</Para></Block></Bill_Part><Bill_Part Part_Type="MainText" CountLines="Yes" RunningHead_E="Criminal Code (bail for persons charged with violent offences), Extradition and Youth Criminal Justice"><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="MainText_DocNo">391342</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes"><Para Style="Session_Reign">1st Session, 39th Parliament,</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes"><Para Style="Session_Reign">55 Elizabeth II, 2006</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes"><Para Style="MainBillOrigin">house of commons of canada</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes"><Para Bold="Yes" Style="MAIN@BillNo_Title">BILL C-350</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes"><Para Style="MAIN@ti;04">An Act to amend the Criminal Code (bail for persons charged with violent offences), the Extradition Act and the Youth Criminal Justice Act</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">Her Majesty, by and with the advice and consent of the Senate and House of Commons of Canada, enacts as follows:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:CRIMINAL CODE--><MarginalNote>R.S., c. C-46<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="10" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center"><B>CRIMINAL CODE</B></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>1.</B> The portion of subsection 145(3) of the <I>Criminal Code</I> before paragraph (<I>a</I>) is replaced by the following:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Failure to comply with condition of undertaking or recognizance<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(3) Every person who is at large on an undertaking or recognizance given to or entered into before a justice or judge and is bound to comply with a condition of that undertaking or recognizance directed by a justice or judge, and every person who is bound to comply with a direction ordered under subsection 515(12), and who fails, without lawful excuse, the proof of which lies on that person, to comply with that condition or direction, is guilty of</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>2.</B> The portion of subsection 499(1) of the Act before paragraph (<I>a</I>) is replaced by the following:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Release from custody by officer in charge where arrest made with warrant<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>499.</B> (1) Where a person who has been arrested with a warrant by a peace officer is taken into custody for an offence other than one <change>listed</change> in section <change>469</change>, the officer in charge may, if the warrant has been endorsed by a justice under subsection 507(6),</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>3.</B> Subsection 503(2) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Conditional release<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(2) If a peace officer or an officer in charge is satisfied that a person described in subsection (1) should be released from custody conditionally, the officer may, unless the person is detained in custody for an offence <change>listed</change> in section <change>469</change>, release that person on the person’s giving a promise to appear or entering into a recognizance in accordance with paragraphs 498(1)(<I>b</I>) to (<I>d</I>) and subsection (2.1).</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>4.</B> Subsection 507(6) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Endorsement of warrant by justice<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(6) A justice who issues a warrant under this section or section 508 or 512 may, unless the offence is one <change>listed</change> in section <change>469</change>, authorize the release of the accused pursuant to section 499 by making an endorsement on the warrant in Form 29.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>5.</B> Subsection 515(1) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Order of Release<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>515.</B> (1) Subject to this section, where an accused who is charged with an offence other than</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0"><change>(<I>a</I>)</change> an offence listed in section 469, <change>or</change>  </Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0"><change>(<I>b</I>) an offence under section 264, 272 or 273, where the court is satisfied that a person who was the victim of or a witness to the alleged offence has made a statement under oath or by solemn affirmation identifying the accused as the person who committed the offence and the justice, after inquiry made or evidence presented under subsection 518(1), is satisfied that the statement is credible or trustworthy in the circumstances, </change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">is taken before a justice, the justice shall, unless a plea of guilty by the accused is accepted, order, in respect of that offence, that the accused be released on his giving an undertaking without conditions, unless the prosecutor, having been given a reasonable opportunity to do so, shows cause, in respect of that offence, why the detention of the accused in custody is justified or why an order under any other provision of this section should be made and where the justice makes an order under any other provision of this section, the order shall refer only to the particular offence for which the accused was taken before the justice.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Cases where no interim release<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><change>(1.1) If an accused is charged with an offence referred to in paragraph (1)(<I>a</I>), or with an offence referred to in paragraph (1)(<I>b</I>) where the circumstances mentioned in that paragraph apply, no court, judge or justice may release the accused before or after the accused has been ordered to stand trial. </change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>6.</B> Section 522 of the Act is repealed.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>7.</B> Subsection 523(1) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Period for which appearance notice, etc., continues in force<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>523.</B> (1) Where an accused, in respect of an offence with which he is charged, has not been taken into custody or has been released from custody under or by virtue of any provision of this Part, the appearance notice, promise to appear, summons, undertaking or recognizance issued to, given or entered into by the accused continues in force, subject to its terms, and applies in respect of any new information charging the same offence or an included offence that was received after the appearance notice, promise to appear, summons, undertaking or recognizance was issued, given or entered into, until his trial is completed, and <change>if</change> the accused is, at his trial, determined to be guilty of the offence, until a sentence within the meaning of section 673 is imposed on the accused unless, at the time the accused is determined to be guilty, the court, judge or justice orders that the accused be taken into custody pending such sentence.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>8.</B> (1) Subsections 524(3) to (7) of the Act are replaced by the following:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Hearing<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(3) Where an accused who has been arrested with a warrant issued under subsection (1), or who has been arrested under subsection (2), is taken before a justice, the justice shall hear the prosecutor and his witnesses, if any, and the accused and his witnesses, if any.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes">(2) The portion of subsection 524(8) of the Act before paragraph (<I>a</I>) is replaced by the following:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Powers of justice after hearing<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(8) Where an accused described in subsection (3) is taken before the justice and the justice finds</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes">(3) Subsection 524(12) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Provisions applicable to proceedings under this section<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(12) The provisions of sections 517, 518 and 519 apply<change>,</change> with such modifications as the circumstances require, in respect of any proceedings under this section.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>9.</B> Subsection 672.16(3) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Presumption of custody in certain circumstances<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(3) An assessment order made in respect of an accused who is detained under subsection 515(6) shall order that the accused be detained in custody under the same circumstances referred to in that subsection, unless the accused shows that custody is not justified under the terms of that subsection.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>10.</B> Subsection 679(7.1) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Release or detention pending new trial or new hearing<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(7.1) Where, with respect to any person, the court of appeal or the Supreme Court of Canada orders a new trial, section 515 applies to the release or detention of that person pending the new trial or new hearing as though that person were charged with the offence for the first time, except that the powers of a justice under section 515 are exercised by a judge of the court of appeal.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>11.</B> The portion of subsection 680(1) of the Act before paragraph (<I>a</I>) is replaced by the following:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Review by court of appeal<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>680.</B> (1) A decision made by a judge of the court of appeal under section 261 or 679 may, on the direction of the chief justice or acting chief justice of the court of appeal, be reviewed by that court and that court may, if it does not confirm the decision,</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>12.</B> Paragraphs (<I>d</I>) and (<I>e</I>) of Form 8 of the Act are replaced by the following:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>d</I>) the accused has contravened or was about to contravene his (promise to appear <I>or</I> undertaking <I>or</I> recognizance) and the same was cancelled, and the detention of the accused in custody is justified or seems proper in the circumstances [524(8)];</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>e</I>) there are reasonable grounds to believe that the accused has after his release from custody on (a promise to appear <I>or</I> an undertaking <I>or</I> a recognizance) committed an indictable offence and the detention of the accused in custody is justified or seems proper in the circumstances [524(8)];</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>13.</B> The portion of subsection 145(3) of the Act before paragraph (<I>a</I>), cited in Form 12, is replaced by the following:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(3) Every person who is at large on an undertaking or recognizance given to or entered into before a justice or judge and is bound to comply with a condition of that undertaking or recognizance directed by a justice or judge, and every person who is bound to comply with a direction ordered under subsection 515(12), and who fails, without lawful excuse, the proof of which lies on that person, to comply with that condition or direction, is guilty of</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>14.</B> The paragraph of Form 29 of the Act is replaced by the following:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">Whereas this warrant is issued under section 507, 508 or 512 of the <I>Criminal Code</I> in respect of an offence other than an offence <change>listed</change> in section <change>469</change> of the <I>Criminal Code</I>, I hereby authorize the release of the accused pursuant to section 499 of that Act.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>15.</B> Item 1 of Form 32 of the Act is replaced by the following:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">1. Whereas the said ................, hereinafter called the accused, has been charged that (<I>set out the offence in respect of which the accused has been charged</I>);</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">Now, therefore, the condition of this recognizance is that if the accused attends court on .............. day, the .................. day of ........................ A.D. ..............................., at ......................... o’clock in the ................... noon and attends thereafter as required by the court in order to be dealt with according to law (<I>or, where date and place of appearance before court are not known at the time recognizance is entered into</I> if the accused attends at the time and place fixed by the court and attends thereafter as required by the court in order to be dealt with according to law) [515, 520, 521, 523, 524, 525, 680];</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">And further, if the accused (<I>insert in Schedule of Conditions any additional conditions that are directed</I>), the said recognizance is void, otherwise it stands in full force and effect.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:EXTRADITION ACT--><MarginalNote>1999, c. 18<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="10" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center"><B>EXTRADITION ACT</B></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>16.</B> Subparagraph 18(1)(<I>a</I>)(i) of the <I>Extradition Act</I> is replaced by the following:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="4" FirstLineIndent="0">(i) the person<change>, having been given a reasonable opportunity to do so,</change> shows cause <change>why</change> their detention in custody is not justified <change>within the meaning of</change> subsection <change>515(10)</change> of the <I>Criminal Code</I>.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes"><!--Heading:YOUTH CRIMINAL JUSTICE ACT--><MarginalNote>2002, c. 1<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="10" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center"><B>YOUTH CRIMINAL JUSTICE ACT</B></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>17.</B> Subsection 33(8) of the <I>Youth Criminal Justice Act </I>is replaced by the following:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Interim release by youth justice court judge only

<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(8) If a young person against whom proceedings have been taken under this Act is charged with an offence <change>listed</change> in section <change>469</change> of the <I>Criminal Code</I>, a youth justice court judge, but no other court, judge or justice, may<change>, before or after the young person has been ordered to stand trial,</change> release the young person from custody <change>if he or she, having been given a</change> <change>reasonable opportunity to do so, shows cause why his or her detention in custody is not justified within the meaning of subsection 515(10) of </change><change>the <I>Criminal Code</I></change>.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Order re no communication<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><change>(8.1) A youth justice court judge referred to in subsection (8) who orders that a young person be detained in custody under this section may include in the order a direction that the young person abstain from communicating, directly or indirectly, with any victim, witness or other person identified in the order except in accordance with the conditions specified in the order that the judge considers necessary.</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Release of young person<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><change>(8.2) If the youth justice court judge does not order that the young person be detained in custody under this section, the judge may order that the young person be released on giving an undertaking or entering into a recognizance described in any of paragraphs 515(2)(<I>a</I>) to (<I>e</I>) of the <I>Criminal Code</I> with the conditions described in subsections 515(4), (4.1) and (4.2) of the <I>Criminal Code</I> that the judge considers desirable.</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Application of sections 517, 518 and 519 of the <I>Criminal Code</I><br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><change>(8.3) The provisions of sections 517, 518, except subsection (2) thereof, and 519 of the <I>Criminal Code</I> apply, with such modifications as the circumstances require, in respect of a hearing held under subsection (8). </change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Other offences<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><change>(8.4) Where a young person is charged with an offence listed in section 469 of the <I>Criminal Code</I> and with any other offence, a judge acting under this section may apply the provisions of this section to that other offence. </change></Para></Block><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="BPT_ImprintE">Published under authority of the Speaker of the House of Commons<br/>Available from:<br/>Publishing and Depository Services<br/>Public Works and Government Services Canada<br/>Ottawa, Ontario K1A 0S5<br/>Telephone: 613-941-5995 or 1-800-635-7943<br/>Fax: 613-954-5779 or 1-800-565-7757<br/>publications@tpsgc-pwgsc.gc.ca<br/>http://publications.gc.ca</Para></Block><Block Align="Yes" LineCnt="N"><Para NoLineBreak="Yes" NoHtml="Yes" Leading="0" Size="0" TopMargin="0" BottomMargin="0"></Para></Block></Bill_Part></Bill>
