<?xml version="1.0"?>
<Bill RHead_reign="55 Eliz. II" RHead_ParlYear="2006" DocumentTitle="BILL C-360" Bill_No="C-360" Document_No="391357" xml:lang="EN" Bill_Type="Non-amending" Stage_Name="First-Reading-House" Reprint="No" xml:space="preserve" ChapterNo_E="C. " ChapterNo_F="ch. " Bill-Origin="commons"><Bill_Part Part_Type="Cover" CountLines="No"><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="CovBillNo">C-360</Para></Block><Block><Para TopMargin="24" Size="9" Leading="10" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0" TextAlign="Center">First Session, Thirty-ninth Parliament,</Para></Block><Block><Para Size="9" Leading="10" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0" TextAlign="Center">55 Elizabeth II, 2006</Para></Block><Block><Para TopMargin="48" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0" Bold="Yes" TextAlign="Center">HOUSE OF COMMONS OF CANADA</Para></Block><Block><Para TopMargin="42" Size="18" Leading="20" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0" Bold="Yes" TextAlign="Center">BILL C-360</Para></Block><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="CovLongTitle">An Act to establish the Office of the Ombudsman for Older Adult Justice and the Canadian Older Adult Justice Agency and to amend the Criminal Code</Para></Block><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="COV_StageLine"></Para></Block><Block><Para Size="9" AllCaps="Yes" Hyphenate="OFF">first reading, October 23, 2006</Para></Block><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="COV_StageLine"></Para></Block><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="Cover_Sponsors"><SC SC_PerCent="85">Mr. St. Amand</SC></Para></Block><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="Cover_DocNo">391357</Para></Block></Bill_Part><Bill_Part CountLines="No" Part_Type="InsideCover"><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="BPT_InsideCoverE">Also available on the Parliament of Canada Web Site at the following address:<br/><B>http://www.parl.gc.ca</B></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><Para TopMargin="108" BottomMargin="4" Size="10" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">SUMMARY</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" Size="8" Leading="9" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">Part 1 establishes the Office of the Ombudsman for Older Adult Justice, responsible for promoting the protection of older adult rights, investigating complaints, and referring to the Minister of Justice matters not settled satisfactorily.
</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" Size="8" Leading="9" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">Part 2 establishes the Canadian Older Adult Justice Agency, responsible for providing resources to promote the protection of older adult rights, including information on the prevention, detection, assessment, identification and treatment of older adult abuse, neglect and exploitation.
</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" Size="8" Leading="9" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">The enactment also amends the <I>Criminal Code</I> to include, as victims of abuse in the commission of an offence, the offender’s father and mother and any person for whom the offender is providing care.
</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" Size="8" Leading="9" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">It also includes, for the purpose of sentencing, the vulnerability of the victim as an aggravating circumstance.
</Para></Block></Bill_Part><Bill_Part Part_Type="MainText" CountLines="Yes" RunningHead_E="Older Adult Justice"><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="MainText_DocNo">391357</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes"><Para Style="Session_Reign">1st Session, 39th Parliament,</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes"><Para Style="Session_Reign">55 Elizabeth II, 2006</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes"><Para Style="MainBillOrigin">house of commons of canada</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes"><Para Bold="Yes" Style="MAIN@BillNo_Title">BILL C-360</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes"><Para Style="MAIN@ti;04">An Act to establish the Office of the Ombudsman for Older Adult Justice and the Canadian Older Adult Justice Agency and to amend the Criminal Code</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><MarginalNote>Preamble
<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">WHEREAS research on the victimization of older adults is relatively recent, as this social issue was brought to the attention of the Canadian public only in the 1980’s;
</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">WHEREAS existing statistics on the victimization of older adults represent only a portion of the actual number of incidents of older adults abuse, as a large number of incidents are concealed or unreported;
</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">WHEREAS the Government of Canada wishes to increase awareness among Canadians that older adult abuse is a significant problem that impacts on the quality of life of many older adults across Canada;
</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">AND WHEREAS the Government of Canada wishes to improve the quality of life and well-being of older adults in Canada by encouraging and supporting research and concrete action dealing with older adult abuse in Canada;
</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">NOW, THEREFORE, Her Majesty, by and with the advice and consent of the Senate and House of Commons of Canada, enacts as follows:
</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:SHORT TITLE
--><Para TopMargin="10" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">SHORT TITLE
</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Short title<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>1.</B> This Act may be cited as the <I>Older Adult Justice Act</I>.
</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:INTERPRETATION
--><Para TopMargin="10" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">INTERPRETATION
</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Definitions<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>2.</B> The definitions in this section apply in this Act.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><MarginalNote>“abuse”<br/>« <I>mauvais traitements</I> »<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0">“abuse” means the knowing infliction of physical, psychological or financial harm on an older adult or the knowing deprivation of goods or services that are necessary to meet the essential needs of or to avoid physical or psychological harm to an older adult.

</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><MarginalNote>“Agency”<br/>« <I>Agence</I> »<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0">“Agency” means the Canadian Older Adult Justice Agency established under section 10.
</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><MarginalNote>“older adult”<br/>« <I>aîné</I> »<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0">“older adult” means an individual 65 years of age or older.
</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><MarginalNote>“older adult justice”<br/>« <I>protection des droits des 
aînés</I> »<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0">“older adult justice” means
</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>a</I>) from a societal perspective, efforts to prevent, detect, treat, intervene in and, where appropriate, prosecute older adult abuse, neglect and exploitation, and to protect older adults while maximizing their autonomy; and

</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>b</I>) from an individual perspective, the recognition of an older adult’s rights, including the right to be free of abuse, neglect and exploitation.

</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><MarginalNote>“Minister”<br/>« <I>ministre</I> »<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0">“Minister” means the Minister of Justice.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><MarginalNote>“neglect”<br/>« <I>négligence</I> »<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0">“neglect” means</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>a</I>) the failure of a caregiver or a guardian or curator to provide the goods or services that are necessary to maintain the health or safety of an older adult; or</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>b</I>) self-neglect.

</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><MarginalNote>“Ombudsman”<br/>« <I>Protecteur des droits des 
aînés</I> »<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0">“Ombudsman” means the person holding the office of the Ombudsman for Older Adult Justice appointed under section 5.
</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:PART 1
--><Para TopMargin="10" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">PART 1
</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:OMBUDSMAN FOR OLDER ADULT JUSTICE
--><Para TopMargin="5" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">OMBUDSMAN FOR OLDER ADULT JUSTICE
</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:Office of Ombudsman
--><Para TopMargin="5" SmallCaps="Yes" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">Office of Ombudsman
</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Office established<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>3.</B> There is hereby established the Office of the Ombudsman for Older Adult Justice.
</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Duties and functions of Ombudsman<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>4.</B> (1) The duties and functions of the Ombudsman are</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>a</I>)  to act as a neutral and objective sounding board, mediator, investigator and reporter on matters relating to older adult abuse, neglect and exploitation;

</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>b</I>) to examine potential issues relating to the protection of older adults from abuse, neglect and exploitation;

</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>c</I>) to identify and suggest ways of improving gaps in the detection, investigation and reporting of older adult abuse;

</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>d</I>) to annually collect and disseminate data relating to the abuse, exploitation and neglect of older adults;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>e</I>) to provide advice to the Government of Canada on older adult justice issues;

</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>f</I>) to suggest a long-term strategic plan for older adult justice programs and for activities relating to the prevention, detection, training, treatment, evaluation, intervention, research and improvement of the older adult justice system; and

</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>g</I>) to assign an expert in sentencing case law or older adult case law to examine existing laws, nationally and internationally, and identify best practices.
</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Additional activities
<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(2) The Ombudsman may perform additional activities, including

</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>a</I>) carrying out studies to determine the national incidence and prevalence of older adult abuse, neglect and exploitation in all settings;

</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>b</I>) developing uniform, validated screening tools to assist individuals, families, practitioners, institutions and communities in detecting ongoing or potential older adult abuse, neglect and exploitation;

</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>c</I>) carrying out various types of intervention research;

</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>d</I>) identifying steps that can be taken and replicated to make homes, neighbourhoods, communities and facilities safer for older adults and enhance older adults’ sense of security in all kinds of environments;

</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>e</I>) researching successful guardianship, curatorship and trust practices and systems to enhance the well-being of persons with diminished capacity; and

</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>f</I>) developing and recommending guide-lines to assist institutional or peer review boards in the review of research.
</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Information program<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(3) The Ombudsman shall maintain a program of communicating information to the victims concerning

</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>a</I>) the functions of the Ombudsman;

</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>b</I>) the circumstances under which the  Ombudsman may commence an investigation or a study; and

</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>c</I>) the independence of the Ombudsman.
</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Appointment<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>5.</B> (1) The Governor in Council shall, by commission under the Great Seal, appoint an Ombudsman after approval of the appointment by resolution of the Senate and House of Commons.
</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Eligibility for appointment<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(2) A person is eligible to be appointed or to continue as Ombudsman only if that person is a Canadian citizen ordinarily resident in Canada or a permanent resident as defined in subsection 2(1) of the <I>Immigration and Refugee Protection Act</I>.
</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Tenure of office and removal<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(3) Subject to this section, the Ombudsman holds office during good behaviour for a term of five years, but may be removed by the Governor in Council at any time on address of the Senate and House of Commons.
</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Further terms<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(4) The Ombudsman, on the expiration of a first or any subsequent term of office, is eligible to be re-appointed for a further term not exceeding five years.
</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Absence or incapacity<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(5) In the event of the absence or incapacity of the Ombudsman or if the office of Ombudsman is vacant, the Governor in Council may appoint another qualified person to hold office instead of the Ombudsman for a term not exceeding six months, and that person shall, while holding that office, have all of the powers, duties and functions of the Ombudsman under this Act or any other Act of Parliament and be paid such salary or other remuneration and expenses as may be fixed by the Governor in Council.
</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Remuneration<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(6) The Ombudsman shall receive such salary or other remuneration, benefits and reimbursement of expenses as may be fixed by the Governor in Council.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Part of federal public administration<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(7) The Office of the Ombudsman is part of the federal public administration.
</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Staff of the Ombudsman<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(8) Such officers and employees as are necessary to enable the Ombudsman to perform the duties and functions and additional activities of the Ombudsman under this Act or any other Act of Parliament shall be appointed in accordance with the <I>Public Service Employment Act</I>.
</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Technical assistance
<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(9) The Ombudsman may engage, on a temporary basis, the services of persons having technical or specialized knowledge of any matter relating to the work of the Ombudsman to advise and assist the Ombudsman in the performance of the duties and functions and additional activities of the Ombudsman under this Act or any other Act of Parliament and, with the approval of the Treasury Board, may fix and pay the remuneration and expenses of such persons.
</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Confidentiality<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(10) Subject to this Act, the Ombudsman and every person acting on behalf or under the direction of the Ombudsman shall not disclose any information that comes to their knowledge in the performance of their duties and functions and additional activities under this Act or any other Act of Parliament.
</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:Complaints and Investigations--><Para TopMargin="10" SmallCaps="Yes" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">Complaints and Investigations</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Complaints<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>6.</B> A person may make a complaint to the Ombudsman, specifying the grounds for the complaint, if the person has reason to believe that an older adult is experiencing

</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>a</I>) abuse or neglect in a domestic setting or in institutional settings; or

</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>b</I>) self-abuse or self-neglect.
</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Investigation or study<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>7.</B> (1) The Ombudsman may commence an investigation or a study</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>a</I>) at the written direction of the Minister; or

</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>b</I>) on the initiative of the Ombudsman.
</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Application of other substantive law<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(2) The provisions of this Act are not deemed to abrogate or supersede the substantive provisions of the <I>Criminal Code</I> or of any other law or statute relating to criminal or police investigations.
</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Discretion<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(3) The Ombudsman has full discretion as to</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>a</I>) whether an investigation or a study should be conducted in relation to a complaint or request;

</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>b</I>) how each investigation or study is to be carried out; and</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>c</I>) whether an investigation or a study should be terminated before completion.
</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>If investigation is necessary<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(4) If an investigation is necessary to carry out the Ombudsman’s mandate in connection with a complaint received by the Ombudsman, the Ombudsman shall thoroughly investigate the complaint.
</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Time limit for completing investigation<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(5) The Ombudsman shall attempt, with the full and complete cooperation of all parties, to complete an investigation within 60 days of its commencement.
</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Complaint rejected<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(6) The Ombudsman may refuse to deal with a complaint or may discontinue dealing with a complaint at any stage if the Ombudsman considers that it is in the public interest to do so.
</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Factors to consider<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(7) For the purposes of subsection (3), the Ombudsman shall consider the following factors:

</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>a</I>) whether the complaint is frivolous or vexatious;

</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>b</I>) whether the complainant lacks sufficient personal interest in the matter;

</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>c</I>) the age of the complainant;

</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>d</I>) the amount of time between the day on which the complainant became aware of the matters giving rise to the complaint and the day on which the complaint was received by the Ombudsman; and

</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>e</I>) the need for judicious and efficient use of the Ombudsman’s resources.
</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Right to require information and documents<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(8) In the course of conducting an investigation or a study, the Ombudsman may require any person

</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>a</I>) to furnish any information that, in the opinion of the Ombudsman, the person may be able to furnish in relation to the matter being investigated or studied; and
</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>b</I>) subject to subsection (7), to produce, for examination by the Ombudsman, any document, paper or thing that, in the opinion of the Ombudsman, relates to the matter being investigated or studied and that may be in the possession or under the control of that person.
</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Return of documents<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(9) The Ombudsman shall return any document, paper or thing produced under paragraph (8)(<I>b</I>) to the person who produced it within 10 days after a request for its return is made to the Ombudsman, but nothing in this subsection precludes the Ombudsman from again requiring its production in accordance with that paragraph.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Right to make copies<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(10) The Ombudsman may make copies of any document, paper or thing produced under paragraph (8)(<I>b</I>).
</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Obstruction<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(11) No person shall obstruct the Ombudsman or any person acting on behalf or under the direction of the Ombudsman in the performance of the Ombudsman’s duties and functions under this Act.
</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Offence and punishment<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(12) Every person who contravenes this section is guilty of an offence and liable on summary conviction to a fine not exceeding five thousand dollars.
</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Disclosure authorized<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(13) The Ombudsman may disclose, or may authorize any person acting on behalf or under the direction of the Ombudsman to disclose, information

</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>a</I>) that, in the opinion of the Ombudsman, is necessary to

</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="4" FirstLineIndent="0">(i) carry out an investigation under this Act, or

</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="4" FirstLineIndent="0">(ii) establish the grounds for findings and recommendations contained in any report under this Act;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>b</I>) that is required  in the course of a prosecution for an offence under this Act, a prosecution for an offence under section 131 of the <I>Criminal Code</I> (perjury) in respect of a statement made under this Act, a review before the Federal Court or an appeal therefrom; and
</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>c</I>) that is obtained in the course of dealing with a matter and that, in the opinion of the Ombudsman, is evidence of a criminal offence committed by any person against an older adult and should be reported to the competent authority.
</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Acts not to be questioned or subject to review<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(14) Except on the ground of lack of jurisdiction, nothing done by the Ombudsman, including the making of any report or recommendation shall be challenged, reviewed, quashed or called into question in any court.
</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Result of investigation or study<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(15) The Ombudsman shall, in such manner and at such time as the Ombudsman considers appropriate, inform the victim and the complainant or the Minister, as the case may be, of the results of the investigation or study, and provide only such information as may be disclosed under the <I>Privacy Act or the Access to Information Act</I>.
</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>No summons<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(16) The Ombudsman or any person acting on behalf or under the direction of the Ombudsman is not a competent or compellable witness, in respect of any matter coming to the know­ledge of the Ombudsman or that person as a result of performing any duties or functions under this Act during an investigation, in any proceeding other than a prosecution for an offence under this Act, a prosecution for an offence under section 131 of the <I>Criminal Code</I> (perjury) in respect of a statement made under this Act, a review before the Federal Court or an appeal therefrom.  
</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Protection of Ombudsman
<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(17) No criminal or civil proceedings lie against the Ombudsman, or against any person acting on behalf or under the direction of the Ombudsman, for anything done, reported or said in good faith in the exercise or performance or purported exercise or performance of any duty or function of the Ombudsman under this Act.
</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Libel or slander<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(18) For the purposes of any law relating to libel or slander,</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>a</I>) anything said, any information supplied, or any document or thing produced in good faith in the course of an investigation carried out by or on behalf of the Ombudsman under this Act is privileged; and</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>b</I>) any report made in good faith by the Ombudsman under this Act and any fair and accurate account of the report made in good faith in a newspaper or any other periodical publication or in a broadcast is privileged. </Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:Findings, Reports and Recommendations--><Para TopMargin="10" SmallCaps="Yes" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">Findings, Reports and Recommendations</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Report on matter not settled<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>8.</B> (1) If a matter mediated by the Ombudsman is not settled to the satisfaction of the Ombudsman or the victim, the Ombudsman shall report the matter to the Minister, giving an opinion as to whether the complaint was justified and a recommendation on how the matter should be settled.
</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Recommendations
<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(2) The Ombudsman may make any recommendation that the Ombudsman considers appropriate, including a recommendation that the law, practice or policy on which the decision, recommendation, act or omission was based, be altered or reconsidered.
</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Action by Minister<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(3) The Minister shall attempt to resolve the matter referred under subsection (1) and shall prepare a report of any settlement made.
</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Tabling report<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(4) The Minister shall forthwith cause every report made under subsection (3) to be laid before both Houses of Parliament.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Annual report to Minister<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>9.</B> (1) The Ombudsman shall submit to the Minister by April 1 of every year a report that

</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>a</I>) describes the activities and accomplishments of, and challenges faced by

</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="4" FirstLineIndent="0">(i) the Ombudsman, and

</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="4" FirstLineIndent="0">(ii) the entities represented by the Ombudsman; and
</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>b</I>) makes recommendations for legislation, model law, or other appropriate action.
</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Report to be laid before Parliament
<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(2) The Minister shall forthwith cause the report to be laid before both Houses of Parliament.
</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:PART 2
--><Para TopMargin="10" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">PART 2
</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:CANADIAN OLDER ADULT JUSTICE AGENCY--><Para TopMargin="5" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">CANADIAN OLDER ADULT JUSTICE AGENCY</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:Establishment of Agency
--><Para TopMargin="5" SmallCaps="Yes" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">Establishment of Agency
</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Agency established<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>10. </B> (1) There is hereby established a not-for-profit corporation to be called the Canadian Older Adult Justice Agency.
</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Not an agent of Her Majesty<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(2) The Agency is not an agent of Her Majesty.
</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Not a departmental or Crown corporation<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(3) The Agency is not a departmental corporation or a Crown corporation within the meaning of the <I>Financial Administration Act</I>.
</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Both official languages to be used<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(4) The Agency shall offer its services to, and communicate with, the public in both official languages of Canada.
</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Head office<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(5) The head office of the Agency shall be at the place in Canada that is designated in the by-laws of the Agency.
</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:Objects and Powers
--><Para TopMargin="10" SmallCaps="Yes" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">Objects and Powers
</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Objects<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>11.</B> (1) The objects of the Agency are to</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>a</I>) coordinate and implement older adult justice policies and programs in cooperation with the governments of the provinces, with aboriginal governments and with government departments or agencies responsible for the protection of older adults;

</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>b</I>) develop the capacity and procedures to collect, maintain and disseminate information relevant to consumers, families, service providers, clinicians, advocates, regulators, law enforcement agencies, policy makers, researchers and public guardians, curators and trustees, including judges and lawyers, with respect to the prevention, detection, assessment, identification and treatment of, as well as intervention in and prosecution of, older adult abuse, neglect and exploitation;

</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>c</I>) provide, in a user-friendly manner, information on

</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="4" FirstLineIndent="0">(i) ways to promote autonomy in the face of aging or diminishing capacity and mobility,

</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="4" FirstLineIndent="0">(ii) ways to avoid becoming a victim of older adult abuse, neglect or exploitation, and

</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="4" FirstLineIndent="0">(iii) advance planning to avoid the need for a guardian, curator  or trustee;

</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>d</I>) provide links and references to other sources of information;
</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>e</I>) compile, analyse and publish a summary of research conducted on older adult abuse, neglect and exploitation and information on how to obtain the original research materials;

</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>f</I>) invite public comments;

</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>g</I>) establish a toll-free number for information and referrals;

</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>h</I>) coordinate activities with resource centres, agencies and database centres with respect to older adult justice;

</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>i</I>) provide funding to public and private agencies and entities to develop or continue the efforts of database centres and information repositories specializing in older adult justice to be linked to the Agency;

</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>j</I>) conduct a national multi-media campaign to raise awareness about older adult abuse, neglect and exploitation;
</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>k</I>) evaluate with provincial counterparts, where applicable, programs designed to meet the needs of older adults and their informal caregivers living in rural and northern locations; and

</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>l</I>) develop and disseminate national practices and procedures relating to protective services for older adults and provide training on those services.
</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Long-term care database<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(2) A long-term care database shall be established as part of the Agency and shall provide, in a consumer-friendly form, comprehensive and   detailed information, including links to websites, about choices relating to long-term care providers, and in particular, information about

</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>a</I>) obtaining the services or employing caregivers to provide long-term care at an individual’s home;

</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>b</I>) options for residential long-term care, including

</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="4" FirstLineIndent="0">(i) the type of care provided by nursing facilities, and

</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="4" FirstLineIndent="0">(ii) the type of care provided by group homes and other residential long-term care facilities; and

</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>c</I>) the care available through specific residential long-term care facilities, including data on the satisfaction level of residents of those facilities and their families.
</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Study
<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(3) The Agency shall conduct a study on consumer concerns relating to residential long-term care facilities to </Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>a</I>) develop definitions for classes of  residential long-term care facilities; and</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>b</I>) collect information on the prices, level of services, oversight and enforcement provisions, and admission and discharge criteria of those facilities.
</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Powers
<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>12.</B> (1) In carrying out its objects, the Agency has the capacity and powers of a natural person, including the power to

</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>a</I>) use any funds that may be provided to it, subject to any terms on which the funds are provided;

</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>b</I>) enter into contracts or agreements in its own name;

</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>c</I>) conduct studies with respect to the exercise of its powers; and

</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>d</I>) do any other thing that is conducive to the attainment of its objects and the exercise of its powers.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Restrictions<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(2) Despite subsection (1), the Agency

</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>a</I>) shall not acquire or construct real property or immovables for valuable consideration, other than those required for its head office;

</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>b</I>) shall expressly state in every contract and agreement that it is entering into the contract or agreement on its own behalf;

</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>c</I>) shall not procure the incorporation of a corporation any shares of which, on incorporation, would be held by, on behalf of or in trust for the Agency; and </Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>d</I>) shall not acquire shares of a corporation that, on acquisition, would be held by, on behalf of or in trust for the Agency.
</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:Board of Directors
--><Para TopMargin="10" SmallCaps="Yes" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">Board of Directors
</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Role<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>13.</B> The affairs of the Agency shall be managed by a board of directors that may, for that purpose, exercise all the powers of the Agency.
</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Composition<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>14.</B> (1) The board of directors shall consist of not more than 15 directors, including the chairperson and the executive director of the Agency, who does not have the right to vote.
</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Non-application of provisions<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(2) Sections 15, 17 and 19 do not apply to the executive director.
</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Appointment<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>15. </B> (1) The directors shall be appointed by the Minister to hold office during good behaviour for a term of not more than three years that will ensure, as far as possible, the expiry in any one year of the terms of office of not more than one half of the directors. A director shall be appointed for not more than two consecutive terms and may be removed by the Minister for cause.
</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Appointment criteria<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(2) The directors shall be chosen in accordance with guidelines established by the Minister in consultation with the older adult community.
</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Guidelines<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(3) The guidelines shall provide for a board of directors composed of men and women who are representative of the diversity and bilingual character of Canadian society and who have experience and expertise in older adult abuse, neglect and exploitation — notably their prevention, intervention, treatment, law enforcement or research — with due consideration to representation of the First Nations, of ethnic and racial minorities and diverse geographic areas, and who may include but are not limited to

</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>a</I>) individuals who represent social service providers;

</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>b</I>) health care providers, including geriatrics, emergency medicine, and nursing and mental health professionals;

</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>c</I>) representatives of the legal profession, judicial systems and law enforcement agencies;

</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>d</I>) gerontologists;

</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>e</I>) psychologists;

</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>f</I>) provincial and local government representatives;

</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>g</I>) organizations providing services to older adults and disabled persons;

</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>h</I>) volunteer groups;

</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>i</I>) representatives of the older adult community;

</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>j</I>) older adult rights advocates;

</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>k</I>) family groups;

</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>l</I>) experts in adult guardianship, curatorship or trust relationships, and those serving as or monitoring guardians, curators and trustees;

</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>m</I>) individuals in forensics-related positions, including coroners and forensic pathologists;

</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>n</I>)  representatives of the financial sector; and

</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>o</I>) individuals with the experience or capacity to enable the Agency to attain its objects.
</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote><I>Statutory Instruments Act</I> does not apply
<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(4) The guidelines referred to in subsection (3) are not statutory instruments for the purposes of the <I>Statutory Instruments Act</I>.
</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Exclusion<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>16.</B> A director shall not be appointed as an officer of the Agency.
</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>No remuneration<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>17.</B> The directors are not entitled to be paid any remuneration, but are entitled to be paid such reasonable travel and other expenses incurred by them in connection with their duties or functions under this Act as may be fixed by the by-laws of the Agency.
</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>By-laws<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>18.</B> (1) The board of directors may make by-laws with respect to the conduct and management of the affairs of the Agency and the carrying out of the duties and functions of the board under this Act, and in particular with respect to

</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>a</I>) the appointment, the remuneration and expenses and the functions and duties of the officers, employees and agents of the Agency;

</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>b</I>) the establishment and the operations of an executive committee and special committees;
</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>c</I>) the different classes of members, the qualifications for membership, the fees and dues payable by members, and the rights and obligations of members; and

</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>d</I>) any other thing relating to the conduct of the activities and affairs of the Agency.
</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>By-law to be sanctioned
<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(2) No by-law of the Agency is valid or shall be acted on until it is sanctioned at a general meeting of the members by at least two-thirds of those present and entitled to vote at the meeting.
</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>By-laws available to the public<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(3) A copy of every by-law shall be kept at the head office of the Agency. Anyone is entitled, during the usual business hours of the Agency, to examine the by-laws and, on payment of a reasonable fee, to make copies of or take extracts from them.  
</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote><I>Statutory Instruments Act</I> does not apply
<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(4) The by-laws made under subsection (1) are not statutory instruments for the purposes of the <I>Statutory Instruments Act</I>.
</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:Chairperson
--><Para TopMargin="10" SmallCaps="Yes" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">Chairperson
</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Designation<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>19.</B> The Minister, after consulting with the directors, shall designate one of them as chairperson to hold office during good behaviour for a term of not more than three years. The chairperson shall be designated for not more than two consecutive terms and may be removed by the Minister for cause.
</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Duties<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>20.</B> The chairperson shall determine the times and places of the meetings of the board of directors and shall preside at those meetings. The chairperson shall perform any other duties or functions that are assigned to the chairperson by the board of directors.
</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Absence or incapacity of chairperson<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>21.</B> If the chairperson is absent or incapacitated or if the office of chairperson is vacant, the board of directors may designate a director to exercise the powers and perform the duties and functions of the chairperson during the absence, incapacity or vacancy, but no person may be so designated for a period exceeding 90 days without the approval of the Minister.
</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:Executive Director
--><Para TopMargin="10" SmallCaps="Yes" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">Executive Director
</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Appointment<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>22.</B> The board of directors shall appoint an executive director of the Agency, who shall be paid such salary as is fixed by the board of directors, from the budget of the Agency.  
</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Duties<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>23.</B> The executive director is the chief executive officer of the Agency and has, on behalf of the board of directors, responsibility for the direction and management of the affairs and day-to-day operations of the Agency.
</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Absence or incapacity of executive director<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>24.</B> If the executive director is absent or incapacitated or if the office of executive director is vacant, the chairperson may designate a person to exercise the powers and perform the duties and functions of the executive director during the absence, incapacity or vacancy, but no person may be so designated for a period exceeding 90 days without the approval of the board of directors.
</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Delegation<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>25.</B>  The executive director may delegate to any person any power, duty or function conferred on the executive director under this Act.
</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:Staff
--><Para TopMargin="10" SmallCaps="Yes" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">Staff
</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Staff<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>26.</B>  The Agency may engage any employees and any technical and professional advisers that it considers necessary for the proper conduct of its activities.
</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Status<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>27.</B> The directors, officers and employees of the Agency are deemed not to be employed in the federal public administration and, for the purposes of the <I>Public Service Superannuation Act</I>, are deemed not to be employed in the public service.
</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:Corporate Plan
--><Para TopMargin="10" SmallCaps="Yes" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">Corporate Plan
</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Corporate plan<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>28.</B> (1) The Agency shall prepare a corporate plan for each fiscal year, and deliver a copy of that plan to the Minister at least 30 days before the start of that fiscal year.
</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Scope and content of corporate plan<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(2) The corporate plan shall encompass all the business and activities of the Agency and shall include a statement of
</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>a</I>)  the Agency’s objectives;

</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>b</I>)  the strategies that the Agency intends to use to achieve those objectives, including its operational and financial strategies and its human resource strategies; and

</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>c</I>)  the Agency’s operating and capital budgets for the next fiscal year.
</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Corporate plan to be made public<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(3) After delivering the corporate plan to the Minister, the Agency shall make the plan public.
</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Corporate plan to be tabled<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(4) The Minister shall cause a copy of the corporate plan to be tabled in each House of Parliament on any of the first fifteen days on which that House is sitting after the Minister receives the plan.
</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:Annual Report--><Para TopMargin="10" SmallCaps="Yes" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">Annual Report</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Annual report<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>29.</B> (1) The chairperson shall, within four months after the end of each fiscal year, deliver a report to the Minister on the operations of the Agency in that fiscal year.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Contents<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(2) The report shall include

</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>a</I>) the financial statements of the Agency and the report of the auditor respecting those statements;

</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>b</I>) a summary of the Agency’s corporate plan; and

</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>c</I>) information about the Agency’s performance with respect to the objectives established in the corporate plan.
</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Remuneration<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(3) The annual financial statements for a fiscal year shall set out the total remuneration, including any reimbursement or monetary benefit, received by each officer from the Agency in that fiscal year, and the amount of any reimbursement or monetary benefit received by each director from the Agency in that fiscal year.
</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Annual report to be tabled<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(4) The Minister shall cause a copy of the annual report to be tabled in each House of Parliament on any of the first fifteen days on which that House is sitting after the Minister receives the report.
</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Annual report to be made public<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(5) After the tabling of the report by the Minister in each House of Parliament, the Agency shall make the report public.
</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:PART 3
--><Para TopMargin="10" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">PART 3
</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:GENERAL--><Para TopMargin="5" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">GENERAL</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:Funding--><Para TopMargin="5" SmallCaps="Yes" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">Funding</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Funding<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>30.</B> The Minister shall establish funding arrangements with the board of directors of the Agency and with the Ombudsman, specifying the manner in which funding will be made available in accordance with a budget approved by the Minister.
</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:Review--><Para TopMargin="10" SmallCaps="Yes" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">Review</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Review after five years<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>31.</B> (1) On the expiration of five years after the coming into force of this Act, the provisions contained herein shall be referred to such committee of the House of Commons, of the Senate or of both Houses of Parliament as may be designated or established by Parliament to review the administration and operation of this Act.
</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Report to Parliament<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(2) The committee designated or established by Parliament for the purpose of subsection (1) shall, as soon as practicable, undertake a comprehensive review of the provisions and operation of this Act and shall, within one year after the review is undertaken or within such further time as the House of Commons may authorize, submit a report to Parliament thereon, including such recommendations pertaining to the continuation of those provisions and changes required therein as the committee may wish to make.
</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:Regulations--><Para TopMargin="10" SmallCaps="Yes" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">Regulations</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Regulations
<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>32.</B> (1) The Governor in Council may make regulations that are necessary for carrying out and giving effect to the provisions of this Act.
</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Contravention of regulation<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(2) A regulation made under subsection (1) may make it an offence to contravene the regulation.
</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:PART 4
--><Para TopMargin="10" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center"><B>PART 4
</B></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:AMENDMENTS AND COMING INTO FORCE
--><Para TopMargin="5" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center"><B>AMENDMENTS AND COMING INTO FORCE</B>
</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:Criminal Code
--><MarginalNote>R.S., c. C-46<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" SmallCaps="Yes" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center"><B>Criminal Code</B>
</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>33.</B> (1) Subparagraph 718.2(<I>a</I>)(ii) of the <I>Criminal Code</I> is replaced by the following:

</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="4" FirstLineIndent="0">(ii)  evidence that the offender, in committing the offence, abused the offender’s spouse or common-law partner, <change>the offender’s child, mother or father, or any person for whom the offender is providing care,</change>  
</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes">(2) Paragraph 718.2(<I>a</I>) of the Act is amended by striking the word “or” at the end of subparagraph (iv), by adding the word “or” at the end of subparagraph (v), and by adding the following after subparagraph (v):

</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="4" FirstLineIndent="0"><change>(vi)  evidence that the victim of the offence was a vulnerable person or an older adult within the meaning of the <I>Older Adult Justice Act</I> or evidence that the offender knowingly targeted the vulnerable person or older adult</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:Coming into Force
--><Para TopMargin="10" SmallCaps="Yes" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center"><B>Coming into Force
</B></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Coming into force<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>34.</B> This Act comes into force on a day or days to be fixed by order of the Governor in Council.
</Para></Block><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="BPT_ImprintE">Published under authority of the Speaker of the House of Commons<br/>Available from:<br/>Publishing and Depository Services<br/>Public Works and Government Services Canada<br/>Ottawa, Ontario K1A 0S5<br/>Telephone: 613-941-5995 or 1-800-635-7943<br/>Fax: 613-954-5779 or 1-800-565-7757<br/>publications@tpsgc-pwgsc.gc.ca<br/>http://publications.gc.ca</Para></Block><Block Align="Yes" LineCnt="N"><Para NoLineBreak="Yes" NoHtml="Yes" Leading="0" Size="0" TopMargin="0" BottomMargin="0"></Para></Block></Bill_Part></Bill>
