<?xml version="1.0"?>
<Bill RHead_reign="55 Eliz. II" RHead_ParlYear="2006" DocumentTitle="BILL C-382" Bill_No="C-382" Document_No="391327" xml:lang="EN" Bill_Type="Non-amending" Stage_Name="First-Reading-House" Reprint="No" xml:space="preserve" ChapterNo_E="C. " ChapterNo_F="ch. " Bill-Origin="commons"><Bill_Part Part_Type="Cover" CountLines="No"><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="CovBillNo">C-382</Para></Block><Block><Para TopMargin="24" Size="9" Leading="10" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0" TextAlign="Center">First Session, Thirty-ninth Parliament,</Para></Block><Block><Para Size="9" Leading="10" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0" TextAlign="Center">55 Elizabeth II, 2006</Para></Block><Block><Para TopMargin="48" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0" Bold="Yes" TextAlign="Center">HOUSE OF COMMONS OF CANADA</Para></Block><Block><Para TopMargin="42" Size="18" Leading="20" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0" Bold="Yes" TextAlign="Center">BILL C-382</Para></Block><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="CovLongTitle">An Act to provide for secure, adequate, accessible and affordable housing for Canadians </Para></Block><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="COV_StageLine"></Para></Block><Block><Para Size="9" AllCaps="Yes" Hyphenate="OFF">first reading, November 22, 2006</Para></Block><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="COV_StageLine"></Para></Block><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="Cover_Sponsors"><SC SC_PerCent="85">Mrs. Mathyssen</SC></Para></Block><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="Cover_DocNo">391327</Para></Block></Bill_Part><Bill_Part CountLines="No" Part_Type="InsideCover"><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="BPT_InsideCoverE">Also available on the Parliament of Canada Web Site at the following address:<br/><B>http://www.parl.gc.ca</B></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><Para TopMargin="108" BottomMargin="4" Size="10" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">SUMMARY</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" Size="8" Leading="9" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">The purpose of this enactment is to respect the dignity and worth of all women, children and men in Canada by protecting their human rights through the provision of secure, adequate, accessible and affordable housing and security in its enjoyment.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" Size="8" Leading="9" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">The enactment is to be achieved by the adoption of financial policies and by the establishment of a national housing strategy and programs to put it into effect.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" Size="8" Leading="9" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">The programs must ensure the supply of such housing to those who cannot otherwise afford it as soon as possible and as a legally enforceable right from January 1, 2007.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" Size="8" Leading="9" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">The Minister of Public Works and Government Services must convene, within 180 days after the coming into force of the enactment, a conference including officials of the federal government and the governments of all provinces and territories and representatives of the municipalities and aboriginal communities, to develop and plan the national housing strategy and programs, and must report to Parliament on the conference within the first five days that the House sits following the expiration of 180 days after the end of the conference.</Para></Block></Bill_Part><Bill_Part Part_Type="MainText" CountLines="Yes" RunningHead_E="Housing Bill of Rights"><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="MainText_DocNo">391327</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes"><Para Style="Session_Reign">1st Session, 39th Parliament,</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes"><Para Style="Session_Reign">55 Elizabeth II, 2006</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes"><Para Style="MainBillOrigin">house of commons of canada</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes"><Para Bold="Yes" Style="MAIN@BillNo_Title">BILL C-382</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes"><Para Style="MAIN@ti;04">An Act to provide for secure, adequate, accessible and affordable housing for Canadians </Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Preamble<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">WHEREAS the provision of and access to adequate housing is a fundamental human right according to paragraph 25(1) of the United Nations <I>Universal Declaration of Human Rights</I>, which reads as follows:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">芒聙聹Everyone has the right to a standard of living adequate for the health and well-being of himself and of his family, including food, clothing, housing and medical care and necessary social services, and the right to security in the event of unemployment, sickness, disability, widowhood, old age or other lack of livelihood in circumstances beyond his control.芒聙聺;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">WHEREAS in 1976 Canada signed the <I>International Covenant on Economic, Social and Cultural Rights</I>, a legally binding treaty, committing Canada to make progress on fully realizing all economic, social and cultural rights, including the right to adequate housing, as outlined in paragraph 11(1) of the Covenant:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">芒聙聹The States Parties to the present Covenant recognize the right of everyone to an adequate standard of living for himself and his family, including adequate food, clothing and housing, and to the continuous improvement of living conditions. The States Parties will take appropriate steps to ensure the realization of this right...芒聙聺;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">WHEREAS the enjoyment of other human rights, such as those to privacy, to respect for the home, to freedom of movement, to freedom from discrimination, to environmental health, to security of the person, to freedom of association and to equality before the law are indivisible from and indispensable to the realization of the right to adequate housing;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">WHEREAS the immediate action required of State Parties to the Covenant arises out of paragraph 2(1) of the Covenant, which provides that State Parties undertake to take steps to carry out its provisions by all appropriate means, including particularly the adoption of legislative measures;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">WHEREAS the United Nations Committee on Economic, Social and Cultural Rights has interpreted this to mean that State Parties are obliged to immediately begin to adopt measures towards the full enjoyment by everyone of the right to housing;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">WHEREAS the United Nations Committee has been highly critical of Canada芒聙聶s failure to make progress on the provision of adequate housing for all Canadians, a criticism made most recently in its concluding observations of December 10, 1998:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">芒聙聹The Committee is gravely concerned that such a wealthy country as Canada has allowed the problem of homelessness and inadequate housing to grow to such proportions that the mayors of Canada芒聙聶s 10 largest cities have now declared homelessness a national disaster.芒聙聺;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">WHEREAS the United Nations Committee issued a specific recommendation that Canada implement a national strategy aimed at reducing homelessness and poverty, which reads in part:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">芒聙聹The Committee recommends that the federal, provincial and territorial governments address homelessness and inadequate housing as a national emergency by reinstating or increasing, as the case may be, social housing programmes for those in need, improving and properly enforcing anti-discrimination legislation in the field of housing, increasing shelter allowances and social assistance rates to realistic levels, providing adequate support services for persons with disabilities, improving protection of security of tenure for tenants and improving protection of affordable rental housing stock from conversion to other uses. The Committee urges the State Party to implement a national strategy for the reduction of homelessness and poverty.芒聙聺;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">WHEREAS Canada芒聙聶s wealth and national budget are more than adequate to ensure that every woman, child and man residing in Canada has secure, adequate, accessible and affordable housing as part of a standard of living that will provide healthy physical, intellectual, emotional, spiritual and social development and a good quality of life;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">WHEREAS achievement of improved housing conditions is best realized through co-operative partnerships of government and civil society and the meaningful involvement of local communities;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">AND WHEREAS the Parliament of Canada wishes to ensure the establishment of national goals and programs that seek to improve the quality of life for all Canadians as a basic right;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">NOW, THEREFORE, Her Majesty, by and with the advice and consent of the Senate and House of Commons of Canada, enacts as follows:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:SHORT TITLE
--><Para TopMargin="10" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">SHORT TITLE
</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Short title<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>1.</B> This Act may be cited as the <I>Housing Bill of Rights</I>.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:INTERPRETATION--><Para TopMargin="10" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">INTERPRETATION</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Definitions<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>2.</B> The definitions in this section apply in this Act.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><MarginalNote>芒聙聹accessible housing芒聙聺<br/>脗芦 <I>logement accessible</I> 脗禄<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0">芒聙聹accessible housing芒聙聺 means housing that is accessible to the individuals who are intended to occupy it, including those who are disadvantaged by age, physical or mental disability or medical condition, or who are victims of a natural disaster.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><MarginalNote>芒聙聹adequate housing芒聙聺<br/>脗芦 <I>logement ad脙漏quat</I> 脗禄<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0">芒聙聹adequate housing芒聙聺 means housing that is habitable and structurally sound, and that provides sufficient space and protection against cold, damp, heat, rain, wind, noise, pollution and other threats to health.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><MarginalNote>芒聙聹affordable housing芒聙聺<br/>脗芦 <I>logement abordable</I> 脗禄<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0">芒聙聹affordable housing芒聙聺 means housing that is available at a cost that does not compromise the attainment and satisfaction of an individual芒聙聶s other basic needs of life, including needs for food, clothing and access to education.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><MarginalNote>芒聙聹Minister芒聙聺<br/>脗芦 <I>ministre</I> 脗禄<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0">芒聙聹Minister芒聙聺 means the Minister of Public Works and Government Services.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:RIGHTS RESPECTING HOUSING--><Para TopMargin="10" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">RIGHTS RESPECTING HOUSING</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote><keep>Right re</keep> provision of housing<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>3.</B> (1) Subject to this Act, every individual has the right to secure, adequate, accessible and affordable housing, as defined in this Act.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Rights enjoyed free of discrimination<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(2) Every individual has the right to the housing referred to in subsection (1) without the discrimination referred to in subsection (3).</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Forbidden grounds of discrimination<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(3) No person shall make any discrimination in respect of another芒聙聶s right to housing under this Act on the basis of race, national or ethnic origin, colour, religion, sex, age, mental or physical disability, family status, the presence of children, sexual orientation, medical status, citizenship, level of education, employment status, social condition or reliance on welfare or other public assistance.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Rights with respect to housing<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>4.</B> Every individual has the following rights with respect to housing:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>a</I>) a right to security of tenure against arbitrary eviction, forced relocation, expropriation or threat of any of them, or against any other form of harassment;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>b</I>) a right to housing that is appropriate to the individual芒聙聶s special needs, including the availability of attention combined with independence;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>c</I>) a right for all children, women and men to a home in a safe and healthy environment;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>d</I>) a right to a home free from violence, threat of violence or other form of harassment, both domestic and from outside the home;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>e</I>) a right to enjoyment and respect of privacy in the home;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>f</I>) a right to the economic security that results from protection from rent increases, property tax increases or other housing cost increases that</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="4" FirstLineIndent="0">(i) are sudden or excessive,</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="4" FirstLineIndent="0">(ii) are primarily intended to yield an unreasonable profit or to increase the value of rental property, or</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="4" FirstLineIndent="0">(iii) have the effect of diminishing the other rights established by this Act.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:ENFORCEMENT, OFFENCES AND PENALTIES--><Para TopMargin="10" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">ENFORCEMENT, OFFENCES AND PENALTIES</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Enforcement of rights<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>5.</B> (1) Every individual has the right to bring an action before a court of competent jurisdiction to enforce the rights to which they are entitled under sections 3 and 4 or otherwise under this Act, or under any other laws designed to grant rights to, ensure security in, and prevent discrimination with regard to, access to housing.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Other remedies protected<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(2) Subsection (1) does not reduce or abrogate any other remedy available at law.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Offences and penalties<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>6.</B> (1) Every person or legal entity that contravenes any provision of this Act, or takes away or threatens a right of an individual granted by this Act, is guilty of an offence punishable on summary conviction and liable</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>a</I>) to a fine of not more than $5,000 for a first offence; and</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>b</I>) to a fine of not more than $10,000 or to imprisonment for not more than six months or to both fine and imprisonment for a second or subsequent offence.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Separate offences<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(2) For the purposes of subsection (1), an act or omission that takes away or threatens the rights of more than one individual constitutes a separate offence in respect of each such individual.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:GOVERNMENT POLICIES AND HOUSING STRATEGY--><Para TopMargin="10" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">GOVERNMENT POLICIES AND HOUSING STRATEGY</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>General government housing policies<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>7.</B> (1) The Minister shall develop and adopt, in cooperation with the governments of all provinces and with representatives of municipalities and the aboriginal communities, which cooperation includes the conference referred to in section 12, policies to ensure that the costs of housing in Canada do not prevent or threaten the attainment and satisfaction of other basic needs, including needs for food, clothing and access to education.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Financial assistance<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(2) The policies mentioned in subsection (1) must provide for</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>a</I>) financial assistance in respect of rent for those who are otherwise unable to afford the rights to rental housing established by this Act; and</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>b</I>) availability of finance and credit without discrimination based on a characteristic listed as a forbidden ground of discrimination in subsection 3(3) for those who, with such finance and credit, may be able to purchase housing.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>National housing strategy for the economically disadvantaged<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>8.</B> (1) The Minister shall develop and adopt, in cooperation with the governments of all provinces and with representatives of municipalities and the aboriginal communities, which cooperation includes the conference referred to in section 12, a national housing strategy and programs to carry it out, to ensure the full exercise of the rights granted by this Act.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Elements of strategy<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(2) The national housing strategy must provide for the availability, by January 1, 2007, of housing that meets the requirements of this Act and that</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>a</I>) is secure, adequate, affordable, accessible, and not for profit in the case of those who cannot otherwise afford it;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>b</I>) reflects the needs of local communities, including aboriginal communities;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>c</I>) does not cost more than thirty percent of the occupants芒聙聶 pre-tax household income;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>d</I>) is appropriate for different needs and provides reasonable design options, including, in an appropriate proportion, access for the elderly and the disabled;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>e</I>) uses design and equipment standardization where appropriate to accelerate construction and minimize cost;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>f</I>) includes not-for-profit rental housing projects, mixed income not-for-profit housing cooperatives, special-needs housing and housing that allows senior citizens to remain in their homes as long as possible;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>g</I>) includes the housing for the homeless specified in section 11;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>h</I>) includes provision for temporary emergency housing and shelter in the event of disasters and crises; and 

</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>i</I>) complies with standards for the maintenance of existing housing stock or for the construction and maintenance of new housing and appropriate health, security and safety standards.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Implementation date<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(3) The national housing strategy described in this section shall be implemented as soon as possible in accordance with section 12 to ensure the fulfillment of subsection (4).</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Legally enforceable by 2007<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(4) The right to secure, adequate, accessible and affordable housing described in this Act is a right that is legally enforceable from January 1, 2007.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Priority for chronically ill-housed and disadvantaged<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>9.</B> The programs developed under section 8 shall ensure that priority in the provision of secure, adequate, accessible and affordable housing is given to</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>a</I>) those who have not had secure, adequate, accessible and affordable housing over an extended period;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>b</I>) those with special housing requirements because of family status or size or because of a mental or physical disability; and</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>c</I>) those who have difficulty in obtaining housing because of a characteristic listed as a forbidden ground of discrimination in subsection 3(3).</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Programs to cover the homeless<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>10.</B> Programs developed under section 8 shall include the provision for the rights of the homeless described in section 11.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Special rights of the homeless<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>11.</B> (1) Every individual who is homeless has a right to the immediate provision by public authorities of adequate, self-contained and appropriate housing.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Inadequate housing<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(2) A hostel, emergency shelter or accommodation that provides only bed and breakfast is not adequate housing for the purposes of subsection (1).</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Appeal<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(3) Every homeless individual who is refused the housing provided for in subsection (1) has the right to appeal the refusal in a court of competent jurisdiction.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Conference<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>12.</B> (1) The Minister shall, within 180 days after the coming into force of this Act, convene a conference of the ministers of the Crown for each province responsible for housing and representatives of municipalities and the aboriginal communities.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Function of conference<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(2) The conference convened pursuant to subsection (1) shall</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>a</I>) develop standards and objectives for the national housing strategy described in section 8, and programs to carry it out;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>b</I>) set targets for the commencement of the programs;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>c</I>) recommend a date by which an additional one percent of the annual expenditures of the federal and all provincial and municipal governments during the fiscal year ending March 31, 2007 are to be assigned to national housing programs throughout Canada; and</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>d</I>)  develop the principles of an agreement between the federal and all provincial governments and representatives of the municipalities and aboriginal communities for the development and delivery of the programs.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Report to Parliament<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>13.</B> The Minister shall cause a report on the conference, including the matters referred to in paragraphs 12(2)(<I>a</I>) to (<I>d</I>), to be laid before each House of Parliament on any one of the first five days that the House sits following the expiration of 180 days after the end of the conference.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:COMING INTO FORCE--><Para TopMargin="10" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">COMING INTO FORCE</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Coming into force<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>14.</B> Sections 5 and 6 and subsection 11(3) come into force on January 1, 2007.</Para></Block><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="BPT_ImprintE">Published under authority of the Speaker of the House of Commons<br/>Available from:<br/>Publishing and Depository Services<br/>Public Works and Government Services Canada<br/>Ottawa, Ontario K1A 0S5<br/>Telephone: 613-941-5995 or 1-800-635-7943<br/>Fax: 613-954-5779 or 1-800-565-7757<br/>publications@tpsgc-pwgsc.gc.ca<br/>http://publications.gc.ca</Para></Block><Block Align="Yes" LineCnt="N"><Para NoLineBreak="Yes" NoHtml="Yes" Leading="0" Size="0" TopMargin="0" BottomMargin="0">脗聞</Para></Block></Bill_Part></Bill>
