<?xml version="1.0"?>
<Bill RHead_reign="55-56 Eliz. II" RHead_ParlYear="2006-2007" DocumentTitle="BILL S-209" Bill_No="S-209" Document_No="0317" xml:lang="EN" Bill_Type="Non-amending" Stage_Name="Third-Reading-Senate" Reprint="No" xml:space="preserve" ChapterNo_E="C. " ChapterNo_F="ch. " Bill-Origin="senate"><Bill_Part Part_Type="Cover" CountLines="No"><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="CovBillNo">S-209</Para></Block><Block><Para TopMargin="24" Size="9" Leading="10" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0" TextAlign="Center">First Session, Thirty-ninth Parliament,</Para></Block><Block><Para Size="9" Leading="10" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0" TextAlign="Center">55-56 Elizabeth II, 2006-2007</Para></Block><Block><Para TopMargin="48" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0" Bold="Yes" TextAlign="Center">SENATE OF CANADA</Para></Block><Block><Para TopMargin="42" Size="18" Leading="20" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0" Bold="Yes" TextAlign="Center">BILL S-209</Para></Block><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="CovLongTitle">An Act concerning personal watercraft in navigable waters</Para></Block><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="COV_StageLine"></Para></Block><Block><Para BottomMargin="14" Size="11" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0" Bold="Yes" TextAlign="Center">AS PASSED</Para></Block><Block><Para Size="8" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0" TextAlign="Center">BY THE SENATE<br/>JUNE 22, 2007</Para></Block><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="COV_StageLine"></Para></Block><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="Cover_DocNo">0317</Para></Block></Bill_Part><Bill_Part CountLines="No" Part_Type="InsideCover"><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="BPT_InsideCoverE">Available on the Parliament of Canada Web Site at the following address:<br/><B>http://www.parl.gc.ca</B></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><Para TopMargin="108" BottomMargin="4" Size="10" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">SUMMARY</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" Size="8" Leading="9" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">This enactment requires the designated Minister to make regulations to prohibit or restrict the use of personal watercraft on designated waterways.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" Size="8" Leading="9" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">A local authority may, after general consultation within the community, including consultation with local residents and with law enforcement agencies, adopt a resolution proposing to the Minister that the use of personal watercraft be prohibited on designated waterways or that some or all of the restrictions established by the regulations apply to designated waterways. These designated waterways may be all or specified parts of navigable waterways in the local authority芒聙聶s area. The Minister may refuse to act on a proposal that would impede navigation.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" Size="8" Leading="9" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">On receiving the resolution and information regarding the consultation that took place, the Minister must publish a notice of the proposal in the <I>Canada Gazette</I>. The Minister must give all interested parties an opportunity to make representations on the proposal during the 90-day period following publication of the notice.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" Size="8" Leading="9" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">The restrictions are made applicable to the designated waterways when the Minister adds them by order to the appropriate schedule to the regulations. Schedule I to the regulations will list those waterways on which personal watercraft are prohibited. Schedule II to the regulations will list those waterways on which their use is subject to restrictions.</Para></Block></Bill_Part><Bill_Part Part_Type="MainText" CountLines="Yes" RunningHead_E="Personal Watercraft"><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="MainText_DocNo">0317</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes"><Para Style="Session_Reign">1st Session, 39th Parliament,</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes"><Para Style="Session_Reign">55-56 Elizabeth II, 2006-2007</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes"><Para Style="MainBillOrigin">senate of canada</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes"><Para Bold="Yes" Style="MAIN@BillNo_Title">BILL S-209</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes"><Para Style="MAIN@ti;04">An Act concerning personal watercraft in navigable waters</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Preamble<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">WHEREAS the Parliament of Canada recognizes that the safe and appropriate use of navigable waterways is a matter of national importance;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">AND WHEREAS Parliament also recognizes that personal watercraft have given rise to considerable public concern because of the particular safety and environmental problems associated with their use;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">AND WHEREAS many communities consider that the <I>Boating Restriction Regulations</I> made under the <I>Canada Shipping Act</I> provide insufficient regulation of the use of personal watercraft;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">AND WHEREAS further restrictions on their use are desirable;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">NOW, THEREFORE, Her Majesty, by and with the advice and consent of the Senate and the House of Commons of Canada, enacts as follows:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Short title<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>1.</B> This Act may be cited as the <I>Personal Watercraft Act</I>.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Definitions<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>2.</B> The definitions in this section apply in this Act.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><MarginalNote>芒聙聹designated waterway芒聙聺<br/>脗芦 <I>voie navigable d脙漏sign脙漏e</I> 脗禄<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0">芒聙聹designated waterway芒聙聺 means a navigable waterway or portion thereof, over which Parliament has jurisdiction, that is, or is proposed to be, added to or removed from Schedule I or Schedule II.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><MarginalNote>芒聙聹local authority芒聙聺<br/>脗芦 <I>autorit脙漏 locale</I> 脗禄<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0">芒聙聹local authority芒聙聺 means</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>a</I>) an incorporated city, metropolitan authority, town, village, township, district, county, rural municipality or other incorporated municipal body however designated; or</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>b</I>) a body, such as a cottage association, a park authority or a port or harbour authority, that the Minister determines to be a local authority for the purposes of this Act.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><MarginalNote>芒聙聹Minister芒聙聺<br/>脗芦 <I>ministre</I> 脗禄<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0">芒聙聹Minister芒聙聺 means the member of the Queen芒聙聶s Privy Council for Canada who is designated by the Governor in Council as the Minister for the purposes of this Act.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><MarginalNote>芒聙聹personal watercraft芒聙聺<br/>脗芦 <I>motomarine</I> 脗禄<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0">芒聙聹personal watercraft芒聙聺 means an enclosed-hull, water-jet-driven pleasure craft with no cockpit, that is designed to be used by one or more persons while straddling, sitting, standing or kneeling.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><MarginalNote>芒聙聹prescribed芒聙聺<br/><I>Version anglaise seulement</I><br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0">芒聙聹prescribed芒聙聺 means prescribed by the regulations.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><MarginalNote>芒聙聹regulations芒聙聺<br/>脗芦 <I>r脙篓glement</I> 脗禄<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0">芒聙聹regulations芒聙聺 means regulations made under section 10.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><MarginalNote>芒聙聹Schedule I芒聙聺<br/>脗芦 <I>annexe I</I> 脗禄<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0">芒聙聹Schedule I芒聙聺 means Schedule I to the regulations.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><MarginalNote>芒聙聹Schedule II芒聙聺<br/>脗芦 <I>annexe II</I> 脗禄<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0">芒聙聹Schedule II芒聙聺 means Schedule II to the regulations.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Purpose<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>3.</B> The purpose of this Act is to provide a method for a local authority to propose to the Minister that restrictions be applied respecting the use of personal watercraft on all or a portion of a navigable waterway over which Parliament has jurisdiction, in order to ensure the safe use and peaceful enjoyment of the waterway and the protection of the environment.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Resolution by local authority<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>4.</B> (1) A local authority may, after general consultation within the community, including consultation with local residents and law enforcement agencies, adopt a resolution proposing to the Minister that, for health, safety or environmental reasons,</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>a</I>) a designated waterway be added to Schedule I;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>b</I>) a designated waterway be added to Schedule II, specifying those prescribed restrictions that the local authority proposes be made applicable to the waterway;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>c</I>) prescribed restrictions be added to or removed from those listed in Schedule II as applicable to a designated waterway; or</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>d</I>) a designated waterway be removed from Schedule I or Schedule II.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Waterway shoreline within
jurisdiction<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(2) A local authority may name in a resolution only a designated waterway the shoreline of which is within the jurisdiction or area of the local authority.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Notice to Minister<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(3) After a resolution has been adopted under subsection (1), the local authority shall send to the Minister</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>a</I>) a certified copy of the resolution; and</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>b</I>) a description of the consultation that was undertaken.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Amending or withdrawing
resolution<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(4) Until an order is made under section 7, a local authority may accommodate representations made to the Minister under subsection 5(3) by passing a further resolution that amends or withdraws the resolution sent to the Minister under subsection (3) and sending a certified copy of the further resolution to the Minister.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Publication of proposed changes<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>5.</B> (1) Subject to section 6, the Minister shall, within 60 days after receiving the information referred to in subsection 4(3), cause to be published in the <I>Canada Gazette</I> a notice of the proposed addition of a designated waterway to or removal of a designated waterway from Schedule I or Schedule II, or the proposed addition or removal of prescribed restrictions applicable to a designated waterway.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Contents of notice<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(2) The Minister shall include in the notice mentioned in subsection (1) the name of the designated waterway, the changes proposed and the date on which the proposed changes are to be made effective.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Opportunity to make representations<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(3) The Minister shall afford a reasonable opportunity for interested persons to make representations to the Minister with respect to the proposed changes within the 90 days following publication of the notice, and shall include in the notice information on how and when such representations may be made.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Navigation impeded<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>6.</B> If, in the opinion of the Minister, the navigation of any navigable waterway would be obstructed, impeded or rendered more difficult or dangerous by reason of adding to or removing from Schedule I or Schedule II a designated waterway, or by reason of adding or removing any prescribed restriction on the use of personal watercraft on a designated waterway listed in Schedule II, the Minister may refuse to publish the proposed changes or to amend the Schedule.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Ministerial orders<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>7.</B> Subject to subsection 4(4) and section 6, following the expiry of the 90 days referred to in subsection 5(3), the Minister shall implement the proposed changes by making an order</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>a</I>) adding a designated waterway to Schedule I;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>b</I>) adding a designated waterway to Schedule II and specifying the prescribed restrictions that are applicable to the waterway;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>c</I>) adding or removing prescribed restrictions applicable to a designated waterway listed in Schedule II; or</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>d</I>) removing a designated waterway from Schedule I or Schedule II.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Ministerial
record<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>8.</B> The Minister shall keep a record of all resolutions received pursuant to subsections 4(3) and (4) and a description of the manner in which they were disposed of, including the reason for refusal in cases where the Minister refuses to make the proposed changes to Schedule I or Schedule II.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Prohibition 芒聙聯 Schedule I
waterways<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>9.</B> (1) No person shall operate a personal watercraft on a waterway listed in Schedule I.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Prohibition 芒聙聯 Schedule II waterways<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(2) No person shall operate a personal watercraft on a waterway listed in Schedule II unless the person complies with the prescribed restrictions applicable to the waterway.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Offence and punishment<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(3) Every person who contravenes subsection (1) or (2) is guilty of an offence and liable on summary conviction to a fine not exceeding five hundred dollars.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Regulations<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>10.</B> The Minister shall make regulations</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>a</I>) establishing a Schedule I listing waterways on which the use of personal watercraft is prohibited;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>b</I>) establishing a Schedule II listing waterways on which the use of personal watercraft is subject to prescribed restrictions and specifying the prescribed restrictions applicable to each waterway</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>c</I>) prescribing restrictions on the use of personal watercraft that may be made applicable to the waterways listed in Schedule II, including, but without limiting the generality of the foregoing, speed limits, restricted hours of operation and limits respecting operating distances from the shoreline;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>d</I>) exempting from the application of the regulations or from any of the prohibitions set out in section 9 those law enforcement officers, environment or wildlife officers, persons providing for safety in connection with an activity on the water and other persons acting in the public interest who, in the opinion of the Minister, should be exempted; and</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>e</I>) generally, for carrying out the purposes and provisions of this Act.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Report to Parliament<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>11.</B> The Minister shall in respect of each year prepare a report with respect to the changes made in Schedules I and II in accordance with this Act during the year and shall cause a copy of the report to be laid before each House of Parliament on any of the first 15 days on which that House is sitting after the Minister completes it.</Para></Block><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="BPT_ImprintE"><br/><br/>Published under authority of the Senate of Canada</Para></Block><Block Align="Yes" LineCnt="N"><Para NoLineBreak="Yes" NoHtml="Yes" Leading="0" Size="0" TopMargin="0" BottomMargin="0">脗聞</Para></Block></Bill_Part></Bill>
