<?xml version="1.0"?>
<Bill RHead_reign="55-56 Eliz. II" RHead_ParlYear="2006-2007" DocumentTitle="BILL S-6" Bill_No="S-6" Document_No="90408" xml:lang="EN" Bill_Type="Non-amending" Stage_Name="Assented-to" Reprint="No" xml:space="preserve" ChapterNo_E="C. 17" ChapterNo_F="ch. 17" Bill-Origin="senate"><Bill_Part Part_Type="Cover" CountLines="No"><Block><Para TopMargin="24" Size="9" Leading="10" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0" TextAlign="Center">First Session, Thirty-ninth Parliament,</Para></Block><Block><Para Size="9" Leading="10" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0" TextAlign="Center">55-56 Elizabeth II, 2006-2007</Para></Block><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="COV@StatutesTitle">STATUTES OF CANADA 2007<br/>CHAPTER 17</Para></Block><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="CovLongTitle">An Act to amend the First Nations Land Management Act</Para></Block><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="COV_StageLine"></Para></Block><Block><Para BottomMargin="14" Size="11" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0" Bold="Yes" TextAlign="Center">ASSENTED TO</Para></Block><Block><Para Size="8" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0" TextAlign="Center">22nd JUNE, 2007</Para></Block><Block><Para TopMargin="4" Size="8" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0" TextAlign="Center">BILL S-6</Para></Block><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="COV_StageLine"></Para></Block></Bill_Part><Bill_Part CountLines="No" Part_Type="InsideCover"><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="BPT_InsideCoverE">Available on the Parliament of Canada Web Site at the following address:<br/><B>http://www.parl.gc.ca</B></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><Para TopMargin="108" BottomMargin="4" Size="10" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">SUMMARY</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" Size="8" Leading="9" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">This enactment amends the <I>First Nations Land Management Act</I> to incorporate, to the extent provided for by the Framework Agreement on First Nation Land Management, the concepts and terminology of the civil law of the Province of Quebec.</Para></Block></Bill_Part><Bill_Part Part_Type="MainText" CountLines="No" RunningHead_E="First Nations Land Management"><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="MAIN@RoyalAssentTitle">55-56 ELIZABETH II</Para></Block><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="MAIN@RoyalAssentTitle">——————</Para></Block><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="MAIN@RoyalAssentTitle">CHAPTER 17</Para></Block><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="LongTitleAssent">An Act to amend the First Nations Land Management Act</Para></Block><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="MAIN@RoyalAssentDate">[<I>Assented to 22nd June, 2007</I>]</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>1999, c. 24<br/></MarginalNote><Para LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">Her Majesty, by and with the advice and consent of the Senate and House of Commons of Canada, enacts as follows:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>1.</B> (1) The definition “<AltLang xml:lang="fr">intérêts</AltLang>” in subsection 2(1) of the French version of the <I>First Nations Land Management Act</I> is repealed.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes">(2) The definitions “first nation land” and “licence” in subsection 2(1) of the Act are replaced by the following:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>“first nation land”<br/>« <I>terres de la première nation</I> »<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0">“first nation land” means reserve land to which a land code applies and includes all the interests or rights in, and resources of, the land that are within the legislative authority of Parliament.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><MarginalNote>“licence”<br/>« <I>permis</I> »<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0">“licence”, in relation to first nation land, means</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>a</I>) in Canada elsewhere than in Quebec, any right of use or occupation of the land other than an interest in that land;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>b</I>) in Quebec, any right to use or occupy the land other than a right as defined in this subsection.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes">(3) The definition “interest” in subsection 2(1) of the English version of the Act is replaced by the following:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>“interest”<br/>« <I>intérêt</I> »<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0">“interest”, in relation to first nation land in Canada elsewhere than in Quebec, means any estate, right or interest of any nature in or to the land, but does not include title to the land. </Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes">(4) Subsection 2(1) of the Act is amended by adding the following in alphabetical order:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>“right”<br/>« <I>droit</I> »<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0">“right”, in relation to first nation land in Quebec, means any right of any nature in or to that land, including the rights of a lessee, but does not include title to the land.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes">(5) Subsection 2(1) of the French version of the Act is amended by adding the following in alphabetical order:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>« intérêt »<br/>“<I>interest</I>”<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0"><AltLang xml:lang="fr">« intérêt » S’agissant des terres de la première nation situées au Canada mais ailleurs qu’au Québec, tout domaine, droit ou autre intérêt portant sur celles-ci; est cependant exclu le titre de propriété.</AltLang></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>2.</B> (1) Paragraphs 6(1)(<I>b</I>) and (<I>c</I>) of the Act are replaced by the following:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>b</I>) the general rules and procedures applicable to the use and occupancy of first nation land, including use and occupancy under</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="4" FirstLineIndent="0">(i) licences and leases, and</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="4" FirstLineIndent="0">(ii) interests or rights in first nation land held pursuant to allotments under subsection 20(1) of the <I>Indian Act</I> or pursuant to the custom of the first nation;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>c</I>) the procedures that apply to the transfer, by testamentary disposition or succession, of any interest or right in first nation land;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes">(2) Paragraph 6(1)(<I>f</I>) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>f</I>) a community consultation process for the development of general rules and procedures respecting, in cases of breakdown of marriage, the use, occupation and possession of first nation land and the division of interests or rights in first nation land;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes">(3) Paragraphs 6(1)(<I>i</I>) and (<I>j</I>) of the Act are replaced by the following:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>i</I>) the establishment or identification of a forum for the resolution of disputes in relation to interests or rights in first nation land;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>j</I>) the general rules and procedures that apply in respect of the granting or expropriation by the first nation of interests or rights in first nation land;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes">(4) Paragraph 6(3)(<I>b</I>) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>b</I>) a description of the interests or rights and licences that have been granted by Her Majesty in or in relation to that land, and the date and other terms of the transfer to the first nation of Her Majesty’s rights and obligations as grantor of those interests or rights and licences;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>3.</B> Subsection 7(2) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Condition<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(2) A portion of a reserve may not be excluded from a land code if the exclusion would have the effect of placing the administration of a lease, other interest or a right in that land in more than one land management regime.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>4.</B> Subsection 10(4) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Third parties<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(4) If other persons have an interest or right in the land that is to be subject to the proposed land code, the council shall, within a reasonable time before the vote, take appropriate measures to inform those persons of the proposed land code, this Act and the date of the vote.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>5.</B> Section 16 of the Act is replaced by the following:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Effect<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>16.</B> (1) After the coming into force of a land code, no interest or right in or licence in relation to first nation land may be acquired or granted except in accordance with the land code of the first nation.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Interests or rights of third parties<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(2) Subject to subsections (3) and (4), interests or rights in and licences in relation to first nation land that exist on the coming into force of a land code continue in accordance with their terms and conditions.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Transfer of rights of Her Majesty<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(3) On the coming into force of the land code of a first nation, the rights and obligations of Her Majesty as grantor in respect of the interests or rights and the licences described in the first nation’s individual agreement are transferred to the first nation in accordance with that agreement.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Interests and rights of first nation members<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(4) Interests or rights in first nation land held on the coming into force of a land code by first nation members pursuant to allotments under subsection 20(1) of the <I>Indian Act</I> or pursuant to the custom of the first nation are subject to the provisions of the land code governing the transfer and lease of interests or rights in first nation land and sharing in natural resource revenues.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>6.</B> Subsection 17(1) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Obligation of first nation<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>17.</B> (1) A first nation shall, in accordance with the Framework Agreement and following the community consultation process provided for in its land code, establish general rules and procedures, in cases of breakdown of marriage, respecting the use, occupation and possession of first nation land and the division of interests or rights in first nation land.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>7.</B> (1) Paragraph 18(1)(<I>b</I>) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>b</I>) grant interests or rights in and licences in relation to that land;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes">(2) Paragraph 18(2)(<I>a</I>) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>a</I>) acquire and hold property;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>8.</B> (1) Paragraph 20(1)(<I>a</I>) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>a</I>) interests or rights in and licences in relation to first nation land;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes">(2) Paragraph 20(2)(<I>b</I>) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>b</I>) subject to section 5, the creation, acquisition and granting of interests or rights in and licences in relation to first nation land and prohibitions in relation thereto;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>9.</B> (1) The portion of subsection 25(3) of the Act before paragraph (<I>b</I>) is replaced by the following:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Regulations<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(3) The Governor in Council may, on the recommendation of the Minister and in accordance with the Framework Agreement, make regulations respecting the administration of the First Nation Land Register, the registration of interests or rights in it and the recording of any other matter, including but not limited to regulations respecting</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>a</I>) the effects of registering interests or rights, including priorities;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes">(2) Paragraph 25(3)(<I>b</I>) of the English version of the Act is replaced by the following:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>b</I>) the payment of fees for the registration of interests or rights and for any other service in relation to the Register;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>10.</B> Subsection 26(2) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Expropriation<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(2) Interests or rights in first nation land may not be expropriated except by Her Majesty or a first nation in accordance with the Framework Agreement and this Act.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>11.</B> (1) Subsections 28(1) and (2) of the Act are replaced by the following:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Expropriation by a first nation<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>28.</B> (1) A first nation may, in accordance with the general rules and procedures contained in its land code, expropriate any interest or right in its first nation land that, in the opinion of its council, is necessary for community works or other first nation community purposes.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Exception<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(2) An interest or right in first nation land obtained under section 35 of the <I>Indian Act</I> or held by Her Majesty is not subject to expropriation by a first nation.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes">(2) Subsection 28(3) of the English version of the Act is replaced by the following:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Effective date<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(3) An expropriation takes effect from the day on which a notice of expropriation is registered in the First Nation Land Register or the thirtieth day after the day on which the notice is served on the person whose interest or right is expropriated, whichever is the earlier.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes">(3) Subsections 28(4) and (5) of the Act are replaced by the following:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Effect of expropriation<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(4) An expropriated interest becomes the property of the first nation free of any previous claim or encumbrance. In Quebec, a first nation becomes the holder of an expropriated right free of any previous right, charge or claim.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Compensation<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(5) A first nation shall pay fair compensation to the holder of an expropriated interest or right and, in determining that compensation, the first nation shall apply the rules set out in the <I>Expropriation Act</I>, with such modifications as the circumstances require.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>12.</B> (1) Subsection 29(1) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Expropriation by Her Majesty<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>29.</B> (1) An interest or right in first nation land may be expropriated by Her Majesty for the use of a federal department or agency and with the consent and by order of the Governor in Council.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes">(2) Paragraphs 29(3)(<I>b</I>) and (<I>c</I>) of the Act are replaced by the following:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>b</I>) reasonable efforts have been made to acquire the interest or right through agreement with the first nation;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>c</I>) the most limited interest or right necessary is expropriated for the shortest time possible; and</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>13.</B> (1) The portion of section 30 of the Act before paragraph (<I>a</I>) is replaced by the following:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Partial expropriation<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>30.</B> If less than the full interest of a first nation, or less than the entire right of a first nation, in first nation land is expropriated by Her Majesty,</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes">(2) Paragraph 30(<I>a</I>) of the English version of the Act is replaced by the following:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>a</I>) the land in which an interest or right is expropriated continues to be first nation land and subject to the provisions of the land code and first nation laws that are not inconsistent with the expropriation; and</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>14.</B> (1) The portion of subsection 31(1) of the Act before paragraph (<I>a</I>) is replaced by the following:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Compensation<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>31.</B> (1) Where an interest or right in first nation land is expropriated by Her Majesty, compensation shall be provided to the first nation consisting of</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes">(2) Subsection 31(2) of the English version of the Act is replaced by the following:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Land of a lesser area<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(2) Land provided to a first nation as compensation may be of an area that is less than the area of the land in which an interest or right has been expropriated if the total area of the land comprised in a reserve of the first nation is not less following the expropriation than at the coming into force of its land code.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes">(3) Paragraph 31(3)(<I>a</I>) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>a</I>) the market value of the expropriated interest or right or of the land in which an interest or right has been expropriated;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes">(4) Paragraph 31(3)(<I>d</I>) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>d</I>) any reduction in the value of any interest or right in first nation land that is not expropriated;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes">(5) Subsection 31(6) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Limit<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(6) Any claim or encumbrance in respect of an interest expropriated by Her Majesty may only be made or discharged against the compensation paid under this section. In Quebec, any right, charge or claim in respect of a right expropriated by Her Majesty may only be made or discharged against the compensation paid under this section.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>15.</B> (1) Subsections 32(1) and (2) of the Act are replaced by the following:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Restitution<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>32.</B> (1) An interest or right in first nation land expropriated by Her Majesty that is no longer required for the purpose for which it was expropriated shall revert to the first nation and, if the full interest or the entire right of the first nation was expropriated, it shall be returned to the first nation in accordance with terms and conditions negotiated by the first nation and the expropriating department or agency.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Improvements<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(2) When an interest or right reverts or is returned to a first nation, the minister responsible for the expropriating department or agency shall determine the disposition of any improvements made to the land.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes">(2) Subsection 32(3) of the English version of the Act is replaced by the following:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Dispute<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(3) If the first nation and the expropriating department or agency cannot agree on the terms and conditions of the return of the full interest or of the entire right, the first nation or the department or agency may, in accordance with the Framework Agreement, refer the matter to an arbitrator.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>16.</B> Section 33 of the Act is replaced by the following:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote><I>Expropriation Act</I><br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>33.</B> Without limiting the generality of section 37, in the event of any inconsistency or conflict between this Act and the <I>Expropriation Act</I> in relation to the expropriation of interests or rights in first nation land by Her Majesty, this Act prevails to the extent of the inconsistency or conflict.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>17.</B> Subsections 38(2) and (3) of the Act are replaced by the following:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Leasehold interests or leases<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(2) Subsection 89(1.1) of the <I>Indian Act</I> continues to apply to leasehold interests or leases in any first nation land that was designated land on the coming into force of a first nation’s land code.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Application<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(3) A land code may extend the application of subsection 89(1.1) of the <I>Indian Act</I>, or any portion of it, to other leasehold interests or leases in first nation land.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>18.</B> Paragraph 39(1)(<I>b</I>) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>b</I>) applies in respect of an interest or right in first nation land that is granted to Her Majesty for the exploitation of oil and gas pursuant to a land code.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Coming into force<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>19.</B> This Act comes into force on a day to be fixed by order of the Governor in Council.</Para></Block><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="BPT_ImprintE"><br/><br/>Published under authority of the Senate of Canada</Para></Block><Block Align="Yes" LineCnt="N"><Para NoLineBreak="Yes" NoHtml="Yes" Leading="0" Size="0" TopMargin="0" BottomMargin="0"></Para></Block></Bill_Part></Bill>
