<?xml version="1.0"?>
<Bill RHead_reign="46-47-48 Eliz. II" RHead_ParlYear="1997-98-99" DocumentTitle="BILL S-25" Bill_No="S-25" Document_No="2315" xml:lang="EN" Bill_Type="Non-amending" Stage_Name="Assented-to" Reprint="No" xml:space="preserve" ChapterNo_E="C. 38" ChapterNo_F="ch. 38" Bill-Origin="senate"><Bill_Part Part_Type="Cover" CountLines="No"><Block><Para TopMargin="24" Size="9" Leading="10" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0" TextAlign="Center">First Session, Thirty-sixth Parliament,</Para></Block><Block><Para Size="9" Leading="10" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0" TextAlign="Center">46-47-48 Elizabeth II, 1997-98-99</Para></Block><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="COV@StatutesTitle">STATUTES OF CANADA 1999<br/>CHAPTER 38</Para></Block><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="CovLongTitle">An Act respecting the Certified General Accountants Association of Canada</Para></Block><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="COV_StageLine"></Para></Block><Block><Para BottomMargin="14" Size="11" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0" Bold="Yes" TextAlign="Center">ASSENTED TO</Para></Block><Block><Para Size="8" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0" TextAlign="Center">29th APRIL, 1999</Para></Block><Block><Para TopMargin="4" Size="8" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0" TextAlign="Center">BILL S-25</Para></Block><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="COV_StageLine"></Para></Block></Bill_Part><Bill_Part CountLines="No" Part_Type="InsideCover"><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="BPT_InsideCoverE">Available on the Parliament of Canada Web Site at the following address:<br/><B>http://www.parl.gc.ca</B></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><Para TopMargin="108" BottomMargin="4" Size="10" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center"><SC SC_PerCent="85">Summary</SC></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" Size="8" Leading="9" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">The purpose of this enactment is to amend the Association芒聙聶s Act of incorporation in order to reflect more accurately the nature and scope of the Association芒聙聶s current activities and to adapt the Act to modern conditions and circumstances.</Para></Block></Bill_Part><Bill_Part Part_Type="MainText" CountLines="No" RunningHead_E="Certified General Accountants Association of Canada"><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="MAIN@RoyalAssentTitle">46-47-48 ELIZABETH II</Para></Block><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="MAIN@RoyalAssentTitle">芒聙聰芒聙聰芒聙聰芒聙聰芒聙聰芒聙聰</Para></Block><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="MAIN@RoyalAssentTitle">CHAPTER 38</Para></Block><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="LongTitleAssent">An Act respecting the Certified General Accountants Association of Canada</Para></Block><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="MAIN@RoyalAssentDate">[<I>Assented to 29th April, 1999</I>]</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Preamble<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">WHEREAS the petitioner was incorporated by an Act of the Parliament of Canada, being chapter 116 of the Statutes of Canada, 1913;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">AND WHEREAS, on July 28, 1982, a Ministerial order to change the name of the petitioner was issued under section 216 of the <I>Canada Corporations Act</I>, Revised Statutes of Canada, 1970, chapter C-32;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">AND WHEREAS the petitioner has by its petition prayed that its Act of incorporation be amended as hereinafter set forth and it is expedient to grant the prayer of the petitioner;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>1913, c. 116<br/></MarginalNote><Para LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">NOW, THEREFORE, Her Majesty, by and with the advice and consent of the Senate and House of Commons of Canada, enacts as follows:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>1.</B> The long title of chapter 116 of the Statutes of Canada, 1913 is replaced by the following:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="10" LeftMargin="4" FirstLineIndent="-4" Hyphenate="OFF">An Act to incorporate the Certified General Accountants Association of Canada</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>2.</B> Sections 1 to 7 of the Act are replaced by the following:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>1.</B> John Leslie, Harry R. Mallison, Fred C. Larivi脙篓re, Chas. A. Bourne, Alex. N. DeTilly, Jas. N. Doyle, Fred J. Walker, Jas. T. Smith, Edward A. Stewart, Jas. R. Murray, Jos. Jones, and John Dick, all of the city of Montreal, accountants, together with such persons as may be admitted to membership of the corporation, are incorporated under the name of the 芒聙聹Certified General Accountants Association of Canada芒聙聺, or, in its short form, 芒聙聹CGA-Canada芒聙聺.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Membership<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>2.</B> CGA-Canada consists of</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>a</I>) persons who are members in good standing of provincial and territorial associations of certified general accountants that are affiliated with CGA-Canada; and</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>b</I>) other persons who qualify and undertake to be bound by the by-laws of the association and are admitted to membership.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Corporate capacity<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>3.</B> Subject to this Act, CGA-Canada has all the powers, rights and privileges of a natural person.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Objects<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>4.</B> (1) The purposes of CGA-Canada are to promote the practice, profession and common interests of certified general accountants.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Powers<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(2) Without limiting the generality of subsection (1), CGA-Canada has in carrying out its purposes all the powers necessary</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>a</I>) to promote the knowledge, skill and proficiency of its members and to that end develop and institute programs, examinations and methods of evaluation of professional knowledge, experience and standards of professional conduct;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>b</I>) to establish categories of membership, determine the rights, privileges, terms and conditions applicable to the categories and fix their fees, dues and levies;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>c</I>) to grant certificates in respect of membership categories and qualifications and to admit persons to membership and expel members for cause;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>d</I>) to create and improve standards of financial accounting, reporting and auditing for its members, which standards may be used by any other person or body;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>e</I>) to conduct, direct, monitor, support and publish research and studies in respect of accounting, auditing and related financial matters;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>f</I>) to encourage and assist provincial, territorial and affiliated associations in the carrying out of their objects, especially the development, implementation, promotion and maintenance of appropriate and uniform standards of professional qualification and conduct and the holding of examinations for admission to membership;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>g</I>) to encourage and assist certified general accountants to adapt to changes in the accounting profession;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>h</I>) to communicate with the public, governments, the accounting profession and other parties in respect of issues, circumstances, policies, practices and other matters that have a national aspect and are of concern or interest to certified general accountants or society generally and to do all such things as are calculated to give the public a greater and more general appreciation of the profession of accountancy;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>i</I>) to promote the advancement of national and international harmonization, coordination and consistency of professional qualifications and of accounting and auditing standards;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>j</I>) to maintain cooperation and liaison with and membership in any other national or international professional, academic or business organizations having similar or related interests to those of CGA-Canada;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>k</I>) to manage the business and property of CGA-Canada;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>l</I>) to do all such other things as are likely to promote the purposes of CGA-Canada.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Non-profit corporation<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>5.</B> The activities of CGA-Canada shall be carried on without pecuniary gain to any member but reasonable remuneration may be paid to a member for services actually rendered to or on behalf of CGA-Canada.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Head office<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>6.</B> The head office of CGA-Canada shall be at such place in Canada as may be fixed by by-law.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Board of Directors<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>7.</B> The affairs and business of CGA-Canada shall be managed by a board of directors consisting of not less than five directors nor more than such specific number of directors as may be fixed by by-law.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Meetings<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>8.</B> (1) Meetings of CGA-Canada may be held as provided by by-law but at least one annual general meeting shall be held in each calendar year at which members</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>a</I>) receive the financial reports for the previous fiscal year;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>b</I>) appoint an auditor for the present fiscal year;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>c</I>) consider new by-laws; and</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>d</I>) conduct such other business as is relevant to the purposes of CGA-Canada and permitted under the by-laws.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Proxies<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(2) A member may be represented and vote by proxy at any annual or special general meeting of CGA-Canada but no proxy may be exercised by a person who is not a member of CGA-Canada.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>3.</B> The Act is amended by renumbering sections 8 to 12 as sections 9 to 13, and by substituting 芒聙聹CGA-Canada芒聙聺 for 芒聙聹the Association芒聙聺 where these words occur in those sections.</Para></Block><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="BPT_ImprintE"><br/><br/>Published under authority of the Senate of Canada</Para></Block><Block Align="Yes" LineCnt="N"><Para NoLineBreak="Yes" NoHtml="Yes" Leading="0" Size="0" TopMargin="0" BottomMargin="0">脗聞</Para></Block></Bill_Part></Bill>
