<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><Bill bill-origin="commons" bill-type="private-public" xml:lang="en" date-time="2021-02-08 09:03:37"><Identification><BillNumber>C-222</BillNumber><Parliament><Session>1</Session><Number>44</Number><RegnalYear><Year-s>70</Year-s><Monarch>Elizabeth II</Monarch></RegnalYear><Year-s>2021</Year-s></Parliament><LongTitle>An Act to amend the Income Tax Act (travel expenses deduction for tradespersons)</LongTitle><ShortTitle status="unofficial" /><RunningHead>An Act to amend the Income Tax Act (travel expenses deduction for tradespersons)</RunningHead><BillHistory><Stages stage="first-reading-house"><Date><YYYY>2021</YYYY><MM>12</MM><DD>16</DD></Date></Stages></BillHistory><BillSponsor><Emphasis style="smallcaps">Mr. Green</Emphasis></BillSponsor><BillRefNumber date-time="2021-02-08">441052</BillRefNumber></Identification><Introduction><Summary><TitleText>SUMMARY</TitleText><Provision><Text>This enactment amends the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Income Tax Act</XRefExternal> to allow tradespersons and indentured apprentices to deduct from their income amounts expended for travelling where they were employed in a construction activity at a job site that is located at least 80 km away from their ordinary place of residence.</Text></Provision></Summary><Enacts><Provision><Text>Her Majesty, by and with the advice and consent <Keep>of the</Keep> Senate and House of Commons of Canada, <Keep>enacts</Keep> as follows:</Text></Provision></Enacts></Introduction><Body><Heading level="1"><MarginalNote><HistoricalNote>R.S., c. 1 (5th Supp.)</HistoricalNote></MarginalNote><TitleText>Income Tax Act</TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><Label>1</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Subsection 8(1) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Income Tax Act</XRefExternal> is amended by adding the following after paragraph (q):</Text><AmendedText change="ins"><SectionPiece><Paragraph><MarginalNote>Tradesperson’s travel expenses</MarginalNote><Label>(q.1)</Label><Text>where the taxpayer was employed as a duly qualified tradesperson or an indentured apprentice in a construction activity at a job site that was located at least 80 km away from their ordinary place of residence, amounts expended by the taxpayer in the year for travelling to and from the job site, if the taxpayer</Text><Subparagraph><Label>(i)</Label><Text>was required under the contract of employment to pay those expenses,</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph><Label>(ii)</Label><Text>did not receive an allowance in respect of those expenses that is not included in computing the taxpayer’s income for the year, and</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph><Label>(iii)</Label><Text>does not claim those expenses as an income deduction or a tax credit for the year under any other provision of this Act;</Text></Subparagraph></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Subsection (1) applies to the 2022 and subsequent taxation years.</Text></Subsection></Section></Body></Bill>