<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><Bill bill-origin="commons" bill-type="private-public" xml:lang="en" date-time="2022-01-12 08:50:17"><Identification><BillNumber>C-234</BillNumber><Parliament><Session>1</Session><Number>44</Number><RegnalYear><Year-s>70-71</Year-s><Monarch>Elizabeth II – 1 Charles III</Monarch></RegnalYear><Year-s>2021-2022-2023</Year-s></Parliament><LongTitle>An Act to amend the Greenhouse Gas Pollution Pricing Act</LongTitle><ShortTitle status="unofficial" /><RunningHead>An Act to amend the Greenhouse Gas Pollution Pricing Act</RunningHead><BillHistory><Stages stage="third-reading-house"><Date><YYYY>2023</YYYY><MM>3</MM><DD>29</DD></Date></Stages></BillHistory><BillRefNumber date-time="2022-01-12">441111</BillRefNumber></Identification><Introduction><Summary><TitleText>SUMMARY</TitleText><Provision><Text>This enactment amends the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Greenhouse Gas Pollution Pricing Act</XRefExternal> to expand the definition of <DefinitionRef>eligible farming machinery</DefinitionRef> and extend the exemption for qualifying farming fuel to marketable natural gas and propane.</Text></Provision></Summary><Enacts><Provision><Text>His Majesty, by and with the advice and consent <Keep>of the</Keep> Senate and House of Commons of Canada, <Keep>enacts</Keep> as follows:</Text></Provision></Enacts></Introduction><Body><Heading level="1"><MarginalNote><HistoricalNote>2018, c. 12, s. 186</HistoricalNote></MarginalNote><TitleText>Greenhouse Gas Pollution
Pricing Act</TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><Label>1</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The definition <DefinitionRef>eligible farming machinery</DefinitionRef> in section 3 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Greenhouse Gas Pollution Pricing Act</XRefExternal> is amended by adding the following after paragraph (b):</Text><AmendedText><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(b.1)</Label><Text>property used for the purpose of providing heating or cooling to a building or similar structure used for raising or housing livestock or for growing crops;</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(1.1)</Label><Text>Paragraph (b.1) of the definition <DefinitionRef>eligible farming machinery</DefinitionRef> in section 3 of the Act is repealed.</Text></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Paragraph (c) of the definition <DefinitionRef>eligible farming machinery</DefinitionRef> in section 3 of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(c)</Label><Text>an industrial machine or a stationary or portable engine, including a grain dryer; or</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(2.1)</Label><Text>Paragraph (c) of the definition <DefinitionRef>eligible farming machinery</DefinitionRef> in section 3 of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(c)</Label><Text>an industrial machine or a stationary or portable engine; or</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(3)</Label><Text>The definition <DefinitionRef>eligible farming machinery</DefinitionRef> in section 3 of the Act is amended by adding “or” at the end of paragraph (e) and by repealing paragraph (f).</Text></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(3.1)</Label><Text>The definition <DefinitionRef>eligible farming machinery</DefinitionRef> in section 3 of the Act is amended by striking out “or” at the end of paragraph (e) and by adding the following after that paragraph:</Text><AmendedText><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(f)</Label><Text>property that is used for the purpose of providing heating or cooling to a building or similar structure; or</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(4)</Label><Text>The definition <DefinitionRef>qualifying farming fuel</DefinitionRef> in section 3 of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><SectionPiece><Definition><Text><DefinedTermEn>qualifying farming fuel</DefinedTermEn> means a type of fuel that is gasoline, light fuel oil, marketable natural gas, propane or a prescribed type of fuel. (<DefinedTermFr>combustible agricole admissible</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Definition></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(5)</Label><Text>The definition <DefinitionRef>qualifying farming fuel</DefinitionRef> in section 3 of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><SectionPiece><Definition><Text><DefinedTermEn>qualifying farming fuel</DefinedTermEn> means a type of fuel that is gasoline, light fuel oil or a prescribed type of fuel. (<DefinedTermFr>combustible agricole admissible</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Definition></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection></Section><Heading level="1"><TitleText>Coming into Force</TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote>Eighth anniversary or postponement</MarginalNote><Label>2</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Subsections 1(1.1), (2.1), (3.1) and (5) come into force on the day that is the 8th anniversary of the day on which this Act comes into force, unless, before that day, their coming into force is postponed by a resolution — whose text is established under subsection (2) — passed by both Houses of Parliament in accordance with the rules set out in subsection (3).</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Order in council</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The Governor in Council may, by order, establish the text of a resolution providing for the postponement and specifying the period of the postponement.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Rules</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>A motion for the adoption of the resolution may be debated in both Houses of Parliament. At the conclusion of the debate, the Speaker of the House of Parliament must immediately put to a vote every question that is necessary to determine whether or not the motion is concurred in.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Subsequent postponements</MarginalNote><Label>(4)</Label><Text>The postponement may be further extended in accordance with the procedure set out in this section, but the reference to “the day that is the 8th anniversary of the day on which this Act comes into force” in subsection (1) is to be read as “the day on which the most recent postponement under this section expires”.</Text></Subsection></Section></Body></Bill>