<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><Bill bill-origin="commons" bill-type="private-public" xml:lang="en" date-time="2020-10-02 10:05:51"><Identification><BillNumber>C-238</BillNumber><Parliament><Session>1</Session><Number>44</Number><RegnalYear><Year-s>70-71</Year-s><Monarch>Elizabeth II</Monarch></RegnalYear><Year-s>2021-2022</Year-s></Parliament><LongTitle>An Act respecting the French language</LongTitle><ShortTitle status="unofficial" /><RunningHead>An Act respecting the French language</RunningHead><BillHistory><Stages stage="first-reading-house"><Date><YYYY>2022</YYYY><MM>2</MM><DD>7</DD></Date></Stages></BillHistory><BillSponsor><Emphasis style="smallcaps">Ms. DeBellefeuille</Emphasis></BillSponsor><BillRefNumber date-time="2020-10-02">441114</BillRefNumber></Identification><Introduction><Summary><TitleText>SUMMARY</TitleText><Provision><Text>This enactment amends the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Canada Labour Code</XRefExternal>, the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Official Languages Act</XRefExternal> and the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Canada Business Corporations Act</XRefExternal> to ensure that these Acts are consistent with the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Charter of the French Language</XRefExternal> in Quebec.</Text></Provision><Provision><Text>It also amends the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Citizenship Act</XRefExternal> to require that permanent residents who ordinarily reside in Quebec must have an adequate knowledge of French in order to obtain citizenship.</Text></Provision></Summary><Enacts><Provision><Text>Her Majesty, by and with the advice and consent <Keep>of the</Keep> Senate and House of Commons of Canada, <Keep>enacts</Keep> as follows:</Text></Provision></Enacts></Introduction><Body><Heading level="1"><MarginalNote><HistoricalNote>R.S., c. L-2
</HistoricalNote></MarginalNote><TitleText>Canada Labour Code</TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><Label>1</Label><Text>The <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Canada Labour Code</XRefExternal> is amended by adding the following after section 4: </Text><AmendedText><Section change="ins"><MarginalNote>Clarification — Quebec</MarginalNote><Label>4.1</Label><Text>Any federal work, undertaking or business operating in Quebec is subject to the requirements of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Charter of the French Language</XRefExternal>, R.S.Q., c. C-11.</Text></Section></AmendedText></Section><Heading level="1"><MarginalNote><HistoricalNote>R.S., c. 31 (4th Supp.)</HistoricalNote></MarginalNote><TitleText>Official Languages Act </TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><Label>2</Label><Text>The preamble of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Official Languages Act</XRefExternal> is amended by adding the following after the last paragraph: </Text><AmendedText change="ins"><Provision><Text>AND WHEREAS the Government of Canada recognizes that French is the official language of Quebec and the common language in Quebec;</Text></Provision></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>3</Label><Text>Subsection 41(2) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><Subsection change="ins"><MarginalNote>Undertaking</MarginalNote><Label>(1.1)</Label><Text>The Government of Canada undertakes not to obstruct the application in Quebec of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Charter of the French Language</XRefExternal>, R.S.Q., c. C-11.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Duty of federal institutions</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Every federal institution has the duty to ensure that positive measures are taken for the implementation of the commitments <Ins>and undertaking under subsections (1) and (1.1), respectively</Ins>. For greater certainty, <Ins>the</Ins> implementation shall be <Ins>consistent with</Ins> the jurisdiction and powers of the provinces <Ins>and in particular, in Quebec, with the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Charter of the French Language</XRefExternal>, R.S.Q., c. C-11</Ins>.</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>4</Label><Text>Section 43 of the Act is amended by adding the following after subsection (1): </Text><AmendedText><Subsection change="ins"><MarginalNote>Implementation in Quebec</MarginalNote><Label>(1.1)</Label><Text>Any measure referred to in subsection (1) shall be implemented, in Quebec, in a manner that is consistent with the objectives of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Charter of the French Language</XRefExternal>, R.S.Q., c. C-11.</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>5</Label><Text>Section 55 of the Act is renumbered as subsection 55(1) and is amended by adding the following: </Text><AmendedText><Subsection change="ins"><MarginalNote>Quebec</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>In Quebec, the Commissioner shall carry out those duties and functions in a manner that does not obstruct the application of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Charter of the French Language</XRefExternal>, R.S.Q., c. C-11.</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Section><Heading level="1"><MarginalNote><HistoricalNote>R.S., c. C-44; 1994, c. 24, s. 1(F)</HistoricalNote></MarginalNote><TitleText>Canada Business Corporations Act</TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><Label>6</Label><Text>Section 10 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Canada Business Corporations Act</XRefExternal> is amended by adding the following after subsection (3): </Text><AmendedText><Subsection change="ins"><MarginalNote>Exception</MarginalNote><Label>(3.1)</Label><Text>Despite subsection (3), the name of a corporation that carries on business in the Province of Quebec shall meet the requirements of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Charter of the French Language</XRefExternal>, R.S.Q., c. C-11.</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Section><Heading level="1"><MarginalNote><HistoricalNote>R.‍S.‍, c. C-29</HistoricalNote></MarginalNote><TitleText>Citizenship Act</TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><Label>7</Label><Text>Paragraphs 5(1)‍(d) and (e) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Citizenship Act</XRefExternal> are replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(d)</Label><Text>if 18 years of age or more but less than <Ins>65</Ins> years of age at the date of his or her application, has an adequate knowledge of one of the official languages of Canada, <Ins>unless the person ordinarily resides in Quebec, in which case he or she must have an adequate knowledge of French</Ins>;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(e)</Label><Text>if 18 years of age or more but less than <Ins>65</Ins> years of age at the date of his or her application, demonstrates in one of the official languages of Canada that he or she has an adequate knowledge of Canada and of the responsibilities and privileges of citizenship, <Ins>unless the person ordinarily resides in Quebec, in which case he or she must demonstrate that knowledge in French</Ins>; and</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Section></Body></Bill>