<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><Bill bill-origin="commons" bill-type="private-public" xml:lang="en" date-time="2018-10-18 11:57:15"><Identification><BillNumber>C-230</BillNumber><Parliament><Session>1</Session><Number>44</Number><RegnalYear><Year-s>70</Year-s><Monarch>Elizabeth II</Monarch></RegnalYear><Year-s>2021-2022</Year-s></Parliament><LongTitle>An Act to amend the Criminal Code (intimidation of health care professionals)</LongTitle><ShortTitle status="unofficial" /><RunningHead>An Act to amend the Criminal Code (intimidation of health care professionals)</RunningHead><BillHistory><Stages stage="first-reading-house"><Date><YYYY>2022</YYYY><MM>2</MM><DD>4</DD></Date></Stages></BillHistory><BillSponsor><Emphasis style="smallcaps">Mrs. Block</Emphasis></BillSponsor><BillRefNumber date-time="2018-10-18">441089</BillRefNumber></Identification><Introduction><Summary><TitleText>SUMMARY</TitleText><Provision><Text>This enactment amends the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Criminal Code</XRefExternal> to make it an offence to intimidate a medical practitioner, nurse practitioner, pharmacist or other health care professional for the purpose of compelling them to take part, directly or indirectly, in the provision of medical assistance in dying. </Text></Provision><Provision><Text>It also makes it an offence to dismiss from employment or to refuse to employ a medical practitioner, nurse practitioner, pharmacist or other health care professional for the reason only that they refuse to take part, directly or indirectly, in the provision of medical assistance in dying.</Text></Provision></Summary><Preamble><Provision><MarginalNote>Preamble</MarginalNote><Text>Whereas everyone has freedom of conscience and religion under section 2 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Canadian Charter of Rights and Freedoms</XRefExternal>;</Text></Provision><Provision><Text>Whereas Parliament considers that it is in the public interest to protect the freedom of conscience of a medical practitioner, nurse practitioner, pharmacist or other health care professional who objects to taking part, directly or indirectly, in the provision of medical assistance in dying;</Text></Provision><Provision><Text>And whereas a regime that would require a medical practitioner, nurse practitioner, pharmacist or other health care professional to provide effective referral to patients could infringe on the freedom of conscience of health care professionals;</Text></Provision><Provision language-align="yes"><Text>Now, therefore, Her Majesty, by and with the advice and consent of the Senate and House of Commons of Canada, enacts as follows:</Text></Provision></Preamble></Introduction><Body><Heading level="1"><TitleText>Short Title</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Short title</MarginalNote><Label>1</Label><Text>This Act may be cited as the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Protection of Freedom of Conscience Act</XRefExternal>. </Text></Section><Heading level="1"><MarginalNote><HistoricalNote>R.S., c. C-46</HistoricalNote></MarginalNote><TitleText>Criminal Code</TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><Label>2</Label><Text>The <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Criminal Code</XRefExternal> is amended by adding the following after section 241.2:</Text><AmendedText><Section change="ins"><MarginalNote>Intimidation</MarginalNote><Label>241.21</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Every person who, for the purpose of compelling a medical practitioner, nurse practitioner, pharmacist or other health care professional to take part, <Keep svc="1">directly</Keep> or indirectly, in the provision of medical assistance in dying, uses coercion or any other form of intimidation is guilty of an offence punishable on summary conviction.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Employers</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Every person who refuses to employ, or dismisses from their employment, a medical practitioner, nurse practitioner, pharmacist or other health care professional for the reason only that they refuse to take part, directly or indirectly, in the provision of medical assist­ance in dying is guilty of an offence punishable on summary conviction.</Text></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Section></Body></Bill>