<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><Bill bill-origin="commons" bill-type="private-public" xml:lang="en" date-time="2021-06-14 14:29:19"><Identification><BillNumber>C-247</BillNumber><Parliament><Session>1</Session><Number>44</Number><RegnalYear><Year-s>70-71</Year-s><Monarch>Elizabeth II</Monarch></RegnalYear><Year-s>2021-2022</Year-s></Parliament><LongTitle>An Act to prohibit fur farming</LongTitle><ShortTitle status="unofficial" /><RunningHead>Prohibition of Fur Farming Act</RunningHead><BillHistory><Stages stage="first-reading-house"><Date><YYYY>2022</YYYY><MM>2</MM><DD>8</DD></Date></Stages></BillHistory><BillSponsor><Emphasis style="smallcaps">Mr. Erskine-Smith</Emphasis></BillSponsor><BillRefNumber date-time="2021-06-14">441124</BillRefNumber></Identification><Introduction><Summary><TitleText>SUMMARY</TitleText><Provision><Text>This enactment establishes prohibitions and offences for certain activities involving fur farming.</Text></Provision></Summary><Enacts><Provision><Text>Her Majesty, by and with the advice and consent <Keep>of the</Keep> Senate and House of Commons of Canada, <Keep>enacts</Keep> as follows:</Text></Provision></Enacts></Introduction><Body><Heading level="1"><TitleText>Short Title</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Short title</MarginalNote><Label>1</Label><Text>This Act may be cited as the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Prohibition of Fur Farming Act</XRefExternal>.</Text></Section><Heading level="1"><TitleText>Interpretation</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Definitions</MarginalNote><Label>2</Label><Text>The following definitions apply in this Act.</Text><Definition><Text><DefinedTermEn>fur farm</DefinedTermEn> means a place where fur-bearing animals are kept in captivity in order for their pelt to be used for commercial purposes. (<DefinedTermFr>ferme d’élevage d’animaux à fourrure</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Definition><Definition><Text><DefinedTermEn>Minister</DefinedTermEn> means the Minister of Agriculture and Agri-Food. (<DefinedTermFr>ministre</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Definition></Section><Heading level="1"><TitleText>Prohibitions</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Prohibitions — fur farm</MarginalNote><Label>3</Label><Text>It is prohibited to</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>own or operate a fur farm or cause a fur farm to be operated;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>breed or inseminate a fur-bearing animal for the purpose of sending it or its offspring to a fur farm;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(c)</Label><Text>slaughter a fur-bearing animal to use its pelt for commercial purposes; or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(d)</Label><Text>give, rent, sell or transport a fur-bearing animal to a fur farm.</Text></Paragraph></Section><Heading level="1"><TitleText>Enforcement</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Offence</MarginalNote><Label>4</Label><Text>Every person who contravenes section 3 is guilty of an offence and liable</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>on conviction on indictment, to a fine of not more than $250,000 or to imprisonment for a term of not more than two years, or to both; or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>on summary conviction, to a fine of not more than $50,000 or to imprisonment for a term of not more than six months, or to both.</Text></Paragraph></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Order of prohibition or restitution</MarginalNote><Label>5</Label><Text>The court may, in addition to any other punishment that may be imposed under section 4, make an order</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>prohibiting the accused from owning, having custody or control of, or residing in the same premises as an animal during any period that the court considers appropriate; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>on application of the Attorney General or on its own motion, directing the accused to pay to a person or an organization that has taken care of a fur-bearing animal as a result of the commission of the offence the reasonable costs that the person or organization incurred in respect of the fur-bearing animal.</Text></Paragraph></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Forfeiture</MarginalNote><Label>6</Label><Text>On <Emphasis style="italic">ex parte</Emphasis> application by the Attorney General, a <DefinitionRef>provincial court judge</DefinitionRef> as defined in section 2 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Criminal Code</XRefExternal> or a <DefinitionRef>judge</DefinitionRef> as defined in subsection 462.3(1) of that Act may order that a fur-bearing animal be forfeited to Her Majesty in right of Canada.</Text></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Forfeiture — if person found guilty</MarginalNote><Label>7</Label><Text>If a person is found guilty of an offence under <Keep>section 4</Keep>, the court may, in addition to any other punishment imposed under that section, order that anything by means of which or in respect of which the offence was committed be forfeited to Her Majesty in right of Canada.</Text></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Disposal</MarginalNote><Label>8</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Anything that is forfeited under section 6 or 7 must be disposed of as the Minister directs.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Priority to transfer</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The Minister must give priority to transferring any fur-bearing animal forfeited to an animal sanctuary, shelter or rescue service.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Regulations
</MarginalNote><Label>9</Label><Text>The Governor in Council may make regulations in respect of a regime that provides compensation for losses incurred as a result of complying with this Act.</Text></Section><Heading level="1"><TitleText>Coming into Force</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>One year after royal assent</MarginalNote><Label>10</Label><Text>This Act comes into force one year after the day on which it receives royal assent.</Text></Section></Body></Bill>