<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><Bill bill-origin="commons" bill-type="private-public" xml:lang="en" date-time="2022-01-27 13:34:14"><Identification><BillNumber>C-245</BillNumber><Parliament><Session>1</Session><Number>44</Number><RegnalYear><Year-s>70-71</Year-s><Monarch>Elizabeth II</Monarch></RegnalYear><Year-s>2021-2022</Year-s></Parliament><LongTitle>An Act to amend the Canada Infrastructure Bank Act</LongTitle><ShortTitle status="unofficial" /><RunningHead>An Act to amend the Canada Infrastructure Bank Act</RunningHead><BillHistory><Stages stage="first-reading-house"><Date><YYYY>2022</YYYY><MM>2</MM><DD>8</DD></Date></Stages></BillHistory><BillSponsor><Emphasis style="smallcaps">Ms. Ashton</Emphasis></BillSponsor><BillRefNumber date-time="2022-01-27">441108</BillRefNumber></Identification><Introduction><Summary><TitleText>SUMMARY</TitleText><Provision><Text>This enactment amends the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Canada Infrastructure Bank Act</XRefExternal> to refocus the purpose of the Bank and to provide that it must give priority to certain investments and infrastructure projects.</Text></Provision></Summary><Enacts><Provision><Text>Her Majesty, by and with the advice and consent <Keep>of the</Keep> Senate and House of Commons of Canada, <Keep>enacts</Keep> as follows:</Text></Provision></Enacts></Introduction><Body><Heading level="1"><MarginalNote><HistoricalNote>2017, c. 20, s. 403</HistoricalNote></MarginalNote><TitleText>Canada Infrastructure Bank Act</TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><Label>1</Label><Text>Section 6 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Canada Infrastructure Bank Act</XRefExternal> is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><Section><MarginalNote>Purpose of Bank</MarginalNote><Label>6</Label><Text>The purpose of the Bank is to invest in infrastructure projects in Canada or partly in Canada that <Ins>are</Ins> in the public interest by, for example, supporting conditions that foster <Ins>climate change mitigation or adaptation</Ins>, or by contributing to the sustainability of infrastructure in Canada.</Text></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>2</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Paragraphs 7(1)(b) and (c) of the Act are replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>invest in infrastructure projects, including by means of innovative financial tools;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(c)</Label><Text>receive unsolicited proposals for infrastructure projects;</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Paragraph 7(1)(e) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(e)</Label><Text>act as a centre of expertise on infrastructure projects;</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>3</Label><Text>Section 7 is amended by adding the following after subsection (1):</Text><AmendedText><Subsection change="ins"><MarginalNote>Priority</MarginalNote><Label>(1.1)</Label><Text>In carrying out the functions set out in subsection (1), the Bank must give priority to:</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>investments from public institutions, all levels of governments and Northern and Indigenous communities;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>infrastructure projects that propose measures aimed at mitigating or adapting to climate change; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(c)</Label><Text>infrastructure projects that are not harmful to the environment.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>4</Label><Text>Section 8 of the Act is amended by adding the following after subsection (1):</Text><AmendedText><Subsection change="ins"><MarginalNote>Membership</MarginalNote><Label>(1.1)</Label><Text>The membership of the Board must include at least</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>one person recommended by an Indigenous organization that represents the interests of First Nations;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>one person recommended by an Indigenous organization that represents the interests of the Inuit; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(c)</Label><Text>one person recommended by an Indigenous organization that represents the interests of the Métis.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>5</Label><Text>The Act is amended by adding the following after section 27:</Text><AmendedText><Section change="ins"><MarginalNote>Special Report</MarginalNote><Label>27.1</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The Bank must annually submit a report to the designated Minister on the investments and infrastructure projects to which priority was given under subsection 7(1.1).</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Tabling in Parliament</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The designated Minister must table the report before each House of Parliament on any of the first 15 days on which that House is sitting after the designated Minister receives it.</Text></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>6</Label><Text>Subsection 28(1) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><Section><MarginalNote>Privileged information</MarginalNote><Label>28</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Subject to subsection (2), all information obtained by the Bank, by any of the Bank’s subsidiaries or by any of the subsidiaries of the Bank’s wholly-owned subsidiaries in relation to the proponents of <Keep svc="1">infrastructure</Keep> projects is privileged and a director, officer, employee, or agent or mandatary of, or adviser or consultant to, the Bank, any of its subsidiaries, or any of the subsidiaries of its wholly-owned subsidiaries must not knowingly communicate, disclose or make available the information, or permit it to be communicated, disclosed or made available.</Text></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Section></Body></Bill>