<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><Bill bill-origin="commons" bill-type="private-public" xml:lang="en" date-time="2022-01-19 11:03:42"><Identification><BillNumber>C-246</BillNumber><Parliament><Session>1</Session><Number>44</Number><RegnalYear><Year-s>70-71</Year-s><Monarch>Elizabeth II</Monarch></RegnalYear><Year-s>2021-2022</Year-s></Parliament><LongTitle>An Act to amend the Constitution Act, 1867 (representation in the House of Commons)</LongTitle><ShortTitle status="unofficial" /><RunningHead>An Act to amend the Constitution Act, 1867 (representation in the House of Commons)</RunningHead><BillHistory><Stages stage="first-reading-house"><Date><YYYY>2022</YYYY><MM>2</MM><DD>8</DD></Date></Stages></BillHistory><BillSponsor><Emphasis style="smallcaps">Mr. Champoux</Emphasis></BillSponsor><BillRefNumber date-time="2022-01-19">441098</BillRefNumber></Identification><Introduction><Summary><TitleText>SUMMARY</TitleText><Provision><Text>This enactment amends section 51 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Constitution Act, 1867</XRefExternal> to provide that the total number of members from the province of Quebec cannot be less than 25% of the total number of members in the House of Commons.</Text></Provision></Summary><Preamble><Provision><MarginalNote>Preamble</MarginalNote><Text>Whereas section 44 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Constitution Act, 1982</XRefExternal> gives Parliament exclusive authority to amend the Constitution of Canada in relation to the House of Commons;</Text></Provision><Provision><Text>Whereas, on December 11, 1995, the House of Commons adopted a motion encouraging all components of the legislative and executive branches of government to recognize Quebec as a distinct society and to be guided accordingly in their conduct;</Text></Provision><Provision><Text>Whereas, on November 24, 2006, the House of Commons adopted a motion recognizing that Quebeckers form a nation within a united Canada;</Text></Provision><Provision><Text>And whereas, on June 16, 2021, the House of Commons adopted a motion agreeing that section 45 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Constitution Act, 1982</XRefExternal> grants the provinces, including Quebec, exclusive jurisdiction to amend their respective constitutions and acknowledging the will of Quebec to enshrine in its constitution that Quebeckers form a nation, that French is the only official language of Quebec and that it is also the common language of the Quebec nation;</Text></Provision><Provision language-align="yes"><Text>Now, therefore, Her Majesty, with the advice and consent of the Senate and House of Commons of Canada, enacts as follows:</Text></Provision></Preamble></Introduction><Body><Heading level="1"><TitleText>Short Title</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Short title</MarginalNote><Label>1</Label><Text>This Act may be cited as the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Constitution Act, 2022 (representation of Quebec)</XRefExternal>.</Text></Section><Heading level="1"><MarginalNote><HistoricalNote>30-31 Vict., c. 3 (U.K.); 1982, c. 11 (U.K.)</HistoricalNote></MarginalNote><TitleText>Constitution Act, 1867</TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><Label>2</Label><Text>Section 51 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Constitution Act, 1867</XRefExternal> is amended by adding the following after rule 4:</Text><AmendedText><Section change="ins"><Label>4.1</Label><Text>After the application of rules 1 and 2 and section 51A, there shall in respect of Quebec be added any additional members needed so that, after the completion of the readjustment, the total number of members for that province is not less than 25% of the total number of members in the House of Commons.</Text></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote>Interpretation</MarginalNote><Label>3</Label><Text>A reference to the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Constitution Acts, 1867 to 1982</XRefExternal> is deemed to include a reference to this Act.</Text></Section></Body></Bill>