<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><Bill bill-origin="commons" bill-type="private-public" xml:lang="en" date-time="2022-01-24 13:27:51"><Identification><BillNumber>C-251</BillNumber><Parliament><Session>1</Session><Number>44</Number><RegnalYear><Year-s>70-71</Year-s><Monarch>Elizabeth II</Monarch></RegnalYear><Year-s>2021-2022</Year-s></Parliament><LongTitle>An Act respecting the development of a federal framework on the conservation of fish stocks and management of pinnipeds
</LongTitle><ShortTitle status="unofficial" /><RunningHead>Conservation of Fish Stocks and Management of Pinnipeds Act</RunningHead><BillHistory><Stages stage="first-reading-house"><Date><YYYY>2022</YYYY><MM>2</MM><DD>9</DD></Date></Stages></BillHistory><BillSponsor><Emphasis style="smallcaps">Mr. Small</Emphasis></BillSponsor><BillRefNumber date-time="2022-01-24">441130</BillRefNumber></Identification><Introduction><Summary><TitleText>SUMMARY</TitleText><Provision><Text>This enactment requires the Minister of Fisheries and Oceans to develop a federal framework on the conservation of fish stocks and management of pinnipeds.</Text></Provision></Summary><Preamble><Provision><MarginalNote>Preamble</MarginalNote><Text>Whereas pinnipeds, such as seals, sea lions and walruses, are natural predators of fish, molluscs and crustaceans;</Text></Provision><Provision><Text>Whereas large populations of pinnipeds are responsible for significant fish, mollusc and crustacean mortalities, damage to fishing equipment and harm to marine ecosystems;</Text></Provision><Provision><Text>And whereas it is vital to protect marine species and their environment by controlling and reducing pinniped predation;</Text></Provision><Provision language-align="yes"><Text>Now, therefore, Her Majesty, by and with the advice and consent of the Senate and House of Commons of Canada, enacts as follows:</Text></Provision></Preamble></Introduction><Body><Heading level="1"><TitleText>Short Title</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Short title</MarginalNote><Label>1</Label><Text>This Act may be cited as the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Conservation of Fish Stocks and Management of Pinnipeds Act</XRefExternal>.</Text></Section><Heading level="1"><TitleText>Interpretation</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Definitions</MarginalNote><Label>2</Label><Text>The following definitions apply in this Act.</Text><Definition><Text><DefinedTermEn>Indigenous governing body</DefinedTermEn> means a council, government or other entity that is authorized to act on behalf of an Indigenous group, community or people that holds rights recognized and affirmed by section 35 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Constitution Act, 1982</XRefExternal>. (<DefinedTermFr>corps dirigeant autochtone</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Definition><Definition><Text><DefinedTermEn>Minister</DefinedTermEn> means the Minister of Fisheries and Oceans. (<DefinedTermFr>ministre</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Definition></Section><Heading level="1"><TitleText>Federal Framework</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Development</MarginalNote><Label>3</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The Minister must, in consultation with representatives of the provincial governments responsible for fisheries, the environment and trade, with Indigenous governing bodies and with other relevant stakeholders, develop a federal framework on the conservation of fish stocks and management of pinnipeds.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Content</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The framework must include measures to</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>promote the conservation and protection of marine ecosystems by addressing the harms caused by pinniped overpopulation;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>provide for yearly pinniped censuses to be conducted;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(c)</Label><Text>regulate the management and control of pinniped populations to establish acceptable levels for pinniped species, determined based on historic levels and the levels of similar species where fish, mollusc and crustacean biomasses are consistently maintained at commercially viable levels in other countries in the northern hemisphere;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(d)</Label><Text>encourage the use of anti-predator mechanisms around fishing facilities or infrastructure, and spawning areas;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(e)</Label><Text>promote year-round control of pinnipeds in order to manage their numbers and mitigate the detrimental effect these marine mammals are having on the environment when acceptable pinniped population levels are exceeded; </Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(f)</Label><Text>address trade barriers on seal products to promote the sale and trade of various seal products by local businesses; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(g)</Label><Text>establish programs and projects, mainly in rural areas, coastal communities and Indigenous communities, to promote the making and selling of pinniped products.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection></Section><Heading level="1"><TitleText>Reports to Parliament</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Tabling of framework</MarginalNote><Label>4</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Within one year after the day on which this Act comes into force, the Minister must prepare a report setting out the federal framework and cause the report to be tabled in each House of Parliament on any of the first 15 days on which that House is sitting after the report is completed.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Publication</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The Minister must publish the report on the website of the Department of Fisheries and Oceans within 10 days after the report has been tabled in both Houses of Parliament.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Annual Report</MarginalNote><Label>5</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Within one year after the report referred to in section 4 has been tabled in both Houses of Parliament, and every year after that, the Minister must prepare a report on the effectiveness of the federal framework, setting out the Minister's conclusions and recommendations, and cause the report to be tabled in each House of Parliament on any of the first 15 days on which that House is sitting after it is completed.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Publication</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The Minister must publish the report on the website of the Department of Fisheries and Oceans within 10 days after the report has been tabled in both Houses of Parliament.</Text></Subsection></Section></Body></Bill>