<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><Bill bill-origin="commons" bill-type="private-public" xml:lang="en" date-time="2022-02-03 13:46:53"><Identification><BillNumber>C-262</BillNumber><Parliament><Session>1</Session><Number>44</Number><RegnalYear><Year-s>70-71</Year-s><Monarch>Elizabeth II</Monarch></RegnalYear><Year-s>2021-2022</Year-s></Parliament><LongTitle>An Act respecting the corporate responsibility to prevent, address and remedy adverse impacts on human rights occurring in relation to business activities conducted abroad</LongTitle><ShortTitle status="unofficial">Corporate Responsibility to Protect Human Rights Act</ShortTitle><RunningHead>Corporate Responsibility to Protect Human Rights Act</RunningHead><BillHistory><Stages stage="first-reading-house"><Date><YYYY>2022</YYYY><MM>3</MM><DD>29</DD></Date></Stages></BillHistory><BillSponsor><Emphasis style="smallcaps">Mr. Julian</Emphasis></BillSponsor><BillRefNumber date-time="2022-02-03">441062</BillRefNumber></Identification><Introduction><Summary><TitleText>SUMMARY</TitleText><Provision><Text>This enactment, among other things, requires businesses to establish processes to prevent, address and remedy adverse impacts on human rights that occur in relation to their business activities conducted abroad.</Text></Provision></Summary><Preamble><Provision><MarginalNote>Preamble</MarginalNote><Text>Whereas the realities of global supply chains, cross-border trade, investment, communications and movement of people are such that Canadian business entities may cause adverse impacts on human rights outside Canada, either through their own activities or through their business relationships; </Text></Provision><Provision><Text>Whereas Canadian business entities have the responsibility to prevent and mitigate actual or potential adverse impacts on human rights that are linked to their business activities conducted outside Canada and, to that end, to act with due diligence;</Text></Provision><Provision><Text>Whereas the right to a remedy is a core tenet of the international human rights system, and the need for victims to have access to an effective remedy is recognized in the United Nations Guiding Principles on Business and Human Rights; </Text></Provision><Provision><Text>Whereas, at present, there is a lack of accountability and recourse and, in the event that a remedy is obtained, it often fails to meet international standards regarding what constitutes adequate, effective and prompt reparation for harm suffered; </Text></Provision><Provision><Text>Whereas ensuring the legal accountability of business entities and ensuring that affected individuals have access to an effective remedy is a vital part of a stateГўВҖВҷs duty to protect against business-related human rights violations; </Text></Provision><Provision><Text>And whereas effective state-based judicial mechanisms are at the core of ensuring access to an effective remedy; </Text></Provision></Preamble><Enacts><Provision><Text>Now, therefore, Her Majesty, by and with the advice and consent <Keep>of the</Keep> Senate and House of Commons of Canada, <Keep>enacts</Keep> as follows:</Text></Provision></Enacts></Introduction><Body><Heading level="1"><TitleText>Short Title</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Short title</MarginalNote><Label>1</Label><Text>This Act may be cited as the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Corporate Responsibility to Protect Human Rights Act</XRefExternal>.</Text></Section><Heading level="1"><TitleText>Interpretation</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Definitions</MarginalNote><Label>2</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The following definitions apply in this Act.</Text><Definition><Text><DefinedTermEn>affiliate</DefinedTermEn>ГўВҖВӮmeans an affiliated entity within the meaning of subsection (2). (<DefinedTermFr>groupe</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Definition><Definition><Text><DefinedTermEn>business relationship</DefinedTermEn>,ГўВҖВӮin respect of an entity, includes a relationship the entity has</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>with any individual
 ГўВҖВ“ including a home-based worker ГўВҖВ“ or entity in its supply chain; and </Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>with any individual, entity or organization that is directly linked to its operations, products or services, including in relation to the provision of security services. (<DefinedTermFr>relation dГўВҖВҷaffaires</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Paragraph></Definition><Definition><Text><DefinedTermEn>entity</DefinedTermEn>ГўВҖВӮmeans a corporation or a trust, partnership or other association but does not include a registered charity, non-profit organization or trade union. (<DefinedTermFr>entitГғВ©</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Definition><Definition><Text><DefinedTermEn>human rights</DefinedTermEn>ГўВҖВӮincludes the right to a healthy environment and the rights recognized under the international human rights instruments listed in the schedule. (<DefinedTermFr>droits de la personne</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Definition><Definition><Text><DefinedTermEn>Minister</DefinedTermEn>ГўВҖВӮmeans the Minister of Justice. (<DefinedTermFr>ministre</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Definition></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Affiliated entities</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>For the purposes of this Act, an entity is affiliated with another entity if</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>one of them is the subsidiary of the other;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>both are subsidiaries of the same entity;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(c)</Label><Text>both are controlled by the same individual or entity; or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(d)</Label><Text>both are affiliated with the same entity at the same time.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Control</MarginalNote><Label>3</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>For the purposes of this Act, an entity is controlled by an individual or another entity if</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>20% or more of the voting interests in the entity are held by or for the benefit of that individual or <Keep>other</Keep> entity, directly or indirectly;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>the individual or other entity, alone or in combination with another entity, is entitled through voting shares or on the basis of an agreement with another party, to cast at least 30% of the votes to elect the directors of the entityГўВҖВҷs board, directly or indirectly; </Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(c)</Label><Text>the individual or other entity influences the management and policies of the entity, directly or indirectly;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(d)</Label><Text>the individual or other entity determines the salary or bonus structure of the entityГўВҖВҷs executives or employees, directly or indirectly;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(e)</Label><Text>the individual or other entity otherwise controls the entity in fact, directly or indirectly; or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(f)</Label><Text>the individual or other entity publicly represents itself as being responsible for or in control of the entity.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Subsidiary</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>An entity is a subsidiary of another entity if</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>it is controlled by</Text><Subparagraph><Label>(i)</Label><Text>that other entity and no other,</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph><Label>(ii)</Label><Text>that other entity and one or more entities each of which is controlled by that other entity, or</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph><Label>(iii)</Label><Text>two or more entities each of which is controlled by that other entity; or</Text></Subparagraph></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>it is a subsidiary of an entity that is a subsidiary of that other entity.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection></Section><Heading level="1"><TitleText>Purpose</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Purpose</MarginalNote><Label>4</Label><Text>The purpose of this Act is to prevent, address and remedy the adverse impacts on human rights that occur in relation to business activities conducted by entities abroad.</Text></Section><Heading level="1"><TitleText>Application</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Application</MarginalNote><Label>5</Label><Text>This Act applies to an entity, other than an entity that is exempted by regulation from the application of this Act,</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>that is incorporated or formed under an Act of Parliament or of the legislature of a province, or otherwise formed in Canada; or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>that has a place of business in Canada, carries on business in Canada or has assets in Canada that are used in carrying on the entityГўВҖВҷs business.</Text></Paragraph></Section><Heading level="1"><TitleText>Obligations</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Duty to prevent adverse impacts ГўВҖВ” entity and its affiliates</MarginalNote><Label>6</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>In carrying out its business activities, every entity has a duty to avoid causing any adverse impacts on human rights from occurring outside Canada as a result of its acts or omissions or those of its affiliates.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Duty to prevent adverse impacts ГўВҖВ” business relationships</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Every entity has a duty to prevent any adverse impacts on human rights from occurring outside Canada as a result of its business relationships.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Liability of entity</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>An entity is liable for any injury that results from its failure to comply with subsection (1) or (2), regardless of whether the injury resulted from an act or omission of the entity, its affiliate or an individual with whom the entity has a business relationship.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Due diligence ГўВҖВ” procedures</MarginalNote><Label>7</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Every entity must develop and implement due diligence procedures in respect of its activities, its affiliates and its business relationships, including procedures enabling the entity to </Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>identify and assess actual and potential adverse impacts on human rights resulting from its activities as well as from its business relationships, including with suppliers or contractors;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>cease any activity that led to the adverse impacts and take remedial action;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(c)</Label><Text>mitigate risks of adverse impacts; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(d)</Label><Text>by means of an internal alert mechanism, be notified of any potential adverse impacts on human rights.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Monitoring</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Every entity must monitor and document the implementation and effectiveness of its due diligence procedures.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Implementation</MarginalNote><Label>8</Label><Text>In developing and implementing its due diligence procedures, an entity must</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>take into account the intersection of sex and gender with other identity factors that include race, national and ethnic origin, Indigenous origin or identity, age, sexual orientation, socio-economic condition, place of residence and disability;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>consult with individuals whose human rights may be directly affected, or representatives of those individuals, as well as with trade unions, employees, affected communities and other relevant stakeholders, including independent experts;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(c)</Label><Text>take into account the standards, practices and procedures recommended by international organizations in relation to businesses and human rights, including those set out in the United Nations Guiding Principles on Business and Human Rights, endorsed by the Human Rights Council in its resolution 17/4 of June 16, 2011; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(d)</Label><Text>have regard to the relationship between human rights and the environment, specifically that a healthy and sustainable environment is integral to the full enjoyment of a wide range of human rights, including the rights to life, health, sustainably produced food and safe water.</Text></Paragraph></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Due diligence annual report</MarginalNote><Label>9</Label><Text>Within one year after the day on which this Act comes into force, and every year after that, every entity must, in accordance with any regulations, make public a report on its due diligence that sets out, for the year to which the report relates,</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>the due diligence procedures that the entity has established and the effectiveness of their implementation;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>the entity's business activities and business relationships, including those in connection with any of its operations, products or services, in respect of which its due diligence procedures apply;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(c)</Label><Text>a list of the entityГўВҖВҷs affiliates in respect of which its due diligence procedures apply;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(d)</Label><Text>the entityГўВҖВҷs activities in respect of which a risk of adverse impacts on human rights has been identified and the measures that the entity has taken to assess and mitigate the risk; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(e)</Label><Text>any other information required by regulation.</Text></Paragraph></Section><Heading level="1"><TitleText>Private Right of Action</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Right to bring an action ГўВҖВ” loss or damage suffered</MarginalNote><Label>10</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>A person who alleges that they have suffered loss or damage as a result of a failure by an entity to comply with its obligations to prevent adverse impacts under this Act may, in a superior court of a province, bring an action against the entity and, in the action, claim relief by way of one or more of the following:</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>damages for any loss or damage suffered;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>aggravated or punitive damages;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(c)</Label><Text>an injunction;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(d)</Label><Text>an order for specific performance;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(e)</Label><Text>the cost of any land remediation; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(f)</Label><Text>any other appropriate relief, including the costs of the action.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Right to bring an action ГўВҖВ” due diligence procedures</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>An action may be brought against an entity in respect of the entityГўВҖВҷs failure to develop and implement due <Keep svc="1">diligence</Keep> procedures provided that the matter arises in the context of the protection of human rights.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Who may bring action</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>The action under subsection (2) may be brought by any person who raises a serious issue and is either directly affected by the matter or</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>has a genuine interest in the matter;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>presents a reasonable means of advancing the proceeding; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(c)</Label><Text>has no conflict of interest with regard to the outcome.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Relief</MarginalNote><Label>(4)</Label><Text>In an action brought under subsection (2), the person may claim relief by way of one or more of the following:</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>damages for any loss suffered;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>aggravated or punitive damages;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(c)</Label><Text>an injunction;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(d)</Label><Text>an order for specific performance; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(e)</Label><Text>any other appropriate relief, including the costs of the action.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Prosecution not precluded</MarginalNote><Label>11</Label><Text>Nothing in this Act precludes the prosecution by the Attorney General of Canada of any offence under the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Criminal Code</XRefExternal> or any other Act of Parliament.</Text></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Limitation period of five years</MarginalNote><Label>12</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>A person may bring an action under subsection 10(1) only within a limitation period of five years beginning on the later of</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>the day on which the person becomes aware of the act or omission on which the action is based, and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>the day on which any criminal proceedings relating to the act or omission are finally disposed of.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Limitation period of two years</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>A person may bring an action under subsection 10(2) only within a limitation period of two years beginning on the day on which the person becomes aware of the failure by the entity to comply with subsection 7(1).</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Suspension of limitation period</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>A limitation period in respect of an action brought against an entity under section 10 is suspended during any period in which the person that suffered the loss or damage</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>is incapable of beginning the action because of any physical or mental condition; or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>is unable to ascertain the identity or the involvement of the entity.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>No limitation period</MarginalNote><Label>(4)</Label><Text>An action arising out of an alleged sexual assault may be commenced at any time. </Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Common law</MarginalNote><Label>(5)</Label><Text>Nothing in this section is to be construed as affecting any right or authority at common law to suspend the limitation period.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Defence</MarginalNote><Label>13</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>In an action under subsection 10(1), it is a defence for the entity to establish that it exercised all due diligence to prevent the adverse impact on human rights in respect of which the action is brought.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Factors to consider</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>In determining whether an entity exercised all due diligence, the court may consider</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>the extent to which the entity complied with any standards of conduct set out in the regulations;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>whether the adverse impact on human rights was, or could have been, identified as a potential risk by the entity in its due diligence procedures;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(c)</Label><Text>whether the entity has a history of causing or contributing to adverse impacts on human rights;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(d)</Label><Text>whether the entity has, in its business relationships with its suppliers, created any incentives to improve human rights standards; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(e)</Label><Text>any other factors that the court considers relevant.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Jurisdiction of Canadian court</MarginalNote><Label>14</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>A Canadian court has jurisdiction to hear and determine an action brought under section 10 if</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>the entity is domiciled or ordinarily resident in the courtГўВҖВҷs jurisdiction;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>the entity submits to the courtГўВҖВҷs jurisdiction; or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(c)</Label><Text>there is a real and substantial connection between the courtГўВҖВҷs jurisdiction and the facts on which the action against the entity is based.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Defendant submits to jurisdiction</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>An entity submits to the jurisdiction of a court if it explicitly submits to the jurisdiction of the court by written agreement or otherwise, either before or after the proceedings commence.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Ordinarily resident</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>An entity is ordinarily resident in a courtГўВҖВҷs jurisdiction if </Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>it has or is required by law to have a registered office or business address in the courtГўВҖВҷs jurisdiction;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>it has registered an address in the courtГўВҖВҷs jurisdiction at which process may be served;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(c)</Label><Text>it has nominated an agent or mandatary in the courtГўВҖВҷs jurisdiction on whom process may be served;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(d)</Label><Text>it has an agent or mandatary, representative, warehouse or place of business in the courtГўВҖВҷs jurisdiction; or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(e)</Label><Text>its central management and control is exercised in the courtГўВҖВҷs jurisdiction. </Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Real and substantial connection</MarginalNote><Label>(4)</Label><Text>There is deemed to be a real and substantial connection between the courtГўВҖВҷs jurisdiction and the facts on which the action against the entity is based if</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>the action relates to business that is conducted in person in the courtГўВҖВҷs jurisdiction over a sustained period;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>the action is brought in respect of a tort or fault within the meaning of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Civil Code of QuГғВ©bec</XRefExternal> that is alleged to have been committed wholly or partially in the courtГўВҖВҷs jurisdiction; </Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(c)</Label><Text>the action relates to obligations under a contract that was entered into in the courtГўВҖВҷs jurisdiction or is governed by the laws of that jurisdiction;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(d)</Label><Text>the action concerns restitutionary obligations arising wholly or in substantial part in the courtГўВҖВҷs jurisdiction; or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(e)</Label><Text>relief is sought by way of an injunction ordering a party to do or refrain from doing anything in the courtГўВҖВҷs jurisdiction. </Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>No limitation</MarginalNote><Label>(5)</Label><Text>Subsection (4) is not to be construed as limiting the plaintiffГўВҖВҷs right to rely on other circumstances to establish a real and substantial connection.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Jurisdiction</MarginalNote><Label>(6)</Label><Text>A court may not refuse to exercise jurisdiction on the sole ground that the matter should be decided by a court outside Canada.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Other proceedings</MarginalNote><Label>(7)</Label><Text>An action brought under section 10 is not affected by any proceedings in respect of the same matter that are pending before any court outside Canada or by any decision of such a court.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Proceedings not precluded</MarginalNote><Label>15</Label><Text>Nothing in this Act is to be construed as precluding the commencement or continuation of proceedings under any other Act of Parliament, or any civil proceedings, in respect of the activities of an entity.</Text></Section><Heading level="1"><TitleText>Conflict of Laws</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Conflict of laws</MarginalNote><Label>16</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>In the event of any inconsistency or conflict between the provisions of this Act or a regulation made under it and any other federal or provincial law, this Act or its regulations prevail to the extent of the inconsistency or conflict.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Agreement or arrangement</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Any provision of an agreement or arrangement that is inconsistent with or conflicts with the provisions of this Act or a regulation made under it is void to the extent of the inconsistency or conflict.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Other obligations</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>Nothing in this section is to be construed as affecting any requirement imposed on an entity under any other federal law, any provincial or foreign law or any contract or arrangement that is more stringent than the requirements under this Act.</Text></Subsection></Section><Heading level="1"><TitleText>Miscellaneous</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Withdrawal of government support</MarginalNote><Label>17</Label><Text>If there are reasonable grounds to believe that an entity has failed to meet its obligations under this Act, the Minister must recommend to the Governor in Council that any government support or funding that is provided to the entity be withdrawn for a specified period or until the entity is in compliance with the Act.</Text></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Legislative proposal ГўВҖВ” commissioner</MarginalNote><Label>18</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Within one year after the day on which this Act comes into force, the Minister must cause to be tabled in each House of Parliament a legislative proposal that would provide for the appointment of a commissioner whose mandate would be to ensure that entities that have business activities or business relationships abroad comply with section 9.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Content of proposal</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The proposal must, among other things, address the following:</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>the method of appointment, tenure and remuneration of the commissioner;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>the general duties and powers of the commissioner;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(c)</Label><Text>the verification of the compliance of entities with their obligations under this Act; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(d)</Label><Text>the conduct of the commissionerГўВҖВҷs office, including the appointment of the necessary employees.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection></Section><Heading level="1"><TitleText>Orders and Regulations</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Regulations</MarginalNote><Label>19</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The Governor in Council may make regulations for carrying out the purposes and provisions of this Act, including regulations</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>specifying what an entity must include in its due diligence procedures, including auditing procedures and standards of conduct; </Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>setting out standards and guidelines to be used by an entity in the assessment of the effectiveness of its due diligence procedures;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(c)</Label><Text>providing for the exemption of an entity or a class of entities from the application of any provision of this Act, including on the basis of revenue or number of employees; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(d)</Label><Text>respecting the information that an entity must include in the annual report referred to in section 9.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Tabling and referral of proposed regulations</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The Minister must cause each regulation that is proposed to be made to be tabled before each House of Parliament, and each House must refer the proposed regulation to the appropriate committee of that House.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Alteration of proposed regulation</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>A proposed regulation that has been tabled before each House of Parliament under subsection (2) does not need to be tabled before either House again if
 it has been altered.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Amendment of schedule
</MarginalNote><Label>20</Label><Text>The Governor in Council may, by order, amend the schedule by adding or deleting a reference to an international human rights instrument.</Text></Section></Body><Schedule><ScheduleFormHeading><Label>SCHEDULE</Label><OriginatingRef>(subsection 2(1) and section 20)</OriginatingRef><TitleText>International Human Rights Instruments</TitleText></ScheduleFormHeading><BilingualGroup><BilingualItemEn>Abolition of Forced Labour Convention, 1957</BilingualItemEn><BilingualItemFr>Convention sur l'abolition du travail forcГғВ©, 1957</BilingualItemFr></BilingualGroup><BilingualGroup><BilingualItemEn>Convention against Torture and Other Cruel, Inhuman or Degrading Treatment or Punishment</BilingualItemEn><BilingualItemFr>Convention contre la torture et autres peines ou traitements cruels, inhumains ou dГғВ©gradants</BilingualItemFr></BilingualGroup><BilingualGroup><BilingualItemEn>Convention on Access to Information, Public Participation in Decision-Making and Access to Justice in Environmental Matters</BilingualItemEn><BilingualItemFr>Convention sur lГўВҖВҷaccГғВЁs ГғВ  lГўВҖВҷinformation, la participation du public au processus dГғВ©cisionnel et lГўВҖВҷaccГғВЁs ГғВ  la justice en matiГғВЁre dГўВҖВҷenvironnement</BilingualItemFr></BilingualGroup><BilingualGroup><BilingualItemEn>Convention on Combating Bribery of Foreign Public Officials in International Business Transactions</BilingualItemEn><BilingualItemFr>Convention sur la lutte contre la corruption dГўВҖВҷagents publics ГғВ©trangers dans les transactions commerciales internationales</BilingualItemFr></BilingualGroup><BilingualGroup><BilingualItemEn>Convention on the Elimination of All Forms of Discrimination against Women</BilingualItemEn><BilingualItemFr>Convention sur l'ГғВ©limination de toutes les formes de discrimination ГғВ  lГўВҖВҷГғВ©gard des femmes</BilingualItemFr></BilingualGroup><BilingualGroup><BilingualItemEn>Convention on the Rights of the Child</BilingualItemEn><BilingualItemFr>Convention relative aux droits de lГўВҖВҷenfant</BilingualItemFr></BilingualGroup><BilingualGroup><BilingualItemEn>Convention on the Rights of Persons with Disabilities</BilingualItemEn><BilingualItemFr>Convention relative aux droits des personnes handicapГғВ©es</BilingualItemFr></BilingualGroup><BilingualGroup><BilingualItemEn>Declaration on the Right and Responsibility of Individuals, Groups and Organs of Society to Promote and Protect Universally Recognized Human Rights and Fundamental Freedoms</BilingualItemEn><BilingualItemFr>DГғВ©claration sur le droit et la responsabilitГғВ© des individus, groupes et organes de la sociГғВ©tГғВ© de promouvoir et protГғВ©ger les droits de l'homme et les libertГғВ©s fondamentales universellement reconnus</BilingualItemFr></BilingualGroup><BilingualGroup><BilingualItemEn>Discrimination (Employment and Occupation) Convention, 1958</BilingualItemEn><BilingualItemFr>Convention concernant la discrimination (emploi et profession), 1958</BilingualItemFr></BilingualGroup><BilingualGroup><BilingualItemEn>Equal Remuneration Convention, 1951</BilingualItemEn><BilingualItemFr>Convention sur lГўВҖВҷГғВ©galitГғВ© de rГғВ©munГғВ©ration, 1951</BilingualItemFr></BilingualGroup><BilingualGroup><BilingualItemEn>Forced Labour Convention, 1930 </BilingualItemEn><BilingualItemFr>Convention sur le travail forcГғВ©, 1930</BilingualItemFr></BilingualGroup><BilingualGroup><BilingualItemEn>Freedom of Association and Protection of the Right to Organise Convention, 1948</BilingualItemEn><BilingualItemFr>Convention sur la libertГғВ© syndicale et la protection du droit syndical, 1948</BilingualItemFr></BilingualGroup><BilingualGroup><BilingualItemEn>Indigenous and Tribal Peoples Convention, 1989</BilingualItemEn><BilingualItemFr>Convention relative aux peuples indigГғВЁnes et tribaux, 1989</BilingualItemFr></BilingualGroup><BilingualGroup><BilingualItemEn>International Covenant on Civil and Political Rights </BilingualItemEn><BilingualItemFr>Pacte international relatif aux droits civils et politiques</BilingualItemFr></BilingualGroup><BilingualGroup><BilingualItemEn>International Covenant on Economic, Social and Cultural Rights</BilingualItemEn><BilingualItemFr>Pacte international relatif aux droits ГғВ©conomiques, sociaux et culturels </BilingualItemFr></BilingualGroup><BilingualGroup><BilingualItemEn>International Convention for the Protection of All Persons from Enforced Disappearance</BilingualItemEn><BilingualItemFr>Convention internationale pour la protection de toutes les personnes contre les disparitions forcГғВ©es</BilingualItemFr></BilingualGroup><BilingualGroup><BilingualItemEn>International Convention on the Elimination of All Forms of Racial Discrimination</BilingualItemEn><BilingualItemFr>Convention internationale sur l'ГғВ©limination de toutes les formes de discrimination raciale</BilingualItemFr></BilingualGroup><BilingualGroup><BilingualItemEn>International Convention on the Protection of the Rights of All Migrant Workers and Members of Their Families</BilingualItemEn><BilingualItemFr>Convention internationale sur la protection des droits de tous les travailleurs migrants et des membres de leur famille</BilingualItemFr></BilingualGroup><BilingualGroup><BilingualItemEn>Minimum Age Convention, 1973</BilingualItemEn><BilingualItemFr>Convention sur l'ГғВўge minimum, 1973</BilingualItemFr></BilingualGroup><BilingualGroup><BilingualItemEn>Right to Organise and Collective Bargaining Convention, 1949</BilingualItemEn><BilingualItemFr>Convention sur le droit d'organisation et de nГғВ©gociation collective, 1949</BilingualItemFr></BilingualGroup><BilingualGroup><BilingualItemEn>United Nations Declaration on the Rights of Indigenous Peoples</BilingualItemEn><BilingualItemFr>DГғВ©claration des Nations Unies sur les droits des peuples autochtones</BilingualItemFr></BilingualGroup><BilingualGroup><BilingualItemEn>Worst Forms of Child Labour Convention, 1999</BilingualItemEn><BilingualItemFr>Convention sur les pires formes de travail des enfants, 1999</BilingualItemFr></BilingualGroup></Schedule></Bill>