<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><Bill bill-origin="commons" bill-type="private-public" xml:lang="en" date-time="2021-12-20 10:10:27"><Identification><BillNumber>C-274</BillNumber><Parliament><Session>1</Session><Number>44</Number><RegnalYear><Year-s>70-71</Year-s><Monarch>Elizabeth II</Monarch></RegnalYear><Year-s>2021-2022</Year-s></Parliament><LongTitle>An Act to amend the Criminal Code (detention in custody)</LongTitle><ShortTitle status="unofficial" /><RunningHead>An Act to amend the Criminal Code (detention in custody)</RunningHead><BillHistory><Stages stage="first-reading-house"><Date><YYYY>2022</YYYY><MM>5</MM><DD>19</DD></Date></Stages></BillHistory><BillSponsor><Emphasis style="smallcaps">Mr. Caputo</Emphasis></BillSponsor><BillRefNumber date-time="2021-12-20">441072</BillRefNumber></Identification><Introduction><Summary><TitleText>SUMMARY</TitleText><Provision><Text>This enactment amends a provision of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Criminal Code</XRefExternal> that governs judicial interim release to provide that an accused who is charged more than twice with certain indictable offences while subject to a summons, appearance notice, undertaking or release order must be detained in custody unless the judge or justice is satisfied that exceptional circumstances warrant their release.</Text></Provision></Summary><Enacts><Provision><Text>Her Majesty, by and with the advice and consent <Keep>of the</Keep> Senate and House of Commons of Canada, <Keep>enacts</Keep> as follows:</Text></Provision></Enacts></Introduction><Body><Heading level="1"><MarginalNote><HistoricalNote>R.S., c. C-46</HistoricalNote></MarginalNote><TitleText>Criminal Code</TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><Label>1</Label><Text>Subsection 524(4) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Criminal Code</XRefExternal> is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><Subsection><MarginalNote>Detention</MarginalNote><Label>(4)</Label><Text>If the judge or justice cancels the summons, appearance notice, undertaking or release order, the judge or justice shall order that the accused be detained in custody unless,</Text><Paragraph><Label><Ins>(a)</Ins></Label><Text>having been given a reasonable opportunity to do so, the accused shows cause why their detention in custody is not justified under subsection 515(10); <Ins>or</Ins></Text></Paragraph><Paragraph change="ins"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>in the case of an accused who has been charged more than twice with an indictable offence punishable by five years or more of imprisonment while subject to the summons, appearance notice, undertaking or release order, the judge or justice is satisfied that exceptional circumstances warrant their release.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection></AmendedText></Section></Body></Bill>