<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><Bill bill-origin="commons" bill-type="private-public" xml:lang="en" date-time="2022-04-14 07:44:14"><Identification><BillNumber>C-278</BillNumber><Parliament><Session>1</Session><Number>44</Number><RegnalYear><Year-s>70-71</Year-s><Monarch>Elizabeth II</Monarch></RegnalYear><Year-s>2021-2022</Year-s></Parliament><LongTitle>An Act to prevent the imposition by the federal government of vaccination mandates for employment and travel</LongTitle><ShortTitle status="unofficial" /><RunningHead>Prevention of Government-imposed Vaccination Mandates Act
</RunningHead><BillHistory><Stages stage="first-reading-house"><Date><YYYY>2022</YYYY><MM>6</MM><DD>2</DD></Date></Stages></BillHistory><BillSponsor><Emphasis style="smallcaps">Mr. Poilievre</Emphasis></BillSponsor><BillRefNumber date-time="2022-04-14">441157</BillRefNumber></Identification><Introduction><Summary><TitleText>SUMMARY</TitleText><Provision><Text>This enactment amends the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Financial Administration Act</XRefExternal> to provide that the Treasury Board may not require as a condition of employment in the federal public administration that a person receive a vaccine against COVID-19. It also amends the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Canada Labour Code</XRefExternal> to provide that regulations may not be made that require, as a term or condition of employment in or in connection with the operation of a federal work, undertaking or business, that a person receive a vaccine against COVID-19.</Text></Provision><Provision><Text>In addition, the enactment amends the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Aeronautics Act</XRefExternal>, the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Railway Safety Act</XRefExternal> and the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Canada Shipping Act, 2001</XRefExternal> to provide that no regulation, order or other instrument made under any of those Acts to prevent the introduction or spread of COVID-19 may prohibit or have the effect of prohibiting a person from boarding an aircraft, a train or a vessel solely on the ground that they have not received a vaccine against that disease. </Text></Provision></Summary><Enacts><Provision><Text>Her Majesty, by and with the advice and consent <Keep>of the</Keep> Senate and House of Commons of Canada, <Keep>enacts</Keep> as follows:</Text></Provision></Enacts></Introduction><Body><Heading level="1"><TitleText>Short Title</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Short title</MarginalNote><Label>1</Label><Text>This Act may be cited as the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Prevention of Government-imposed Vaccination Mandates Act</XRefExternal>.</Text></Section><Heading level="1"><MarginalNote><HistoricalNote>R.S., c. F-11</HistoricalNote></MarginalNote><TitleText>Financial Administration Act</TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><Label>2</Label><Text>Subsection 11.1(2) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Financial Administration Act</XRefExternal> is amended by striking out âandâ at the end of paragraph (a) and by adding the following after that paragraph:</Text><AmendedText><SectionPiece><Paragraph change="ins"><Label>(a.1)</Label><Text>do not include the power to require as a term or condition of employment in the federal public administration that a person receive a vaccine against the coronavirus disease 2019 (COVID-19) or to provide for the termination of an employee, or for a suspension of or a reduction in their pay, solely on the ground that they have not received a vaccine against COVID-19; and</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Section><Heading level="1"><MarginalNote><HistoricalNote>R.S., c. L-2</HistoricalNote></MarginalNote><TitleText>Canada Labour Code</TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><Label>3</Label><Text>Section 157 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Canada Labour Code</XRefExternal> is amended by adding the following after subsection (1.1):</Text><AmendedText change="ins"><Subsection><MarginalNote>Limitation â COVID-19</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>No regulation may be made under this Part that requires, as a term or condition of employment in or in connection with the operation of a federal work, undertaking or business, that a person receive a vaccine against the coroÂ­<Keep>navirus</Keep> disease 2019 (COVID-19).</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Section><Heading level="1"><MarginalNote><HistoricalNote>R.S., c. A-2</HistoricalNote></MarginalNote><TitleText>Aeronautics Act</TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><Label>4</Label><Text>The <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Aeronautics Act</XRefExternal> is amended by adding the following after section 4.74: </Text><AmendedText><Section change="ins"><MarginalNote>Limitation â COVID-19</MarginalNote><Label>4.741</Label><Text>No regulation, notice, order, security measure or emergency direction made under this Part to prevent the introduction or spread of the coronavirus disease 2019 (COVID-19) may prohibit or have the effect of prohibiting a person from entering an aircraft on the sole ground that they have not received a vaccine against that disease.</Text></Section></AmendedText></Section><Heading level="1"><MarginalNote><HistoricalNote>R.S., c. 32 (4th Supp.)</HistoricalNote></MarginalNote><TitleText>Railway Safety Act</TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><Label>5</Label><Text>The <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Railway Safety Act</XRefExternal> is amended by adding the following after section 47.2:</Text><AmendedText><Section change="ins"><MarginalNote>Limitation â COVID-19</MarginalNote><Label>47.21</Label><Text>No regulation, order, emergency directive or other instrument made under this Act to prevent the introduction or spread of the coronavirus disease 2019 (COVID-19) may prohibit or have the effect of prohibiting a person from boarding railway equipment on the sole ground that they have not received a vaccine against that disease.</Text></Section></AmendedText></Section><Heading level="1"><MarginalNote><HistoricalNote>2001, c. 26</HistoricalNote></MarginalNote><TitleText>Canada Shipping Act, 2001</TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><Label>6</Label><Text>Section 120 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Canada Shipping Act, 2001</XRefExternal> is amended by adding the following after subsection (1): </Text><AmendedText><Subsection change="ins"><MarginalNote>Limitation â COVID-19</MarginalNote><Label>(1.1)</Label><Text>No regulation made under this section to prevent the introduction or spread of the coronavirus disease 2019 (COVID-19) may prohibit or have the effect of prohibiting a person from boarding a vessel on the sole ground that they have not received a vaccine against that disease.
</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>7</Label><Text>Section 136 of the Act is amended by adding the following after subsection (1):</Text><AmendedText><Subsection change="ins"><MarginalNote>Limitation â COVID-19</MarginalNote><Label>(1.1)</Label><Text>No regulation made under this section to prevent the introduction or spread of the coronavirus disease 2019 (COVID-19) may prohibit or have the effect of prohibiting a person from boarding a vessel on the sole ground that they have not received a vaccine against that disease.
</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Section></Body></Bill>