<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><Bill bill-origin="commons" bill-type="private-public" xml:lang="en" date-time="2022-05-25 08:48:54"><Identification><BillNumber>C-286</BillNumber><Parliament><Session>1</Session><Number>44</Number><RegnalYear><Year-s>70-71</Year-s><Monarch>Elizabeth II</Monarch></RegnalYear><Year-s>2021-2022</Year-s></Parliament><LongTitle>An Act to amend the Immigration and Refugee Protection Act (recognition of foreign credentials)</LongTitle><ShortTitle status="unofficial" /><RunningHead>An Act to amend the Immigration and Refugee Protection Act (recognition of foreign credentials)</RunningHead><BillHistory><Stages stage="first-reading-house"><Date><YYYY>2022</YYYY><MM>6</MM><DD>15</DD></Date></Stages></BillHistory><BillSponsor><Emphasis style="smallcaps">Mr. Redekopp</Emphasis></BillSponsor><BillRefNumber date-time="2022-05-25">441145</BillRefNumber></Identification><Introduction><Summary><TitleText>SUMMARY</TitleText><Provision><Text>This enactment amends the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Immigration and Refugee Protection Act</XRefExternal> to authorize the Governor in Council, after consultation with the provinces, to make regulations in relation to the recognition of foreign credentials.</Text></Provision></Summary><Preamble><Provision><MarginalNote>Preamble</MarginalNote><Text>Whereas the Government of Canada is committed to an immigration system that allows Canada to welcome newcomers from around the world;</Text></Provision><Provision><Text>Whereas the Government of Canada is committed to the successful integration of permanent residents into Canadian society; </Text></Provision><Provision><Text>Whereas the Government of Canada acknowledges that recognizing the foreign credentials of permanent residents is essential to their successful integration;</Text></Provision><Provision><Text>Whereas some newcomers to Canada seeking to work in certain professions or trades face hurdles and uncertainty regarding the assessment of their educational credentials by Canadian organizations and, in the case of professions or trades for which licensing by a federal or provincial authority is required, regarding the likelihood of their being licensed by that authority;</Text></Provision><Provision><Text>And whereas the Government of Canada is committed to securing, in cooperation with the provinces, due recognition of the foreign credentials of permanent residents and to enhancing the transparency of the credential assessment and licensing processes in order to promote certainty for those seeking to practise their profession or trade in Canada;</Text></Provision><Provision language-align="yes"><Text>Now, therefore, Her Majesty, by and with the advice and consent <Keep>of the</Keep> Senate and House of Commons of Canada, <Keep>enacts</Keep> as follows:</Text></Provision></Preamble></Introduction><Body><Heading level="1"><TitleText>Short Title</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Short title</MarginalNote><Label>1</Label><Text>This Act may be cited as the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Recognition of Foreign Credentials Act</XRefExternal>.</Text></Section><Heading level="1"><MarginalNote><HistoricalNote>2001, c. 27</HistoricalNote></MarginalNote><TitleText>Immigration and Refugee Protection Act</TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><Label>2</Label><Text>The <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Immigration and Refugee Protection Act</XRefExternal> is amended by adding the following after sec­<Keep>tion 87.4:</Keep></Text><AmendedText><Section change="ins"><MarginalNote>Regulations</MarginalNote><Label>87.41</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The Governor in Council, on the recommendation of the Minister of Employment and Social Development, after consultation by the Minister with the provinces and the Minister of Labour, may make regulations prescribing the foreign diplomas, certificates or credentials of foreign nationals who apply for permanent resident visas as members of the prescribed class of federal skilled workers or of a class referred to in an instruction given under paragraph 10.3(1)(a) that are equivalent to Canadian educational credentials for the purposes of this Act.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Definition — <DefinedTermEn>Canadian educational credential</DefinedTermEn></MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>In this section, <DefinedTermEn>Canadian educational credential</DefinedTermEn> means any secondary school diploma or any post-<Keep>secondary</Keep> diploma, certificate or credential that is issued on the completion of a Canadian program of study or training at an educational or training institution that is recognized by the provincial authorities responsible for registering, accrediting, supervising and regulating such institutions.</Text></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Section></Body></Bill>