<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><Bill bill-origin="commons" bill-type="private-public" xml:lang="en" date-time="2022-05-17 16:16:24"><Identification><BillNumber>C-289</BillNumber><Parliament><Session>1</Session><Number>44</Number><RegnalYear><Year-s>70-71</Year-s><Monarch>Elizabeth II</Monarch></RegnalYear><Year-s>2021-2022</Year-s></Parliament><LongTitle>An Act to amend the Criminal Code (identity verification)</LongTitle><ShortTitle status="unofficial" /><RunningHead>An Act to amend the Criminal Code (identity verification)</RunningHead><BillHistory><Stages stage="first-reading-house"><Date><YYYY>2022</YYYY><MM>6</MM><DD>16</DD></Date></Stages></BillHistory><BillSponsor><Emphasis style="smallcaps">Mr. Chambers</Emphasis></BillSponsor><BillRefNumber date-time="2022-05-17">441152</BillRefNumber></Identification><Introduction><Summary><TitleText>SUMMARY</TitleText><Provision><Text>This enactment amends the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Criminal Code</XRefExternal> to make it an offence for any person to knowingly make a false or misleading statement or to knowingly provide false or misleading information, including by omission, to a person or entity listed in section 5 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Proceeds of Crime (Money Laundering) and Terrorist Financing Act</XRefExternal> with respect to the verification of the identity of a person or entity under that Act.</Text></Provision></Summary><Enacts><Provision><Text>Her Majesty, by and with the advice and consent <Keep>of the</Keep> Senate and House of Commons of Canada, <Keep>enacts</Keep> as follows:</Text></Provision></Enacts></Introduction><Body><Heading level="1"><MarginalNote><HistoricalNote>R.S., c. C-46</HistoricalNote></MarginalNote><TitleText>Criminal Code</TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><Label>1</Label><Text>The heading before section 462.31 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Criminal Code</XRefExternal> is replaced by the following :</Text><AmendedText><Heading level="2"><TitleText>Offences</TitleText></Heading></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>2</Label><Text>The Act is amended by adding the following after section 462.31:</Text><AmendedText><Section change="ins"><MarginalNote>Identity verification</MarginalNote><Label>462.311</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Everyone commits an offense who knowingly makes a false or misleading statement or knowingly provides false or misleading information, including by omission, whether directly or indirectly, to a person or entity referred to in section 5 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Proceeds of Crime (Money Laundering) and Terrorist Financing Act</XRefExternal> respecting the identity of a person or entity to be verified under section 6.1 of that Act, including with respect to the ownership, control or structure of the entity.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Punishment</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Everyone who commits an offence under subsection (1) is guilty of</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>an indictable offence and liable to a fine of not more than $1,000,000 or to imprisonment for a term of not more than 10 years, or to both; or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>an offence punishable on summary conviction and liable to a fine of not more than $10,000 or to <Keep svc="1">imprisonment</Keep> for a term of not more than two years less a day, or to both.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Section></Body></Bill>