<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><Bill bill-origin="commons" bill-type="private-public" xml:lang="en" date-time="2021-11-08 10:22:26"><Identification><BillNumber>C-281</BillNumber><Parliament><Session>1</Session><Number>44</Number><RegnalYear><Year-s>70-71</Year-s><Monarch>Elizabeth II √¢¬Ä¬ì 1 Charles III</Monarch></RegnalYear><Year-s>2021-2022-2023</Year-s></Parliament><LongTitle>An Act to amend the Department of Foreign Affairs, Trade and Development Act, the Justice for Victims of Corrupt Foreign Officials Act (Sergei Magnitsky Law), the Broadcasting Act and the Prohibiting Cluster Munitions Act</LongTitle><ShortTitle status="unofficial">International Human Rights Act</ShortTitle><RunningHead>An Act to amend the Department of Foreign Affairs, Trade and Development Act, the Justice for Victims ... </RunningHead><BillHistory><Stages stage="report-house"><Date><YYYY>2023</YYYY><MM>5</MM><DD>4</DD></Date><StageText>Reprinted as amended by the Standing Committee on Foreign Affairs and International Development as a working copy for the use of the House of Commons at Report Stage and as reported to the House on May√Ç¬Ý4, 2023</StageText></Stages></BillHistory><BillSponsor><Emphasis style="smallcaps">Mr. Lawrence</Emphasis></BillSponsor><BillRefNumber date-time="2021-11-08">441170</BillRefNumber></Identification><Introduction><Summary><TitleText>SUMMARY</TitleText><Provision list-item="no" language-align="yes"><Text>This enactment amends the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Department of Foreign Affairs, Trade and Development Act</XRefExternal> to impose certain requirements on the Minister of Foreign Affairs in relation to international human rights. It also amends the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Justice for Victims of Corrupt Foreign Officials Act (Sergei Magnitsky Law)</XRefExternal> to require the Minister of Foreign Affairs to respond to a report submitted by a parliamentary committee that recommends that sanctions be imposed under that Act against a foreign national.</Text></Provision><Provision list-item="no" language-align="yes"><Text>In addition, this enactment amends the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Broadcasting Act</XRefExternal> to prohibit the issue or renewal of a licence in 
relation to a broadcasting undertaking that is vulnerable to being significantly influenced by a foreign national or entity that has committed acts or omissions that the
Senate or the House of Commons has recognized as genocide or that is subject to sanctions under the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Justice for Victims of Corrupt Foreign Officials Act (Sergei Magnitsky Law)</XRefExternal> or under the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Special Economic Measures Act</XRefExternal>.
</Text></Provision><Provision language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>Finally, it amends the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Prohibiting Cluster Munitions Act</XRefExternal> to prohibit a person from investing in an entity that has contravened certain provisions of the Act.</Text></Provision></Summary><Enacts><Provision><Text>His Majesty, by and with the advice and consent <Keep>of the</Keep> Senate and House of Commons of Canada, <Keep>enacts</Keep> as follows:</Text></Provision></Enacts></Introduction><Body><Heading level="1"><TitleText>Short Title</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Short title</MarginalNote><Label>1</Label><Text>This Act may be cited as the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">International Human Rights Act</XRefExternal>.</Text></Section><Heading level="1"><MarginalNote><HistoricalNote>2013, c. 33, s. 174</HistoricalNote></MarginalNote><TitleText>Department of Foreign Affairs, Trade
and Development Act</TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><Label>2</Label><Text>Section 10 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Department of Foreign Affairs, Trade and Development Act</XRefExternal> is amended by adding the following after subsection (3):</Text><AmendedText><Subsection><MarginalNote>Human rights</MarginalNote><Label>(4)</Label><Text>In exercising his or her powers, duties and functions under this Act in respect of the conduct of the external affairs of Canada, the Minister is to publish, at least once in every calendar year, <Ins>a report that includes</Ins></Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text><Ins>an outline of</Ins> the measures that the <Ins>Government of Canada</Ins> has taken to advance human rights internationally as part of Canada√¢¬Ä¬ôs foreign policy;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>a list that sets out the <Ins>following information relating to</Ins> prisoners of conscience for whose release the Government of Canada is actively working:</Text><Subparagraph change="ins"><Label>(i)</Label><Text>the number of prisoners of conscience detained by each government or detaining authority,</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph change="ins"><Label>(ii)</Label><Text>the names of the prisoners of conscience,</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph change="ins"><Label>(iii)</Label><Text>the circumstances of the detentions,</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph change="ins"><Label>(iv)</Label><Text>the efforts that the Government of Canada has made to visit those prisoners and to attend their trials or hearings, including the number of requests made for such visits and the responses of the detaining governments or authorities, and</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph change="ins"><Label>(v)</Label><Text>other actions taken by the Government of Canada to support prisoners of conscience including those detained or experiencing treatment in contravention to human rights standards; and</Text></Subparagraph></Paragraph><Paragraph change="ins"><Label>(c)</Label><Text>a description of the Government of Canada√¢¬Ä¬ôs communications with the families of prisoners of conscience and its consultations with civil society on matters of human rights.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection change="ins"><MarginalNote>Information not to be included</MarginalNote><Label>(5)</Label><Text>In preparing the list referred to in paragraph (4)(b), the Minister must make all reasonable efforts to consult with family members or representatives of the prisoners of conscience and may decide not to include certain information in the list if a person consulted by the Minister requests that the information not be included, or the Minister is satisfied that not including it would be in the best interests of the advancement of human rights or the personal safety of the prisoner.</Text></Subsection><Subsection change="ins"><MarginalNote>Strategy</MarginalNote><Label>(6)</Label><Text>The Minister must develop and maintain a government-wide international human rights strategy.</Text></Subsection><Subsection change="ins"><MarginalNote>Definition of <DefinitionRef>prisoner of conscience</DefinitionRef></MarginalNote><Label>(7)</Label><Text>In this section, <DefinedTermEn>prisoner of conscience</DefinedTermEn> means an individual who, in contravention of international human rights standards, has been detained or otherwise physically restricted solely because of their identity or their conscientiously held beliefs, including religious or political beliefs.</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Section><Heading level="1"><MarginalNote><HistoricalNote>2017, c. 21</HistoricalNote></MarginalNote><TitleText>Justice for Victims of Corrupt Foreign Officials Act (Sergei Magnitsky Law)</TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><Label>3</Label><Text>The <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Justice for Victims of Corrupt Foreign Officials Act (Sergei Magnitsky Law)</XRefExternal> is amended by adding the following after section 5:</Text><AmendedText><Section><MarginalNote>Response to recommendation of committee</MarginalNote><Label>5.1</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>If a motion adopted by a committee of the Senate, of the House of Commons or of both Houses of Parliament recommends that an order or regulation be considered or made under section 4 in relation to a foreign national, the Minister must prepare a response advising the committee whether or not the order or regulation <Ins>has been</Ins> made and setting out the reasons for the decision. </Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Tabling of response</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The response must be tabled in the Senate or the House of Commons or in both Houses of Parliament, as the case may be, within <Ins>the timeline</Ins> specified <Ins>in the Standing Orders or rules of the Senate for responses to</Ins> committee <Ins>reports</Ins> and must be posted in a prominent location on the website of the Department of Foreign Affairs, Trade and Development on the day after it is tabled.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Prorogation or dissolution</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>If Parliament is prorogued before the response is tabled, the Minister must post the response in a prominent location on the website of the Department of Foreign Affairs, Trade and Development within the time limit referred to in subsection (2) regarding the tabling of the response. <Ins>If Parliament is prorogued or dissolved before the response is tabled</Ins>, the response must be tabled as soon as feasible after the commencement of the next session of Parliament.</Text></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Section><Heading level="1"><MarginalNote><HistoricalNote>1991, c. 11</HistoricalNote></MarginalNote><TitleText>Broadcasting Act</TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><Label>4</Label><Text>The <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Broadcasting Act</XRefExternal> is amended by adding the following after subsection 22(1):</Text><AmendedText><Subsection><MarginalNote>Restriction √¢¬Ä¬î broadcasting undertakings subject to influence</MarginalNote><Label>(1.1)</Label><Text>No licence shall be issued or renewed under this Part in relation to a broadcasting undertaking, including one that distributes foreign programming that is √¢¬Ä¬î <Ins>despite any measure that the Commission could take under this Part</Ins> √¢¬Ä¬î vulnerable to being <Ins>significantly</Ins> influenced by a foreign national or entity</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>that has committed acts or omissions that the Senate or the House of Commons has recognized as genocide; or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>that is the subject of an order or regulation made under section 4 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Justice for Victims of Corrupt Foreign Officials Act (Sergei Magnitsky Law)</XRefExternal> or section 4 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Special Economic Measures Act</XRefExternal>.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection></AmendedText></Section><Heading level="1"><MarginalNote><HistoricalNote>2014, c. 27</HistoricalNote></MarginalNote><TitleText>Prohibiting Cluster Munitions Act</TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><Label>5</Label><Text>Section 4 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Prohibiting Cluster Munitions Act</XRefExternal> is replaced by the following: </Text><AmendedText><Section><MarginalNote>Purpose</MarginalNote><Label>4</Label><Text>The purpose of this Act is to implement Canada√¢¬Ä¬ôs commitments under the Convention, <Ins>particularly its obligations under Article 5 (Victim assistance) and Article 6 (International cooperation and assistance) of the Convention, prohibit the provision of financial assistance</Ins> and to restrict investments in relation to cluster munitions, explosive submunitions and explosive bomblets.</Text></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>6</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Paragraph 6(e) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(d.1)</Label><Text>directly or indirectly, individually or as a shareholder or partner or otherwise, acquire or have any pecuniary interest in √¢¬Ä¬î or make or guarantee a loan to √¢¬Ä¬î a person, knowing that the person has committed, or has aided or abetted in the commission of, any act referred to in paragraphs (a) to (d);</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(e)</Label><Text>attempt to commit any act referred to in paragraphs (a) to (d.1);</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Paragraphs 6(f) to (h) of the English version of the Act are replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(f)</Label><Text>aid, abet or counsel another person to commit any act referred to in paragraphs (a) to (d.1);</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(g)</Label><Text>conspire with another person to commit any act referred to in paragraphs (a) to (d.1); or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(h)</Label><Text>receive, comfort or assist another person, knowing that the person has committed, or has aided or abetted in the commission of, any act referred to in paragraphs (a) to (d.1), for the purpose of enabling the person to escape.</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>7</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Paragraph 11(3)(a) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>aiding, abetting or counselling another person to commit any act referred to in paragraphs 6(a) to (d.1), if it would not be an offence for that other person to commit that act;</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Paragraphs 11(3)(b) and (c) of the English version of the Act are replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>conspiring with another person to commit any act referred to in paragraphs 6(a) to (d.1), if it would not be an offence for that other person to commit that act; or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(c)</Label><Text>receiving, comforting or assisting another person, knowing that that other person has committed, or has aided or abetted in the commission of, any act referred to in paragraphs 6(a) to (d.1), for the purpose of enabling that other person to escape, if it was not an offence for that other person to commit that act.</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection></Section><Heading level="1"><TitleText>Transitional Provision</TitleText></Heading><Section type="transitional"><MarginalNote>Non-application</MarginalNote><Label>8</Label><Text>Paragraph 6(d.1) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Prohibiting Cluster Munitions Act</XRefExternal>, as enacted by subsection 6(1) of this Act, does not apply, for a period of one year beginning the day on which section 5 of this Act comes into force, to a person in respect of a pecuniary interest that they had, or a loan or loan guarantee that they made, before that day.</Text></Section></Body></Bill>