<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><Bill bill-origin="commons" bill-type="private-public" xml:lang="en" date-time="2022-03-25 10:48:10"><Identification><BillNumber>C-299</BillNumber><Parliament><Session>1</Session><Number>44</Number><RegnalYear><Year-s>70-71</Year-s><Monarch>Elizabeth II – 1 Charles III</Monarch></RegnalYear><Year-s>2021-2022</Year-s></Parliament><LongTitle>An Act to amend the Criminal Code (life imprisonment)</LongTitle><ShortTitle status="unofficial" /><RunningHead>An Act to amend the Criminal Code (life imprisonment)</RunningHead><BillHistory><Stages stage="first-reading-house"><Date><YYYY>2022</YYYY><MM>10</MM><DD>4</DD></Date></Stages></BillHistory><BillSponsor><Emphasis style="smallcaps">Mr. Caputo</Emphasis></BillSponsor><BillRefNumber date-time="2022-03-25">441134</BillRefNumber></Identification><Introduction><Summary><TitleText>SUMMARY</TitleText><Provision><Text>This enactment amends the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Criminal Code</XRefExternal> to increase the maximum penalty to life imprisonment for certain indictable offences.</Text></Provision></Summary><Enacts><Provision><Text>His Majesty, by and with the advice and consent <Keep>of the</Keep> Senate and House of Commons of Canada, <Keep>enacts</Keep> as follows:</Text></Provision></Enacts></Introduction><Body><Heading level="1"><MarginalNote><HistoricalNote>R.S., c. C-46</HistoricalNote></MarginalNote><TitleText>Criminal Code</TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><Label>1</Label><Text>Paragraph 151(a) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Criminal Code</XRefExternal> is replaced by the following: </Text><AmendedText><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>is guilty of an indictable offence and is liable to imprisonment for <Ins>life</Ins> and to a minimum punishment of imprisonment for a term of one year; or</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>2</Label><Text>Paragraph 152(a) of the Act is replaced by the following: </Text><AmendedText><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>is guilty of an indictable offence and is liable to imprisonment for <Ins>life</Ins> and to a minimum punishment of imprisonment for a term of one year; or</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>3</Label><Text>Paragraph 153(1.1)(a) of the Act is replaced by the following: </Text><AmendedText><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>is guilty of an indictable offence and is liable to imprisonment for <Ins>life</Ins> and to a minimum punishment of imprisonment for a term of one year; or</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>4</Label><Text>Paragraph 153.1(1)(a) of the Act is replaced by the following: </Text><AmendedText><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>an indictable offence and liable to imprisonment for <Ins>life</Ins>; or </Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>5</Label><Text>Subsection 155(2) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><Subsection><MarginalNote>Punishment</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Everyone who commits incest is guilty of an indictable offence and is liable to imprisonment for <Ins>life</Ins> and, if the other person is under the age of 16 years, to a minimum punishment of imprisonment for a term of five years.</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>6</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Subsections 163.1(2) and (3) of the Act are replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><Subsection><MarginalNote>Making child pornography</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Every person who makes, prints, publishes or possesses for the purpose of publication any child pornography is guilty of an indictable offence and liable to imprisonment for <Ins>life</Ins> and to a minimum punishment of imprisonment for a term of one year.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Distribution, etc. of child pornography</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>Every person who transmits, makes available, distributes, sells, advertises, imports, exports or possesses for the purpose of transmission, making available, distribution, sale, advertising or exportation any child pornography is guilty of an indictable offence and liable to imprisonment for <Ins>life</Ins> and to a minimum punishment of imprisonment for a term of one year.</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Paragraph 163.1(4)(a) of the Act is replaced by the following: </Text><AmendedText><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>an indictable offence and is liable to imprisonment for <Ins>life</Ins> and to a minimum punishment of imprisonment for a term of one year; or</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(3)</Label><Text>Paragraph 163.1(4.1)(a) of the Act is replaced by the following: </Text><AmendedText><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>an indictable offence and is liable to imprisonment for <Ins>life</Ins> and to a minimum punishment of imprisonment for a term of one year; or</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>7</Label><Text>Sections 170 and 171 of the Act are replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><Section><MarginalNote>Parent or guardian procuring sexual activity</MarginalNote><Label>170</Label><Text>Every parent or guardian of a person under the age of 18 years who procures the person for the purpose of engaging in any sexual activity prohibited by this Act with a person other than the parent or guardian is guilty of an indictable offence and liable to imprisonment for <Ins>life</Ins> and to a minimum punishment of imprisonment for a term of one year.</Text></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Householder permitting prohibited sexual activity</MarginalNote><Label>171</Label><Text>Every owner, occupier or manager of premises, or any other person who has control of premises or assists in the management or control of premises, who knowingly permits a person under the age of 18 years to resort to or to be in or on the premises for the purpose of engaging in any sexual activity prohibited by this Act is guilty of an indictable offence and liable to imprisonment for <Ins>life</Ins> and to a minimum punishment of imprisonment for a term of one year.</Text></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>8</Label><Text>Paragraph 171.1(2)(a) of the Act is replaced by the following: </Text><AmendedText><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>is guilty of an indictable offence and is liable to imprisonment for <Ins>life</Ins> and to a minimum punishment of imprisonment for a term of six months; or</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>9</Label><Text>Paragraph 172.1(2)(a) of the Act is replaced by the following: </Text><AmendedText><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>is guilty of an indictable offence and is liable to imprisonment for <Ins>life</Ins> and to a minimum punishment of imprisonment for a term of one year; or</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>10</Label><Text>Paragraph 172.2(2)(a) of the Act is replaced by the following: </Text><AmendedText><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>is guilty of an indictable offence and is liable to imprisonment for <Ins>life</Ins> and to a minimum punishment of imprisonment for a term of one year; or</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>11</Label><Text>Paragraph 271(a) of the Act is replaced by the following: </Text><AmendedText><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>an indictable offence and is liable to imprisonment for <Ins>life and</Ins>, if the complainant is under the age of 16 years, to a minimum punishment of imprisonment for a term of one year; or</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>12</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The portion of paragraph 272(2)(a) of the Act before subparagraph (i) is replaced by the following: </Text><AmendedText><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>if a restricted firearm or prohibited firearm is used in the commission of the offence or if any firearm is used in the commission of the offence and the offence is committed for the benefit of, at the direction of, or in association with, a criminal organization, to imprisonment for <Ins>life</Ins> and to a minimum punishment of imprisonment for a term of</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Paragraph 272(2)(a.1) of the Act is replaced by the following: </Text><AmendedText><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(a.1)</Label><Text>in any other case where a firearm is used in the commission of the offence, to imprisonment for <Ins>life</Ins> and to a minimum punishment of imprisonment for a term of four years; and</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(3)</Label><Text>Paragraph 272(2)(b) of the Act is replaced by the following: </Text><AmendedText><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>in any other case, to imprisonment for <Ins>life</Ins>.</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>13</Label><Text>Subsection 279.01(1) of the Act is replaced by the following: </Text><AmendedText><Subsection><MarginalNote>Trafficking in persons</MarginalNote><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Every person who recruits, transports, transfers, receives, holds, conceals or harbours a person, or exercises control, direction or influence over the movements of a person, for the purpose of exploiting them or facilitating their exploitation is guilty of an indictable offence and liable <Ins>to imprisonment for life and to a minimum punishment of imprisonment for a term of</Ins></Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>five years if they kidnap, commit an aggravated assault or aggravated sexual assault against, or cause death to, the victim during the commission of the offence; or </Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>four years in any other case.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>14</Label><Text>Subsection 279.011(1) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><Subsection><MarginalNote>Trafficking of a person under the age of eighteen years</MarginalNote><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Every person who recruits, transports, transfers, receives, holds, conceals or harbours a person under the age of eighteen years, or exercises control, direction or influence over the movements of a person under the age of eighteen years, for the purpose of exploiting them or facilitating their exploitation is guilty of an indictable offence and liable <Ins>to imprisonment for life and to a minimum punishment of imprisonment for a term of</Ins></Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>six years if they kidnap, commit an aggravated assault or aggravated sexual assault against, or cause death to, the victim during the commission of the offence; or </Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>five years, in any other case.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>15</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Paragraph 279.02(1)(a) of the Act is replaced by the following: </Text><AmendedText><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>an indictable offence and liable to imprisonment for <Ins>life</Ins>; or</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Subsection 279.02(2) of the Act is replaced by the following: </Text><AmendedText><Subsection><MarginalNote>Material benefit — trafficking of person under 18 years</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Everyone who receives a financial or other material benefit, knowing that it is obtained by or derived directly or indirectly from the commission of an offence under subsection 279.011(1), is guilty of an indictable offence and liable to imprisonment for <Ins>life</Ins> and to a minimum punishment of imprisonment for a term of two years.</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Subsection></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>16</Label><Text>The portion of subsection 286.1(2) of the Act before paragraph (a) is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><Subsection><MarginalNote>Obtaining sexual services for consideration from person under 18 years</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Everyone who, in any place, obtains for consideration, or communicates with anyone for the purpose of obtaining for consideration, the sexual services of a person under the age of 18 years is guilty of an indictable offence and liable to imprisonment for <Ins>life</Ins> and to a minimum punishment of imprisonment for a term of </Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>17</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Paragraph 286.2(1)(a) of the Act is replaced by the following: </Text><AmendedText><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>an indictable offence and liable to imprisonment for <Ins>life</Ins>; or</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Subsection 286.2(2) of the Act is replaced by the following: </Text><AmendedText><Subsection><MarginalNote>Material benefit from sexual services provided by person under 18 years</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Everyone who receives a financial or other material benefit, knowing that it is obtained by or derived directly or indirectly from the commission of an offence under subsection 286.1(2), is guilty of an indictable offence and liable to imprisonment for <Ins>life</Ins> and to a minimum punishment of imprisonment for a term of two years.</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Subsection></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>18</Label><Text>Section 286.3 of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><Subsection><MarginalNote>Procuring</MarginalNote><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Everyone who procures a person to offer or provide sexual services for consideration or, for the purpose of facilitating an offence under subsection 286.1(1), recruits, holds, conceals or harbours a person who offers or provides sexual services for consideration, or exercises control, direction or influence over the movements of that person, is guilty of an indictable offence and liable to imprisonment for <Ins>life</Ins>.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Procuring — person under 18 years</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Everyone who procures a person under the age of 18 years to offer or provide sexual services for consideration or, for the purpose of facilitating an offence under subsection 286.1(2), recruits, holds, conceals or harbours a person under the age of 18 who offers or provides sexual services for consideration, or exercises control, direction or influence over the movements of that person, is guilty of an indictable offence and liable to imprisonment for <Ins>life</Ins> and to a minimum punishment of imprisonment for a term of five years.</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Section></Body></Bill>