<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><Bill bill-origin="commons" bill-type="private-public" xml:lang="en" date-time="2021-06-01 13:23:30"><Identification><BillNumber>C-297</BillNumber><Parliament><Session>1</Session><Number>44</Number><RegnalYear><Year-s>70-71</Year-s><Monarch>Elizabeth II</Monarch></RegnalYear><Year-s>2021-2022</Year-s></Parliament><LongTitle>An Act to amend the Canada Elections Act (Indigenous languages)</LongTitle><ShortTitle status="unofficial" /><RunningHead>An Act to amend the Canada Elections Act (Indigenous languages)</RunningHead><BillHistory><Stages stage="first-reading-house"><Date><YYYY>2022</YYYY><MM>6</MM><DD>22</DD></Date></Stages></BillHistory><BillSponsor><Emphasis style="smallcaps">Ms. Idlout</Emphasis></BillSponsor><BillRefNumber date-time="2021-06-01">441151</BillRefNumber></Identification><Introduction><Summary><TitleText>SUMMARY</TitleText><Provision><Text>This enactment amends the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Canada Elections Act</XRefExternal> to provide that, in certain circumstances, electors are to be supplied with ballots in an Indigenous language.</Text></Provision></Summary><Enacts><Provision><Text>Her Majesty, by and with the advice and consent <Keep>of the</Keep> Senate and House of Commons of Canada, <Keep>enacts</Keep> as follows:</Text></Provision></Enacts></Introduction><Body><Heading level="1"><MarginalNote><HistoricalNote>2000, c. 9</HistoricalNote></MarginalNote><TitleText>Canada Elections Act</TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><Label>1</Label><Text>The <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Canada Elections Act</XRefExternal> is amended by adding the following after section 116:</Text><AmendedText><Section change="ins"><MarginalNote>Obligation re Indigenous languages</MarginalNote><Label>116.1</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>In an electoral district that is on Indigenous land, the Chief Electoral Officer may require that all the ballots for that electoral district be prepared and printed in both official languages as well as in the Indigenous language or languages of the electors, using the appropriate writing systems for each language, including syllabics if applicable.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Definition of <DefinitionRef>Indigenous land</DefinitionRef></MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>For the purpose of subsection (1), <DefinedTermEn>Indigenous land</DefinedTermEn> means</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>a reserve and any other land that is set apart for the use and benefit of a band under the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Indian Act</XRefExternal>; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>land that is subject to a comprehensive or specific claim agreement, or a self-government
agreement, between the Government of Canada and an Indigenous people of Canada.
</Text></Paragraph></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>2</Label><Text>The Act is amended by adding the following after section 186:</Text><AmendedText><Section change="ins"><MarginalNote>Special ballots — Indigenous languages</MarginalNote><Label>186.01</Label><Text>On request by an elector who makes an application for registration and special ballot that the special ballot be printed in an Indigenous language, the Chief Electoral Officer shall instruct that the special ballot that is supplied to them be printed in that Indigenous language, using the appropriate writing systems for that language, including syllabics if applicable. </Text></Section></AmendedText></Section></Body></Bill>