<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><Bill bill-origin="commons" bill-type="private-public" xml:lang="en" date-time="2018-12-11 14:44:14"><Identification><BillNumber>C-290</BillNumber><Parliament><Session>1</Session><Number>44</Number><RegnalYear><Year-s>70-71</Year-s><Monarch>Elizabeth II</Monarch></RegnalYear><Year-s>2021-2022</Year-s></Parliament><LongTitle>An Act to amend the Public Servants Disclosure Protection Act</LongTitle><ShortTitle status="unofficial" /><RunningHead>An Act to amend the Public Servants Disclosure Protection Act</RunningHead><BillHistory><Stages stage="first-reading-house"><Date><YYYY>2022</YYYY><MM>6</MM><DD>16</DD></Date></Stages></BillHistory><BillSponsor><Emphasis style="smallcaps">Mr. Garon</Emphasis></BillSponsor><BillRefNumber date-time="2018-12-11">441175</BillRefNumber></Identification><Introduction><Summary><TitleText>SUMMARY</TitleText><Provision><Text>This enactment amends the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Public Servants Disclosure Protection Act</XRefExternal> to, among other things, expand the application of the Act to additional categories of public servants, permit that a protected disclosure be made to an officer within the portion of the public sector in which the public servant is employed, extend the period during which a reprisal complaint may be filed and add a duty to provide support to public servants.</Text></Provision></Summary><Enacts><Provision><Text>Her Majesty, by and with the advice and consent <Keep>of the</Keep> Senate and House of Commons of Canada, <Keep>enacts</Keep> as follows:</Text></Provision></Enacts></Introduction><Body><Heading level="1"><TitleText>Short Title</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Short title</MarginalNote><Label>1</Label><Text>This Act may be cited as the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Public Sector Integrity Act</XRefExternal>.</Text></Section><Heading level="1"><MarginalNote><HistoricalNote>2005, c. 46</HistoricalNote></MarginalNote><TitleText>Public Servants Disclosure Protection Act</TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><Label>2</Label><Text>The third paragraph of the preamble of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Public Servants Disclosure Protection Act</XRefExternal> is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><SectionPiece><Provision><Text>confidence in public institutions can be enhanced by establishing effective procedures for the disclosure of wrongdoings and for <Ins>the protection of</Ins> public servants who <Ins>are involved in the disclosure of</Ins> wrongdoings, and by establishing a code of conduct for the public sector;</Text></Provision></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>3</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The definition <DefinedTermEn>investigation</DefinedTermEn> in subsection 2(1) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><SectionPiece><Definition><Text><DefinedTermEn>investigation</DefinedTermEn> means, for the purposes of sections 24, 25, 26 to 31, 33, 36 and 37, an investigation into a disclosure and an investigation commenced under section 33. (<DefinedTermFr>enquête</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Definition></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The portion of the definition <DefinedTermEn>protected disclosure</DefinedTermEn> in subsection 2(1) of the Act before paragraph (a) is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><SectionPiece><Definition><Text><DefinedTermEn>protected disclosure</DefinedTermEn> means a disclosure that is made by a public servant</Text></Definition></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(3)</Label><Text>The definition <DefinitionRef>public servant</DefinitionRef> in subsection
2(1) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><SectionPiece><Definition><Text><DefinedTermEn>public servant</DefinedTermEn> means every person employed in the public sector, <Ins>every person retained under contract to perform services for the public sector</Ins>, every member of the Royal Canadian Mounted Police and every chief executive. (<DefinedTermFr>fonctionnaire</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Definition></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection><Label>(4)</Label><Text>The portion of the definition <DefinedTermEn>reprisal</DefinedTermEn> in subsection 2(1) of the Act before paragraph (a) is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><SectionPiece><Definition><Text><DefinedTermEn>reprisal</DefinedTermEn> means any of the following measures taken against a public servant because the public servant has made a protected disclosure, <Ins>has witnessed another public servant making a protected disclosure, has collab­orated with another public servant in the making of a protected disclosure, has been mistaken for a public servant who made a protected disclosure</Ins> or has cooperated in an investigation into a disclosure or an investigation commenced under section 33: </Text></Definition></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection><Label>(5)</Label><Text>The definition <DefinedTermEn>reprisal</DefinedTermEn> in subsection 2(1) of the Act is amended by replacing paragraph (c) with the following:</Text><AmendedText><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(c)</Label><Text>the termination of employment <Ins>or contract</Ins> of the public servant, including, in the case of a member of the Royal Canadian Mounted Police, a discharge or dismissal;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph change="ins"><Label>(c.1)</Label><Text>an act or omission that constitutes a failure to provide support to the public servant as required <Keep>under</Keep> paragraph 11(1)(a);</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>4</Label><Text>Paragraphs 8(c) to (f) of the Act are replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><SectionPiece><Paragraph change="ins"><Label>(b.1)</Label><Text>a case of abuse of authority;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(c)</Label><Text>a mismanagement in the public sector;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph change="ins"><Label>(c.1)</Label><Text>political interference in the public sector;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(d)</Label><Text>an act or omission that creates a danger to the life, health or safety of persons, or to the environment, other than a danger that is inherent in the <Keep>perform­</Keep><Keep>ance</Keep> of the duties or functions of a public servant;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(e)</Label><Text>a breach of a code of conduct established under section 5 or 6; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(f)</Label><Text>directing or counselling a person to commit a wrongdoing set out in any of paragraphs (a) to (e).</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>5</Label><Text>Paragraph 11(1)(a) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><SectionPiece><Paragraph change="ins"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>provide support to a public servant who has made a protected disclosure, has witnessed another public servant making a protected disclosure, has collaborated with another public servant in the making of a protected disclosure or has been mis­<Keep>taken</Keep> for a public servant who made a protected disclosure;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label><Ins>(a.1)</Ins></Label><Text>subject to paragraph (c) and any other Act of Parliament and to the principles of procedural fairness and natural justice, protect the identity of persons involved in the disclosure process, including that of persons making disclosures, witnesses and persons alleged to be responsible for wrongdoings;</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>6</Label><Text>Sections 12 to 14 of the Act are replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><Section><MarginalNote>Disclosure to supervisor or officer</MarginalNote><Label>12</Label><Text>A public servant may disclose any information that <Ins>he or she</Ins> believes could show that a wrongdoing has been committed or is about to be committed, or that could show that <Ins>he or she</Ins> has been asked to commit a wrongdoing to <Ins>any</Ins> supervisor <Ins>or officer in the portion of the public sector in which he or she is employed</Ins> or to the senior officer designated for the purpose by the chief <Keep>exec­</Keep>utive of the portion of the public sector in which <Ins>he or she</Ins> is employed.</Text></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Disclosure to the Commissioner</MarginalNote><Label>13</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>A public servant <Ins>or former public servant</Ins> may disclose information referred to in section 12 to the Commissioner.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Exception</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Nothing in this Act authorizes a public servant <Ins>or former public servant</Ins> to disclose to the Commissioner a confidence of the Queen’s Privy Council for Canada in respect of which subsection 39(1) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Canada Evidence Act</XRefExternal> applies or any information that is subject to solicitor-client privilege. The Commissioner may not use the confidence or information if it is disclosed.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Disclosure concerning the Office of the Public Sector Integrity Commissioner</MarginalNote><Label>14</Label><Text>A disclosure that a public servant <Ins>or former public servant</Ins> is entitled to make under section 13 that concerns the Office of the Public Sector Integrity Commissioner may be made to the Auditor General of Canada who has, in relation to that disclosure, the powers, duties and protections of the Commissioner under this Act.</Text></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>7</Label><Text>The portion of section 15.1 of the Act before paragraph (a) is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><Section><MarginalNote>Requirements when making a disclosure</MarginalNote><Label>15.1</Label><Text>In making a disclosure under this Act, a public servant <Ins>or former public servant</Ins> must</Text></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>8</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The portion of subsection 16(1) of the Act before paragraph (a) is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><Section><MarginalNote>Disclosure to public</MarginalNote><Label>16</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>A disclosure that a public servant <Ins>or former public servant</Ins> may make under sections 12 to 14 may be made to the public if there is not sufficient time to make the disclosure under those sections and the public servant <Ins>or former public servant</Ins> believes on reasonable grounds that the subject-matter of the disclosure is an act or omission that</Text></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Paragraph 16(1)(b) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>constitutes an imminent risk of a danger to the life, health <Ins>or</Ins> safety of persons, or to the environment.</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection><Label>(3)</Label><Text>Subsection 16(2) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><Subsection><MarginalNote>Rights not affected </MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Nothing in subsection (1) affects the rights of a public servant <Ins>or former public servant</Ins> to make to the public in accordance with the law a disclosure that is not protected under this Act.</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Subsection></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>9</Label><Text>Section 18.1 of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><Section><MarginalNote>Other obligations to report</MarginalNote><Label>18.1</Label><Text>Nothing in this Act relating to the making of disclosures is to be construed as affecting any obligation of a public servant <Ins>or former public servant</Ins> to disclose, report or otherwise give notice of any matter under any other Act of Parliament.</Text></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>10</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Subsections 19.1(1) and (2) of the Act are replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><Section><MarginalNote>Complaints</MarginalNote><Label>19.1</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>A public servant or former public servant who <Ins>believes</Ins> that a reprisal has been taken against <Ins>them</Ins> may file with the Commissioner a complaint in a form acceptable to the Commissioner. The complaint may also be filed by a person designated by the public servant or former public servant for the purpose.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Time for making complaint</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The complaint must be filed <Ins>within one year</Ins> after the day on which the complainant knew, or in the Commissioner’s opinion ought to have known, that the reprisal was taken.</Text></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Subsection 19.1(4) of the Act is repealed.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><Label>(3)</Label><Text>Paragraph 19.1(5)(b) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>the complaint is filed within <Ins>one year</Ins> after those procedures have been exhausted.</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>11</Label><Text>The Act is amended by adding the following after section 19.1:</Text><AmendedText><Section change="ins"><MarginalNote>Complaint concerning the Office of the Public Sector Integrity Commissioner</MarginalNote><Label>19.11</Label><Text>A complaint under section 19.1 that concerns the Office of the Public Sector Integrity Commissioner may be filed with the Auditor General of Canada who has, in relation to that complaint, the powers, duties and protections of the Commissioner under this Act.</Text></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>12</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Paragraphs 19.3(1)(a) to (d) of the Act are replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>if the complainant is a member or former member of the Royal Canadian Mounted Police, the subject-matter of the complaint has been adequately dealt with by the procedures referred to in subsection 19.1(5); or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>the complaint is beyond the jurisdiction of the Commissioner. </Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Subsections 19.3(2) and (3) of the Act are repealed.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>13</Label><Text>Subsections 19.4(4) and (5) of the Act are replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><Subsection><MarginalNote>Effect of not dealing with complaint</MarginalNote><Label>(4)</Label><Text>If the Commissioner decides not to deal with a complaint and sends the complainant a written notice setting out the reasons for that decision, the period of time that begins on the day on which the complaint was filed and ends on the day on which the notice is sent is not to be included in the calculation of any time the complainant has to avail himself or herself of any procedure under any other Act of Parliament or collective agreement in respect of the measure alleged to constitute the reprisal.</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>14</Label><Text>Subsection 19.5(3) of the Act is amended by striking out “and” at the end of paragraph (b), by adding “and” at the end of paragraph (c), and by adding the following after paragraph (c):</Text><AmendedText><SectionPiece><Paragraph change="ins"><Label>(d)</Label><Text>in the case where the complainant makes an application to the Tribunal for the orders referred to in subsection 21.01(1) in respect of the complaint, the day on which the Tribunal makes a determination that the complainant was not subject to a reprisal taken by the person.</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>15</Label><Text>Subsection 19.6(3) of the Act is amended by striking out “and” at the end of paragraph (c) and by adding the following after that paragraph:</Text><AmendedText><SectionPiece><Paragraph change="ins"><Label>(c.1)</Label><Text>in the case where the complainant makes an application to the Tribunal for the orders referred to in subsection 21.01(1) in respect of the complaint, the day on which the Tribunal makes a determination that the complainant was not subject to a reprisal taken by the person, and</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>16</Label><Text>Subsection 20.2(3) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><Subsection><MarginalNote>Application barred</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>If the Commissioner approves a settlement that relates to disciplinary action, if any, that is to be imposed on a person,</Text><Paragraph><Label><Ins>(a)</Ins></Label><Text>the Commissioner may not apply to the Tribunal for an order referred to in paragraph 20.4(1)(b) in respect of the person; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph change="ins"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>the complainant may not apply to the Tribunal for an order referred to in subsection 21.01(1) in respect of the person.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>17</Label><Text>Subsection 20.4(3) of the Act is amended by adding “and” at the end of paragraph (a) and by replacing paragraphs (b) to (d) by the following:</Text><AmendedText><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>the complaint should be dismissed on any ground mentioned in <Ins>paragraph 19.3(1)(a) or (b)</Ins>.</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>18</Label><Text>The heading before section 21.1 of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><Heading level="3"><TitleText>Applications <Ins>to the Tribunal</Ins></TitleText></Heading></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>19</Label><Text>The Act is amended by adding the following before section 21.1:</Text><AmendedText><Section change="ins"><MarginalNote>Application by complainant</MarginalNote><Label>21.01</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>A complainant whose complaint is dismissed by the Commissioner under section 20.5 may apply to the Tribunal for a determination of whether or not a reprisal was taken against him or her and, if the Tribunal determines that a reprisal was taken, the complainant may apply for an order respecting a remedy in his or her favour and an order respecting disciplinary action against any person or persons identified by the complainant in the application as being the person or persons who took the reprisal.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Time for making application<Emphasis style="bold" /></MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The application must be filed not later than 60 days after the day on which the complainant is notified under section 20.6.</Text></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>20</Label><Text>Subsection 21.1(1) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><Section><MarginalNote>Assignment of member or members </MarginalNote><Label>21.1</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>On receipt of an application made by <Ins>a complainant under subsection 21.01(1) or by</Ins> the Commissioner under subsection 20.4(1), the Chairperson of the Tribunal must assign a member of the Tribunal to deal with the application, but the Chairperson may assign a panel of three members if he or she considers that the complexity of the matter requires that it be dealt with by three members. Every decision of the member or panel is a decision of the Tribunal.</Text></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>21</Label><Text>The Act is amended by adding the following after section 21.3:</Text><AmendedText><Section change="ins"><MarginalNote>Proof of reprisal</MarginalNote><Label>21.31</Label><Text>An application made by the Commissioner to the Tribunal under subsection 20.4(1) is, in the absence of evidence to the contrary, proof that a reprisal was taken against the complainant. </Text></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>22</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Subsection 21.4(2) of the Act is amended by striking out “and” at the end of paragraph (b), by adding “and” at the end of paragraph (c), and by adding the following after paragraph (c):</Text><AmendedText><SectionPiece><Paragraph change="ins"><Label>(d)</Label><Text>the person or persons identified in the application as having taken the alleged reprisal.</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Subsection 21.4(3) of the Act is repealed.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>23</Label><Text>Subsection 21.5(1) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><Section><MarginalNote>Determination — paragraph 20.4(1)(b) and subsection 21.01(1)</MarginalNote><Label>21.5</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>On application made for the orders referred to in paragraph 20.4(1)(b) <Ins>or subsection 21.01(1)</Ins>, the Tribunal must determine whether the complainant has been subject to a reprisal and whether the person or persons identified by the Commissioner <Ins>or the complainant, as the case may be</Ins>, in the application as having taken the alleged reprisal actually took it. If it determines that a reprisal was taken, the Tribunal may, regardless of whether or not it has determined that the reprisal was taken by the person or persons named in the application, make an order granting a remedy to the complainant.</Text></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>24</Label><Text>Section 22 of the Act is amended by adding the following after paragraph (a):</Text><AmendedText><SectionPiece><Paragraph change="ins"><Label>(a.1)</Label><Text>assess the internal disclosure procedures established by a chief executive under section 10 and, on the Commissioner’s own initiative or at the request of any party, conduct a review of the receiving of and dealing with disclosures of wrongdoings under those procedures;</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>25</Label><Text>Section 23 of the Act is repealed.</Text></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>26</Label><Text>Paragraph 24(1)(c) of the Act is repealed.</Text></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>27</Label><Text>Paragraph 25(1)(j) of the Act is repealed.</Text></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>28</Label><Text>Paragraph 25.1(1)(e) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(e)</Label><Text>any public servant <Ins>or former public servant</Ins> who is considering making a complaint under this Act regarding an alleged reprisal taken against him or her; or</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>29</Label><Text>Subsection 33(1) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><Section><MarginalNote>Power to investigate other wrongdoings</MarginalNote><Label>33</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>If, during the course of an investigation or as a result of any information provided to the Commissioner by a person who is not a public servant, the Commissioner has reason to believe that another wrongdoing, or a wrongdoing, as the case may be, has been committed, he or she may, subject to <Ins>section</Ins> 24, commence an investigation into the wrongdoing if he or she believes on reasonable grounds that the public interest requires an <Keep svc="1">investigation.</Keep> The provisions of this Act applicable to investigations commenced as the result of a disclosure apply to investigations commenced under this section.</Text></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>30</Label><Text>Section 34 of the Act is repealed.</Text></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>31</Label><Text>Subsection 35(1) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><Section><MarginalNote>Remittal of information</MarginalNote><Label>35</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>If the Commissioner has reasonable grounds to suspect that information obtained in the course of an investigation may be used in the investigation or prosecution of an alleged contravention of any Act of Parliament or of the legislature of a province, he or she may, in addition to or in lieu of continuing the investigation, remit the information, at that point in time, to a peace officer having jurisdiction to investigate the alleged contravention, to the Attorney General of Canada or <Ins>to the Auditor General of Canada</Ins>.</Text></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>32</Label><Text>Paragraph 37(b) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>a situation that has come to his or her attention in the course of carrying out his or her duties exists that constitutes an imminent risk of a danger to the life, health or safety of persons, or to the environment.</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>33</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Paragraphs 38(2)(b) and (c) of the Act are replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>the number of disclosures received, <Ins>broken down by type of wrongdoing</Ins>, and the number of them that were acted on and those that were not acted on;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(c)</Label><Text>the number of investigations commenced under this Act, <Ins>the number of investigations concluded, the average duration of an investigation and a summary of investigations that, in the Commissioner’s opinion, are of interest to Canadians</Ins>;</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Section 38 is amended by adding the following after subsection (2):</Text><AmendedText><Subsection change="ins"><MarginalNote>Details</MarginalNote><Label>(2.1)</Label><Text>The information referred in paragraphs (2)(a) to (d.1) is to be broken down by portion of the public sector and by region of Canada. </Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Subsection></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>34</Label><Text>Section 40 of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><Section><MarginalNote>False statements</MarginalNote><Label>40</Label><Text>No person shall, in a disclosure of a wrongdoing or in the course of any investigation under this Act, knowingly make a false or misleading statement, either orally or in writing, to a supervisor, <Ins>an officer</Ins>, a senior officer, the Commissioner or a person acting on behalf of or under the direction of any of them.</Text></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>35</Label><Text>The portion of subsection 42.1(1) of the Act before paragraph (a) is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><Section><MarginalNote>Prohibition — employer</MarginalNote><Label>42.1</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>No employer shall take any of the following measures against an employee by reason only that the employee has, on the basis of reasonable belief, provided information concerning an alleged wrongdoing in the public sector to the Commissioner or, if the alleged wrongdoing relates to the Office of the Public Sector Integrity Commissioner, to the Auditor General of Canada — or by reason only that the employer believes that the employee will do so:</Text></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>36</Label><Text>Subsections 42.2(1) and (2) of the Act are replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><Section><MarginalNote>Prohibition — termination of contract or withholding of payments</MarginalNote><Label>42.2</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>A public servant or any person purporting to act on behalf of Her Majesty in right of Canada or a portion of the public sector shall not terminate any contract with Her Majesty in right of Canada or any portion of the public sector, or withhold any payment that is due and payable in respect of any such contract, by reason only that the other party to the contract or any of that other party’s employees has, on the basis of reasonable belief, provided information concerning an alleged wrongdoing in the public sector to the Commissioner or, if the alleged wrongdoing relates to the Office of the Public Sector Integrity Commissioner, to the Auditor General of Canada.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Prohibition — entering into contract</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>A public servant or any person purporting to act on behalf of Her Majesty in right of Canada or a portion of the public sector shall not, in considering whether to enter into a contract with a person, take into account that the person or any of the person’s employees has, in the past, on the basis of reasonable belief, provided information concerning an alleged wrongdoing in the public sector to the Commissioner or, if the alleged wrongdoing relates to the Office of the Public Sector Integrity Commissioner, to the Auditor General of Canada.</Text></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>37</Label><Text>Paragraphs 42.3(a) and (b) of the Act are replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>an indictable offence and liable to a fine of not more than $<Ins>200,000</Ins> or to imprisonment for a term of not more than two years, or to both that fine and that imprisonment; or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>an offence punishable on summary conviction and liable to a fine of not more than $<Ins>100,000</Ins> or to <Keep>im­</Keep><Keep>prisonment</Keep> for a term of not more than six months, or to both that fine and that imprisonment.</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>38</Label><Text>The Act is amended by adding the following after section 44.1:</Text><AmendedText><Section change="ins"><MarginalNote>Identity of persons involved in disclosure</MarginalNote><Label>44.2</Label><Text>The Commissioner and every person acting on behalf of or under the direction of the Commissioner may disclose the identity of any person involved in the disclosure process, including that of a person making a disclosure, a witness and a person alleged to be responsible for wrongdoings, with the consent of that person.</Text></Section><Section change="ins"><MarginalNote>Disclosure of information obtained in the course of an investigation</MarginalNote><Label>44.3</Label><Text>Subject to the provisions of this Act and any other Act of Parliament, the Commissioner may disclose to a chief executive or the Tribunal any information obtained in the course of an investigation if, in the Commissioner’s opinion, the public interest in making the disclosure clearly outweighs the potential harm from the disclosure. </Text></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>39</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The portion of subsection 49(1) of the Act before paragraph (a) is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><Section><MarginalNote>Restriction</MarginalNote><Label>49</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Subject to subsections (2) and (3), when making a report under section 38, the Commissioner shall not disclose any information that the Government of Canada or any portion of the public sector is taking measures to protect, including, but not limited to, information that</Text></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Paragraph 49(3)(a) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>the disclosure is necessary to establish the grounds for any finding or recommendation in a report under section 38; and</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>40</Label><Text>The portion of section 51 before paragraph (a) is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><Section><MarginalNote>Saving</MarginalNote><Label>51</Label><Text>Subject to <Ins>subsection</Ins> 21.8(4), nothing in this Act is to be construed as prohibiting</Text></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>41</Label><Text>Section 54 of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><Section><MarginalNote>Review</MarginalNote><Label>54</Label><Text><Ins>On the fifth anniversary of the day on which this section comes into force, and every five years after that</Ins>, the President of the Treasury Board must cause to be conducted an independent review of this Act, and its administration and operation, and must cause a report on the review to be laid before each House of Parliament on any of the first 15 days on which that House is sitting after the review is completed.</Text></Section></AmendedText></Section></Body></Bill>