<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><Bill bill-origin="commons" bill-type="private-public" xml:lang="en" date-time="2022-03-30 13:20:16"><Identification><BillNumber>C-300</BillNumber><Parliament><Session>1</Session><Number>44</Number><RegnalYear><Year-s>70-71</Year-s><Monarch>Elizabeth II – 1 Charles III</Monarch></RegnalYear><Year-s>2021-2022</Year-s></Parliament><LongTitle>An Act to amend the Department of Public Works and Government Services Act, the Defence Production Act and the Federal-Provincial Fiscal Arrangements Act (Canadian products and services)</LongTitle><ShortTitle status="unofficial" /><RunningHead>An Act to amend the Department of Public Works and Government Services Act, ...</RunningHead><BillHistory><Stages stage="first-reading-house"><Date><YYYY>2022</YYYY><MM>10</MM><DD>24</DD></Date></Stages></BillHistory><BillSponsor><Emphasis style="smallcaps">Ms. Mathyssen</Emphasis></BillSponsor><BillRefNumber date-time="2022-03-30">441055</BillRefNumber></Identification><Introduction><Summary><TitleText>SUMMARY</TitleText><Provision><Text>This enactment amends the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Department of Public Works and Government Services Act</XRefExternal> and the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Defence Production Act</XRefExternal> to provide that, in relation to the acquisition of products and services for use by government departments, preference must be given to Canadian products and services.</Text></Provision><Provision language-align="yes"><Text>It also amends the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Federal-Provincial Fiscal Arrangements Act</XRefExternal> to provide for a new transfer to the provinces for the purpose of giving preference to Canadian products and services.</Text></Provision></Summary><Enacts><Provision><Text>His Majesty, by and with the advice and consent <Keep>of the</Keep> Senate and House of Commons of Canada, <Keep>enacts</Keep> as follows:</Text></Provision></Enacts></Introduction><Body><Heading level="1"><MarginalNote><HistoricalNote>1996, c. 16</HistoricalNote></MarginalNote><TitleText>Department of Public Works and Government Services Act</TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><Label>1</Label><Text>Section 2 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Department of Public Works and Government Services Act</XRefExternal> is amended by adding the following in alphabetical order:</Text><AmendedText><SectionPiece><Definition change="ins"><Text><DefinedTermEn>Canadian product</DefinedTermEn> means a product</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>of which more than 50% of the total value is manufactured, produced or assembled
in Canada and, in the case of an assembled product, whose final assembly is done in Canada, or
</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>in the case of a natural resource, of which more than 50% of the total value originates in
Canada; (<DefinedTermFr>produit canadien</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Paragraph></Definition><Definition change="ins"><Text><DefinedTermEn>Canadian service</DefinedTermEn> means a service offered by</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>a Canadian citizen,</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>a <DefinitionRef>permanent resident</DefinitionRef>, within the meaning of subsection 2(1) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Immigration and
Refugee Protection Act</XRefExternal>,
</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(c)</Label><Text>the Government of Canada, a provincial or local government, or a department, board or agency of that government,</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(d)</Label><Text>a partnership, trust or joint venture in which a person, or any combination of persons referred to in paragraph (a), (b), (c) or (e), beneficially owns or controls, directly or indirectly, interests representing in value more than 50% of the total value of the assets of the partnership, trust or joint venture, as the case may be,</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(e)</Label><Text>a Canadian corporation, or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(f)</Label><Text>a non-profit organization of which more than half of the members are persons referred
to in paragraph (a) or (b); (<DefinedTermFr>service canadien</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Paragraph></Definition></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>2</Label><Text>Section 7 of the Act is amended by adding the following after subsection (1):</Text><AmendedText><Subsection change="ins"><MarginalNote>Canadian products and services</MarginalNote><Label>(1.1)</Label><Text>In exercising the powers or performing the duties or functions assigned to the Minister under this or any other Act of Parliament, the Minister shall give preference to Canadian products and Canadian services, unless doing so would conflict with Canada’s obligations under an international agreement.</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Section><Heading level="1"><MarginalNote><HistoricalNote>R.S., c. D-1
</HistoricalNote></MarginalNote><TitleText>Defence Production Act</TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><Label>3</Label><Text>Section 16 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Defence Production Act</XRefExternal> is renumbered as subsection 16(1) and is amended by adding the following:
</Text><AmendedText><Subsection change="ins"><MarginalNote>Canadian products and services</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>In exercising the powers of procurement under subsection (1), the Minister shall give preference to <DefinitionRef>Canadian products</DefinitionRef> and <DefinitionRef>Canadian services</DefinitionRef>, within the meaning of section 2 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Department of Public Works and Government Services Act</XRefExternal>, unless doing so would conflict with Canada’s obligations under an international agreement.</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Section><Heading level="1"><MarginalNote><HistoricalNote>R.S., c. F-8; 1995, c. 17, s. 45</HistoricalNote></MarginalNote><TitleText>Federal-Provincial Fiscal Arrangements Act 

</TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><Label>4</Label><Text>The <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Federal-Provincial Fiscal Arrangements Act</XRefExternal> is amended by adding the following after section 25.91:</Text><AmendedText><Heading level="1" change="ins"><Label>PART V.2</Label><TitleText>Preference to Canadian Products and Services Transfer</TitleText></Heading><Heading level="2" change="ins"><TitleText>Canadian Products and Services</TitleText></Heading><Section change="ins"><MarginalNote>Purposes</MarginalNote><Label>25.92</Label><Text>A Preference to Canadian Products and Services Transfer is to be provided to the provinces for the purpose of giving preference to the acquisition of <DefinitionRef>Canadian products</DefinitionRef> and <DefinitionRef>Canadian services</DefinitionRef>, within the meaning of section 2 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Department of Public Works and Government Services Act</XRefExternal>.</Text></Section><Section change="ins"><MarginalNote>Amount</MarginalNote><Label>25.93</Label><Text>The Preference to Canadian Products and Services Transfer is to consist of a cash contribution of $100,000 to be provided to each province for each fiscal year beginning after March 31, 2023.</Text></Section><Heading level="2" change="ins"><TitleText>Payments</TitleText></Heading><Section change="ins"><MarginalNote>Payments out of C.R.F.</MarginalNote><Label>25.94</Label><Text>The Minister may make payments out of the Consolidated Revenue Fund for the purpose of the transfer provided in section 25.93.</Text></Section></AmendedText></Section></Body></Bill>