<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><Bill bill-origin="commons" bill-type="private-public" xml:lang="en" date-time="2022-10-26 16:26:48"><Identification><BillNumber>C-303</BillNumber><Parliament><Session>1</Session><Number>44</Number><RegnalYear><Year-s>70-71</Year-s><Monarch>Elizabeth II – 1 Charles III</Monarch></RegnalYear><Year-s>2021-2022</Year-s></Parliament><LongTitle>An Act to amend the Royal Canadian Mounted Police Act</LongTitle><ShortTitle status="unofficial" /><RunningHead>An Act to amend the Royal Canadian Mounted Police Act</RunningHead><BillHistory><Stages stage="first-reading-house"><Date><YYYY>2022</YYYY><MM>11</MM><DD>1</DD></Date></Stages></BillHistory><BillSponsor><Emphasis style="smallcaps">Mr. MacGregor</Emphasis></BillSponsor><BillRefNumber date-time="2022-10-26">441194</BillRefNumber></Identification><Introduction><Summary><TitleText>SUMMARY</TitleText><Provision><Text>This enactment amends the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Royal Canadian Mounted Police Act</XRefExternal> to clarify the scope of the directions that the Minister of Public Safety and Emergency Preparedness can issue to the Commissioner of the Royal Canadian Mounted Police and to require that all directions be issued in writing. It also provides for reporting and publishing requirements with respect to those directions.</Text></Provision></Summary><Enacts><Provision><Text>His Majesty, by and with the advice and consent <Keep>of the</Keep> Senate and House of Commons of Canada, <Keep>enacts</Keep> as follows:</Text></Provision></Enacts></Introduction><Body><Heading level="1"><MarginalNote><HistoricalNote>R.S., c. R-10</HistoricalNote></MarginalNote><TitleText>Royal Canadian Mounted Police Act</TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><Label>1</Label><Text>The <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Royal Canadian Mounted Police Act</XRefExternal> is amended by adding the following after section 5:</Text><AmendedText><Section change="ins"><MarginalNote>Directions</MarginalNote><Label>5.1</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The Minister may issue a direction to the Commissioner to establish priorities, objectives and policies for the Force.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Exclusions</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The Minister shall not issue a direction in respect of the following:</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>operational decisions, including the day-to-day operations of the Force;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>matters respecting law enforcement decisions in specific cases, such as those relating to investigations, arrests and prosecutions; or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(c)</Label><Text>any matter that would interfere with the Commissioner's powers or authority conferred under subsection 5(1) in relation to the control and management of the Force.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Directions in writing
</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>When issuing directions to the Commissioner, the Minister shall do so in writing.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Report to Parliament</MarginalNote><Label>(4)</Label><Text>The Minister shall cause a copy of any direction issued to the Commissioner to be tabled in each House of Parliament on any of the first 15 days on which that House is sitting after the day on which the direction is issued.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote><XRefExternal reference-type="act">Statutory Instruments Act</XRefExternal></MarginalNote><Label>(5)</Label><Text>A direction is not a statutory instrument for the purposes of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Statutory Instruments Act</XRefExternal>. However, it must be published in the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Canada Gazette</XRefExternal>.</Text></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Section></Body></Bill>