<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><Bill bill-origin="commons" bill-type="private-public" xml:lang="en" date-time="2022-11-04 07:32:04"><Identification><BillNumber>C-306</BillNumber><Parliament><Session>1</Session><Number>44</Number><RegnalYear><Year-s>70-71</Year-s><Monarch>Elizabeth II ГўВҖВ“ 1 Charles III</Monarch></RegnalYear><Year-s>2021-2022</Year-s></Parliament><LongTitle>An Act to establish National WomenГўВҖВҷs Entrepreneurship Day</LongTitle><ShortTitle status="unofficial" /><RunningHead>National Women's Entrepreneurship Day Act</RunningHead><BillHistory><Stages stage="first-reading-house"><Date><YYYY>2022</YYYY><MM>11</MM><DD>17</DD></Date></Stages></BillHistory><BillSponsor><Emphasis style="smallcaps">Mrs. Valdez</Emphasis></BillSponsor><BillRefNumber date-time="2022-11-04">441219</BillRefNumber></Identification><Introduction><Summary><TitleText>SUMMARY</TitleText><Provision><Text>This enactment designates the 19th of November in each year as ГўВҖВңNational WomenГўВҖВҷs Entrepreneurship DayГўВҖВқ.</Text></Provision></Summary><Preamble><Provision><MarginalNote>Preamble</MarginalNote><Text>Whereas, on November 19, 2014, the WomenГўВҖВҷs Entrepreneurship Day Organization spearheaded the first WomenГўВҖВҷs Entrepreneurship Day to celebrate and support women in business worldwide;</Text></Provision><Provision><Text>Whereas WomenГўВҖВҷs Entrepreneurship Day is recognized  by the United Nations and is already celebrated in over 140 countries;</Text></Provision><Provision><Text>Whereas women have been subject to barriers in regard to entrepreneurship and starting businesses;</Text></Provision><Provision><Text>Whereas Parliament considers that women entrepreneurs should have every opportunity to start up and scale up their businesses;</Text></Provision><Provision><Text>Whereas Parliament considers that it is important to recognize the resilience and empowerment of women entrepreneurs and their contribution to society;</Text></Provision><Provision><Text>And whereas Parliament considers that it is fitting that November 19 of each year be officially designated as ГўВҖВңNational WomenГўВҖВҷs Entrepreneurship DayГўВҖВқ in order to celebrate Canadian women entrepreneurs;</Text></Provision><Provision language-align="yes"><Text>Now, therefore, His Majesty, by and with the advice and consent of the Senate and House of Commons of Canada, enacts as follows:</Text></Provision></Preamble></Introduction><Body><Heading level="1"><TitleText>Short Title</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Short title</MarginalNote><Label>1</Label><Text>This Act may be cited as the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">National Women's Entrepreneurship Day Act</XRefExternal>.</Text></Section><Heading level="1"><TitleText>National WomenГўВҖВҷs Entrepreneurship Day</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Designation</MarginalNote><Label>2</Label><Text>Throughout Canada, in each year, the 19th day of November is to be known as ГўВҖВңNational WomenГўВҖВҷs Entrepreneurship DayГўВҖВқ.</Text></Section></Body></Bill>