<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><Bill bill-origin="commons" bill-type="private-public" xml:lang="en" date-time="2023-01-27 13:31:44"><Identification><BillNumber>C-316</BillNumber><Parliament><Session>1</Session><Number>44</Number><RegnalYear><Year-s>70-71</Year-s><Monarch>Elizabeth II 芒聙聯 1-2 Charles III</Monarch></RegnalYear><Year-s>2021-2022-2023-2024</Year-s></Parliament><LongTitle>An Act to amend the Department of Canadian Heritage Act (Court Challenges Program)</LongTitle><ShortTitle status="unofficial" /><RunningHead>Court Challenges Program Act</RunningHead><BillHistory><Stages stage="report-house"><Date><YYYY>2024</YYYY><MM>6</MM><DD>13</DD></Date><StageText>Reprinted as amended by the Standing Committee on Canadian Heritage as a working copy for the use of the House of Commons at Report Stage and as reported to the House on June脗聽13, 2024</StageText></Stages></BillHistory><BillSponsor><Emphasis style="smallcaps">Mr. McKinnon</Emphasis></BillSponsor><BillRefNumber date-time="2023-01-27">441221</BillRefNumber></Identification><Introduction><Summary><TitleText>SUMMARY</TitleText><Provision><Text>This enactment amends the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Department of Canadian Heritage Act</XRefExternal> to specify that, in exercising the powers and performing the duties and functions assigned to the Minister of Canadian Heritage under that Act, he or she shall maintain the Court Challenges Program.</Text></Provision></Summary><Preamble><Provision><MarginalNote>Preamble</MarginalNote><Text>Whereas the Government of Canada first created the Court Challenges Program in 1978 to help official language minority communities take legal action to clarify and affirm their language rights;</Text></Provision><Provision><Text>Whereas, following the adoption of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Canadian Charter of Rights and Freedoms</XRefExternal>, the scope of the Court Challenges Program was broadened to include new language rights as well as human rights;
</Text></Provision><Provision><Text>Whereas, in 1992, the Government of Canada cancelled the Court Challenges Program before restoring it in 1994 and then cancelling it and restoring it several times over the years;
</Text></Provision><Provision><Text>Whereas it is of utmost importance <Ins>that it be possible</Ins> to bring before the courts test cases of national significance that aim to clarify and assert certain constitutional and quasi-constitutional official language rights and human rights, particularly such rights that are recognized and guaranteed by the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Canadian Charter of Rights and Freedoms</XRefExternal>;</Text></Provision><Provision><Text>And whereas Parliament recognizes the need to entrench into law an independently administered program to give a voice to those who might not have the ability to bring court challenges forward in order to clarify, expand and breathe life into constitutional equality, linguistic rights and human rights, particularly such rights that are recognized and guaranteed by the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Canadian Charter of Rights and Freedoms</XRefExternal>, and to hold government to account;</Text></Provision></Preamble><Enacts><Provision><Text>Now, therefore, His Majesty, by and with the advice and consent <Keep>of the</Keep> Senate and House of Commons of Canada, <Keep>enacts</Keep> as follows:</Text></Provision></Enacts></Introduction><Body><Heading level="1"><TitleText>Short Title</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Short title</MarginalNote><Label>1</Label><Text>This Act may be cited as the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Court Challenges Program Act</XRefExternal>.</Text></Section><Heading level="1"><MarginalNote><HistoricalNote>1995, c. 11</HistoricalNote></MarginalNote><TitleText>Department of Canadian Heritage Act</TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><Label>2</Label><Text>Section 5 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Department of Canadian Heritage Act</XRefExternal> is amended by striking out 芒聙聹and芒聙聺 at the end of paragraph (a) and by adding the following after that paragraph:</Text><AmendedText><SectionPiece><Paragraph change="ins"><Label>(a.1)</Label><Text>establish and implement the program referred to in section 7.1 of this Act and paragraph 43(1)(c) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Official Languages Act</XRefExternal> that is administered by an organization independent of the Government of Canada and whose purpose is to provide funding for test cases of national significance to be brought before the courts to clarify and assert constitutional and quasi-<Keep>constitutional</Keep> official language rights and constitutional human rights that are guaranteed by the <XRefExternal reference-type="regulation">Canadian Charter of Rights and Freedoms</XRefExternal>; and</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>3</Label><Text>The Act is amended by adding the following after section 5:</Text><AmendedText><Section><MarginalNote>Annual report</MarginalNote><Label>5.1</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The independent organization responsible for administering the program <Ins>referred to in section 7.1 of this Act and paragraph 43(1)(c) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Official Languages Act</XRefExternal></Ins> shall, each year, submit to the Minister a report on the administration of the program, in which it shall set out a summary of its organizational activities to demonstrate the impact of its work and provide a transparent picture of the direction, goals and financial performance of the program, as well as an overview of the cases that received funding in the previous year <Ins>and any outreach and promotional activities that were conducted with groups affected by these cases</Ins>.</Text></Subsection><Subsection change="ins"><MarginalNote>Annual report 芒聙聯 additional content</MarginalNote><Label>(1.1)</Label><Text>The annual report shall also state, for each of the program芒聙聶s two components, the number of applications that were denied funding.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Tabling in Parliament</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The Minister shall cause the annual report to be tabled before each House of Parliament on any of the first 15 days on which that House is sitting after the Minister receives the report.</Text></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Section><Heading level="1" type="transitional"><TitleText>Transitional Provision</TitleText></Heading><Section type="transitional"><Label>4</Label><Text>[<Emphasis style="italic">Deleted</Emphasis>]</Text></Section></Body></Bill>