<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><Bill bill-origin="commons" bill-type="private-public" xml:lang="en" date-time="2022-10-24 13:21:48"><Identification><BillNumber>C-329</BillNumber><Parliament><Session>1</Session><Number>44</Number><RegnalYear><Year-s>70-71</Year-s><Monarch>Elizabeth II – 1 Charles III</Monarch></RegnalYear><Year-s>2021-2022-2023</Year-s></Parliament><LongTitle>An Act to establish a national framework respecting attention deficit hyperactivity disorder</LongTitle><ShortTitle status="unofficial">National Framework on Attention Deficit Hyperactivity Disorder Act</ShortTitle><RunningHead>National Framework on
Attention Deficit Hyperactivity Disorder Act</RunningHead><BillHistory><Stages stage="first-reading-house"><Date><YYYY>2023</YYYY><MM>3</MM><DD>30</DD></Date></Stages></BillHistory><BillSponsor><Emphasis style="smallcaps">Ms. McPherson</Emphasis></BillSponsor><BillRefNumber date-time="2022-10-24">441182</BillRefNumber></Identification><Introduction><Summary><TitleText>SUMMARY</TitleText><Provision><Text>This enactment provides for the development of a national framework on attention deficit hyperactivity disorder.</Text></Provision></Summary><Preamble><Provision><MarginalNote>Preamble</MarginalNote><Text>Whereas attention deficit hyperactivity disorder is a chronic neurodevelopmental disorder that affects over one million Canadians;</Text></Provision><Provision><Text>Whereas this disorder affects both children and adults, regardless of ethnic origin or <Keep>socio-economic</Keep> status;</Text></Provision><Provision><Text>Whereas many students with this disorder do not graduate high school;</Text></Provision><Provision><Text>And whereas many persons with this disorder have at least one comorbid psychiatric disorder, such as anxiety, depression or substance abuse disorder, and are believed to have a shorter life expectancy due to such psychiatric or other comorbidities;</Text></Provision><Provision language-align="yes"><Text>Now, therefore, His Majesty, by and with the advice and consent <Keep>of the</Keep> Senate and House of Commons of Canada, <Keep>enacts</Keep> as follows:</Text></Provision></Preamble></Introduction><Body><Heading level="1"><TitleText>Short Title</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Short title</MarginalNote><Label>1</Label><Text>This Act may be cited as the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">National Framework on Attention Deficit Hyperactivity Disorder Act</XRefExternal>.</Text></Section><Heading level="1"><TitleText>Interpretation</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Definitions</MarginalNote><Label>2</Label><Text>The following definitions apply in this Act.</Text><Definition><Text><DefinedTermEn>Indigenous governing body</DefinedTermEn> means a council, government or other entity that is authorized to act on behalf of an Indigenous group, community or people that holds rights recognized and affirmed by section 35 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Constitution Act, 1982</XRefExternal>. (<DefinedTermFr>corps dirigeant autochtone</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Definition><Definition><Text><DefinedTermEn>Minister</DefinedTermEn> means the Minister of Health. (<DefinedTermFr>ministre</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Definition></Section><Heading level="1"><TitleText>National Framework on Attention Deficit Hyperactivity Disorder</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Development</MarginalNote><Label>3</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The Minister must, in consultation with the representatives of the provincial governments and Indigenous governing bodies responsible for health and education, as well as other relevant stakeholders, develop a national framework on attention deficit hyperactivity disorder.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Content</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The national framework must include measures to</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>provide for the development of resources to help individuals with attention deficit hyperactivity disorder and their families better recognize, understand and manage the disorder;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>ensure that educators are equipped with the knowledge, training and resources needed to support students with attention deficit hyperactivity disorder and related learning comorbid disorders;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(c)</Label><Text>improve training for medical and mental health practitioners on attention deficit hyperactivity disorder;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(d)</Label><Text>ensure that all medical and mental health practitioners can access training and support in relation to evidence-based approaches to attention deficit hyperactivity disorder assessment and treatment; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(e)</Label><Text>facilitate equitable access for individuals with attention deficit hyperactivity disorder and their families to medical and mental health practitioners who have received training on this disorder.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection></Section><Heading level="1"><TitleText>Reports to Parliament</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Tabling of national framework</MarginalNote><Label>4</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Within two years after the day on which this Act comes into force, the Minister must prepare a report setting out the national framework and cause it to be tabled in each House of Parliament on any of the first 15 days on which that House is sitting after the report is completed.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Publication</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The Minister must publish the report on the website of the Department of Health within 10 days after the day on which it is tabled in both Houses of Parliament.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Report</MarginalNote><Label>5</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Within five years after the report referred to in section 4 has been tabled in both Houses of Parliament, the Minister must prepare a report on the effectiveness of the national framework that also sets out the Minister’s conclusions and recommendations.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Tabling of report</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The Minister must cause the report to be tabled in each House of Parliament on any of the first 15 days on which that House is sitting after the report is completed.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Publication</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>The Minister must publish the report on the website of the Department of Health within 10 days after the day on which it is tabled in both Houses of Parliament.</Text></Subsection></Section></Body></Bill>