<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><Bill bill-origin="commons" bill-type="private-public" xml:lang="en" date-time="2017-11-07 15:57:21"><Identification><BillNumber>C-328</BillNumber><Parliament><Session>1</Session><Number>44</Number><RegnalYear><Year-s>70-71</Year-s><Monarch>Elizabeth II – 1 Charles III</Monarch></RegnalYear><Year-s>2021-2022-2023</Year-s></Parliament><LongTitle>An Act respecting the development of a national strategy on student loan debt</LongTitle><ShortTitle status="unofficial" /><RunningHead>Student Debt Relief Act</RunningHead><BillHistory><Stages stage="first-reading-house"><Date><YYYY>2023</YYYY><MM>3</MM><DD>29</DD></Date></Stages></BillHistory><BillSponsor><Emphasis style="smallcaps">Mr. Davies</Emphasis></BillSponsor><BillRefNumber date-time="2017-11-07">441245</BillRefNumber></Identification><Introduction><Summary><TitleText>SUMMARY</TitleText><Provision><Text>This enactment provides for the development of a national strategy with the objective of reducing student loan debt.</Text></Provision></Summary><Enacts><Provision><Text>His Majesty, by and with the advice and consent <Keep>of the</Keep> Senate and House of Commons of Canada, <Keep>enacts</Keep> as follows:</Text></Provision></Enacts></Introduction><Body><Heading level="1"><TitleText>Short Title</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Short title</MarginalNote><Label>1</Label><Text>This Act may be cited as the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Student Debt Relief Act</XRefExternal>.</Text></Section><Heading level="1"><TitleText>Interpretation</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Definition of <DefinedTermEn>Minister</DefinedTermEn></MarginalNote><Label>2</Label><Text>In this Act, <DefinedTermEn>Minister</DefinedTermEn> means the Minister of Employment and Social Development.</Text></Section><Heading level="1"><TitleText>National Strategy on Student Loan Debt</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>National Strategy</MarginalNote><Label>3</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The Minister, in consultation with representatives of the provincial governments responsible for education, must develop a national strategy to reduce student loan debt that includes an assessment of the following measures:
</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>canceling debt from government provided student loans;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>permanently eliminating interest from government provided student loans;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(c)</Label><Text>increasing non-repayable student grants; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(d)</Label><Text>protecting future students by reducing the cost of post-secondary education across Canada.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Conference</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The Minister must hold at least one conference with representatives of the provincial governments respon­sible for education for the purpose of developing the strategy.</Text></Subsection></Section><Heading level="1"><TitleText>Reports to Parliament</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Report to Parliament</MarginalNote><Label>4</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Within one year after the day on which this Act comes into force, the Minister must prepare a report setting out the national strategy and cause it to be laid before each House of Parliament.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Publication </MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The Minister must post the report on the website of the Department of Employment and Social Development within 30 days after the day on which the report is tabled in Parliament.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Review by Minister</MarginalNote><Label>5</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Within three years after the report referred to in section 4 has been tabled in both Houses of Parliament, the Minister must, in consultation with representatives of the provincial governments responsible for education, undertake a comprehensive review of the national strat­egy and prepare a report setting out the Minister's findings and recommendations.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Tabling of report</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The Minister must cause the report of the review to be tabled in each House of Parliament on any of the first 15 days on which that House is sitting after it is completed.</Text></Subsection></Section></Body></Bill>