<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><Bill bill-origin="commons" bill-type="private-public" xml:lang="en" date-time="2016-06-10 15:11:17"><Identification><BillNumber>C-323</BillNumber><Parliament><Session>1</Session><Number>44</Number><RegnalYear><Year-s>70-71</Year-s><Monarch>Elizabeth II – 1 Charles III</Monarch></RegnalYear><Year-s>2021-2022-2023</Year-s></Parliament><LongTitle>An Act to amend the Excise Tax Act (mental health services)</LongTitle><ShortTitle status="unofficial" /><RunningHead>An Act to amend the Excise Tax Act (mental health services)</RunningHead><BillHistory><Stages stage="first-reading-house"><Date><YYYY>2023</YYYY><MM>3</MM><DD>9</DD></Date></Stages></BillHistory><BillSponsor><Emphasis style="smallcaps">Mr. Ellis</Emphasis></BillSponsor><BillRefNumber date-time="2016-06-10">441248</BillRefNumber></Identification><Introduction><Summary><TitleText>SUMMARY</TitleText><Provision><Text>This enactment amends the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Excise Tax Act</XRefExternal> in order to exempt psychotherapy and mental health counselling services from the goods and services tax.</Text></Provision></Summary><Preamble><Provision><MarginalNote>Preamble
</MarginalNote><Text>Whereas nearly one quarter of Canadians over the age of 15 report that they have mental health needs that have not been met;</Text></Provision><Provision><Text>Whereas publicly funded mental health services, such as counselling and psychotherapy, are not easily accessible or available when they are most needed;</Text></Provision><Provision><Text>Whereas Canadians seeking mental health services may have to pay for those services privately;</Text></Provision><Provision><Text>And whereas many Canadians lack private coverage for such services;</Text></Provision></Preamble><Enacts><Provision language-align="yes"><Text>Now, therefore, His Majesty, by and with the advice and consent <Keep>of the</Keep> Senate and House of Commons of Canada, <Keep>enacts</Keep> as follows:</Text></Provision></Enacts></Introduction><Body><Heading level="1"><MarginalNote><HistoricalNote>R.S., c. E-15</HistoricalNote></MarginalNote><TitleText>Excise Tax Act
</TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><Label>1</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The portion of the definition <DefinedTermEn>practitioner</DefinedTermEn> in section 1 of Part II of Schedule V to the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Excise Tax Act</XRefExternal> before paragraph (b) is replaced with the following:</Text><AmendedText><SectionPiece><Definition><Text><DefinedTermEn>practitioner</DefinedTermEn>, in respect of a supply of optometric, chiropractic, physiotherapy, chiropodic, podiatric, osteopathic, audiological, speech-language pathology, occupational therapy, psychological, <Ins>psychotherapy, mental health counselling</Ins>, midwifery, dietetic, acupuncture or naturopathic services, means a person who</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>practises the profession of optometry, chiropractic, physiotherapy, chiropody, podiatry, osteopathy, audiology, speech-language pathology, occupational therapy, psychology, <Ins>psychotherapy, mental health counselling</Ins>, midwifery, dietetics, acupuncture or naturopathy as a naturopathic doctor, as the case may be,</Text></Paragraph></Definition></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Section 7 of Part II of Schedule V to the Act is amended by adding the following after paragraph (j):</Text><AmendedText><SectionPiece><Paragraph change="ins"><Label>(j.1)</Label><Text>psychotherapy services;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph change="ins"><Label>(j.2)</Label><Text>mental health counselling services;</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection></Section><Heading level="1"><TitleText>Coming into Force</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Six months after royal assent</MarginalNote><Label>2</Label><Text>This Act comes into force six months after the day on which it receives royal assent.</Text></Section></Body></Bill>