<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><Bill bill-origin="commons" bill-type="private-public" xml:lang="en" date-time="2023-03-31 12:55:40"><Identification><BillNumber>C-331</BillNumber><Parliament><Session>1</Session><Number>44</Number><RegnalYear><Year-s>70-71</Year-s><Monarch>Elizabeth II – 1 Charles III</Monarch></RegnalYear><Year-s>2021-2022-2023</Year-s></Parliament><LongTitle>An Act to amend the Canadian Security Intelligence Service Act (duty of candour)</LongTitle><ShortTitle status="unofficial" /><RunningHead>An Act to amend the Canadian Security Intelligence Service Act (duty of candour)</RunningHead><BillHistory><Stages stage="first-reading-house"><Date><YYYY>2023</YYYY><MM>5</MM><DD>2</DD></Date></Stages></BillHistory><BillSponsor><Emphasis style="smallcaps">Mrs. Zahid</Emphasis></BillSponsor><BillRefNumber date-time="2023-03-31">441224</BillRefNumber></Identification><Introduction><Summary><TitleText>SUMMARY</TitleText><Provision><Text>This enactment amends the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Canadian Security Intelligence Service Act</XRefExternal> to provide that the Canadian Security Intelligence Service shall report on breaches of its duty of candour to the courts. It also amends the oath of office taken by the Director and employees to include a solemn promise to fulfill that duty.</Text></Provision></Summary><Enacts><Provision><Text>His Majesty, by and with the advice and consent <Keep>of the</Keep> Senate and House of Commons of Canada, <Keep>enacts</Keep> as follows:</Text></Provision></Enacts></Introduction><Body><Heading level="1"><MarginalNote><HistoricalNote>R.S., c. C-23</HistoricalNote></MarginalNote><TitleText>Canadian Security Intelligence Service Act</TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><Label>1</Label><Text>Section 6 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Canadian Security Intelligence Service Act</XRefExternal> is amended by adding the following after subsection (6):</Text><AmendedText><Subsection change="ins"><MarginalNote>Breaches of duty of candour</MarginalNote><Label>(7)</Label><Text>The reports shall also include</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>the number of times that the Service has or may have breached its duty of candour to the courts in the performance of its duties and functions under this Act in relation to applications for warrants; </Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>a description of each breach; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(c)</Label><Text>information on any remedial measures taken by the Service in response to each breach.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>2</Label><Text>Section 20.2 of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><Section><MarginalNote>Report</MarginalNote><Label>20.2</Label><Text>The Service shall, within three months after the end of each calendar year, submit to the Minister a report of the activities of the Service during the preceding calendar year, <Ins>including a general description of the information provided under subsection 6(7) for the same period</Ins>, and the Minister shall cause the report to be laid before each House of Parliament on any of the first 15 days on which that House is sitting after the Minister receives it.</Text></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>3</Label><Text>The oath of office set out in the schedule to the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><ScheduleFormHeading><TitleText>Oath of Office</TitleText></ScheduleFormHeading><List><Item><Text>I, ………………….. , swear that I will faithfully and impartially to the best of my abilities perform the duties required of me as (the Director, an employee) of the Canadian Security Intelligence Service, <Ins>including duties owed to the courts, such as the duty of candour</Ins>. So help me God.</Text></Item></List></AmendedText></Section></Body></Bill>