<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><Bill bill-origin="commons" bill-type="private-public" xml:lang="en" date-time="2020-08-12 13:07:41"><Identification><BillNumber>C-332</BillNumber><Parliament><Session>1</Session><Number>44</Number><RegnalYear><Year-s>70-71</Year-s><Monarch>Elizabeth II – 1-2 Charles III</Monarch></RegnalYear><Year-s>2021-2022-2023-2024</Year-s></Parliament><LongTitle>An Act to amend the Criminal Code (coercive <Ins>control of intimate partner</Ins>)</LongTitle><ShortTitle status="unofficial" /><RunningHead>An Act to amend the Criminal Code (coercive control of intimate partner)</RunningHead><BillHistory><Stages stage="report-house"><Date><YYYY>2024</YYYY><MM>3</MM><DD>22</DD></Date><StageText>Reprinted as amended by the Standing Committee on Justice and Human Rights as a working copy for the use of the House of Commons at Report Stage and as reported to the House on March 22, 2024</StageText></Stages></BillHistory><BillSponsor><Emphasis style="smallcaps">Ms. Collins</Emphasis></BillSponsor><BillRefNumber date-time="2020-08-12">441268</BillRefNumber></Identification><Introduction><Summary><TitleText>SUMMARY</TitleText><Provision><Text>This enactment amends the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Criminal Code</XRefExternal> to create an offence of exercising coercive control of an intimate partner by engaging in a pattern of conduct that consists of any combination, or any repeated instances, of any of the following acts: using, attempting to use or threatening to use violence against certain persons, coercing or attempting to coerce the intimate partner to engage in sexual activity or engaging in other conduct that could reasonably be expected to cause the intimate partner to believe that their safety, or the safety of a person known to them, is threatened.</Text></Provision><Provision language-align="yes"><Text>It also makes consequential amendments to other Acts.</Text></Provision></Summary><Enacts><Provision><Text>His Majesty, by and with the advice and consent <Keep>of the</Keep> Senate and House of Commons of Canada, <Keep>enacts</Keep> as follows:</Text></Provision></Enacts></Introduction><Body><Heading level="1"><MarginalNote><HistoricalNote>R.S., c. 46</HistoricalNote></MarginalNote><TitleText>Criminal Code</TitleText></Heading><Section change="ins" type="amending"><Label>0.1</Label><Text>Paragraph 109(1)(b) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Criminal Code</XRefExternal> is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>an offence under subsection 85(1) (using firearm in commission of offence), 85(2) (using imitation firearm in commission of offence), 95(1) (possession of prohibited or restricted firearm with ammunition), 99(1) (weapons trafficking), 100(1) (possession for purpose of weapons trafficking), 102(1) (making automatic firearm), 102.1(1) (possession of computer data), 102.1(2) (distribution of computer data), 103(1) (importing or exporting knowing it is unauthorized) or 104.1(1) (altering cartridge magazine) or section 264 (criminal harassment) or 264.01 (coercive control of intimate partner),</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>1</Label><Text>The Act is amended by adding the following after section 264:</Text><AmendedText><Section><MarginalNote>Offence</MarginalNote><Label>264.01</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Everyone commits an offence who engages in a <Ins>pattern of conduct referred to in subsection (2)</Ins></Text><Paragraph change="ins"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>with intent to cause their intimate partner to believe that the intimate partner’s safety is threatened; or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph change="ins"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>being reckless as to whether that pattern could cause their intimate partner to believe that the intimate partner’s safety is threatened.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection change="ins"><MarginalNote>Pattern of conduct</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>A pattern of conduct consists of any combination, or any repeated instances, of any of the following acts:</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>using, attempting to use or threatening to use violence against</Text><Subparagraph><Label>(i)</Label><Text>the intimate partner,</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph><Label>(ii)</Label><Text>any person under the age of 18 who is the intimate partner’s child or who is in the intimate partner’s lawful care or charge,</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph><Label>(iii)</Label><Text>any other person known to the intimate partner, or</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph><Label>(iv)</Label><Text>any animal that is in the care or is the property of the intimate partner;</Text></Subparagraph></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>coercing or attempting to coerce the intimate partner to engage in sexual activity;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(c)</Label><Text>engaging in any other conduct — including conduct listed in any of the following subparagraphs — if, in all the circumstances, the conduct could reasonably be expected to cause the intimate partner to believe that the intimate partner’s safety, or the safety of a person known to them, is threatened:</Text><Subparagraph><Label>(i)</Label><Text>controlling, attempting to control or monitoring the intimate partner’s actions, movements or social interactions, including by a means of telecommunication,</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph><Label>(ii)</Label><Text>controlling or attempting to control the manner in which the intimate partner cares for any person under the age of 18 referred to in subparagraph (a)(ii) or any animal referred to in subparagraph (a)(iv),</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph><Label>(iii)</Label><Text>controlling or attempting to control any matter related to the intimate partner’s employment or education,</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph><Label>(iv)</Label><Text>controlling or attempting to control the intimate partner’s finances or other property or monitoring their finances,</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph><Label>(v)</Label><Text>controlling or attempting to control the intimate partner’s expression of gender, physical appearance, manner of dress, diet, taking of medication or access to health services or to medication,</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph><Label>(vi)</Label><Text>controlling or attempting to control the intimate partner’s expression of their thoughts, their opinions, their religious, spiritual or other beliefs, or their culture, including the intimate partner’s use of their language or their access to their linguistic, religious, spiritual or cultural community,</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph><Label>(vii)</Label><Text>threatening to die by suicide or to self-harm.</Text></Subparagraph></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection change="ins"><MarginalNote>Circumstances</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>The circumstances referred to in paragraph (2)(c) include the nature of the relationship between the accused and the intimate partner, in particular whether the intimate partner is in a position of vulnerability in relation to the accused.</Text></Subsection><Subsection change="ins"><MarginalNote>Punishment</MarginalNote><Label>(4)</Label><Text>Everyone who commits an offence under this section is</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>guilty of an indictable offence and liable to imprisonment for a term of not more than 10 years; or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>guilty of an offence punishable on summary conviction.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection change="ins"><MarginalNote>For greater certainty
</MarginalNote><Label>(5)</Label><Text>For the purposes of this section, and for greater certainty, a person’s safety includes their psychological safety.</Text></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section change="ins" type="amending"><Label>2</Label><Text>Subsection 486.3(2) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><Subsection><MarginalNote>Accused not to cross-examine complainant — certain offences</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>In any proceedings against an accused in respect of an offence under any of sections 264, 264.01, 271, 272 and 273, the judge or justice shall, on application of the prosecutor in respect of a witness who is a victim, or on application of such a witness, order that the accused not personally cross-examine the witness, unless the judge or justice is of the opinion that the proper administration of justice requires the accused to personally conduct the cross-examination. If such an order is made, the judge or justice shall appoint counsel to conduct the cross-examination.</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Section><Section change="ins" type="amending"><Label>3</Label><Text>Paragraph (c) of the definition <DefinedTermEn>secondary designated offence</DefinedTermEn> in section 487.04 of the Act is amended by adding the following after subparagraph (v):</Text><AmendedText><SectionPiece><Subparagraph><Label>(v.1)</Label><Text>section 264.01 (coercive control of intimate partner),</Text></Subparagraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Section><Section change="ins" type="amending"><Label>4</Label><Text>Paragraph (a) of the definition <DefinedTermEn>secondary offence</DefinedTermEn> in subsection 490.011(1) of the Act is amended by adding the following after subparagraph (ix):</Text><AmendedText><SectionPiece><Subparagraph><Label>(ix.1)</Label><Text>section 264.01 (coercive control of intimate partner),</Text></Subparagraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Section><Section change="ins" type="amending"><Label>5</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Subsection 515(4.1) of the Act is amended by adding the following after paragraph (b):</Text><AmendedText><SectionPiece><Paragraph><MarginalNote> </MarginalNote><Label>(b.01)</Label><Text>an offence under section 264.01 (coercive control of intimate partner),</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Paragraph 515(4.3)(b) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>an offence described in section 264, 264.01 or 423.1 or subsection 423.2(1);</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection></Section><Heading level="1" change="ins"><TitleText>Consequential Amendments</TitleText></Heading><Heading level="2" change="ins"><MarginalNote><HistoricalNote>R.S., c. E-15</HistoricalNote></MarginalNote><TitleText>Excise Tax Act</TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending" change="ins"><Label>6</Label><Text>Clause 295(5.04)(a)(i)(D) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Excise Tax Act</XRefExternal> is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><SectionPiece><Clause><Label>(D)</Label><Text>sections 144, 264, 264.01, 271, 279, 279.02, 281 and 333.1, paragraphs 334(a) and 348(1)(e) and sections 349, 435 and 462.31 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Criminal Code</XRefExternal>,</Text></Clause></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Section><Heading level="2" change="ins"><MarginalNote><HistoricalNote>R.S., c. N-5</HistoricalNote></MarginalNote><TitleText>National Defence Act</TitleText></Heading><Section change="ins" type="amending"><Label>7</Label><Text>Subsection 183.3(2) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">National Defence Act</XRefExternal> is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><Subsection><MarginalNote>Accused not to cross-examine complainant — certain offences</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>In proceedings against an accused person in respect of an offence punishable under section 130 that is an offence under section 264, 264.01, 271, 272 or 273 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Criminal Code</XRefExternal>, a military judge shall, on application of the prosecutor in respect of a witness who is a victim, or on application of such a witness, order that the accused person not personally cross-examine the witness, unless the military judge is of the opinion that the proper administration of military justice requires the accused person to personally conduct the cross-examination. If such an order is made, the military judge shall direct the Director of Defence Counsel Services to provide counsel to conduct the cross-examination.</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Section><Heading level="2" change="ins"><MarginalNote><HistoricalNote>R.S., c. 1 (5th Supp.)</HistoricalNote></MarginalNote><TitleText>Income Tax Act</TitleText></Heading><Section change="ins" type="amending"><Label>8</Label><Text>Clause 241(9.5)(a)(i)(D) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Income Tax Act</XRefExternal> is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><SectionPiece><Clause><Label>(D)</Label><Text>sections 144, 264, 264.01, 271, 279, 279.02, 281 and 333.1, paragraphs 334(a) and 348(1)(e) and sections 349, 435 and 462.31 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Criminal Code</XRefExternal>,</Text></Clause></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Section><Heading level="2" change="ins"><MarginalNote><HistoricalNote>1995, c. 39</HistoricalNote></MarginalNote><TitleText>Firearms Act</TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending" change="ins"><Label>9</Label><Text>Subparagraph 5(2)(a)(iii) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Firearms Act</XRefExternal> is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><SectionPiece><Subparagraph><Label>(iii)</Label><Text>an offence under section 264 (criminal harassment) or 264.01 (coercive control of intimate partner) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Criminal Code</XRefExternal>,</Text></Subparagraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Section><Heading level="2" change="ins"><MarginalNote><HistoricalNote>2002, c. 22</HistoricalNote></MarginalNote><TitleText>Excise Act, 2001</TitleText></Heading><Section change="ins" type="amending"><Label>10</Label><Text>Clause 211(6.4)(a)(i)(D) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Excise Act, 2001</XRefExternal> is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><SectionPiece><Clause><Label>(D)</Label><Text>sections 144, 264, 264.01, 271, 279, 279.02, 281 and 333.1, paragraphs 334(a) and 348(1)(e) and sections 349, 435 and 462.31 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Criminal Code</XRefExternal>,</Text></Clause></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Section><Heading level="1" change="ins"><TitleText>Coordinating Amendment</TitleText></Heading><Section change="ins" type="amending"><MarginalNote>2023, c. 32</MarginalNote><Label>11</Label><Text>On the first day on which both subsection 13.3(1) of <XRefExternal reference-type="act">An Act to amend certain Acts and to make certain consequential amendments (firearms)</XRefExternal>, chapter 32 of the Statutes of Canada, 2023, and subsection 5(1) of this Act are in force, subsection 515(4.1) of the French version of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Criminal Code</XRefExternal> is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><Subsection><MarginalNote>Condition additionnelle</MarginalNote><Label>(4.1)</Label><Text><Language xml:lang="fr">Lorsqu’il rend une ordonnance en vertu du paragraphe (2) dans le cas d’une infraction perpétrée avec usage, tentative ou menace de violence contre autrui, d’une infraction de terrorisme, de l’infraction visée aux articles 264 (harcèlement criminel), 264.01 (contrôle coercitif d’un partenaire intime) ou 423.1 (intimidation d’une personne associée au système judiciaire) ou au paragraphe 423.2(1) (intimidation — services de santé), d’une infraction à l’un des articles 9 à 14 de la <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Loi sur le cannabis</XRefExternal>, d’une infraction à l’un des articles 5 à 7 de la <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Loi réglementant certaines drogues et autres substances</XRefExternal>, d’une infraction relative à une arme à feu, une arbalète, une arme prohibée, une arme à autorisation restreinte, un dispositif prohibé, une pièce d’arme à feu, des munitions, des munitions prohibées ou des substances explosives, d’une infraction visée au paragraphe 20(1) de la <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Loi sur la protection de l’information</XRefExternal>, ou d’une infraction visée aux paragraphes 21(1) ou 22(1) ou à l’article 23 de cette loi commise à l’égard d’une infraction visée au paragraphe 20(1) de cette loi, le juge de paix doit, s’il en arrive à la conclusion qu’il est souhaitable de le faire pour la sécurité du prévenu, de la victime ou de toute autre personne, assortir l’ordonnance d’une condition lui interdisant, jusqu’à ce qu’il soit jugé conformément à la loi, d’avoir en sa possession de tels objets ou l’un ou plusieurs de ceux-ci.</Language></Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Section><Heading level="1" change="ins"><TitleText>Coming into Force</TitleText></Heading><Section change="ins" type="amending"><MarginalNote>Order in council
</MarginalNote><Label>12</Label><Text>Sections 0.1 to 10 come into force on a day to be fixed by order of the Governor in Council.</Text></Section></Body></Bill>