<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><Bill bill-origin="commons" bill-type="private-public" xml:lang="en" date-time="2022-11-07 08:40:30"><Identification><BillNumber>C-330</BillNumber><Parliament><Session>1</Session><Number>44</Number><RegnalYear><Year-s>70-71</Year-s><Monarch>Elizabeth II â 1 Charles III</Monarch></RegnalYear><Year-s>2021-2022-2023</Year-s></Parliament><LongTitle>An Act to amend the Canada Labour Code (successor rights and obligations â airports)</LongTitle><ShortTitle status="unofficial" /><RunningHead>An Act to amend the Canada Labour Code (successor rights and obligations â airports)</RunningHead><BillHistory><Stages stage="first-reading-house"><Date><YYYY>2023</YYYY><MM>4</MM><DD>20</DD></Date></Stages></BillHistory><BillSponsor><Emphasis style="smallcaps">Mr. Boulerice</Emphasis></BillSponsor><BillRefNumber date-time="2022-11-07">441081</BillRefNumber></Identification><Introduction><Summary><TitleText>SUMMARY</TitleText><Provision><Text>This enactment amends the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Canada Labour Code</XRefExternal> to provide that an employer who is an airport authority or a provider of services to an airport authority and who replaces a previous contractor must observe the certification of the previous trade union and the terms and conditions of employment, rights and privileges of the employees of the previous contractor.</Text></Provision></Summary><Enacts><Provision><Text>His Majesty, by and with the advice and consent <Keep>of the</Keep> Senate and House of Commons of Canada, <Keep>enacts</Keep> as follows:</Text></Provision></Enacts></Introduction><Body><Heading level="1"><MarginalNote><HistoricalNote>R.S., c. L-2</HistoricalNote></MarginalNote><TitleText>Canada Labour Code</TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><Label>1</Label><Text>Section 44 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Canada Labour Code</XRefExternal> is amended by adding the following after subsection (3):</Text><AmendedText><Subsection change="ins"><MarginalNote>Clarification</MarginalNote><Label>(4)</Label><Text>This section applies to an employer who is an airport authority or a provider of services to an airport authority.</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>2</Label><Text>Section 47.3 of the Act is amended by adding the following after subsection (2):</Text><AmendedText><Subsection change="ins"><MarginalNote>Terms and conditions of employment, rights and privileges</MarginalNote><Label>(2.1)</Label><Text>An employer who succeeds a previous contractor and who is an airport authority or a provider of services to an airport authority in accordance with a contract or other arrangement must observe the certification of the previous trade union and the terms and conditions of employment, rights and privileges of the employees of the previous contractor.</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Section></Body></Bill>