<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><Bill bill-origin="commons" bill-type="private-public" xml:lang="en" date-time="2023-06-13 17:06:16"><Identification><BillNumber>C-348</BillNumber><Parliament><Session>1</Session><Number>44</Number><RegnalYear><Year-s>70-71</Year-s><Monarch>Elizabeth II – 1 Charles III</Monarch></RegnalYear><Year-s>2021-2022-2023</Year-s></Parliament><LongTitle>An Act to establish Somali Heritage Month</LongTitle><ShortTitle status="unofficial">Somali Heritage Month Act</ShortTitle><RunningHead>An Act to establish Somali Heritage Month</RunningHead><BillHistory><Stages stage="first-reading-house"><Date><YYYY>2023</YYYY><MM>6</MM><DD>21</DD></Date></Stages></BillHistory><BillSponsor><Emphasis style="smallcaps">Mr. Baker</Emphasis></BillSponsor><BillRefNumber date-time="2023-06-13">441282</BillRefNumber></Identification><Introduction><Summary><TitleText>SUMMARY</TitleText><Provision><Text>This enactment designates the month of July as “Somali Heritage Month”.</Text></Provision></Summary><Preamble><Provision><MarginalNote>Preamble</MarginalNote><Text>Whereas Canada’s strength is reflected in the diversity of its population and of its local communities; </Text></Provision><Provision><Text>Whereas today Canada is home to many Canadians of Somali heritage;</Text></Provision><Provision><Text>Whereas Canada and Somalia are linked by strong people-to-people ties and Canada is home to one of the world’s largest Somali diaspora communities; </Text></Provision><Provision><Text>Whereas Canadians of Somali descent have left and continue to leave a historic mark on Canada, with contributions that span communities across the country and are reflected in Canada’s economic, political, social and cultural life;</Text></Provision><Provision><Text>Whereas Parliament wishes to recognize that Canadians of Somali descent have and continue to make significant contributions to Canada, and wishes to better inform Canadians about those contributions by recognizing and celebrating them;</Text></Provision><Provision><Text>Whereas Canadians of Somali descent celebrate Somalia’s Independence Day each year on July 1; </Text></Provision><Provision><Text>And whereas several celebrations also take place in Canada in July that highlight the rich culture and heritage of the Somali people; </Text></Provision></Preamble><Enacts><Provision><Text>Now, therefore, His Majesty, by and with the advice and consent <Keep>of the</Keep> Senate and House of Commons of Canada, <Keep>enacts</Keep> as follows:</Text></Provision></Enacts></Introduction><Body><Heading level="1"><TitleText>Short Title</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Short title</MarginalNote><Label>1</Label><Text>This Act may be cited as the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Somali Heritage Month Act</XRefExternal>.</Text></Section><Heading level="1"><TitleText>Somali Heritage Month</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Somali Heritage Month</MarginalNote><Label>2</Label><Text>Throughout Canada, in each year, the month of July is to be known as “Somali Heritage Month”.</Text></Section></Body></Bill>