<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><Bill bill-origin="commons" bill-type="private-public" xml:lang="en" date-time="2023-06-09 14:11:03"><Identification><BillNumber>C-344</BillNumber><Parliament><Session>1</Session><Number>44</Number><RegnalYear><Year-s>70-71</Year-s><Monarch>Elizabeth II – 1 Charles III</Monarch></RegnalYear><Year-s>2021-2022-2023</Year-s></Parliament><LongTitle>An Act to amend the Wrecked, Abandoned or Hazardous Vessels Act (national strategy respecting abandoned vessels)</LongTitle><ShortTitle status="unofficial" /><RunningHead>An Act to amend the Wrecked, Abandoned or Hazardous Vessels Act (national strategy respecting abandoned vessels)</RunningHead><BillHistory><Stages stage="first-reading-house"><Date><YYYY>2023</YYYY><MM>6</MM><DD>15</DD></Date></Stages></BillHistory><BillSponsor><Emphasis style="smallcaps">Ms. Barron</Emphasis></BillSponsor><BillRefNumber date-time="2023-06-09">441280</BillRefNumber></Identification><Introduction><Summary><TitleText>SUMMARY</TitleText><Provision><Text>This enactment amends the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Wrecked, Abandoned or Hazardous Vessels Act</XRefExternal> to provide for the development and implementation of a national strategy to address the abandonment of vessels.</Text></Provision></Summary><Enacts><Provision><Text>His Majesty, by and with the advice and consent <Keep>of the</Keep> Senate and House of Commons of Canada, <Keep>enacts</Keep> as follows:</Text></Provision></Enacts></Introduction><Body><Heading level="1"><MarginalNote><HistoricalNote>2019, c. 1</HistoricalNote></MarginalNote><TitleText>Wrecked, Abandoned or Hazardous Vessels Act</TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><Label>1</Label><Text>Section 2 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Wrecked, Abandoned or Hazardous Vessels Act</XRefExternal> is amended by adding the following definition in alphabetical order:</Text><AmendedText change="ins"><SectionPiece><Definition><Text><DefinedTermEn>Indigenous governing body</DefinedTermEn> means a council, government or other entity that is authorized to act on behalf of an Indigenous group, community or people that holds rights recognized and affirmed by section 35 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Constitution Act, 1982</XRefExternal>. (<DefinedTermFr>corps dirigeant autochtone</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Definition></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>2</Label><Text>The Act is amended by adding the following after section 129:</Text><AmendedText change="ins"><Heading level="1"><Label>PART 6.1</Label><TitleText>National Strategy Respecting Abandoned Vessels</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>National strategy</MarginalNote><Label>129.1</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The Minister must develop and implement a national strategy to address the abandonment of vessels.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Content</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The strategy must include measures to</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>develop a system to promptly and effectively identify the owners of vessels;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>evaluate the adequacy of fees in respect of the disposition cost of vessels;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(c)</Label><Text>develop a turn-in program that includes the designation of disposal areas for vessels;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(d)</Label><Text>develop innovative recycling initiatives for wrecked vessels and their components, along with enforceable standards to reduce environmental and social impacts;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(e)</Label><Text>develop a mooring plan for vessels;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(f)</Label><Text>provide support to local businesses offering salvage services; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(g)</Label><Text>improve the process for disposing of wrecked and abandoned vessels.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Content</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>The strategy must also</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>include an assessment of the adequacy of the resources, including those of the Canadian Coast Guard, dedicated to preventing and responding to the abandonment of vessels; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>provide for, where appropriate, cooperation and partnership with provincial governments and Indigenous governing bodies on the implementation of any measures referred to in subsection (2), and for an assessment of the timelines required to do so.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection></Section><Section change="ins"><MarginalNote>Report to Parliament</MarginalNote><Label>129.2</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Within one year after the day on which this Act comes into force, the Minister must prepare a report setting out the national strategy and the schedule for its implementation and cause it to be tabled in each House of Parliament on any of the first 15 days on which that House is sitting after it is completed.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Publication of report</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The Minister must publish the report on the website of the Department of Transport within 30 days after the day on which the report is tabled in both Houses of Parliament.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section change="ins"><MarginalNote>Annual report</MarginalNote><Label>129.3</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The Minister must, during the year in which the second anniversary of the coming into force of this Act occurs and each year after that, prepare a report on the progress made in implementing the national strategy and any changes made to it.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Tabling of report</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The Minister must cause the report to be tabled in each House of Parliament on any of the first 15 days on which that House is sitting after it is completed.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Publication of report</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>The Minister must publish the report on the website of the Department of Transport within 30 days after the day on which the report is tabled in both Houses of Parliament.</Text></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Section></Body></Bill>