<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><Bill bill-origin="commons" bill-type="private-public" xml:lang="en" date-time="2023-04-26 12:44:56"><Identification><BillNumber>C-349</BillNumber><Parliament><Session>1</Session><Number>44</Number><RegnalYear><Year-s>70-71</Year-s><Monarch>Elizabeth II – 1 Charles III</Monarch></RegnalYear><Year-s>2021-2022-2023</Year-s></Parliament><LongTitle>An Act to establish National Rabies Awareness Day and to provide for the development of a national strategy for combating rabies in Canada</LongTitle><ShortTitle status="unofficial" /><RunningHead>National Strategy for the Eradication of Rabies Act</RunningHead><BillHistory><Stages stage="first-reading-house"><Date><YYYY>2023</YYYY><MM>6</MM><DD>21</DD></Date></Stages></BillHistory><BillSponsor><Emphasis style="smallcaps">Mr. Hanley</Emphasis></BillSponsor><BillRefNumber date-time="2023-04-26">441247</BillRefNumber></Identification><Introduction><Summary><TitleText>SUMMARY</TitleText><Provision><Text>This enactment designates the 28th day of September in each year as “National Rabies Awareness Day”. It also provides for the development of a national strategy to promote measures to combat rabies, particularly in domesticated canine and other animal populations, within Canada.</Text></Provision></Summary><Preamble><Provision><MarginalNote>Preamble</MarginalNote><Text>Whereas, in northern, remote and rural regions of Canada, Canadians and their domesticated animals are at high risk of exposure to rabies, as the virus circulates freely in Arctic fox and red fox populations and roaming dogs that come into contact with rabid wildlife contract rabies, thereby threatening public safety;</Text></Provision><Provision><Text>Whereas northern, remote and rural regions of Canada do not have regular access to veterinary services and decades of periodic access to veterinary services, delivered by mobile veterinary outreach programs, have not proven successful in addressing the risk of rabies in these regions in the long term;</Text></Provision><Provision><Text>Whereas the lack of adequate rabies prevention and control in the north also poses a significant problem for southern Canada, both in cities and rural areas, because of the growing movement of unwanted dogs from northern communities to adoptive homes in the south, which risks the introduction of rabies to pets and livestock in southern regions and the resulting health and economic costs;</Text></Provision><Provision><Text>And whereas Parliament considers that creating a national strategy for combatting rabies is in the best interest of all Canadians;</Text></Provision></Preamble><Enacts><Provision language-align="yes"><Text>Now, therefore, His Majesty, by and with the advice and consent of the Senate and House of Commons of Canada, enacts as follows:</Text></Provision></Enacts></Introduction><Body><Heading level="1"><TitleText>Short Title</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Short title</MarginalNote><Label>1</Label><Text>This Act may be cited as the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">National Strategy for the Eradication of Rabies Act</XRefExternal>.</Text></Section><Heading level="1"><TitleText>Interpretation</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Definitions</MarginalNote><Label>2</Label><Text>The following definitions apply in this Act.</Text><Definition><Text><DefinedTermEn>Indigenous governing body</DefinedTermEn> means a council, government or other entity that is authorized to act on behalf of an Indigenous group, community or people that holds rights recognized and affirmed by section 35 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Constitution Act, 1982</XRefExternal>. (<DefinedTermFr>corps dirigeant autochtone</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Definition><Definition><Text><DefinedTermEn>Minister</DefinedTermEn> means the Minister of Agriculture and Agri-Food. (<DefinedTermFr>ministre</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Definition></Section><Heading level="1"><TitleText>National Rabies Awareness Day</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Designation</MarginalNote><Label>3</Label><Text>Throughout Canada, in each year, the 28th day of September is to be known as “National Rabies Awareness Day”.</Text></Section><Heading level="1"><TitleText>National Strategy for Combating Rabies</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Development</MarginalNote><Label>4</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The Minister must, in consultation with provincial government representatives responsible for rabies management and animal control, Indigenous governing bodies, representatives from northern, remote and rural communities and other relevant stakeholders, develop a national strategy for combating rabies which will support improved access to rabies testing, vaccination, prevention and treatment with the objective of combating the disease in domesticated canine and other animal populations in Canada and work with communities to reduce the risk of rabies.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Content</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The strategy must include measures designed to achieve the following objectives:</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>support better access to rabies vaccines and identify solutions to the logistical challenges of delivering rabies vaccines to northern communities;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>establish lay rabies vaccination programs where appropriate and, in particular, in northern communities;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(c)</Label><Text>enhance rabies surveillance capabilities in northern communities, namely by improving the availability of direct rapid immunohistochemical testing;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(d)</Label><Text>support community-led initiatives that aim to</Text><Subparagraph><Label>(i)</Label><Text>reduce the risk of rabies and spread of rabies amongst canine and other animal populations, including education campaigns and efforts to reduce dog aggression, and</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph><Label>(ii)</Label><Text>humanely address animal overpopulation where appropriate, including through non-surgical contraception;</Text></Subparagraph></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(e)</Label><Text>study the barriers to the use of non-surgical contraception for animals and for dogs in particular; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(f)</Label><Text>monitor international developments in rabies treatment and prevention programs and determine their relevancy for the Canadian context.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Considerations</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>When developing the strategy under subsection (1), the Minister must</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>offer to collaborate with Indigenous governing bodies and northern, remote and rural communities in relation to the development of measures under subsection (2), where appropriate; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>use a multisectoral and multidisciplinary collaborative approach, known as a One Health approach, that focuses on the human, animal, plant and ecosystem health and welfare interface.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection></Section><Heading level="1"><TitleText>Reports to Parliament</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Tabling of strategy</MarginalNote><Label>5</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Within two years after the day on which this Act comes into force, the Minister must prepare a report setting out the national strategy and cause it to be tabled in each House of Parliament on any of the first 15 days on which that House is sitting after it is completed.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Publication</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The Minister must publish the report on the website of the Department of Agriculture and Agri-Food within 10 days after the day on which it is tabled in both Houses of Parliament.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Review</MarginalNote><Label>6</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Within two years after the day on which the report referred to in section 5 is tabled in both Houses of Parliament, the Minister must undertake a review of the strategy and prepare a report, setting out the Minister’s conclusions and recommendations, on the effectiveness of the strategy and on the current state of prevention and treatment of rabies in Canada and must cause the report to be tabled in each House of Parliament on any of the first 15 days on which that House is sitting after it is completed.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Consultations</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>In reviewing the strategy, the Minister must consult with relevant stakeholders, including those referred to in subsection 4(1).</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Publication</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>The Minister must publish the report on the website of the Department of Agriculture and Agri-Food within 10 days after the day on which it is tabled in both Houses of Parliament.</Text></Subsection></Section></Body></Bill>