<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><Bill bill-origin="commons" bill-type="private-public" xml:lang="en" date-time="2023-06-07 17:14:57"><Identification><BillNumber>C-353</BillNumber><Parliament><Session>1</Session><Number>44</Number><RegnalYear><Year-s>70-71</Year-s><Monarch>Elizabeth II – 1-2 Charles III</Monarch></RegnalYear><Year-s>2021-2022-2023</Year-s></Parliament><LongTitle>An Act to provide for the imposition of restrictive measures against foreign hostage takers and those who practice arbitrary detention in state-to-state relations and to make related amendments to the Proceeds of Crime (Money Laundering) and Terrorist Financing Act and the Immigration and Refugee Protection Act</LongTitle><ShortTitle status="unofficial" /><RunningHead>Foreign Hostage Takers Accountability Act</RunningHead><BillHistory><Stages stage="first-reading-house"><Date><YYYY>2023</YYYY><MM>9</MM><DD>19</DD></Date></Stages></BillHistory><BillSponsor><Emphasis style="smallcaps">Ms. Lantsman</Emphasis></BillSponsor><BillRefNumber date-time="2023-06-07">441262</BillRefNumber></Identification><Introduction><Summary><TitleText>SUMMARY</TitleText><Provision><Text>This enactment authorizes the Government of Canada to take restrictive measures against foreign nationals, foreign states and foreign entities that engage in hostage taking or arbitrary detention in state-to-state relations of Canadians or eligible protected persons outside Canada. It also requires the Minister of Foreign Affairs to provide assistance to the families of such hostages and detained individuals and to establish and implement programs to encourage cooperation for the release of such Canadians and eligible protected persons. Finally, this enactment makes related amendments to the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Proceeds of Crime (Money Laundering) and Terrorist Financing Act</XRefExternal> and the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Immigration and Refugee Protection Act</XRefExternal>.</Text></Provision></Summary><Preamble><Provision><MarginalNote>Preamble </MarginalNote><Text>Whereas terrorist organizations, criminal groups and other state and non-state actors who take hostages for financial, political or other gains threaten the integrity of the international political system and the safety of Canadian nationals and other persons abroad;</Text></Provision><Provision><Text>Whereas autocratic regimes continue to arbitrarily detain Canadians or nationals of Canada’s allies, sometimes under the guise of legal proceedings, to gain leverage and undermine the country’s sovereignty in domestic and foreign affairs;</Text></Provision><Provision><Text>Whereas hostage taking and the arbitrary detention of Canadian nationals in state-to-state relations are acts that undermine the rule of law and threaten Canada's national security and foreign policy;</Text></Provision><Provision><Text>Whereas Canadian nationals deserve to be protected by the Government of Canada from foreign threats and interference;</Text></Provision><Provision><Text>Whereas timely intelligence information regarding Canadian nationals held hostage can be vital in securing the safe return of those hostages, but can be extremely difficult to obtain;</Text></Provision><Provision><Text>Whereas human rights and the rule of law are integral to international law and Canada has repeatedly asserted its commitment to promoting international justice and respect for human rights;</Text></Provision><Provision><Text>Whereas Canada signed and ratified the International Convention against the Taking of Hostages, adopted by resolution 34/146 of the General Assembly of the United Nations on December 17, 1979;</Text></Provision><Provision><Text>Whereas hostage taking is a criminal offence in Canada;</Text></Provision><Provision><Text>Whereas Canada launched the Declaration Against Arbitrary Detention in State-to-State Relations on February 15, 2021, in Ottawa;</Text></Provision><Provision><Text>And whereas Canadians continue to be held hostage and arbitrarily detained in foreign jurisdictions and are at risk of being tortured or killed;</Text></Provision></Preamble><Enacts><Provision><Text>Now, therefore, His Majesty, by and with the advice and consent of the Senate and House of Commons of Canada, enacts as follows:</Text></Provision></Enacts></Introduction><Body><Heading level="1"><TitleText>Short Title</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Short title</MarginalNote><Label>1</Label><Text>This Act may be cited as the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Foreign Hostage Takers Accountability Act</XRefExternal>.</Text></Section><Heading level="1"><TitleText>Interpretation</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Definitions</MarginalNote><Label>2</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The following definitions apply in this Act.</Text><Definition><Text><DefinedTermEn>Canadian corporation</DefinedTermEn> means a corporation incorporated or continued by or under the laws of Canada or of a province. (<DefinedTermFr>personne morale canadienne</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Definition><Definition><Text><DefinedTermEn>Canadian national</DefinedTermEn> means a Canadian citizen or a <DefinitionRef>permanent resident</DefinitionRef> within the meaning of subsection 2(1) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Immigration and Refugee Protection Act</XRefExternal>. (<DefinedTermFr>ressortissant canadien</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Definition><Definition><Text><DefinedTermEn>eligible protected person</DefinedTermEn> means an individual who is a protected person within the meaning of subsection 95(2) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Immigration and Refugee Protection Act</XRefExternal> and who has not been determined to be inadmissible under that Act on security grounds, on grounds of violating human or international rights or on grounds of serious criminality, criminality or organized criminality. (<DefinedTermFr>personne protégée admissible</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Definition><Definition><Text><DefinedTermEn>entity</DefinedTermEn> means, other than in the definition <DefinitionRef>State or entity</DefinitionRef>, a corporation, trust, partnership, fund, or unincorporated association or organization. (<DefinedTermFr>entité</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Definition><Definition><Text><DefinedTermEn>foreign national</DefinedTermEn> means an individual who is not</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>a Canadian national; or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>a national of a State or entity with which Canada is party to an <DefinitionRef>extradition agreement</DefinitionRef> as defined in section 2 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Extradition Act</XRefExternal> or whose name is set out in the schedule to that Act. (<DefinedTermFr>étranger</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Paragraph></Definition><Definition><Text><DefinedTermEn>foreign state</DefinedTermEn> means a country other than Canada, and includes any of its political subdivisions, its government and any of its departments, the government or any department of any of its political subdivisions, any of its agencies and any agency of any of its political subdivisions, but does not include a State or entity with which Canada is party to an <DefinitionRef>extradition agreement</DefinitionRef> as defined in section 2 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Extradition Act</XRefExternal> or whose name is set out in the schedule to that Act. (<DefinedTermFr>État étranger</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Definition><Definition><Text><DefinedTermEn>hostage taking</DefinedTermEn> has the meaning assigned by subsection 279.1(1) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Criminal Code</XRefExternal>. (<DefinedTermFr>prendre en otage</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Definition><Definition><Text><DefinedTermEn>judge</DefinedTermEn> means a judge of a superior court of the province where property described in an order made under paragraph 5(1)(b) is situated. (<DefinedTermFr>juge</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Definition><Definition><Text><DefinedTermEn>Minister</DefinedTermEn> means the Minister of Foreign Affairs. (<DefinedTermFr>ministre</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Definition><Definition><Text><DefinedTermEn>person</DefinedTermEn> means, other than in the definition <DefinitionRef>eligible protected person</DefinitionRef>, an individual, entity or foreign state. (<DefinedTermFr>personne</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Definition><Definition><Text><DefinedTermEn>property</DefinedTermEn> means any type of property, whether real or personal or immovable or movable, or tangible or intangible or corporeal or incorporeal, and includes money, funds, currency, digital assets and virtual currency. (<DefinedTermFr>bien</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Definition><Definition><Text><DefinedTermEn>State or entity</DefinedTermEn> has the same meaning as in section 2 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Extradition Act</XRefExternal>. (<DefinedTermFr>État ou entité</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Definition></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Arbitrary detention in state-to-state relations</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>For the purposes of this Act, an individual is arbitrarily detained in state-to-state relations when a person arbitrarily arrests or detains the individual to compel action from, or exercise leverage over, a foreign government.</Text></Subsection></Section><Heading level="1"><TitleText>His Majesty</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Binding on His Majesty</MarginalNote><Label>3</Label><Text>This Act is binding on His Majesty in right of Canada or a province.</Text></Section><Heading level="1"><TitleText>Purposes of Act</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Purposes</MarginalNote><Label>4</Label><Text>The purposes of this Act are</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>to enable the Government of Canada to take restrictive measures against foreign nationals, foreign states or foreign entities that engage in hostage taking or arbitrary detention in state-to-state relations of Canadian nationals or eligible protected persons outside Canada;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>to ensure that families of such hostages and detained individuals receive timely information and assistance; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(c)</Label><Text>to encourage individuals to cooperate with the Government of Canada to secure the release of such hostages and detained individuals.</Text></Paragraph></Section><Heading level="1"><TitleText>Restrictive Measures</TitleText></Heading><Heading level="2"><TitleText>Orders and Regulations</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Orders and regulations</MarginalNote><Label>5</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The Governor in Council may, if the Governor in Council is of the opinion that any of the circumstances described in subsection (2) has occurred,</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>make any orders or regulations that the Governor in Council considers necessary with respect to the restriction or prohibition of any of the activities referred to in subsection (3) in relation to a foreign national, foreign state or foreign entity; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>by order, cause to be seized or restrained in the manner set out in the order, any property situated in Canada that is owned — or that is held or controlled, directly or indirectly — by the foreign national, foreign state or foreign entity.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Circumstances</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The circumstances referred to in subsection (1) are the following:</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>a foreign national, foreign state or foreign entity is responsible for, or complicit in, the hostage taking or the arbitrary detention in state-to-state relations of a Canadian national or eligible protected person outside Canada; or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>a foreign national, foreign state or foreign entity has materially assisted, sponsored, or provided <Keep svc="1">financial,</Keep> material or technological support for, or goods or services in support of, the hostage taking or the arbitrary detention in state-to-state relations of a Canadian national or eligible protected person outside Canada.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Restricted or prohibited activities</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>Orders and regulations may be made under paragraph (1)(a) with respect to the restriction or prohibition of any of the following activities, whether carried out in or outside Canada:</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>the dealing, directly or indirectly, by any person in Canada or by any Canadian national or Canadian corporation outside Canada in any property, wherever situated, that is owned — or that is held or controlled, directly or indirectly — by that foreign national, foreign state or foreign entity, any person in that foreign state or a national of that foreign state who does not ordinarily reside in Canada;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>the entering into or facilitating, directly or indirectly, by any person in Canada or by any Canadian national or Canadian corporation outside Canada, of any financial transaction related to a dealing referred to in paragraph (a);</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(c)</Label><Text>the provision by any person in Canada or by any Canadian national or Canadian corporation outside Canada of financial services or any other services to, for the benefit of or on the direction or order of the foreign national, foreign state or foreign entity;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(d)</Label><Text>the acquisition by any person in Canada or by any Canadian national or Canadian corporation outside Canada of financial services or any other services for the benefit of or on the direction or order of the foreign national, foreign state or foreign entity; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(e)</Label><Text>the making available by any person in Canada or by any Canadian national or Canadian corporation outside Canada of any property, wherever situated, to the foreign national, foreign state or foreign entity or to a person acting on behalf of the foreign national, foreign state or foreign entity.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Cessation of effect</MarginalNote><Label>(4)</Label><Text>Orders and regulations made under paragraph (1)(a) must specify the day on which they cease to have effect.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Regulations</MarginalNote><Label>6</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The Governor in Council may make regulations </Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>authorizing the Minister to</Text><Subparagraph><Label>(i)</Label><Text>issue to any person in Canada or to any Canadian national or Canadian corporation outside Canada a permit to carry out a specified activity or transaction, or class of activity or transaction, that is restricted or prohibited under this Act, or</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph><Label>(ii)</Label><Text>issue a general permit allowing any person in Canada or any Canadian national or Canadian corporation outside Canada to carry out a specified activity or transaction, or class of activity or transaction, that is restricted or prohibited under this Act; and</Text></Subparagraph></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>establishing conditions for the issuance of those permits.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Terms and conditions</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>A permit may include terms and conditions that are consistent with this Act and the orders and regulations made under it.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Revocation, etc.</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>The Minister may amend, suspend, revoke or reinstate any permit issued under regulations made under subsection (1).</Text></Subsection></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Provision of information</MarginalNote><Label>7</Label><Text>The Minister may require any person to provide to the Minister, within the time and in the form and manner specified, any information that, in the Minister’s opinion, is relevant for the purposes of the making, administration or enforcement of an order or regulation referred to in subsection 5(1).</Text></Section><Heading level="2"><TitleText>Forfeiture Orders</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Forfeiture</MarginalNote><Label>8</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>On application by the Minister, a judge must order that the property that is the subject of the application be forfeited to His Majesty in right of Canada if the judge determines, based on the evidence presented, that the property</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>is described in an order made under paragraph 5(1)(b); and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>is owned by the foreign national, foreign state or foreign entity referred to in that order or is held or controlled, directly or indirectly, by that foreign national, foreign state or foreign entity.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Notice</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Before making the order, the judge must require notice to be given to any person who, in the judge’s opinion, appears to have an interest in or right to the property, and the judge may hear any such person.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Manner of giving notice</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>The notice must</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>be given in the manner that the judge directs or that may be specified in the rules of the court;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>specify the period that the judge considers reasonable or that may be set out in the rules of the court during which a person may, before the order is made, make an application to the judge asserting their interest in or right to the property; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(c)</Label><Text>set out a description of the property.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Application by person</MarginalNote><Label>(4)</Label><Text>Any person — other than a foreign national, foreign state or foreign entity described in paragraphs 5(2)(a) or (b) — who claims an interest in or right to property that is forfeited to His Majesty under subsection (1) may, within 30 days after the day on which the property is forfeited, apply in writing to a judge for an order declaring that their interest or right is not affected by the forfeiture, declaring the nature and extent of the interest or right and directing the Minister to pay to the person an amount equal to the value of their interest or right.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Not a Crown corporation</MarginalNote><Label>9</Label><Text>If the property that is the subject of a forfeiture order consists of all of the shares of a corporation, the corporation is deemed not to be a <DefinitionRef>Crown corporation</DefinitionRef> as defined in subsection 83(1) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Financial Administration Act</XRefExternal>.</Text></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Payment out of Proceeds Account</MarginalNote><Label>10</Label><Text>After consulting with the Minister of Finance, the Minister may — at the times and in the manner, and on any terms and conditions, that the Minister considers appropriate — pay out of the <DefinitionRef>Proceeds Account</DefinitionRef>, as defined in section 2 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Seized Property Management Act</XRefExternal>, amounts not exceeding the net proceeds from the disposition of property forfeited under section 8, but only to compensate hostages or detained individuals referred to in subsection 5(2) or, if deceased, their estates or successions.</Text></Section><Heading level="2"><TitleText>Tabling in Parliament</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Order or regulation</MarginalNote><Label>11</Label><Text>The Minister must cause a copy of each order or regulation made under paragraph 5(1)(a) to be tabled before each House of Parliament on any of the first 15 days on which that House is sitting after the day on which the order or regulation is made.</Text></Section><Heading level="2"><TitleText>Termination of Order or Regulation</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Application — termination of order or regulation</MarginalNote><Label>12</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>A foreign national, foreign state or foreign entity that is the subject of an order or regulation made under paragraph 5(1)(a) may apply in writing to the Minister to cease being the subject of the order or regulation.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Application — property</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>A foreign national, foreign state or foreign entity whose property is the subject of an order made under paragraph 5(1)(b) may, unless the property is the subject of a forfeiture order, apply at any time in writing to the Minister to request that the property cease being the subject of the order made under that paragraph.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Reasonable grounds</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>On receipt of the application, the Minister must decide whether there are reasonable grounds to recommend to the Governor in Council that the order or regulation be amended or repealed, as the case may be, so that the applicant or their property ceases to be the subject of it.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Criteria</MarginalNote><Label>(4)</Label><Text>In deciding whether there are reasonable grounds to make the recommendation, the Minister must consider whether any of the following circumstances apply:</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>there is evidence that the applicant did not engage in the activity in response to which the order or regulation was made;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>the applicant is or has been prosecuted or convicted for that activity;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(c)</Label><Text>the applicant released the hostage or detained individual or assisted in efforts to procure their release;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(d)</Label><Text>it is in the interest of national security that the order or regulation be amended or repealed.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Time limit</MarginalNote><Label>(5)</Label><Text>The Minister must make a decision on the application within 90 days after the day on which the Minister receives it.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Notice if application rejected</MarginalNote><Label>(6)</Label><Text>The Minister must give notice without delay to the applicant of any decision to reject the application.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>New application</MarginalNote><Label>(7)</Label><Text>If there has been a material change in the applicant’s circumstances since their last application under subsection (1) was submitted, they may submit another application.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Reasonable expenses</MarginalNote><Label>13</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>A foreign national who is the subject of an order or regulation made under section 5 may apply to the Minister in writing for a certificate to exempt property from the application of the order or regulation if the property is necessary to meet the reasonable expenses of the applicant and their dependents.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Certificate</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>If the Minister determines that the property is necessary to meet the reasonable expenses of the applicant and their dependents, the Minister must issue a certificate to the applicant.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Time limit</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>The Minister must make a decision on the application and, if applicable, issue a certificate within 90 days after the day on which the Minister receives the application.</Text></Subsection></Section><Heading level="2"><TitleText>Offences</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Offence and punishment</MarginalNote><Label>14</Label><Text>Every person who knowingly contravenes or knowingly fails to comply with an order or regulation made under section 5</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>is guilty of an indictable offence and is liable to imprisonment for a term of not more than five years; or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>is guilty of an offence punishable on summary conviction and is liable to a fine of not more than $25,000 or to imprisonment for a term of not more than one year, or to both.</Text></Paragraph></Section><Heading level="2"><TitleText>General</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>No civil liability</MarginalNote><Label>15</Label><Text>A person that, in relation to any property that is the subject of an order or regulation made under section 5, acts reasonably in taking, or omitting to take, measures to comply with the order or regulation is not liable in any civil action arising from having taken or omitted to take the measures if they took all reasonable steps to satisfy themselves that the property was property that is the subject of the order or regulation.</Text></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Ranking</MarginalNote><Label>16</Label><Text>All secured and unsecured rights and interests in any property that is the subject of an order made under subsection 5(1)(b) that are held by a person, other than the foreign national, foreign state or foreign entity that is the subject of the order, are entitled to the same ranking that they would have been entitled to had the order not been made unless the property is forfeited to His Majesty in right of Canada under section 8.</Text></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Costs</MarginalNote><Label>17</Label><Text>Any costs incurred by or on behalf of His Majesty in right of Canada in relation to the seizure or restraint of property under an order made under paragraph 5(1)(b) or the disposal of property forfeited under section 8 are the liability of the owner of the property and constitute a debt due to His Majesty in right of Canada that may be recovered in any court of competent jurisdiction.</Text></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Proceedings not precluded</MarginalNote><Label>18</Label><Text>The making of an order or regulation under section 5 does not preclude the commencement of proceedings under any Act of Parliament other than this Act, or any civil proceedings, in respect of any property that is the subject of the order or regulation.</Text></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Mistaken identity</MarginalNote><Label>19</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Any individual in Canada or any Canadian outside Canada whose name is the same as or similar to the name of a foreign national who is the subject of an order or regulation made under section 5 may, if they claim not to be that foreign national, apply to the Minister in writing for a certificate stating that they are not that foreign national.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Determination by Minister</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Within 45 days after the day on which the application is received, the Minister must</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>if the Minister is satisfied that the applicant is not the foreign national, issue the certificate to the applicant; or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>if the Minister is not so satisfied, provide a notice to the applicant of the determination.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection></Section><Heading level="1"><TitleText>Assistance to Families</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Assistance to families</MarginalNote><Label>20</Label><Text>The Minister must provide timely information and assistance to the families of Canadian nationals or eligible protected persons who are taken hostage or arbitrarily detained in state-to-state relations outside Canada by foreign nationals, foreign states or foreign entities, including by</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>providing advice and guidance to families;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>directing families to appropriate supports and services, including mental health resources; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(c)</Label><Text>facilitating communications, when appropriate, among the foreign nationals, foreign states or foreign entities, the families and the hostages or detained individuals.</Text></Paragraph></Section><Heading level="1"><TitleText>Programs to Encourage Cooperation</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Programs</MarginalNote><Label>21</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The Minister may, in cooperation with the Minister of Citizenship and Immigration, establish and implement programs designed to encourage individuals to cooperate with the Government of Canada to secure the release of Canadian nationals and eligible protected persons who are held hostage or arbitrarily detained in state-to-state relations outside Canada.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Monetary reward</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>If an individual provides critical information leading to the release and repatriation of a hostage or detained individual, the Minister may pay a monetary reward to the individual who provides that information in an amount and manner determined by the Minister.</Text></Subsection></Section><Heading level="1"><TitleText>Review and Reports</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Report on implementation</MarginalNote><Label>22</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The Minister must, after the end of each fiscal year, prepare a report on the implementation of this Act, including</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>summary information about Canadian nationals and eligible protected persons being held hostage or arbitrarily detained in state-to-state relations outside Canada by foreign nationals, foreign states or foreign entities; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>information on the effectiveness of orders and regulations made under section 5 and programs established under section 21.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Tabling in Parliament</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The Minister must cause a copy of the report to be tabled before each House of Parliament on any of the first 15 days on which that House is sitting after the report is completed.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Review of Act</MarginalNote><Label>23</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Within 10 years after the day on which this Act comes into force, a comprehensive review of the provisions and operation of this Act must be undertaken by the committee of the Senate, of the House of Commons or of both Houses of Parliament that is designated or established for that purpose.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Report</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The committee must, within a year after the review is undertaken — or within any further period that the Senate, the House of Commons or both Houses of Parliament, as the case may be, authorize — submit a report on the review to the appropriate House, or in the case of a committee of both Houses, to each House, that includes a statement of any changes that the committee recommends.</Text></Subsection></Section><Heading level="1"><TitleText>Related Amendments</TitleText></Heading><Heading level="2"><MarginalNote><HistoricalNote>2000, c. 17; 2001, c. 41, s. 48</HistoricalNote></MarginalNote><TitleText>Proceeds of Crime (Money Laundering) and Terrorist Financing Act</TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><Label>24</Label><Text>The definition <DefinitionRef>foreign state</DefinitionRef> in subsection 2(1) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Proceeds of Crime (Money Laundering) and Terrorist Financing Act</XRefExternal> is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><SectionPiece><Definition><Text><DefinedTermEn>foreign state</DefinedTermEn>, except for the purposes of <Ins>paragraph 11.11(1)(b.4)</Ins> and Part 2, means a country other than Canada and includes any political subdivision or territory of a foreign state. (<DefinedTermFr>État étranger</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Definition></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>25</Label><Text>Subsection 11.11(1) of the Act is amended by adding the following after paragraph (b.3):</Text><AmendedText><SectionPiece><Paragraph change="ins"><Label>(b.4)</Label><Text>a <DefinitionRef>foreign national</DefinitionRef>, <DefinitionRef>foreign state</DefinitionRef> or <DefinitionRef>entity</DefinitionRef>, as those terms are defined in section 2 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Foreign Hostage Takers Accountability Act</XRefExternal>, that is subject to an order or regulation made under paragraph 5(1)(a) of that Act, or whose property is the subject of an order made under paragraph 5(1)(b) of that Act;</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Section><Heading level="2"><MarginalNote><HistoricalNote>2001, c. 27</HistoricalNote></MarginalNote><TitleText>Immigration and Refugee Protection Act</TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><Label>26</Label><Text>Subsection 25.1(2) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Immigration and Refugee Protection Act</XRefExternal> is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><Subsection change="ins"><MarginalNote>Release and repatriation</MarginalNote><Label>(1.1)</Label><Text>The Minister may, on the recommendation of the Minister of Foreign Affairs, examine the circumstances concerning a foreign national and their family members who are inadmissible — other than under section 34, 35 or 37 — or who do not meet the requirements of this Act and may grant the foreign national and their family members permanent resident status or an exemption from any applicable criteria or obligations of this Act if the foreign national provides critical information leading to the release and repatriation of a <DefinitionRef>Canadian national</DefinitionRef> or <DefinitionRef>eligible protected person</DefinitionRef>, as those terms are defined in section 2 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Foreign Hostage Takers Accountability Act</XRefExternal>, who is held hostage or arbitrarily detained in state-to-state relations in circumstances described in subsection 5(2) of that Act.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Exemption</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The Minister may exempt the foreign national <Ins>and their family members, if applicable</Ins>, from the payment of any applicable fees in respect of the examination of their circumstances under subsection (1) <Ins>or (1.1)</Ins>.</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>27</Label><Text>Paragraph 35(1)(e) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(e)</Label><Text>being a person, other than a permanent resident, who is currently the subject of an order or regulation made under section 4 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="regulation">Justice for Victims of Corrupt Foreign Officials Act (Sergei Magnitsky Law)</XRefExternal> <Ins>or section 5 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Foreign Hostage Takers Accountability Act</XRefExternal></Ins>.</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Section></Body></Bill>