<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><Bill bill-origin="commons" bill-type="private-public" xml:lang="en" date-time="2023-09-25 17:15:57"><Identification><BillNumber>C-366</BillNumber><Parliament><Session>1</Session><Number>44</Number><RegnalYear><Year-s>70-71</Year-s><Monarch>Elizabeth II – 1-2 Charles III</Monarch></RegnalYear><Year-s>2021-2022-2023</Year-s></Parliament><LongTitle>An Act to amend the Food and Drugs Act (substances in menstrual tampons)</LongTitle><ShortTitle status="unofficial" /><RunningHead>An Act to amend the Food and Drugs Act (substances in menstrual tampons)</RunningHead><BillHistory><Stages stage="first-reading-house"><Date><YYYY>2023</YYYY><MM>11</MM><DD>21</DD></Date></Stages></BillHistory><BillSponsor><Emphasis style="smallcaps">Mr. MacGregor</Emphasis></BillSponsor><BillRefNumber date-time="2023-09-25">441300</BillRefNumber></Identification><Introduction><Summary><TitleText>SUMMARY</TitleText><Provision><Text>This enactment amends the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Food and Drugs Act</XRefExternal> to provide that labels on menstrual tampons must include a list of the substances they contain.</Text></Provision></Summary><Preamble><Provision><MarginalNote>Preamble</MarginalNote><Text>Whereas there is a lack of readily accessible information about the risks of substances contained in menstrual tampon products on human health;</Text></Provision><Provision><Text>Whereas the creation of labelling requirements for menstrual tampons on absorbency and toxic shock syndrome has led to increased awareness and positive health outcomes among Canadians;</Text></Provision><Provision><Text>And whereas Parliament wishes to strengthen labelling requirements for these products in order to increase transparency and better allow Canadians to make informed choices about menstrual products;</Text></Provision></Preamble><Enacts><Provision language-align="yes"><Text>Now, therefore, His Majesty, by and with the advice and consent <Keep>of the</Keep> Senate and House of Commons of Canada, <Keep>enacts</Keep> as follows:</Text></Provision></Enacts></Introduction><Body><Heading level="1"><MarginalNote><HistoricalNote>R.S., c. F-27</HistoricalNote></MarginalNote><TitleText>Food and Drugs Act</TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><Label>1</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Subsection 20(2) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Food and Drugs Act</XRefExternal> is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><Subsection><MarginalNote>Devices labelled or packaged in contravention of Act or regulations</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>A device that is not labelled or packaged as required by, or is labelled or packaged contrary to, <Ins>this Act or</Ins> the regulations shall be deemed to be labelled or packaged contrary to subsection (1).</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Section 20 of the Act is amended by adding the following after subsection (2):</Text><AmendedText><Subsection change="ins"><MarginalNote>Labelling of menstrual tampons</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>In addition to meeting the requirements under this Act for devices, labels for menstrual tampons shall include a list of the substances they contain.</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Subsection></Section><Heading level="1"><TitleText>Coming into Force</TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote>Eighteen months after royal assent</MarginalNote><Label>2</Label><Text>This Act comes into force on the day that, in the eighteenth month after the month in which it receives royal assent, has the same calendar number as the day on which it receives royal assent or, if that eighteenth month has no day with that number, the last day of that eighteenth month.</Text></Section></Body></Bill>