<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!--Arbortext, Inc., 1988-2010, v.4002--><Bill bill-origin="commons" bill-type="govt-public" xml:lang="en"><Identification><BillNumber>C-37</BillNumber><Parliament><Session>1</Session><Number>44</Number><RegnalYear><Year-s>70-71</Year-s><Monarch>Elizabeth II – 1 Charles III</Monarch></RegnalYear><Year-s>2021-2022</Year-s></Parliament><LongTitle>An Act to amend the Department of Employment and Social Development Act and to make consequential amendments to other Acts (Employment Insurance Board of Appeal)</LongTitle><ShortTitle status="unofficial">An Act to amend the Department of Employment and Social Development Act and to make consequential amendments to other Acts (Employment Insurance Board of Appeal)</ShortTitle><RunningHead>An Act to amend the Department of Employment and Social Development Act and to make consequential amendments to other Acts ...</RunningHead><BillHistory><Stages stage="first-reading-house"><Date><YYYY>2022</YYYY><MM>12</MM><DD>14</DD></Date></Stages></BillHistory><BillSponsor>MINISTER OF EMPLOYMENT, WORKFORCE DEVELOPMENT AND DISABILITY INCLUSION<LineBreak /> </BillSponsor><BillRefNumber date-time="2022-12-13">91124</BillRefNumber></Identification><Introduction><Summary><TitleText>SUMMARY</TitleText><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>This enactment amends the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Department of Employment and Social Development Act</XRefExternal> to, among other things,</Text><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>establish the Employment Insurance Board of Appeal to hear appeals of decisions made under the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Employment Insurance Act</XRefExternal> instead of the Employment Insurance Section of the General Division of the Social Security Tribunal; and</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>eliminate the requirement for leave to appeal decisions relating to the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Employment Insurance Act</XRefExternal> to the Appeal Division of the Tribunal.</Text></Provision></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>It also makes consequential amendments to other Acts.</Text></Provision></Summary><TableOfProvisions label-column-width="2.5"><Heading level="1"><TitleText>TABLE OF PROVISIONS</TitleText></Heading><Heading level="1"><TitleText>An Act to amend the Department of Employment and Social Development Act and to make consequential amendments to other Acts (Employment Insurance Board of Appeal)</TitleText></Heading><Label><Emphasis style="bold">1</Emphasis></Label><Text><XRefExternal reference-type="act">Department of Employment and Social Development Act</XRefExternal></Text><Heading level="1"><TitleText>Consequential Amendments</TitleText></Heading><Label><Emphasis style="bold">26</Emphasis></Label><Text><XRefExternal reference-type="act">Federal Courts Act</XRefExternal></Text><Label><Emphasis style="bold">27</Emphasis></Label><Text><XRefExternal reference-type="act">Labour Adjustment Benefits Act</XRefExternal></Text><Label><Emphasis style="bold">30</Emphasis></Label><Text><XRefExternal reference-type="act">Income Tax Act</XRefExternal></Text><Label><Emphasis style="bold">32</Emphasis></Label><Text><XRefExternal reference-type="act">Employment Insurance Act</XRefExternal></Text><Heading level="1" type="transitional"><TitleText>Transitional Provisions</TitleText></Heading><Label><Emphasis style="bold">34</Emphasis></Label><Text>Definitions</Text><Label><Emphasis style="bold">35</Emphasis></Label><Text>Part-time members</Text><Label><Emphasis style="bold">36</Emphasis></Label><Text>Members of Board of Appeal</Text><Label><Emphasis style="bold">37</Emphasis></Label><Text>No compensation</Text><Label><Emphasis style="bold">38</Emphasis></Label><Text>Application for leave to appeal</Text><Label><Emphasis style="bold">39</Emphasis></Label><Text>Appeal of Employment Insurance Section decision</Text><Label><Emphasis style="bold">40</Emphasis></Label><Text>Ongoing appeal of Employment Insurance Section decision</Text><Label><Emphasis style="bold">41</Emphasis></Label><Text>Question of constitutional law</Text><Label><Emphasis style="bold">42</Emphasis></Label><Text>Ongoing appeal before Employment Insurance Section</Text><Label><Emphasis style="bold">43</Emphasis></Label><Text>Board of Appeal access to documents and information</Text><Label><Emphasis style="bold">44</Emphasis></Label><Text>Transfer of documents and information</Text><Label><Emphasis style="bold">45</Emphasis></Label><Text>Section 53 of <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Department of Employment and Social Development Act</XRefExternal></Text><Label><Emphasis style="bold">46</Emphasis></Label><Text>Section 241 of <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Budget Implementation Act, 2021, No. 1</XRefExternal></Text><Label><Emphasis style="bold">47</Emphasis></Label><Text><XRefExternal reference-type="act">Employment Insurance Act</XRefExternal></Text><Label><Emphasis style="bold">48</Emphasis></Label><Text><XRefExternal reference-type="act">Labour Adjustment Benefits Act</XRefExternal></Text><Heading level="1"><TitleText>Coming into Force</TitleText></Heading><Label><Emphasis style="bold">49</Emphasis></Label><Text>Order in council</Text></TableOfProvisions><Enacts><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>His Majesty, by and with the advice and consent of the Senate and House of Commons of Canada, enacts as follows:</Text></Provision></Enacts></Introduction><Body><Heading level="1"><MarginalNote><HistoricalNote>2005, c. 34; 2013, c. 40, s. 205</HistoricalNote></MarginalNote><TitleText>Department of Employment and Social Development Act</TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><Label>1</Label><Text>Section 2 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Department of Employment and Social Development Act</XRefExternal> is amended by adding the following in alphabetical order:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><SectionPiece><Definition change="ins"><Text><DefinedTermEn>Board of Appeal</DefinedTermEn> means the Employment Insurance Board of Appeal established under section 43.01. (<DefinedTermFr>Conseil d’appel</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Definition></SectionPiece></AmendedText><ExplanatoryNote><TitleText>Department of Employment and Social Development Act</TitleText><Label><Emphasis style="italic">Clause 1</Emphasis>:</Label><ExplanatoryText>New.</ExplanatoryText></ExplanatoryNote></Section><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote><HistoricalNote>2012, c. 19, s. 224</HistoricalNote></MarginalNote><Label>2</Label><Text>The headings “Social Security Tribunal” and “Establishment and Administration” before section 44 of the Act are replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Heading level="1"><TitleText><Ins>Board of Appeal and</Ins> Social Security Tribunal</TitleText></Heading><Heading level="2"><TitleText><Ins>Board of Appeal</Ins></TitleText></Heading><Heading level="3"><TitleText>Establishment and Administration</TitleText></Heading></AmendedText><ExplanatoryNote><Label><Emphasis style="italic">Clause 2</Emphasis>:</Label><ExplanatoryText>Existing text of the headings:</ExplanatoryText><ExistingText><Heading level="1"><TitleText>Social Security Tribunal</TitleText></Heading><Heading level="2"><TitleText>Establishment and Administration</TitleText></Heading></ExistingText></ExplanatoryNote></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>3</Label><Text>The Act is amended by adding the following before section 44:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Section change="ins"><MarginalNote>Establishment of Board of Appeal</MarginalNote><Label>43.01</Label><Text>The Employment Insurance Board of Appeal is established.</Text></Section><Section change="ins"><MarginalNote>Appointment — Executive Head</MarginalNote><Label>43.02</Label><Subsection change="ins"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The Executive Head of the Board of Appeal is to be appointed by the Governor in Council, on the recommendation of the Minister after consultation by the Minister with the Commission, to hold office during pleasure on a full-time basis for a renewable term of not more than five years.</Text></Subsection><Subsection change="ins"><MarginalNote>Appointment — regional coordinators</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>On the recommendation of the Minister after consultation by the Minister with the Commission, the Governor in Council may appoint not more than six regional coordinators to hold office during pleasure on a full-time or part-time basis for a renewable term of not more than five years that will ensure, to the extent possible, the end in any one year of the terms of office of not more than one half of the regional coordinators.</Text></Subsection><Subsection change="ins"><MarginalNote>Diversity</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>Recommendations under subsection (2) are to be made having regard to the importance of having regional coordinators who are representative of the diversity of Canadian society.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section change="ins"><MarginalNote>Composition</MarginalNote><Label>43.03</Label><Subsection change="ins"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The Board of Appeal consists of the Executive Head, the regional coordinators and the following members:</Text><Paragraph change="ins"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>members to be appointed by the Governor in Council, on the recommendation of the Minister after consultation by the Minister with the Commission, to hold office during pleasure on a part-time basis for a renewable term of not more than five years;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph change="ins"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>members to be appointed by the Commission to hold office during pleasure on a part-time basis for a renewable term of not more than five years, each of whom must be an <DefinitionRef>employer</DefinitionRef>, within the meaning of subsection 2(1) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Employment Insurance Act</XRefExternal>, or, at the time of the appointment, a representative of such employers; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph change="ins"><Label>(c)</Label><Text>members to be appointed by the Commission to hold office during pleasure on a part-time basis for a renewable term of not more than five years, each of whom must be an <DefinitionRef>insured person</DefinitionRef>, within the meaning of subsection 2(1) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Employment Insurance Act</XRefExternal>, or, at the time of the appointment, a representative of such insured persons.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection change="ins"><MarginalNote>Terms of members</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Members are to be appointed for terms that will ensure, to the extent possible, the end in any one year of the terms of office of not more than one half of the members appointed under each of paragraphs (1)(a) to (c).</Text></Subsection><Subsection change="ins"><MarginalNote>Equal number</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>To the extent possible, an equal number of members is to be appointed under each of paragraphs (1)(a) to (c).</Text></Subsection><Subsection change="ins"><MarginalNote>Regional representation and diversity</MarginalNote><Label>(4)</Label><Text>Recommendations under paragraph (1)(a) and appointments under paragraphs (1)(b) and (c) are to be made having regard to the importance of regional representation in the membership of the Board of Appeal as well as the importance of having members who are representative of the diversity of Canadian society.</Text></Subsection><Subsection change="ins"><MarginalNote>Completion of ongoing matters</MarginalNote><Label>(5)</Label><Text>A person who ceases to be a member for any reason other than removal may, at the request of the Executive Head, within 12 weeks after ceasing to be a member, carry out and complete any duties and functions that they would otherwise have had in connection with any matter that came before the Board of Appeal while they were still a member and in respect of which there was any proceeding in which they participated as a member. For that purpose, the person is deemed to be a member.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section change="ins"><MarginalNote>Executive Head</MarginalNote><Label>43.04</Label><Subsection change="ins"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The Executive Head has supervision over and direction of the day-to-day work of the Board of Appeal. In particular, the Executive Head is responsible for the management of the regional coordinators and the members of the Board of Appeal, including providing them with training and guidance with respect to their duties and functions and evaluating their performance.</Text></Subsection><Subsection change="ins"><MarginalNote>Report on overall performance</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The Executive Head is to report regularly to the Commission, through the Chairperson of the Commission, on the overall performance of the Board of Appeal.</Text></Subsection><Subsection change="ins"><MarginalNote>Regional coordinators</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>Regional coordinators assist the Executive Head and perform any duties and functions that the Executive Head may assign.</Text></Subsection><Subsection change="ins"><MarginalNote>Delegation — regional coordinators</MarginalNote><Label>(4)</Label><Text>The Executive Head may delegate to any regional coordinator any of the Executive Head’s powers, duties or functions, except the power to delegate under this <Keep svc="1">subsection,</Keep> the duty to report under subsection (2), the duty to select members under subsection 43.05(1) and the duty to select a regional coordinator under subsection 43.05(2).</Text></Subsection><Subsection change="ins"><MarginalNote>Members assigned to region</MarginalNote><Label>(5)</Label><Text>The Executive Head is to assign each member of the Board of Appeal to a particular region to hear appeals in that region, taking into account the member’s ordinary place of residence. However, a member may be selected to hear appeals in other regions for operational reasons.</Text></Subsection><Subsection change="ins"><MarginalNote>Absence — Executive Head</MarginalNote><Label>(6)</Label><Text>In the event of the absence or incapacity of the Executive Head or a vacancy in that office, the Chairperson of the Commission may authorize a person to act as Executive Head, on any terms and conditions that the Chairperson may specify, but no person so authorized has authority to act for a term of more than 90 days without the Governor in Council’s approval given on the recommendation of the Minister after consultation by the Minister with the Commission.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section change="ins"><MarginalNote>Board of Appeal hearings — three-member panels</MarginalNote><Label>43.05</Label><Subsection change="ins"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>An appeal to the Board of Appeal is to be heard before a panel of three members selected by the Executive Head. One member, who is to be the presiding member of the panel, is to be selected from among the members referred to in paragraph 43.03(1)(a), one member is to be selected from among the members referred to in paragraph 43.03(1)(b) and one member is to be selected from among the members referred to in paragraph 43.03(1)(c).</Text></Subsection><Subsection change="ins"><MarginalNote>Determination of regional coordinator</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The Executive Head is to select a regional coordinator to</Text><Paragraph change="ins"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>determine if an extension of time to bring an appeal to the Board of Appeal should be granted;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph change="ins"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>determine if an appeal before the Board of Appeal has been abandoned; or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph change="ins"><Label>(c)</Label><Text>hear an application to reopen an appeal that has been determined to be abandoned.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection change="ins"><MarginalNote>Delegation — employees of Department</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>The Executive Head may delegate to any employees of the Department, referred to in section 43.08, the duty to select members under subsection (1) and the duty to select a regional coordinator under subsection (2).</Text></Subsection></Section><Section change="ins"><MarginalNote>Remuneration</MarginalNote><Label>43.06</Label><Subsection change="ins"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The Executive Head, the regional coordinators and the members of the Board of Appeal are to be paid the remuneration fixed by the Governor in Council.</Text></Subsection><Subsection change="ins"><MarginalNote>Expenses — Executive Head</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The Executive Head is entitled to be paid, in accordance with Treasury Board directives, reasonable travel and living expenses incurred by the Executive Head while absent from the Executive Head’s ordinary place of work in the course of performing the Executive Head’s duties and functions.</Text></Subsection><Subsection change="ins"><MarginalNote>Expenses — full-time regional coordinators</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>Each full-time regional coordinator is entitled to be paid, in accordance with Treasury Board directives, reasonable travel and living expenses incurred by them while absent from their ordinary place of work in the course of performing their duties and functions as a regional coordinator.</Text></Subsection><Subsection change="ins"><MarginalNote>Expenses — part-time regional coordinators and members</MarginalNote><Label>(4)</Label><Text>Each part-time regional coordinator and each member of the Board of Appeal is entitled to be paid, in accordance with Treasury Board directives, reasonable travel and living expenses incurred by them while absent from their ordinary place of residence in the course of performing their duties and functions as a regional coordinator or a member of the Board of Appeal, as the case may be.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section change="ins"><MarginalNote><XRefExternal reference-type="act">Public Service Superannuation Act</XRefExternal></MarginalNote><Label>43.07</Label><Subsection change="ins"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The Executive Head and the full-time regional coordinators are deemed to be employed in the public service for the purposes of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Public Service Superannuation Act</XRefExternal>.</Text></Subsection><Subsection change="ins"><MarginalNote>Other benefits</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The Executive Head, the regional coordinators and the members of the Board of Appeal are deemed to be employees for the purposes of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Government Employees Compensation Act</XRefExternal> and to be employed in the federal public administration for the purposes of regulations made under section 9 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Aeronautics Act</XRefExternal>.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section change="ins"><MarginalNote>Employees, services and facilities</MarginalNote><Label>43.08</Label><Text>The Minister is responsible for providing the Board of Appeal with the employees of the Department, the support services and the facilities that are needed by the Board of Appeal to exercise its powers and perform its duties and functions.</Text></Section><Section change="ins"><MarginalNote>Immunity</MarginalNote><Label>43.09</Label><Text>No civil proceedings lie against the Executive Head, any regional coordinator or any member of the Board of Appeal for anything done or said in good faith in the exercise or purported exercise of a power or in the performance or purported performance of a duty or function of the Board of Appeal.</Text></Section><Section change="ins"><MarginalNote>Competence and compellability</MarginalNote><Label>43.1</Label><Text>The Executive Head, the regional coordinators and the members of the Board of Appeal are not competent or compellable to appear as a witness in any civil proceedings in respect of any matter coming to their knowledge in the course of the exercise of a power or in the performance of a duty or function of the Board of Appeal.</Text></Section><Heading level="2" change="ins"><TitleText>Social Security Tribunal</TitleText></Heading><Heading level="3" change="ins"><TitleText>Establishment and Administration</TitleText></Heading></AmendedText><ExplanatoryNote><Label><Emphasis style="italic">Clause 3</Emphasis>:</Label><ExplanatoryText>New.</ExplanatoryText></ExplanatoryNote></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>4</Label><Text>The Act is amended by adding the following after section 43.1:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Heading change="ins" level="3"><TitleText><Ins>Appeal to Board of Appeal</Ins></TitleText></Heading><Section change="ins"><MarginalNote><Ins>Appeal — time limit</Ins></MarginalNote><Label><Ins>43.11</Ins></Label><Subsection change="ins"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>An appeal of a decision made under section 112 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Employment Insurance Act</XRefExternal> must be brought to the Board of Appeal in the prescribed form and manner and within 30 days after the day on which the decision is communicated to the appellant.</Text></Subsection><Subsection change="ins"><MarginalNote>Extension</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The Board of Appeal may allow further time within which an appeal is to be brought, but in no case may an appeal be brought more than one year after the day on which the decision is communicated to the appellant.</Text></Subsection><Subsection change="ins"><MarginalNote>Decision in writing</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>The Board of Appeal must give a decision made under subsection (2) in writing and a copy of the decision must be sent to the appellant, the Commission and any other party.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section change="ins"><MarginalNote>Constitutional questions</MarginalNote><Label>43.12</Label><Text>The Board of Appeal may not consider any question of constitutional law.</Text></Section><Section change="ins"><MarginalNote>Decision</MarginalNote><Label>43.13</Label><Subsection change="ins"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The Board of Appeal may dismiss the appeal or confirm, rescind or vary a decision of the Commission in whole or in part or give the decision that the Commission should have given.</Text></Subsection><Subsection change="ins"><MarginalNote>Decision in writing with reasons</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The Board of Appeal must give a decision made under subsection (1) in writing, with reasons, and send copies of the decision and reasons to the appellant, the Commission and any other party.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section change="ins"><MarginalNote>Time limits</MarginalNote><Label>43.14</Label><Text>The Executive Head may, in any particular case for special reasons, extend the time within which the Board of Appeal is required by regulation to make a decision under subsection 43.13(1).</Text></Section><Section change="ins"><MarginalNote>Expenses and allowances</MarginalNote><Label>43.15</Label><Text>Any party who is required to attend a hearing may, if the Executive Head considers it warranted in any particular case for any reasons provided for in the regulations, be reimbursed for their travel or living expenses up to the amounts determined by the Treasury Board, or be paid any allowance, including compensation for lost remuneration, in accordance with the rates fixed by the Treasury Board.</Text></Section><Section change="ins"><MarginalNote>Appeal — region</MarginalNote><Label>43.16</Label><Subsection change="ins"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>An appeal is to be heard in the appellant’s region, except in the circumstances provided for in the regulations.</Text></Subsection><Subsection change="ins"><MarginalNote>Appeal — format</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>An appeal is to be heard in the format selected by the appellant, except in the circumstances provided for in the regulations.</Text></Subsection><Subsection change="ins"><MarginalNote>Hearings in private</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>All or part of a Board of Appeal hearing may be held in private in the circumstances provided for in the regulations.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section change="ins"><MarginalNote>Representation of party</MarginalNote><Label>43.17</Label><Text>A party may, at their own expense, be represented by a representative of their choice.</Text></Section><Section change="ins"><MarginalNote>Powers of Board of Appeal</MarginalNote><Label>43.18</Label><Subsection change="ins"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Subject to section 43.12, the Board of Appeal may decide any question of law or fact that is necessary for the disposition of any application made or appeal brought under this Act.</Text></Subsection><Subsection change="ins"><MarginalNote><XRefExternal reference-type="act">Employment Insurance Act</XRefExternal></MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>If a question specified in section 90 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Employment Insurance Act</XRefExternal> arises in the consideration of an <Keep svc="1">application</Keep> or in an appeal, it must be determined by an authorized officer of the Canada Revenue Agency, as provided by that section.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section change="ins"><MarginalNote>Abandonment of appeals</MarginalNote><Label>43.19</Label><Subsection change="ins"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The Board of Appeal may determine that an appeal before it has been abandoned if it has failed to contact the appellant despite reasonable efforts having been made to do so or if the appellant fails to communicate with it on being requested to do so.</Text></Subsection><Subsection change="ins"><MarginalNote>Reopening abandoned appeals</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The Board of Appeal, on application, may reopen an appeal it has determined to be abandoned if it is satisfied that</Text><Paragraph change="ins"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>in making the determination, it failed to observe a principle of natural justice; or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph change="ins"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>the appellant’s failure to communicate with it was due to circumstances beyond the appellant’s control and the application was made within 30 days after the day on which those circumstances were resolved.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection change="ins"><MarginalNote>Decision in writing</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>The Board of Appeal must give a decision made under subsection (1) or (2) in writing and a copy of the decision must be sent to the appellant, the Commission and any other party.</Text></Subsection></Section></AmendedText><ExplanatoryNote><Label><Emphasis style="italic">Clause 4</Emphasis>:</Label><ExplanatoryText>New.</ExplanatoryText></ExplanatoryNote></Section><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote><HistoricalNote>2012, c. 19, s. 224</HistoricalNote></MarginalNote><Label>5</Label><Text>Subsection 44(2) of the Act is repealed.</Text><ExplanatoryNote><Label><Emphasis style="italic">Clause 5</Emphasis>:</Label><ExplanatoryText>Existing text of subsection 44(2):</ExplanatoryText><ExistingText><Subsection><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The General Division consists of the Income Security Section and the Employment Insurance Section.</Text></Subsection></ExistingText></ExplanatoryNote></Section><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote><HistoricalNote>2012, c. 19, s. 224</HistoricalNote></MarginalNote><Label>6</Label><Text>Subsection 45(2) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Subsection><MarginalNote>Chairperson and Vice-chairpersons</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The Governor in Council designates one of the full-time members to hold office as the Chairperson and <Ins>two</Ins> full-time members to hold office as Vice-chairpersons, one of whom is responsible for the Appeal Division and one of whom is responsible for the <Ins>General Division</Ins>.</Text></Subsection></AmendedText><ExplanatoryNote><Label><Emphasis style="italic">Clause 6</Emphasis>:</Label><ExplanatoryText>Existing text of subsection 45(2):</ExplanatoryText><ExistingText><Subsection><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The Governor in Council designates one of the full-time members to hold office as the Chairperson and three full-time members to hold office as Vice-chairpersons, one of whom is responsible for the Appeal Division, one of whom is responsible for the Income Security Section and one of whom is responsible for the Employment Insurance Section.</Text></Subsection></ExistingText></ExplanatoryNote></Section><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote><HistoricalNote>2012, c. 19, s. 224</HistoricalNote></MarginalNote><Label>7</Label><Text>Subsections 46(2) and (3) of the Act are replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Subsection><MarginalNote>Members</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Each member exercises any powers and performs any duties and functions that the Vice-chairperson who is <Keep svc="1">responsible</Keep> for the Division for which they hear matters may assign.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Assignment</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>The Chairperson may assign members to hear matters in the Appeal Division or the <Ins>General Division</Ins>.</Text></Subsection></AmendedText><ExplanatoryNote><Label><Emphasis style="italic">Clause 7</Emphasis>:</Label><ExplanatoryText>Existing text of subsections 46(2) and (3):</ExplanatoryText><ExistingText><Subsection><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Each member exercises any powers and performs any duties and functions that the Vice-chairperson who is responsible for the Division or Section for which they hear matters may assign.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><Label>(3)</Label><Text>Subject to section 47, the Chairperson may assign members to hear matters in the Appeal Division, the Income Security Section or the Employment Insurance Section.</Text></Subsection></ExistingText></ExplanatoryNote></Section><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote><HistoricalNote>2012, c. 19, s. 224</HistoricalNote></MarginalNote><Label>8</Label><Text>Section 47 of the Act is repealed.</Text><ExplanatoryNote><Label><Emphasis style="italic">Clause 8</Emphasis>:</Label><ExplanatoryText>Existing text of section 47:</ExplanatoryText><ExistingText><Section><Label>47</Label><Text>The Minister must consult a committee composed of the Chairperson of the Tribunal and the commissioners referred to in paragraphs 20(2)(c) and (d) before recommending to the Governor in Council any person to be appointed as a member of the Tribunal who may hear matters in the Employment Insurance Section.</Text></Section></ExistingText></ExplanatoryNote></Section><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote><HistoricalNote>2012, c. 19, s. 224</HistoricalNote></MarginalNote><Label>9</Label><Text>Subsection 51(2) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Subsection><MarginalNote>Absence — other</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>If subsection (1) does not apply owing to the absence or incapacity of the Vice-chairperson of the Appeal Division, or if the office of Vice-chairperson of the Appeal Division is vacant, the Minister may authorize <Ins>the</Ins> Vice-chairperson <Ins>of the General Division</Ins> to act as Chairperson and that Vice-chairperson may exercise all the powers and perform all the duties and functions of the Chairperson.</Text></Subsection></AmendedText><ExplanatoryNote><Label><Emphasis style="italic">Clause 9</Emphasis>:</Label><ExplanatoryText>Existing text of subsection 51(2):</ExplanatoryText><ExistingText><Subsection><Label>(2)</Label><Text>If subsection (1) does not apply owing to the absence or incapacity of the Vice-chairperson of the Appeal Division, or if the office of Vice-chairperson of the Appeal Division is vacant, the Minister may authorize another Vice-chairperson to act as Chairperson and that Vice-chairperson may exercise all the powers and perform all the duties and functions of the Chairperson.</Text></Subsection></ExistingText></ExplanatoryNote></Section><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote><HistoricalNote>2012, c. 19, s. 224</HistoricalNote></MarginalNote><Label>10</Label><Text>The heading “Organization of Tribunal” before section 52 of the Act is repealed.</Text><ExplanatoryNote><Label><Emphasis style="italic">Clause 10</Emphasis>:</Label><ExplanatoryText>Existing text of the heading:</ExplanatoryText><ExistingText><Heading level="2"><TitleText>Organization of Tribunal</TitleText></Heading></ExistingText></ExplanatoryNote></Section><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote><HistoricalNote>2012, c. 19, s. 224</HistoricalNote></MarginalNote><Label>11</Label><Text>Subsection 52(1) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Section><MarginalNote>Appeal — time limit</MarginalNote><Label>52</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>An appeal of a decision must be brought to the General Division in the prescribed form and manner and within 90 days after the day on which the decision is communicated to the appellant.</Text></Subsection></Section></AmendedText><ExplanatoryNote><Label><Emphasis style="italic">Clause 11</Emphasis>:</Label><ExplanatoryText>Existing text of subsection 52(1):</ExplanatoryText><ExistingText><Section><Label>52</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>An appeal of a decision must be brought to the General Division in the prescribed form and manner and within,</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>in the case of a decision made under the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Employment Insurance Act</XRefExternal>, 30 days after the day on which it is communicated to the appellant; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>in any other case, 90 days after the day on which the decision is communicated to the appellant.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection></Section></ExistingText></ExplanatoryNote></Section><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote><HistoricalNote>2012, c. 19, s. 224; 2021, c. 23, s. 225</HistoricalNote></MarginalNote><Label>12</Label><Text>Section 54 of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Section><MarginalNote>Decision</MarginalNote><Label>54</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The General Division may dismiss the appeal or confirm, rescind or vary a decision of the Minister in whole or in part or give the decision that the Minister should have given.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Reasons</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The General Division may give a decision orally or in writing and must give reasons. Copies of the decision and reasons, written or, in the case of an oral decision and reasons, reduced to writing, must be sent to the appellant, the Minister and any other party.</Text></Subsection></Section></AmendedText><ExplanatoryNote><Label><Emphasis style="italic">Clause 12</Emphasis>:</Label><ExplanatoryText>Existing text of section 54:</ExplanatoryText><ExistingText><Section><Label>54</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The General Division may dismiss the appeal or confirm, rescind or vary a decision of the Minister or the Commission in whole or in part or give the decision that the Minister or the Commission should have given.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The General Division may give a decision orally or in writing and must give reasons. Copies of the decision and reasons, written or, in the case of an oral decision and reasons, reduced to writing, must be sent to the appellant and the Minister or the Commission, as the case may be, and any other party.</Text></Subsection></Section></ExistingText></ExplanatoryNote></Section><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote><HistoricalNote>2012, c. 19, s. 224</HistoricalNote></MarginalNote><Label>13</Label><Text>The heading before section 55 of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Heading level="3"><TitleText><Ins>Appeal to Tribunal</Ins> — Appeal Division</TitleText></Heading><Heading level="4"><TitleText><Ins>Decisions of Board of Appeal</Ins></TitleText></Heading></AmendedText><ExplanatoryNote><Label><Emphasis style="italic">Clause 13</Emphasis>:</Label><ExplanatoryText>Existing text of the heading:</ExplanatoryText><ExistingText><Heading level="3"><TitleText>Appeal Division</TitleText></Heading></ExistingText></ExplanatoryNote></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>14</Label><Text>The Act is amended by adding the following before section 55:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Section change="ins"><MarginalNote>Appeal</MarginalNote><Label>54.1</Label><Text>Any decision of the Board of Appeal may be appealed to the Appeal Division by any person who is the subject of the decision and any other prescribed person.</Text></Section><Section change="ins"><MarginalNote>Appeal — time limit</MarginalNote><Label>54.2</Label><Subsection change="ins"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The appeal must be brought to the Appeal Division in the prescribed form and manner and within 30 days after the day on which the decision and reasons are communicated in writing to the appellant.</Text></Subsection><Subsection change="ins"><MarginalNote>Extension</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The Appeal Division may allow further time within which an appeal is to be brought, but in no case may an appeal be brought more than one year after the day on which the decision and reasons are communicated in writing to the appellant.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section change="ins"><MarginalNote>Grounds of appeal</MarginalNote><Label>54.3</Label><Text>The only grounds of appeal of a decision made by the Board of Appeal are that</Text><Paragraph change="ins"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>the Board of Appeal failed to observe a principle of natural justice or otherwise acted beyond or refused to exercise its jurisdiction;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph change="ins"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>the Board of Appeal erred in law in making its decision, whether or not the error appears on the face of the record;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph change="ins"><Label>(c)</Label><Text>the Board of Appeal based its decision on an erroneous finding of fact that it made in a perverse or capricious manner or without regard for the material before it; or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph change="ins"><Label>(d)</Label><Text>a question of constitutional law remains to be determined.</Text></Paragraph></Section><Section change="ins"><MarginalNote>New evidence — constitutional questions</MarginalNote><Label>54.4</Label><Text>If an appeal to the Appeal Division of a decision of the Board of Appeal is in respect of a question of constitutional law, the Appeal Division may hear new evidence in relation to the question.</Text></Section><Section change="ins"><MarginalNote>Decision</MarginalNote><Label>54.5</Label><Subsection change="ins"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The Appeal Division may dismiss the appeal, give the decision that the Board of Appeal should have given, refer the matter back to the Board of Appeal for reconsideration in accordance with any directions that the Appeal Division considers appropriate or confirm, rescind or vary the decision of the Board of Appeal in whole or in part. The Appeal Division may make a decision on a question of constitutional law.</Text></Subsection><Subsection change="ins"><MarginalNote>Reasons</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The Appeal Division must give its decision in writing, with reasons, and send copies of the decision and reasons to the appellant and any other party.</Text></Subsection></Section><Heading level="4"><TitleText><Ins>Decisions of General Division</Ins></TitleText></Heading></AmendedText><ExplanatoryNote><Label><Emphasis style="italic">Clause 14</Emphasis>:</Label><ExplanatoryText>New.</ExplanatoryText></ExplanatoryNote></Section><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote><HistoricalNote>2012, c. 19, s. 224; 2021, c. 23, ss. 226 and 227</HistoricalNote></MarginalNote><Label>15</Label><Text>Sections 56 and 57 of the Act are replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Section><MarginalNote>Leave</MarginalNote><Label>56</Label><Text>An appeal to the Appeal Division <Ins>of a decision made by the Income Security Section</Ins> may only be brought if leave to appeal is granted.</Text></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Appeal — Employment Insurance Section</MarginalNote><Label>57</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>An appeal of a decision made by the Employment Insurance Section must be <Ins>brought</Ins> to the Appeal Division in the prescribed form and manner and within 30 days after the day on which the decision and reasons are communicated in writing to the appellant.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Appeal — Income Security Section</MarginalNote><Label><Ins>(1.1)</Ins></Label><Text><Ins>An</Ins> application for leave to <Ins>appeal</Ins> a decision made by the Income Security Section <Ins>must be</Ins> made <Ins>to</Ins> the <Ins>Appeal Division</Ins> in the <Ins>prescribed form</Ins> and <Ins>manner</Ins> and <Ins>within</Ins> 90 days after the day on which the decision and reasons are communicated in writing to the appellant.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Extension</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The Appeal Division may allow further time within which an <Ins>appeal is to be brought or an</Ins> application for<PageBreak /> leave to appeal is to be made, but in no case may an <Ins>appeal be brought or an</Ins> application be made more than one year after the day on which the decision and reasons are communicated in writing to the appellant.</Text></Subsection></Section></AmendedText><ExplanatoryNote><Label><Emphasis style="italic">Clause 15</Emphasis>:</Label><ExplanatoryText>Existing text of sections 56 and 57:</ExplanatoryText><ExistingText><Section><Label>56</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>An appeal to the Appeal Division may only be brought if leave to appeal is granted.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><Label>(2)</Label><Text>(Repealed, 2021, c. 23, s. 226)</Text></Subsection></Section><Section><Label>57</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>An application for leave to appeal must be made to the Appeal Division in the prescribed form and manner and within</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>in the case of a decision made by the Employment Insurance Section, 30 days after the day on which the decision and reasons are communicated in writing to the appellant; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>in the case of a decision made by the Income Security Section, 90 days after the day on which the decision and reasons are communicated in writing to the appellant.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The Appeal Division may allow further time within which an application for leave to appeal is to be made, but in no case may an <Keep svc="1">application</Keep> be made more than one year after the day on which the decision and reasons are communicated in writing to the appellant.</Text></Subsection></Section></ExistingText></ExplanatoryNote></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>16</Label><Text>Sections 56 and 57 of the Act are replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Section><MarginalNote>Leave</MarginalNote><Label>56</Label><Text>An appeal to the Appeal Division of a decision made by the General Division may only be brought if leave to appeal is granted.</Text></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Appeal — General Division</MarginalNote><Label>57</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>An application for leave to appeal a decision made by the General Division must be made to the Appeal Division in the prescribed form and manner and within 90 days after the day on which the decision and reasons are communicated in writing to the appellant.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Extension</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The Appeal Division may allow further time within which an application for leave to appeal is to be made, but in no case may an application be made more than one year after the day on which the decision and reasons are communicated in writing to the appellant.</Text></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote><HistoricalNote>2012, c. 19, s. 224; 2021, c. 23, ss. 228(1) and (2)(E)</HistoricalNote></MarginalNote><Label>17</Label><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Subsection 58(1) of the Act is repealed.</Text><ExplanatoryNote><Label><Emphasis style="italic">Clause 17</Emphasis>: (1) and (2)</Label><ExplanatoryText>Existing text of subsections 58(1) and (2):</ExplanatoryText><ExistingText><Section><Label>58</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The only grounds of appeal of a decision made by the Employment Insurance Section are that the Section</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>failed to observe a principle of natural justice or otherwise acted beyond or refused to exercise its jurisdiction;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>erred in law in making its decision, whether or not the error appears on the face of the record; or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(c)</Label><Text>based its decision on an erroneous finding of fact that it made in a perverse or capricious manner or without regard for the material before it.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Leave to appeal is refused if the Appeal Division is satisfied that the appeal has no reasonable chance of success.</Text></Subsection></Section></ExistingText></ExplanatoryNote></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><MarginalNote><HistoricalNote>2012, c. 19, s. 224</HistoricalNote></MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Subsection 58(2) of the Act is repealed.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote><HistoricalNote>2021, c. 23, s. 229</HistoricalNote></MarginalNote><Label>18</Label><Text>Section 58.1 of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Section><MarginalNote>Leave to appeal — General Division</MarginalNote><Label>58.1</Label><Text>Leave to appeal a decision made by the <Ins>General Division</Ins> is to be granted if the application for leave to appeal</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>raises an arguable case that the <Ins>General Division</Ins> failed to observe a principle of natural justice or otherwise acted beyond or refused to exercise its jurisdiction;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>raises an arguable case that the <Ins>General Division</Ins> erred in law, in fact or in mixed law and fact, in making its decision; or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(c)</Label><Text>sets out evidence that was not presented to the <Ins>General Division</Ins>.</Text></Paragraph></Section></AmendedText><ExplanatoryNote><Label><Emphasis style="italic">Clause 18</Emphasis>:</Label><ExplanatoryText>Existing text of section 58.1:</ExplanatoryText><ExistingText><Section><Label>58.1</Label><Text>Leave to appeal a decision made by the Income Security Section is to be granted if the application for leave to appeal</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>raises an arguable case that the Section failed to observe a principle of natural justice or otherwise acted beyond or refused to exercise its jurisdiction;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>raises an arguable case that the Section erred in law, in fact or in mixed law and fact, in making its decision; or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(c)</Label><Text>sets out evidence that was not presented to the Section.</Text></Paragraph></Section></ExistingText></ExplanatoryNote></Section><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote><HistoricalNote>2021, c. 23, s. 229</HistoricalNote></MarginalNote><Label>19</Label><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Subsection 58.2(1) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Section><MarginalNote>Decision — leave to appeal</MarginalNote><Label>58.2</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The Appeal Division must either grant or refuse leave to appeal a decision made by the <Ins>Income Security Section</Ins>.</Text></Subsection></Section></AmendedText><ExplanatoryNote><Label><Emphasis style="italic">Clause 19</Emphasis>: (1)</Label><ExplanatoryText>Existing text of subsection 58.2(1):</ExplanatoryText><ExistingText><Section><Label>58.2</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The Appeal Division must either grant or refuse leave to appeal a decision made by the General Division.</Text></Subsection></Section></ExistingText></ExplanatoryNote></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Subsection 58.2(1) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Section><MarginalNote>Decision — leave to appeal</MarginalNote><Label>58.2</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The Appeal Division must either grant or refuse leave to appeal a decision made by the General Division.</Text></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Subsection></Section><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote><HistoricalNote>2021, c. 23, s. 229</HistoricalNote></MarginalNote><Label>20</Label><Text>Section 58.3 of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Section><MarginalNote>Hearing <Language xml:lang="la">de novo</Language> — General Division</MarginalNote><Label>58.3</Label><Text>An appeal to the Appeal Division of a decision made by the <Ins>General Division</Ins> is to be heard and determined as a new proceeding.</Text></Section></AmendedText><ExplanatoryNote><Label><Emphasis style="italic">Clause 20</Emphasis>:</Label><ExplanatoryText>Existing text of section 58.3:</ExplanatoryText><ExistingText><Section><Label>58.3</Label><Text>An appeal to the Appeal Division of a decision made by the Income Security Section is to be heard and determined as a new proceeding.</Text></Section></ExistingText></ExplanatoryNote></Section><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote><HistoricalNote>2012, c. 19, s. 224; 2021, c. 23, ss. 230(1)</HistoricalNote></MarginalNote><Label>21</Label><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Subsection 59(1) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Section><MarginalNote>Decision</MarginalNote><Label>59</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The Appeal Division may dismiss the appeal, give the decision that the General Division should have given or confirm, rescind or vary the decision of the General Division in whole or in part. In the case of an appeal of a decision made by the Employment Insurance Section, the Appeal Division may also refer the matter back to the <Ins>Board of Appeal</Ins> for reconsideration in accordance with any directions that the Appeal Division considers appropriate.</Text></Subsection></Section></AmendedText><ExplanatoryNote><Label><Emphasis style="italic">Clause 21</Emphasis>: (1)</Label><ExplanatoryText>Existing text of subsection 59(1):</ExplanatoryText><ExistingText><Section><Label>59</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The Appeal Division may dismiss the appeal, give the decision that the General Division should have given or confirm, rescind or vary the decision of the General Division in whole or in part. In the case of an appeal of a decision made by the Employment Insurance Section, the Appeal Division may also refer the matter back to the Employment Insurance Section for reconsideration in accordance with any directions that the Appeal Division considers appropriate.</Text></Subsection></Section></ExistingText></ExplanatoryNote></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Subsection 59(1) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Section><MarginalNote>Decision</MarginalNote><Label>59</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The Appeal Division may dismiss the appeal, give the decision that the General Division should have given or confirm, rescind or vary the decision of the General Division in whole or in part.</Text></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Subsection></Section><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote><HistoricalNote>2012, c. 19, s. 224; 2021, c. 23, s. 235</HistoricalNote></MarginalNote><Label>22</Label><Text>Section 67 of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Section><MarginalNote>Time limits</MarginalNote><Label>67</Label><Text>The Chairperson or a Vice-chairperson may, in any particular case for special reasons, extend the time within which the Tribunal is required by regulation to make a decision under subsections 54(1), <Ins>54.5(1)</Ins>, 58.2(1) and 59(1).</Text></Section></AmendedText><ExplanatoryNote><Label><Emphasis style="italic">Clause 22</Emphasis>:</Label><ExplanatoryText>Existing text of section 67:</ExplanatoryText><ExistingText><Section><Label>67</Label><Text>The Chairperson or a Vice-chairperson may, in any particular case for special reasons, extend the time within which the Tribunal is required by regulation to make a decision under subsections 54(1), 58.2(1) and 59(1).</Text></Section></ExistingText></ExplanatoryNote></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>23</Label><Text>The Act is amended by adding the following after section 68:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Section change="ins"><MarginalNote>Access to documents and information by Appeal Division</MarginalNote><Label>68.01</Label><Text>On the request of the Appeal Division, the Board of Appeal must provide the Appeal Division with any documents and information that are necessary for the Appeal Division to decide an application or appeal.</Text></Section></AmendedText><ExplanatoryNote><Label><Emphasis style="italic">Clause 23</Emphasis>:</Label><ExplanatoryText>New.</ExplanatoryText></ExplanatoryNote></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>24</Label><Text>The Act is amended by adding the following before section 69:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Section change="ins"><MarginalNote>Commission</MarginalNote><Label>68.2</Label><Text>The Commission may, with the approval of the Governor in Council, make regulations with regard to the Board of Appeal respecting</Text><Paragraph change="ins"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>the quorum for a panel referred to in subsection 43.05(1);</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph change="ins"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>the appointment process for and conflicts of interest of members of the Board of Appeal referred to in paragraphs 43.03(1)(b) and (c);</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph change="ins"><Label>(c)</Label><Text>the circumstances in which a hearing may be held in private;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(d)</Label><Text>the procedure to be followed on applications made or appeals brought to the Board of Appeal;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(e)</Label><Text>the circumstances under which information is deemed to have been communicated or received;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(f)</Label><Text>the time within which the Board of Appeal must make a decision under subsection 43.13(1);</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(g)</Label><Text>any special reasons for the purposes of section 43.14;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(h)</Label><Text>any reasons for the purposes of section 43.15;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(i)</Label><Text>the power to exclude any person from a hearing when oral evidence concerning a circumstance of sexual or other harassment is being given;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(j)</Label><Text>the form and manner that is to be prescribed for the purposes of subsection 43.11(1);</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(k)</Label><Text>regions for the purposes of subsections 43.04(5) and 43.16(1);</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(l)</Label><Text>the circumstances for the purposes of subsection 43.16(1); and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(m)</Label><Text>the circumstances for the purposes of subsection 43.16(2).</Text></Paragraph></Section></AmendedText><ExplanatoryNote><Label><Emphasis style="italic">Clause 24</Emphasis>:</Label><ExplanatoryText>New.</ExplanatoryText></ExplanatoryNote></Section><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote><HistoricalNote>2012, c. 19, s. 224; 2021, c. 23, s. 236(2)</HistoricalNote></MarginalNote><Label>25</Label><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Paragraph 69(c) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(c)</Label><Text>the time within which the Tribunal must make a decision under subsections 54(1), <Ins>54.5(1)</Ins>, 58.2(1) and 59(1);</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText><ExplanatoryNote><Label><Emphasis style="italic">Clause 25</Emphasis>: (1) and (2)</Label><ExplanatoryText>Relevant portion of section 69:</ExplanatoryText><ExistingText><Section><Label>69</Label><Text>The Governor in Council may make regulations respecting the manner in which the Tribunal may conduct its business, including regulations respecting</Text><Paragraph><Label>...</Label><Text> </Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(c)</Label><Text>the time within which the Tribunal must make a decision under subsections 54(1), 58.2(1) and 59(1);</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>...</Label><Text> </Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(f)</Label><Text>anything that, by this Part, is to be prescribed by regulation.</Text></Paragraph></Section></ExistingText></ExplanatoryNote></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><MarginalNote><HistoricalNote>2012, c. 19, s. 224</HistoricalNote></MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Paragraph 69(f) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(f)</Label><Text>anything that is to be prescribed by <Ins>subsection 52(1), section 54.1, subsection 54.2(1), section 55 and subsections 57(1) and (1.1)</Ins>.</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(3)</Label><Text>Paragraph 69(f) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(f)</Label><Text>anything that is to be prescribed by subsection 52(1), section 54.1, subsection 54.2(1), section 55 and subsection 57(1).</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection></Section><Heading level="1"><TitleText>Consequential Amendments</TitleText></Heading><Heading level="2"><MarginalNote><HistoricalNote>R.S, c. F-7; 2002, c. 8, s. 14</HistoricalNote></MarginalNote><TitleText><XRefExternal reference-type="act">Federal Courts Act</XRefExternal></TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote><HistoricalNote>2012, c. 19, s. 272(2); 2013, c. 40, par. 236(1)(d); 2021, c. 23, s. 237</HistoricalNote></MarginalNote><Label>26</Label><Text>Paragraph 28(1)(g.1) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Federal Courts Act</XRefExternal> is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(g.1)</Label><Text>the Appeal Division of the Social Security Tribunal established under section 44 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Department of Employment and Social Development Act</XRefExternal>, unless the decision is made under subsection <Ins>54.2(2) or</Ins> 57(2) or section 58.2 of that Act or relates to an appeal respecting a decision relating to further time to make a request under subsection <Ins>43.11(2) or</Ins> 52(2) of that Act, section 81 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Canada Pension Plan</XRefExternal>, section 27.1 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Old Age Security Act</XRefExternal> or section 112 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Employment Insurance Act</XRefExternal>;</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText><ExplanatoryNote><TitleText>Federal Courts Act</TitleText><Label><Emphasis style="italic">Clause 26</Emphasis>:</Label><ExplanatoryText>Relevant portion of subsection 28(1):</ExplanatoryText><ExistingText><Section><Label>28</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The Federal Court of Appeal has jurisdiction to hear and determine applications for judicial review made in respect of any of the following federal boards, commissions or other tribunals:</Text><Paragraph><Label>...</Label><Text> </Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(g.1)</Label><Text>the Appeal Division of the Social Security Tribunal established under section 44 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Department of Employment and Social Development Act</XRefExternal>, unless the decision is made under subsection 57(2) or section 58.2 of that Act or relates to an appeal respecting a decision relating to further time to make a request under subsection 52(2) of that Act, section 81 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Canada Pension Plan</XRefExternal>, section 27.1 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Old Age Security Act</XRefExternal> or section 112 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Employment Insurance Act</XRefExternal>;</Text></Paragraph></Subsection></Section></ExistingText></ExplanatoryNote></Section><Heading level="2"><MarginalNote><HistoricalNote>R.S., c. L-1</HistoricalNote></MarginalNote><TitleText><XRefExternal reference-type="act">Labour Adjustment Benefits Act</XRefExternal></TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote><HistoricalNote>2012, c. 19, s. 273(2); 2013, c. 40, subpar. 236(1)(f)(i)</HistoricalNote></MarginalNote><Label>27</Label><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The definition <DefinedTermEn>Social Security Tribunal</DefinedTermEn> in subsection 2(1) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Labour Adjustment Benefits Act</XRefExternal> is repealed.</Text><ExplanatoryNote><TitleText>Labour Adjustment Benefits Act</TitleText><Label><Emphasis style="italic">Clause 27</Emphasis>: (1)</Label><ExplanatoryText>Existing text of the definition:</ExplanatoryText><ExistingText><SectionPiece><Definition><Text><DefinedTermEn>Social Security Tribunal</DefinedTermEn> means the Social Security Tribunal established under section 44 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Department of Employment and Social Development Act</XRefExternal>; (<DefinedTermFr>Tribunal de la sécurité sociale</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Definition></SectionPiece></ExistingText></ExplanatoryNote></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Subsection 2(1) of the Act is amended by adding the following in alphabetical order:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><SectionPiece><Definition><Text><Ins><DefinedTermEn>Employment Insurance Board of Appeal</DefinedTermEn> means the Employment Insurance Board of Appeal established under section 43.01 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Department of Employment and Social Development Act</XRefExternal>. (<DefinedTermFr>Conseil d’appel en assurance-emploi</DefinedTermFr>)</Ins></Text></Definition></SectionPiece></AmendedText><ExplanatoryNote><Label>(2)</Label><ExplanatoryText>New.</ExplanatoryText></ExplanatoryNote></Subsection></Section><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote><HistoricalNote>2012, c. 19, s. 274; 2013, c. 40, subpar. 236(1)(f)(ii)</HistoricalNote></MarginalNote><Label>28</Label><Text>Subsections 13(6) and (7) of the Act are replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Subsection><MarginalNote>Reference to Employment Insurance Board of Appeal</MarginalNote><Label>(6)</Label><Text>The Commission may at any time within 14 days after receiving an application under subsection (1) refer the application or a question arising from it to the <Ins>Employment Insurance Board of Appeal</Ins> for a decision on it.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Proceedings before Employment Insurance Board of Appeal</MarginalNote><Label>(7)</Label><Text>If an application or question is referred to the <Ins>Employment Insurance Board of Appeal</Ins> under subsection (6), the <Ins>Employment Insurance Board of Appeal</Ins> must conduct its proceedings in respect of that application or question in accordance with the procedure for appeals under the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Department of Employment and Social Development Act</XRefExternal>.</Text></Subsection></AmendedText><ExplanatoryNote><Label><Emphasis style="italic">Clause 28</Emphasis>:</Label><ExplanatoryText>Existing text of subsections 13(6) and (7):</ExplanatoryText><ExistingText><Subsection><Label>(6)</Label><Text>The Commission may at any time within 14 days after receiving an application under subsection (1) refer the application or a question arising from it to the General Division of the Social Security Tribunal for a decision on it.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><Label>(7)</Label><Text>If an application or question is referred to the General Division of the Social Security Tribunal under subsection (6), the Tribunal must conduct its proceedings in respect of that application or question in accordance with the procedure for appeals under the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Department of Employment and Social Development Act</XRefExternal>.</Text></Subsection></ExistingText></ExplanatoryNote></Section><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote><HistoricalNote>2012, c. 19, s. 275</HistoricalNote></MarginalNote><Label>29</Label><Text>Subsection 31(2) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Section><MarginalNote>Appeal of Commission decision</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Any person may, at any time within 30 days after the day a decision of the Commission under this Act, other than subsection 14(2) or (3), is communicated to <Ins>them</Ins>, or within any further time that the Commission may in any particular case for special reason allow, appeal to the <Ins>Employment Insurance Board of Appeal</Ins>.</Text></Section></AmendedText><ExplanatoryNote><Label><Emphasis style="italic">Clause 29</Emphasis>:</Label><ExplanatoryText>Existing text of subsection 31(2):</ExplanatoryText><ExistingText><Subsection><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Any person may, at any time within 30 days after the day a decision of the Commission under this Act, other than subsection 14(2) or (3), is communicated to him or her, or within any further time that the Commission may in any particular case for special reason allow, appeal to the Social Security Tribunal.</Text></Subsection></ExistingText></ExplanatoryNote></Section><Heading level="2"><MarginalNote><HistoricalNote>R.S., c. 1 (5th Supp.)</HistoricalNote></MarginalNote><TitleText><XRefExternal reference-type="act">Income Tax Act</XRefExternal></TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><Label>30</Label><Text>Subparagraph 56(1)(l)(ii) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Income Tax Act</XRefExternal> is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><SectionPiece><Subparagraph><Label>(ii)</Label><Text>reimbursement of costs incurred in relation to a decision of the Canada Employment Insurance Commission under the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Employment Insurance Act</XRefExternal> or to an appeal of such a decision to the Social Security Tribunal <Ins>or the Employment Insurance Board of Appeal under the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Department of Employment and Social Development Act</XRefExternal></Ins>,</Text></Subparagraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText><ExplanatoryNote><TitleText>Income Tax Act</TitleText><Label><Emphasis style="italic">Clause 30</Emphasis>:</Label><ExplanatoryText>Relevant portion of subsection 56(1):</ExplanatoryText><ExistingText><Section><Label>56</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Without restricting the generality of section 3, there shall be included in computing the income of a taxpayer for a taxation year,</Text><Paragraph><Label>...</Label><Text> </Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(l)</Label><Text>amounts received by the taxpayer in the year as</Text><Subparagraph><Label>...</Label><Text> </Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph><Label>(ii)</Label><Text>reimbursement of costs incurred in relation to a decision of the Canada Employment Insurance Commission under the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Employment Insurance Act</XRefExternal> or to an appeal of such a decision to the Social Security Tribunal,</Text></Subparagraph></Paragraph></Subsection></Section></ExistingText></ExplanatoryNote></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>31</Label><Text>Subparagraph 60(o)(ii) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><SectionPiece><Subparagraph><Label>(ii)</Label><Text>a decision of the Canada Employment Insurance Commission under the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Employment Insurance Act</XRefExternal> or to an appeal of such a decision to the Social Security Tribunal <Ins>or the Employment Insurance Board of Appeal under the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Department of Employment and Social Development Act</XRefExternal></Ins>,</Text></Subparagraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText><ExplanatoryNote><Label><Emphasis style="italic">Clause 31</Emphasis>:</Label><ExplanatoryText>Relevant portion of section 60:</ExplanatoryText><ExistingText><Section><Label>60</Label><Text>There may be deducted in computing a taxpayer’s income for a taxation year such of the following amounts as are applicable</Text><Paragraph><Label>...</Label><Text> </Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(o)</Label><Text>amounts paid by the taxpayer in the year in respect of fees or expenses incurred in preparing, instituting or prosecuting an objection to, or an appeal in relation to,</Text><Subparagraph><Label>...</Label><Text> </Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph><Label>(ii)</Label><Text>a decision of the Canada Employment Insurance Commission under the Employment Insurance Act or to an appeal of such a decision to the Social Security Tribunal,</Text></Subparagraph></Paragraph></Section></ExistingText></ExplanatoryNote></Section><Heading level="2"><MarginalNote><HistoricalNote>1996, c. 23</HistoricalNote></MarginalNote><TitleText><XRefExternal reference-type="act">Employment Insurance Act</XRefExternal></TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote><HistoricalNote>2012, c. 19, s. 247; 2013, c. 40, subpar. 236(1)(c)(iii)</HistoricalNote></MarginalNote><Label>32</Label><Text>Section 113 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Employment Insurance Act</XRefExternal> is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Section><MarginalNote>Appeal to Employment Insurance Board of Appeal</MarginalNote><Label>113</Label><Text>A party who is dissatisfied with a decision of the Commission made under section 112, including a decision in relation to further time to make a request, may appeal the decision to the <Ins>Employment Insurance Board of Appeal</Ins> established under section <Ins>43.01</Ins> of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Department of Employment and Social Development Act</XRefExternal>.</Text></Section></AmendedText><ExplanatoryNote><TitleText>Employment Insurance Act</TitleText><Label><Emphasis style="italic">Clause 32</Emphasis>:</Label><ExplanatoryText>Existing text of section 113:</ExplanatoryText><ExistingText><Section><Label>113</Label><Text>A party who is dissatisfied with a decision of the Commission made under section 112, including a decision in relation to further time to make a request, may appeal the decision to the Social Security Tribunal established under section 44 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Department of Employment and Social Development Act</XRefExternal>.</Text></Section></ExistingText></ExplanatoryNote></Section><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote><HistoricalNote>2012, c. 19, s. 247; 2013, c. 40, subpar. 236(1)(c)(iv)</HistoricalNote></MarginalNote><Label>33</Label><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Subsection 114(1) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Section><MarginalNote>Payment of benefit pending appeal</MarginalNote><Label>114</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>If a claim for benefits is allowed by the General Division of the Social Security Tribunal established under section 44 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Department of Employment and Social Development Act</XRefExternal> <Ins>or the Employment Insurance Board of</Ins> <Ins>Appeal established under section 43.01 of that Act</Ins>, benefits are payable in accordance with the decision of the Tribunal <Ins>or the Employment Insurance Board of Appeal, as the case may be</Ins>, even though an appeal is pending, and any benefits paid under this section after the decision of the Tribunal <Ins>or the Employment Insurance Board of Appeal, as the case may be</Ins>, are to be treated as having been duly paid and are not recoverable from the claimant, even if the final determination of the question is adverse to the claimant.</Text></Subsection></Section></AmendedText><ExplanatoryNote><Label><Emphasis style="italic">Clause 33</Emphasis>: (1)</Label><ExplanatoryText>Existing text of subsection 114(1):</ExplanatoryText><ExistingText><Section><Label>114</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>If a claim for benefits is allowed by the General Division of the Social Security Tribunal established under section 44 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Department of Employment and Social Development Act</XRefExternal>, benefits are payable in accordance with the decision of the Tribunal even though an appeal is pending, and any benefits paid under this section after the Tribunal’s decision are to be treated as having been duly paid and are not recoverable from the claimant, even if the final determination of the question is adverse to the claimant.</Text></Subsection></Section></ExistingText></ExplanatoryNote></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Subsection 114(1) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Section><MarginalNote>Payment of benefit pending appeal</MarginalNote><Label>114</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>If a claim for benefits is allowed by the Employment Insurance Board of Appeal established under section 43.01 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Department of Employment and Social Development Act</XRefExternal>, benefits are payable in accordance with the decision of the Employment Insurance Board of Appeal even though an appeal is pending, and any benefits paid under this section after the decision of the Employment Insurance Board of Appeal are to be treated as having been duly paid and are not recoverable from the claimant, even if the final determination of the question is adverse to the claimant.</Text></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><MarginalNote><HistoricalNote>2012, c. 19, s. 247</HistoricalNote></MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>Paragraph 114(2)(a) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>if the appeal to the Appeal Division of the Social Security Tribunal was brought within 21 days after the day on which the decision of the General Division of the Social Security Tribunal <Ins>or the Employment Insurance Board of Appeal, as the case may be</Ins>, was given and on the ground that the claimant ought to be disentitled under section 36; and</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText><ExplanatoryNote><Label>(3)</Label><ExplanatoryText>Relevant portion of subsection 114(2):</ExplanatoryText><ExistingText><Subsection><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Subsection (1) does not apply</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>if the appeal to the Appeal Division of the Social Security Tribunal was brought within 21 days after the day on which the decision of the General Division of the Social Security Tribunal was given and on the ground that the claimant ought to be disentitled under section 36; and</Text></Paragraph></Subsection></ExistingText></ExplanatoryNote></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(4)</Label><Text>Paragraph 114(2)(a) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>if the appeal to the Appeal Division of the Social Security Tribunal was brought within 21 days after the day on which the decision of the Employment Insurance Board of Appeal was given and on the ground that the claimant ought to be disentitled under section 36; and</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection></Section><Heading level="1" type="transitional"><TitleText>Transitional Provisions</TitleText></Heading><Section type="transitional"><MarginalNote>Definitions</MarginalNote><Label>34</Label><Text>The following definitions apply in this section and sections <XRefInternal>35</XRefInternal> to <XRefInternal>48</XRefInternal>.</Text><Definition><Text><DefinedTermEn>Appeal Division</DefinedTermEn> means the Appeal Division of the Tribunal. (<DefinedTermFr>division d’appel</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Definition><Definition><Text><DefinedTermEn>Board of Appeal</DefinedTermEn> means the Employment Insurance Board of Appeal established under section 43.01 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Department of Employment and Social Development Act</XRefExternal>. (<DefinedTermFr>Conseil d’appel</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Definition><Definition><Text><DefinedTermEn>Employment Insurance Section</DefinedTermEn> means the Employment Insurance Section of the General Division. (<DefinedTermFr>section de l’assurance-emploi</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Definition><Definition><Text><DefinedTermEn>General Division</DefinedTermEn> means, except for the purposes of subsections 35(2) and 37(2), the General Division referred to in section 44 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Department of Employment and Social Development Act</XRefExternal>, as it reads on the day on which this section comes into force. (<DefinedTermFr>division générale</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Definition><Definition><Text><DefinedTermEn>Tribunal</DefinedTermEn> means the Social Security Tribunal established under section 44 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Department of Employment and Social Development Act</XRefExternal>. (<DefinedTermFr>Tribunal</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Definition></Section><Section type="transitional"><MarginalNote>Part-time members</MarginalNote><Label>35</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Part-time members of the Tribunal who, immediately before the day on which section <XRefInternal>5</XRefInternal> comes into force, are assigned to hear matters in the Employment Insurance Section become part-time members of the Board of Appeal on that day.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Full-time members</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Full-time members of the Tribunal who, immediately before the day on which section <XRefInternal>5</XRefInternal> comes into force, are assigned to hear matters in the Employment Insurance Section are assigned to hear matters in the General Division on that day.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Vice-chairperson</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>The Vice-chairperson of the Tribunal who, immediately before the day on which section <XRefInternal>5</XRefInternal> comes into force, is responsible for the Employment Insurance Section becomes a full-time regional coordinator of the Board of Appeal on that day.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Power of Governor in Council</MarginalNote><Label>(4)</Label><Text>On the recommendation of the Minister of Employment and Social Development made after that Minister has consulted with the Chairperson of the Tribunal and the Executive Head of the Board of Appeal, the Governor in Council may make an order specifying that, on a day that is specified in the order and that is before the day on which section <XRefInternal>5</XRefInternal> comes into force,</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>the Vice-chairperson who is responsible for the Employment Insurance Section becomes a full-time regional coordinator of the Board of Appeal; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>a part-time member of the Tribunal who is assigned to hear matters in the Employment Insurance Section becomes a part-time member of the Board of Appeal.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection></Section><Section type="transitional"><MarginalNote>Members of Board of Appeal</MarginalNote><Label>36</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Each member of the Board of Appeal referred to in subsection <XRefInternal>35</XRefInternal>(1) or paragraph <XRefInternal>35</XRefInternal>(4)(b)</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>on becoming a member, ceases to be a member of the Tribunal;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>subject to paragraph (d), continues in office for the remainder of the term for which they were appointed as a member of the Tribunal;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(c)</Label><Text>for that term, is deemed to be appointed under paragraph 43.03(1)(a) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Department of Employment and Social Development Act</XRefExternal>;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(d)</Label><Text>despite paragraph 43.03(1)(a) of that Act, holds office during good behaviour for that term and may be removed for cause by the Governor in Council at any time during that term; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(e)</Label><Text>on the expiry of that term, is eligible to be reappointed under that paragraph 43.03(1)(a) to hold office at pleasure.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Regional coordinator of Board of Appeal</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The regional coordinator of the Board of Appeal referred to in subsection <XRefInternal>35</XRefInternal>(3) or paragraph <XRefInternal>35</XRefInternal>(4)(a)</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>on becoming a regional coordinator, ceases to be a member of the Tribunal;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>subject to paragraph (d), continues in office for the remainder of the term for which they were appointed as a member of the Tribunal;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(c)</Label><Text>for that term, is deemed to be appointed under subsection 43.02(2) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Department of Employment and Social Development Act</XRefExternal>;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(d)</Label><Text>despite subsection 43.02(2) of that Act, holds office during good behaviour for that term and may be removed for cause by the Governor in Council at any time during that term; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(e)</Label><Text>on the expiry of that term, is eligible to be reappointed under that subsection 43.02(2) to hold office at pleasure.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection type="transitional"><MarginalNote>Part-time members — remuneration</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>On becoming a part-time member of the Board of Appeal and for the remainder of the term referred to in paragraph (1)(b), a former part-time member of the Tribunal who was assigned to hear matters in the Employment Insurance Section is entitled to remuneration that is no less than the remuneration that they received as a part-time member of the Tribunal.</Text></Subsection><Subsection type="transitional"><MarginalNote>Vice-chairperson — remuneration</MarginalNote><Label>(4)</Label><Text>On becoming a regional coordinator of the Board of Appeal and for the remainder of the term referred to in paragraph (2)(b), a former Vice-chairperson of the Tribunal who was responsible for the Employment Insurance Section is entitled to the same remuneration as they received as Vice-chairperson.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section type="transitional"><MarginalNote>No compensation</MarginalNote><Label>37</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Despite the provisions of any contract, agreement or order, no former member of the General Division, including the former Vice-chairperson responsible for the Employment Insurance Section, has any right to claim or receive any compensation, damages, indemnity or other form of relief from His Majesty in right of Canada or from any employee or agent of His Majesty for ceasing to hold office in the Tribunal, or for the abolition of that office, by the operation of this Act.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>No compensation — full-time members</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Despite the provisions of any contract, agreement or order, no full-time member of the Tribunal who was assigned to hear matters in the Employment Insurance Section has any right to claim or receive any compensation, damages, indemnity or other form of relief from His Majesty in right of Canada or from any employee or agent of His Majesty for being assigned to hear matters in the General Division by the operation of this Act.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section type="transitional"><MarginalNote>Application for leave to appeal</MarginalNote><Label>38</Label><Text>If an application for leave to appeal a decision made by the Employment Insurance Section is ongoing before the Appeal Division immediately before the day on which section <XRefInternal>4</XRefInternal> comes into force, the application for leave to appeal becomes a notice of appeal on that day. The notice of appeal is deemed to have been filed on the day on which the application for leave to appeal was filed.</Text></Section><Section type="transitional"><MarginalNote>Appeal of Employment Insurance Section decision</MarginalNote><Label>39</Label><Text>Any decision made by the Employment Insurance Section before the day on which section <XRefInternal>5</XRefInternal> comes into force may be appealed to the Appeal Division and sections 55, 57, 58 and 59 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Department of Employment and Social Development Act</XRefExternal>, as those sections read on the day on which section <XRefInternal>4</XRefInternal> comes into force, apply in respect of the appeal.</Text></Section><Section type="transitional"><MarginalNote>Ongoing appeal of Employment Insurance Section decision</MarginalNote><Label>40</Label><Text>An appeal of a decision made by the Employment Insurance Section that is ongoing before the Appeal Division immediately before the day on which section <XRefInternal>5</XRefInternal> comes into force is to be dealt with in accordance with sections 57, 58 and 59 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Department of Employment and Social Development Act</XRefExternal>, as those sections read on the day on which section <XRefInternal>4</XRefInternal> comes into force.</Text></Section><Section type="transitional"><MarginalNote>Question of constitutional law</MarginalNote><Label>41</Label><Text>The Appeal Division is not authorized under subsection 59(1) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Department of Employment and Social Development Act</XRefExternal>, as it read on the day on which section <XRefInternal>4</XRefInternal> comes into force, to refer a question of constitutional law back to the Board of Appeal for reconsideration.</Text></Section><Section type="transitional"><MarginalNote>Ongoing appeal before Employment Insurance Section</MarginalNote><Label>42</Label><Text>An appeal that is ongoing before the Employment Insurance Section immediately before the day on which section <XRefInternal>5</XRefInternal> comes into force is deemed to be an appeal before the Board of Appeal under subsection 43.11(1) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Department of Employment and Social Development Act</XRefExternal> on that day.</Text></Section><Section type="transitional"><MarginalNote>Board of Appeal access to documents and information</MarginalNote><Label>43</Label><Text>The Board of Appeal is entitled to access any documents and information of the Tribunal that are necessary for the Board of Appeal to decide an application or appeal.</Text></Section><Section type="transitional"><MarginalNote>Transfer of documents and information</MarginalNote><Label>44</Label><Text>The Tribunal must transfer to the Board of Appeal any documents and information that relate to appeals referred to in section <XRefInternal>42</XRefInternal>.</Text></Section><Section type="transitional"><MarginalNote>Section 53 of <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Department of Employment and Social Development Act</XRefExternal></MarginalNote><Label>45</Label><Text>Despite section 240 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Budget Implementation Act, 2021</XRefExternal>, <XRefExternal reference-type="act">No. 1</XRefExternal>, if, on an appeal of a decision made by the Employment Insurance Section under section 53 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Department of Employment and Social Development Act</XRefExternal>, as it read immediately before the day on which Division 20 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Budget Implementation Act, 2021</XRefExternal>, <XRefExternal reference-type="act">No. 1</XRefExternal> comes into force, the Appeal Division decides to refer a matter back to the Employment Insurance Section for reconsideration, the Appeal Division must refer the matter back to the Board of Appeal for reconsideration.</Text></Section><Section type="transitional"><MarginalNote>Section 241 of <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Budget Implementation Act, 2021, No. 1</XRefExternal></MarginalNote><Label>46</Label><Subsection type="transitional"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Section 241 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Budget Implementation Act, 2021</XRefExternal>, <XRefExternal reference-type="act">No. 1</XRefExternal> does not apply in respect of a decision in relation to the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Employment Insurance Act</XRefExternal> under section 66 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Department of Employment and Social Development Act</XRefExternal>, as it read immediately before the day on which Division 20 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Budget Implementation Act, 2021</XRefExternal>, <XRefExternal reference-type="act">No. 1</XRefExternal> comes into force, or in respect of an application under that section 66 in relation to the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Employment Insurance Act</XRefExternal> that is ongoing immediately before the day on which section <XRefInternal>4</XRefInternal> comes into force.</Text></Subsection><Subsection type="transitional"><MarginalNote>Section 66 of <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Department of Employment and Social Development Act</XRefExternal></MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Any matter relating to a decision or an application referred to in subsection (1) is to be dealt with in accordance with section 66 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Department of Employment and Social Development Act</XRefExternal>, as it read immediately before the day on which Division 20 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Budget Implementation Act, 2021, No. 1</XRefExternal> comes into force.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section type="transitional"><MarginalNote><XRefExternal reference-type="act">Employment Insurance Act</XRefExternal></MarginalNote><Label>47</Label><Text>Subsections 114(1) and (2) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Employment Insurance Act</XRefExternal>, as those subsections read on the day on which section <XRefInternal>4</XRefInternal> comes into force, continue to apply in relation to a claim for benefits that is allowed by the General Division before the day on which section <XRefInternal>5</XRefInternal> comes into force.</Text></Section><Section type="transitional"><MarginalNote><XRefExternal reference-type="act">Labour Adjustment Benefits Act</XRefExternal></MarginalNote><Label>48</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Subsection 13(7) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Labour Adjustment Benefits Act</XRefExternal>, as it read immediately before the day on which section <XRefInternal>4</XRefInternal> comes into force, continues to apply — until the day on which section <XRefInternal>5</XRefInternal> comes into force — in respect of an application or a question that was referred to the General Division under subsection 13(6) of that Act before the day on which section <XRefInternal>4</XRefInternal> comes into force.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Ongoing application or question</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>An application or a question that was referred to the General Division under subsection 13(6) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Labour Adjustment Benefits Act</XRefExternal> and that is ongoing immediately before the day on which section <XRefInternal>5</XRefInternal> comes into force is deemed to be an application or a question referred to the Board of Appeal on that day.</Text></Subsection></Section><Heading level="1"><TitleText>Coming into Force</TitleText></Heading><Section type="CIF"><MarginalNote>Order in council</MarginalNote><Label>49</Label><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Sections <XRefInternal>4</XRefInternal> and <XRefInternal>13</XRefInternal> to <XRefInternal>15</XRefInternal>, subsections <XRefInternal>17</XRefInternal>(2), <XRefInternal>19</XRefInternal>(1) and <XRefInternal>21</XRefInternal>(1), sections <XRefInternal>22</XRefInternal> and <XRefInternal>23</XRefInternal>, subsections <XRefInternal>25</XRefInternal>(1) and (2), sections <XRefInternal>26</XRefInternal> to <XRefInternal>32</XRefInternal>, subsections <XRefInternal>33</XRefInternal>(1) and (3), sections <XRefInternal>38</XRefInternal>, <XRefInternal>41</XRefInternal>, <XRefInternal>43</XRefInternal>, <XRefInternal>45</XRefInternal> and <XRefInternal>46</XRefInternal> and subsection <XRefInternal>48</XRefInternal>(1) come into force on a day to be fixed by order of the Governor in Council.</Text></Subsection><Subsection type="CIF"><MarginalNote>Order in council</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Sections <XRefInternal>5</XRefInternal> to <XRefInternal>9</XRefInternal>, <XRefInternal>11</XRefInternal>, <XRefInternal>12</XRefInternal> and <XRefInternal>16</XRefInternal>, subsection <XRefInternal>17</XRefInternal>(1), section <XRefInternal>18</XRefInternal>, subsection <XRefInternal>19</XRefInternal>(2), section <XRefInternal>20</XRefInternal>, subsections <XRefInternal>21</XRefInternal>(2), <XRefInternal>25</XRefInternal>(3) and <XRefInternal>33</XRefInternal>(2) and (4), sections <XRefInternal>39</XRefInternal>, <XRefInternal>40</XRefInternal>, <XRefInternal>42</XRefInternal>, <XRefInternal>44</XRefInternal> and <XRefInternal>47</XRefInternal> and subsection <XRefInternal>48</XRefInternal>(2) come into force on a day to be fixed by order of the Governor in Council, but that day must be after the day fixed under subsection (1).</Text></Subsection></Section></Body></Bill>