<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><Bill bill-origin="commons" bill-type="private-public" xml:lang="en" date-time="2023-11-09 09:23:14"><Identification><BillNumber>C-384</BillNumber><Parliament><Session>1</Session><Number>44</Number><RegnalYear><Year-s>70-71</Year-s><Monarch>Elizabeth II – 1-2 Charles III</Monarch></RegnalYear><Year-s>2021-2022-2023-2024</Year-s></Parliament><LongTitle>An Act to establish Turkish Heritage Month</LongTitle><ShortTitle status="unofficial" /><RunningHead>Turkish Heritage Month Act</RunningHead><BillHistory><Stages stage="first-reading-house"><Date><YYYY>2024</YYYY><MM>3</MM><DD>18</DD></Date></Stages></BillHistory><BillSponsor><Emphasis style="smallcaps">Mr. Masse</Emphasis></BillSponsor><BillRefNumber date-time="2023-11-09">441325</BillRefNumber></Identification><Introduction><Summary><TitleText>SUMMARY</TitleText><Provision><Text>This enactment designates the month of October as “Turkish Heritage Month”.</Text></Provision></Summary><Preamble><Provision><MarginalNote>Preamble</MarginalNote><Text>Whereas the first Turks arrived in Canada in the late 1800s, settling in Brantford, Ontario, in the years after Confederation;</Text></Provision><Provision><Text>Whereas the population of Turkish Canadians has since grown considerably and includes people from such Turkic nations as Azerbaijan, Kazakhstan, East Turkestan, Uzbekistan, Turkmenistan, Tajikistan and Tatarstan;</Text></Provision><Provision><Text>Whereas young, dynamic Turkish Canadian communities continue to flourish throughout Canada;</Text></Provision><Provision><Text>Whereas Turkish Canadians from all walks of life have contributed substantially to Canada’s social, economic and political life; </Text></Provision><Provision><Text>Whereas Turkish Canadians have made rich and significant contributions to the cultural fabric of Canada, including through food, literature, music and fashion;</Text></Provision><Provision><Text>And whereas Parliament wishes to recognize and celebrate the historic mark that Turkish Canadians have made and continue to make on Canadian society;</Text></Provision></Preamble><Enacts><Provision><Text>Now, therefore, His Majesty, by and with the advice and consent <Keep>of the</Keep> Senate and House of Commons of Canada, <Keep>enacts</Keep> as follows:</Text></Provision></Enacts></Introduction><Body><Heading level="1"><TitleText>Short Title</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Short title</MarginalNote><Label>1</Label><Text>This Act may be cited as the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Turkish Heritage Month Act</XRefExternal>.</Text></Section><Heading level="1"><TitleText>Turkish Heritage Month</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Turkish Heritage Month</MarginalNote><Label>2</Label><Text>Throughout Canada, in each year, the month of October is to be known as “Turkish Heritage Month”.</Text></Section></Body></Bill>