<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><Bill bill-origin="commons" bill-type="private-public" xml:lang="en" date-time="2023-09-28 16:57:19"><Identification><BillNumber>C-386</BillNumber><Parliament><Session>1</Session><Number>44</Number><RegnalYear><Year-s>70-71</Year-s><Monarch>Elizabeth II – 1-2 Charles III</Monarch></RegnalYear><Year-s>2021-2022-2023-2024</Year-s></Parliament><LongTitle>An Act respecting the establishment and award of a Special Service Medal for Domestic Emergency Relief Operations</LongTitle><ShortTitle status="unofficial" /><RunningHead>Special Service Medal for Domestic Emergency Relief Operations Act</RunningHead><BillHistory><Stages stage="first-reading-house"><Date><YYYY>2024</YYYY><MM>3</MM><DD>22</DD></Date></Stages></BillHistory><BillSponsor><Emphasis style="smallcaps">Mr. Doherty</Emphasis></BillSponsor><BillRefNumber date-time="2023-09-28">441365</BillRefNumber></Identification><Introduction><Summary><TitleText>SUMMARY</TitleText><Provision><Text>This enactment establishes a medal to be awarded to members and former members of the Canadian Forces, members and former members of the Royal Canadian Mounted Police, firefighters and former firefighters and first responders and former first responders who have served in certain domestic emergency relief operations.</Text></Provision></Summary><Enacts><Provision><Text>His Majesty, by and with the advice and consent <Keep>of the</Keep> Senate and House of Commons of Canada, <Keep>enacts</Keep> as follows:</Text></Provision></Enacts></Introduction><Body><Heading level="1"><TitleText>Short Title</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Short Title</MarginalNote><Label>1</Label><Text>This Act may be cited as the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Special Service Medal for Domestic Emergency Relief Operations Act</XRefExternal>.</Text></Section><Heading level="1"><TitleText>Medal</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Establishment</MarginalNote><Label>2</Label><Text>A medal to be called the Special Service Medal for Domestic Emergency Relief Operations is established.</Text></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Design of Medal</MarginalNote><Label>3</Label><Text>The Governor in Council may determine the design of the Medal and its associated ribbon. </Text></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Award of Medal</MarginalNote><Label>4</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>On the recommendation of a minister referred to in section 7, the Governor in Council may, for service performed for a period of at least seven days in support of domestic emergency relief operations designated by the Governor in Council, award the Medal to</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>members and former members of the Canadian Forces;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>members and former members of the Royal Canadian Mounted Police;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(c)</Label><Text>firefighters and former firefighters; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(d)</Label><Text>first responders and former first responders.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Single award</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The Medal is not to be awarded more than once to the same person, but additional bars may be awarded for multiple operations and may be worn with the medal.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Excluded persons</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>The Medal is not to be awarded to a person within a class of persons excluded by the regulations.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Posthumous award</MarginalNote><Label>5</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The Medal may be awarded posthumously.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Presentation</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>If the Medal is awarded posthumously, it is presented to the person who, in the opinion of the minister who nominated the person, is best suited to receive it.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Wearing of Medal</MarginalNote><Label>6</Label><Text>The Medal is to be worn in accordance with the order of precedence set out in the <XRefExternal reference-type="standard">Canadian Orders, Decorations and Medals Directive, 1998</XRefExternal>.</Text></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Nomination — Minister of National Defence</MarginalNote><Label>7</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The Minister of National Defence may nominate for award of the Medal those persons who are qualified under the regulations to be nominated for the Medal and who are members or former members of the Canadian Forces.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Nomination — Minister of Public Safety and Emergency Preparedness</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The Minister of Public Safety and Emergency Preparedness may nominate for award of the Medal those persons who are qualified under the regulations to be nominated for the Medal and who are members or former members of the Royal Canadian Mounted Police.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Nomination — other ministers</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>Any other minister of the Crown may nominate for award of the Medal those persons who are qualified under the regulations to be nominated for the Medal, who are members or former members of the Canadian Forces or of the Royal Canadian Mounted Police and who are serving under the administration of that minister or in a program under the administration of that minister.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Recommendation — provincial minister</MarginalNote><Label>(4)</Label><Text>Any provincial minister may recommend to the Minister of Public Safety and Emergency Preparedness the nomination for award of the Medal of those persons who are qualified under the regulations to be nominated for the Medal and who are firefighters or former firefighters or first responders or former first responders.</Text></Subsection></Section><Heading level="1"><TitleText>Regulations</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Regulations</MarginalNote><Label>8</Label><Text>The Governor in Council may make regulations</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>prescribing classes of persons who are excluded from entitlement to the Medal; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>respecting the qualifications of persons or classes of persons who may be nominated for the Medal.</Text></Paragraph></Section><Heading level="1"><TitleText>Prerogative</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Royal prerogative not affected</MarginalNote><Label>9</Label><Text>Nothing in this Act limits the right of the Governor General to exercise all powers and authorities of His Majesty in respect of the Medal.</Text></Section></Body></Bill>