<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><Bill bill-origin="commons" bill-type="private-public" xml:lang="en" date-time="2024-04-15 12:09:51"><Identification><BillNumber>C-388</BillNumber><Parliament><Session>1</Session><Number>44</Number><RegnalYear><Year-s>70-71</Year-s><Monarch>Elizabeth II – 1-2 Charles III</Monarch></RegnalYear><Year-s>2021-2022-2023-2024</Year-s></Parliament><LongTitle>An Act to fast track energy and mining projects and to facilitate the provision of munitions to Ukraine and develop its munitions industry</LongTitle><ShortTitle status="unofficial">Boosting Canadian Energy and Mining Projects and Ukraine’s Munitions Supply Act</ShortTitle><RunningHead>Boosting Canadian Energy and Mining Projects and Ukraine’s Munitions Supply Act</RunningHead><BillHistory><Stages stage="first-reading-house"><Date><YYYY>2024</YYYY><MM>5</MM><DD>2</DD></Date></Stages></BillHistory><BillSponsor><Emphasis style="smallcaps">Mr. Genuis</Emphasis></BillSponsor><BillRefNumber date-time="2024-04-15">441362</BillRefNumber></Identification><Introduction><Summary><TitleText>SUMMARY</TitleText><Provision><Text>This enactment provides for the preparation of a plan to fast track Canadian energy and mining projects.</Text></Provision><Provision language-align="yes"><Text>It also amends the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Defence Production Act</XRefExternal>, the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Export and Import Permits Act</XRefExternal>, the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Export Development Act</XRefExternal> and the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Business Development Bank of Canada Act</XRefExternal> to facilitate the provision of munitions to Ukraine by</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1" language-align="yes"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>requiring the donation of surplus defence supplies to Ukraine;</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>removing the authority to include on the <Emphasis style="italic">Export Control List</Emphasis> certain munitions if intended for export to Ukraine;</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1"><Label>(c)</Label><Text>extending the <Emphasis style="italic">General Export Permit No. 47 — Export of Arms Trade Treaty Items to the United States</Emphasis> to include the export of certain munitions to Ukraine;</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1"><Label>(d)</Label><Text>extending the <Emphasis style="italic">General Brokering Permit No. 1</Emphasis> to the brokering of certain munitions that are to be imported into Ukraine for end-use in Ukraine; and</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1"><Label>(e)</Label><Text>directing Export Development Canada and the Business Development Bank of Canada to give preference to the development of munitions manufacturing capacity in Ukraine.</Text></Provision></Summary><Enacts><Provision><Text>His Majesty, by and with the advice and consent <Keep>of the</Keep> Senate and House of Commons of Canada, <Keep>enacts</Keep> as follows:</Text></Provision></Enacts></Introduction><Body><Heading level="1"><TitleText>Short Title</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Short title</MarginalNote><Label>1</Label><Text>This Act may be cited as the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Boosting Canadian Energy and Mining Projects and Ukraine’s Munitions Supply Act</XRefExternal>.</Text></Section><Heading level="1"><Label>PART 1</Label><TitleText>Plan to Fast Track Energy and Mining Projects</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Preparation of plan</MarginalNote><Label>2</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Within 60 days after the day on which this Act comes into force, the Minister of Natural Resources must, in collaboration with representatives of the provincial governments responsible for natural resources, prepare a detailed plan to fast track energy and mining projects, including those related to liquefied natural gas and civilian nuclear energy, that includes measures to displace energy exports from hostile countries and support energy cooperation with allies and partners.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Publication in the <Emphasis style="italic">Canada Gazette</Emphasis></MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The Minister of Natural Resources must publish the plan, or give notice of its availability, in Part I of the <Emphasis style="italic">Canada Gazette</Emphasis> and in any other manner that that Minister considers appropriate. </Text></Subsection></Section><Heading level="1"><Label>PART 2</Label><TitleText>Provision of Munitions to Ukraine</TitleText></Heading><Heading level="2"><MarginalNote><HistoricalNote>R.S., c. D-1</HistoricalNote></MarginalNote><TitleText>Defence Production Act</TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><Label>3</Label><Text>The <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Defence Production Act</XRefExternal> is amended by adding the following after section 16:</Text><AmendedText><Section change="ins"><MarginalNote>Donation of surplus</MarginalNote><Label>16.1</Label><Text>For as long as any territory of Ukraine is occupied by armed forces of the Russian Federation, the Minister of National Defence must periodically review Canada’s inventory of defence supplies, and the Minister must offer to donate to Ukraine any defence supplies that, in the opinion of the Minister of National Defence, are surplus or no longer useful to Canada.</Text></Section></AmendedText></Section><Heading level="2"><MarginalNote><HistoricalNote>R.S., c. E-19
</HistoricalNote></MarginalNote><TitleText>Export and Import Permits Act

</TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><Label>4</Label><Text>Section 3 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Export and Import Permits Act</XRefExternal> is amended by adding the following after subsection (2):</Text><AmendedText><Subsection change="ins"><MarginalNote>Export Control List — Ukraine
</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>Despite any conditions imposed under subsection (2), any type of munition that is intended for export to the United States and that is excluded from the Export Control List shall not be included on the Export Control List if it is intended for export to Ukraine.</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>5</Label><Text>Section 7 of the Act is amended by adding the following after subsection (1.1):</Text><AmendedText><Subsection change="ins"><MarginalNote>General Permit — Export to Ukraine</MarginalNote><Label>(1.2)</Label><Text>For as long as any permit issued under subsection (1.1) to export any type of munition to the United States is in force, the export of the same type of munition to Ukraine is also permitted, subject to the terms and conditions described in that permit.</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>6</Label><Text>Section 7.1 of the Act is amended by adding the following after subsection (2):</Text><AmendedText><Subsection change="ins"><MarginalNote>General Permit to broker — brokering for Ukraine</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>For as long as is in force any permit issued under subsection (2) to broker any type of munition that is to be imported into any country specified in the permit for end-use in that country, brokering the types of munition specified in that permit that are to be imported into Ukraine for end-use in Ukraine is also permitted, subject to the terms and conditions specified in that permit.</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Section><Heading level="2"><MarginalNote><HistoricalNote>R.S., c. E-20; 2001, c. 33, s.2(F)</HistoricalNote></MarginalNote><TitleText>Export Development Act</TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><Label>7</Label><Text>Section 10 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Export Development Act</XRefExternal> is amended by adding the following after subsection (1.01):</Text><AmendedText><Subsection change="ins"><MarginalNote>Development of munitions manufacturing capacity in Ukraine</MarginalNote><Label>(1.011)</Label><Text>In carrying out its purpose under paragraph (1)(c), the Corporation shall give preference to the development of munitions manufacturing capacity in Ukraine.</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Section><Heading level="2"><MarginalNote><HistoricalNote>1995, c. 28</HistoricalNote></MarginalNote><TitleText>Business Development Bank of Canada Act</TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><Label>8</Label><Text>Section 4 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Business Development Bank of Canada Act</XRefExternal> is amended by adding the following after subsection (2): </Text><AmendedText><Subsection change="ins"><MarginalNote>Development of munitions manufacturing capacity in Ukraine</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>Despite subsection (1), the Bank must give preference to supporting projects to develop munitions manufacturing capacity in Ukraine.</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>9</Label><Text>Paragraph 14(5)(b) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>the investment</Text><Subparagraph change="ins"><Label>(i)</Label><Text>supports munitions manufacturing capacity in Ukraine, or</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph><Label><Ins>(ii)</Ins></Label><Text>is of a category prescribed by the regulations.</Text></Subparagraph></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Section></Body></Bill>