<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><Bill bill-origin="commons" bill-type="private-public" xml:lang="en" date-time="2023-10-10 13:54:02"><Identification><BillNumber>C-385</BillNumber><Parliament><Session>1</Session><Number>44</Number><RegnalYear><Year-s>70-71</Year-s><Monarch>Elizabeth II – 1-2 Charles III</Monarch></RegnalYear><Year-s>2021-2022-2023-2024</Year-s></Parliament><LongTitle>An Act to amend the Motor Vehicle Transport Act</LongTitle><ShortTitle status="unofficial" /><RunningHead>An Act to amend the Motor Vehicle Transport Act</RunningHead><BillHistory><Stages stage="first-reading-house"><Date><YYYY>2024</YYYY><MM>3</MM><DD>19</DD></Date></Stages></BillHistory><BillSponsor><Emphasis style="smallcaps">Mr. Shields</Emphasis></BillSponsor><BillRefNumber date-time="2023-10-10">441287</BillRefNumber></Identification><Introduction><Summary><TitleText>SUMMARY</TitleText><Provision><Text>This enactment amends the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Motor Vehicle Transport Act</XRefExternal> to specify that, for a driver transporting livestock or insects, hours spent driving, or on duty, within a radius of 240 kilometres of the origin or final destination of a trip do not count towards the maximum number of hours of service per day permitted for that driver. </Text></Provision></Summary><Enacts><Provision><Text>His Majesty, by and with the advice and consent <Keep>of the</Keep> Senate and House of Commons of Canada, <Keep>enacts</Keep> as follows:</Text></Provision></Enacts></Introduction><Body><Heading level="1"><MarginalNote><HistoricalNote>R.S., c. 29 (3rd Supp.); 2001, c. 13, s. 1</HistoricalNote></MarginalNote><TitleText>Motor Vehicle Transport Act</TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><Label>1</Label><Text>Subsection 2(1) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Motor Vehicle Transport Act</XRefExternal> is amended by adding the following in alphabetical order:</Text><AmendedText change="ins"><SectionPiece><Definition><Text><DefinedTermEn>prescribed</DefinedTermEn> means prescribed by regulation; (<Emphasis style="italic">Version anglaise seulement</Emphasis>)</Text></Definition></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>2</Label><Text>The Act is amended by adding the following after the heading “Extra-Provincial Motor Carrier Safety” before section 7:</Text><AmendedText change="ins"><Heading level="2"><TitleText>Safety Fitness Certificate</TitleText></Heading></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>3</Label><Text>The Act is amended by adding the following after section 10:</Text><AmendedText change="ins"><Heading level="2"><TitleText>Hours of Service</TitleText></Heading><Section change="ins"><MarginalNote>Daily driving time</MarginalNote><Label>11</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>No person who is engaged in the operation of an extra-provincial motor carrier undertaking shall request, require or allow a driver to drive and no driver shall drive after the driver has accumulated the prescribed number of hours of driving time in a day.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Daily on-duty time</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>No person who is engaged in the operation of an <Keep>extra</Keep>-provincial motor carrier undertaking shall request, require or allow a driver to drive and no driver shall drive after the driver has accumulated the prescribed number of hours of on-duty time in a day.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Definition of <DefinedTermEn>day</DefinedTermEn></MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>For the purposes of this section, <DefinedTermEn>day</DefinedTermEn>, in respect of a driver, means a 24-hour period that begins at the hour designated by a person who is engaged in the operation of an extra-provincial motor carrier undertaking, if this designation is made for at least seven consecutive days.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section change="ins"><MarginalNote>Mandatory off-duty time after driving</MarginalNote><Label>12</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>No person who is engaged in the operation of an extra-provincial motor carrier undertaking shall request, require or allow a driver to drive and no driver shall drive after the driver has accumulated the prescribed number of hours of driving time unless the driver takes at least the prescribed number of consecutive hours of off-duty time before driving again.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Mandatory off-duty time after on-duty time</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>No person who is engaged in the operation of an <Keep>extra</Keep>-provincial motor carrier undertaking shall request, require or allow a driver to drive and no driver shall drive after the driver has accumulated the prescribed number of hours of on-duty time unless the driver takes at least the prescribed number of consecutive hours of off-duty time before driving again.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Interval between off-duty times</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>No person who is engaged in the operation of an <Keep>extra</Keep>-provincial motor carrier undertaking shall request, require or allow a driver to drive and no driver shall drive after the prescribed number of hours have elapsed between the conclusion of the most recent period of prescribed consecutive hours of off-duty time and the beginning of the next period of prescribed consecutive hours of off-duty time.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section change="ins"><MarginalNote>Exception</MarginalNote><Label>13</Label><Text>In the case of drivers transporting <DefinitionRef>livestock</DefinitionRef>, as defined in section 2 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="regulation">Health of Animals Regulations</XRefExternal>, or insects, the following hours of driving time and hours of on-duty time shall not be counted towards the number of hours of driving time and the number of hours of on-duty time referred to in sections 11 and 12:</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>hours spent within a radius of 240 kilometres of the origin of a trip; and </Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>hours spent within a radius of 240 kilometres of the final destination of a trip. </Text></Paragraph></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>4</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Subsection 16.1(1) of the Act is amended by adding the following after paragraph (d):</Text><AmendedText change="ins"><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(d.1)</Label><Text>defining “driver”, “on-duty time” and “off-duty time” for the purposes of this Act;</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Subsection 16.1(1) of the Act is amended by striking out “and” at the end of paragraph (h), by adding “and” at the end of paragraph (i) and by adding the following after paragraph (i):</Text><AmendedText change="ins"><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(j)</Label><Text>prescribing anything that is to be prescribed under this Act.</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection></Section></Body></Bill>