<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><Bill bill-origin="commons" bill-type="private-public" xml:lang="en" date-time="2024-02-06 10:55:16"><Identification><BillNumber>C-381</BillNumber><Parliament><Session>1</Session><Number>44</Number><RegnalYear><Year-s>70-71</Year-s><Monarch>Elizabeth II – 1-2 Charles III</Monarch></RegnalYear><Year-s>2021-2022-2023-2024</Year-s></Parliament><LongTitle>An Act to amend the Criminal Code (extortion)</LongTitle><ShortTitle status="unofficial" /><RunningHead>An Act to amend the Criminal Code (extortion)</RunningHead><BillHistory><Stages stage="first-reading-house"><Date><YYYY>2024</YYYY><MM>2</MM><DD>12</DD></Date></Stages></BillHistory><BillSponsor><Emphasis style="smallcaps">Mr. Uppal</Emphasis></BillSponsor><BillRefNumber date-time="2024-02-06">441357</BillRefNumber></Identification><Introduction><Summary><TitleText>SUMMARY</TitleText><Provision><Text>This enactment amends the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Criminal Code</XRefExternal> to:</Text></Provision><Provision><Label>(a)	</Label><Text>amend mandatory minimum penalties in relation to the offence of extortion, including when the offence is committed for the benefit of, at the direction of, or in association with, a criminal organization; and</Text></Provision><Provision><Label>(b)</Label><Text>add arson as an aggravating factor for the purposes of sentencing when a person is convicted of extortion.</Text></Provision></Summary><Preamble><Provision><MarginalNote>Preamble</MarginalNote><Text>Whereas the safety and security of property is essential to a functioning society as well as to the prosperity of individuals and families;</Text></Provision><Provision><Text>Whereas, according to police reports, there has been a significant increase in rates of extortion in Canada over the last decade;</Text></Provision><Provision><Text>Whereas new Canadians are particularly vulnerable to extortion, including from overseas criminal organizations, which undermines Canada’s reputation as a safe and orderly society;</Text></Provision><Provision><Text>Whereas Parliament believes that the federal legislature must ensure that the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Criminal Code</XRefExternal> responds to changing criminal behaviour and reflects the seriousness of criminal offences;</Text></Provision><Provision><Text>And whereas Parliament believes that the increase in extortion involving the use of a firearm or arson is particularly alarming, as it involves not only property damage but also serious threats to life;</Text></Provision></Preamble><Enacts><Provision language-align="yes"><Text>Now, therefore, His Majesty, by and with the advice and consent of the Senate and House of Commons of Canada, enacts as follows:</Text></Provision></Enacts></Introduction><Body><Heading level="1"><TitleText>Short Title</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Short title</MarginalNote><Label>1</Label><Text>This Act may be cited as the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Protection against Extortion Act</XRefExternal>.</Text></Section><Heading level="1"><MarginalNote><HistoricalNote>R.S., 1985, c. C-46</HistoricalNote></MarginalNote><TitleText>Criminal Code</TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><Label>2</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The portion of paragraph 346(1.1)(a) of the Act before subparagraph (i) is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>if a restricted firearm or prohibited firearm is used in the commission of the offence or if the offence is committed for the benefit of, at the direction of, or in association with, a criminal organization, to imprisonment for life and to a minimum punishment of imprisonment for a term of</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Paragraph 346(1.1)(b) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><SectionPiece><Paragraph change="ins"><Label>(a.1)</Label><Text>if a firearm other than a restricted firearm or prohibited firearm is used in the commission of the offence, to imprisonment for life and to a minimum punishment of imprisonment for a term of four years; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>in any other case, to imprisonment for life <Ins>and to a minimum punishment of imprisonment for a term of three years</Ins>.</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(3)</Label><Text>Section 346 of the Act is amended by adding the following after subsection (1.3):</Text><AmendedText><Subsection change="ins"><MarginalNote>Aggravating factor</MarginalNote><Label>(1.4)</Label><Text>If a person is convicted of an offence under this section, the court that imposes the sentence shall consider as an aggravating factor the fact that the person, in committing the offence, also committed an offence under any of sections 433 to 435.</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Subsection></Section></Body></Bill>