<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><Bill bill-origin="commons" bill-type="private-public" xml:lang="en" date-time="2024-05-06 13:41:09"><Identification><BillNumber>C-391</BillNumber><Parliament><Session>1</Session><Number>44</Number><RegnalYear><Year-s>70-71</Year-s><Monarch>Elizabeth II – 1-2 Charles III</Monarch></RegnalYear><Year-s>2021-2022-2023-2024</Year-s></Parliament><LongTitle>An Act to amend the Criminal Code and the Controlled Drugs and Substances Act (possession of weapons and drugs in hospitals)</LongTitle><ShortTitle status="unofficial">Safe Hospitals Act</ShortTitle><RunningHead>Safe Hospitals Act</RunningHead><BillHistory><Stages stage="first-reading-house"><Date><YYYY>2024</YYYY><MM>5</MM><DD>28</DD></Date></Stages></BillHistory><BillSponsor><Emphasis style="smallcaps">Ms. Findlay</Emphasis></BillSponsor><BillRefNumber date-time="2024-05-06">441386</BillRefNumber></Identification><Introduction><Summary><TitleText>SUMMARY</TitleText><Provision><Text>This enactment amends the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Criminal Code</XRefExternal> to require the court to consider as an aggravating circumstance the fact that a person was in possession of a weapon in or near a hospital, on or near hospital grounds or in or near any other public health care facility.</Text></Provision><Provision language-align="yes"><Text>It also amends the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Controlled Drugs and Substances Act</XRefExternal> to prevent the Minister from granting an exemption that would result in the illicit or unprescribed use of a controlled substance in a hospital.</Text></Provision></Summary><Enacts><Provision><Text>His Majesty, by and with the advice and consent <Keep>of the</Keep> Senate and House of Commons of Canada, <Keep>enacts</Keep> as follows:</Text></Provision></Enacts></Introduction><Body><Heading level="1"><TitleText>Short Title</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Short title</MarginalNote><Label>1</Label><Text>This Act may be cited as the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Safe Hospitals Act</XRefExternal>.</Text></Section><Heading level="1"><MarginalNote><HistoricalNote>R.S., c. C-46</HistoricalNote></MarginalNote><TitleText>Criminal Code</TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><Label>2</Label><Text>Section 88 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Criminal Code</XRefExternal> is amended by adding the following after subsection (2):</Text><AmendedText><Subsection change="ins"><MarginalNote>Aggravating circumstance — hospital or health care facility</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>Without limiting the generality of section 718.2, if a person is convicted of an offence under subsection (1), the court imposing the sentence shall consider as an aggravating circumstance the fact that the offence was committed in or near a hospital, on or near hospital grounds or in or near any other public health care facility.</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Section><Heading level="1"><MarginalNote><HistoricalNote>1996, c. 19</HistoricalNote></MarginalNote><TitleText>Controlled Drugs and Substances Act</TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><Label>3</Label><Text>Section 56 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Controlled Drugs and Substances Act</XRefExternal> is amended by adding the following after subsection (2):</Text><AmendedText><Subsection change="ins"><MarginalNote>Exception</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>The Minister is not authorized under subsection (1) to grant an exemption that would result in the illicit or unprescribed use of a controlled substance in a hospital.</Text></Subsection><Subsection change="ins"><MarginalNote>For greater certainty</MarginalNote><Label>(4)</Label><Text>For greater certainty, subsection (3) does not apply to the prescribed use of a controlled substance in a hospital by a patient, as authorized by, and under the supervision of, a practitioner.</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Section></Body></Bill>