<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><Bill bill-origin="commons" bill-type="private-public" xml:lang="en" date-time="2024-06-04 12:16:02"><Identification><BillNumber>C-404</BillNumber><Parliament><Session>1</Session><Number>44</Number><RegnalYear><Year-s>70-71</Year-s><Monarch>Elizabeth II – 1-2 Charles III</Monarch></RegnalYear><Year-s>2021-2022-2023-2024</Year-s></Parliament><LongTitle>An Act to establish National Conversion Therapy Awareness Day</LongTitle><ShortTitle status="unofficial" /><RunningHead>National Conversion Therapy Awareness Day Act</RunningHead><BillHistory><Stages stage="first-reading-house"><Date><YYYY>2024</YYYY><MM>6</MM><DD>13</DD></Date></Stages></BillHistory><BillSponsor><Emphasis style="smallcaps">Mr. Gerretsen</Emphasis></BillSponsor><BillRefNumber date-time="2024-06-04">441393</BillRefNumber></Identification><Introduction><Summary><TitleText>SUMMARY</TitleText><Provision><Text>This enactment establishes the 7th of January in each year as “National Conversion Therapy Awareness Day”.</Text></Provision></Summary><Preamble><Provision><MarginalNote>Preamble</MarginalNote><Text>Whereas conversion therapy is based on and propagates myths and stereotypes about sexual orientation, gender identity and gender expression;</Text></Provision><Provision><Text>Whereas conversion therapy seeks to change an individual’s sexual orientation to heterosexual, to change an individual’s gender identity to cisgender, or to change an individual’s gender expression so that it corresponds to the sex assigned to them at birth;</Text></Provision><Provision><Text>Whereas conversion therapy has caused significant harm to persons who have been subjected to it, including depression, anxiety, self-rejection, social isolation, suicidal ideation and suicide attempts, as well as infringing on their rights to dignity and equality;</Text></Provision><Provision><Text>Whereas, in December 2021, both the Senate and the House of Commons unanimously passed Bill C-4, which banned the harmful practice of conversion therapy;</Text></Provision><Provision><Text>Whereas, on January 7, 2022, the day on which Bill C-4 came into force, conversion therapy became illegal in Canada;</Text></Provision><Provision><Text>And whereas Parliament considers that it is desirable to raise awareness of the harms caused by conversion therapy and that it is fitting that the 7th of January be established as a day of reflection;</Text></Provision></Preamble><Enacts><Provision language-align="yes"><Text>Now, therefore, His Majesty, by and with the advice and consent of the Senate and House of Commons of Canada, enacts as follows:</Text></Provision></Enacts></Introduction><Body><Heading level="1"><TitleText>Short Title</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Short title</MarginalNote><Label>1</Label><Text>This Act may be cited as the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">National Conversion Therapy Awareness Day Act</XRefExternal>.</Text></Section><Heading level="1"><TitleText>National Conversion Therapy Awareness Day</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Designation</MarginalNote><Label>2</Label><Text>Throughout Canada, in each year, the 7th day of January is to be known as “National Conversion Therapy Awareness Day”.</Text></Section></Body></Bill>