<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><Bill bill-origin="commons" bill-type="private-public" xml:lang="en" date-time="2024-04-26 15:23:26"><Identification><BillNumber>C-400</BillNumber><Parliament><Session>1</Session><Number>44</Number><RegnalYear><Year-s>70-71</Year-s><Monarch>Elizabeth II – 1-2 Charles III</Monarch></RegnalYear><Year-s>2021-2022-2023-2024</Year-s></Parliament><LongTitle>An Act to establish a framework for the continued access to and use of cash in Canada and to make related amendments to other Acts</LongTitle><ShortTitle status="unofficial">This Act may be cited as the Framework on the Access to and Use of Cash Act</ShortTitle><RunningHead>Framework on the Access to and Use of Cash Act</RunningHead><BillHistory><Stages stage="first-reading-house"><Date><YYYY>2024</YYYY><MM>6</MM><DD>13</DD></Date></Stages></BillHistory><BillSponsor><Emphasis style="smallcaps">Mr. Falk</Emphasis></BillSponsor><BillRefNumber date-time="2024-04-26">441273</BillRefNumber></Identification><Introduction><Summary><TitleText>SUMMARY</TitleText><Provision><Text>This enactment provides for the development and implementation of a framework to ensure that cash continues to be available throughout Canada.</Text></Provision><Provision language-align="yes"><Text>It also amends the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Currency Act</XRefExternal> and the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Bank of Canada Act</XRefExternal> to remove the Governor in Council’s power to call in coins and notes. Finally, it amends the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Bank of Canada Act</XRefExternal> to prohibit the Bank of Canada from issuing a digital form of the dollar.</Text></Provision></Summary><Preamble><Provision><MarginalNote>Preamble</MarginalNote><Text>Whereas the use of cash is significantly more prevalent among vulnerable population groups such as seniors, Indigenous Peoples, newcomers to Canada and persons with low-income, including those living in poverty or who rely on income assistance programs;</Text></Provision><Provision><Text>Whereas non-profit organizations and community organizations rely on cash for charitable fundraising activities;</Text></Provision><Provision><Text>And whereas cash as a form of payment provides a higher level of privacy than digital alternatives and that Canadians’ right to privacy is enshrined in the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Canadian Charter of Rights and Freedoms</XRefExternal> and the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Privacy Act</XRefExternal>, as well as provincial privacy legislation;</Text></Provision></Preamble><Enacts><Provision><Text>Now, therefore, His Majesty, by and with the advice and consent <Keep>of the</Keep> Senate and House of Commons of Canada, <Keep>enacts</Keep> as follows:</Text></Provision></Enacts></Introduction><Body><Heading level="1"><TitleText>Short Title</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Short title</MarginalNote><Label>1</Label><Text>This Act may be cited as the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Framework on the Access to and Use of Cash Act</XRefExternal>.</Text></Section><Heading level="1"><TitleText>Interpretation</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Definitions</MarginalNote><Label>2</Label><Text>The following definitions apply in this Act.</Text><Definition><Text><DefinedTermEn>cash</DefinedTermEn> means coins and notes referred to in subsection 8(1) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Currency Act</XRefExternal>. (<DefinedTermFr>espèces</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Definition><Definition><Text><DefinedTermEn>Minister</DefinedTermEn> means the Minister of Finance. (<DefinedTermFr>ministre</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Definition></Section><Heading level="1"><TitleText>Comprehensive Review</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Review by Minister</MarginalNote><Label>3</Label><Text>Within 90 days after the day on which this Act comes into force, the Minister must undertake a comprehensive review of existing legislation, regulations and policies in relation to the availability of cash within financial institutions.</Text></Section><Heading level="1"><TitleText>Framework</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Development</MarginalNote><Label>4</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The Minister must develop and implement a framework to ensure continued access to cash in Canada.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Contents</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The framework must include measures to</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>ensure that all persons in Canada have access to cash by ensuring, among other things, that the necessary infrastructure is present across Canada to allow cash withdrawals and deposits, and determining a reasonable distance for people to travel to withdraw or deposit cash;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>protect the ability of persons in Canada to continue to use cash despite the availability of digital currencies, including cryptocurrencies;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(c)</Label><Text>incentivize businesses and creditors to accept payments made in cash;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(d)</Label><Text>remove barriers and disincentives in relation to donations made in cash to non-profit organizations and community organizations, without compromising efforts to curtail money laundering, fraud and other financial crimes; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(e)</Label><Text>ensure the long-term viability of Canada’s cash infrastructure — which includes the equipment and facilities required for the sorting, storing and <Keep svc="1">distribution</Keep> of cash — by ensuring that it remains effective, resilient and sustainable.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection></Section><Heading level="1"><TitleText>Reports to Parliament</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Tabling of framework</MarginalNote><Label>5</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Within 18 months after the day on which this Act comes into force, the Minister must prepare a report setting out the framework and any recommendations related to its development and implementation and cause the report to be tabled in each House of Parliament on any of the first 15 days on which that House is sitting after it is completed.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Publication</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The Minister must publish the report on the website of the Department of Finance within 10 days after the report has been tabled in both Houses of Parliament.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Review</MarginalNote><Label>6</Label><Text>Within three years after the report referred to in section 5 has been tabled in both Houses of Parliament, the Minister must, in consultation with the parties referred to in subsection 4(2), undertake a review of the implementation, effectiveness and social and economic impacts of the framework, prepare a report setting out any findings and recommendations and cause the report to be tabled in each House of Parliament on any of the first 15 days on which that House is sitting after it is completed.</Text></Section><Heading level="1"><TitleText>Related Amendments</TitleText></Heading><Heading level="2"><MarginalNote><HistoricalNote>R.S., c. C-52</HistoricalNote></MarginalNote><TitleText>Currency Act</TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><Label>7</Label><Text>Subsection 9(1) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Currency Act</XRefExternal> is repealed.</Text></Section><Heading level="2"><MarginalNote><HistoricalNote>R.S., c. B-2</HistoricalNote></MarginalNote><TitleText>Bank of Canada Act</TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><Label>8</Label><Text>Section 23 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Bank of Canada Act</XRefExternal> is renumbered as subsection 23(1) and is amended by adding the following:</Text><AmendedText><Subsection change="ins"><MarginalNote>Prohibition — central bank digital currency
</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The Bank shall not issue a digital form of the dollar.</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>9</Label><Text>Subparagraph 25(2)(b)(ii) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><SectionPiece><Subparagraph><Label>(ii)</Label><Text>its notes <Ins>that were called in</Ins> by an order made under the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Currency Act</XRefExternal>.</Text></Subparagraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Section></Body></Bill>