<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><Bill bill-origin="commons" bill-type="private-public" xml:lang="en" date-time="2024-06-13 16:50:23"><Identification><BillNumber>C-419</BillNumber><Parliament><Session>1</Session><Number>44</Number><RegnalYear><Year-s>70-71</Year-s><Monarch>Elizabeth II – 1-2-3 Charles III</Monarch></RegnalYear><Year-s>2021-2022-2023-2024</Year-s></Parliament><LongTitle>An Act to establish a national strategy for universal eye care
</LongTitle><ShortTitle status="unofficial">National Strategy for Universal Eye Care Act</ShortTitle><RunningHead>National Strategy for Universal Eye Care Act</RunningHead><BillHistory><Stages stage="first-reading-house"><Date><YYYY>2024</YYYY><MM>11</MM><DD>19</DD></Date></Stages></BillHistory><BillSponsor><Emphasis style="smallcaps">Mr. Davies</Emphasis></BillSponsor><BillRefNumber date-time="2024-06-13">441383</BillRefNumber></Identification><Introduction><Summary><TitleText>SUMMARY</TitleText><Provision><Text>This enactment provides for the development of a national strategy to support universal access to eye care, vision correction and vision aids across Canada.</Text></Provision></Summary><Preamble><Provision><MarginalNote>Preamble</MarginalNote><Text>Whereas access to eye care varies widely across Canada, resulting in inequitable outcomes;</Text></Provision><Provision><Text>Whereas more than 70 percent of private eye care expenses in Canada are incurred by Canadians out of pocket;</Text></Provision><Provision><Text>Whereas the cost of eye care can be a significant barrier for many Canadians, leading to challenges in accessing routine and preventative eye care services;</Text></Provision><Provision><Text>Whereas access to eye care services can contribute to improved health outcomes by preserving vision and preventing avoidable vision loss;</Text></Provision><Provision><Text>Whereas the cost of vision loss in Canada is expected to grow to over $30 billion by 2032;</Text></Provision><Provision><Text>And whereas most cases of vision loss in Canada are reversible, preventable, or treatable if diagnosed early and if treatment is accessible;</Text></Provision></Preamble><Enacts><Provision><Text>Now, therefore, His Majesty, by and with the advice and consent <Keep>of the</Keep> Senate and House of Commons of Canada, <Keep>enacts</Keep> as follows:</Text></Provision></Enacts></Introduction><Body><Heading level="1"><TitleText>Short Title</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Short title</MarginalNote><Label>1</Label><Text>This Act may be cited as the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">National Strategy for Universal Eye Care Act</XRefExternal>.</Text></Section><Heading level="1"><TitleText>Interpretation</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Definition of <Emphasis style="italic">Indigenous governing body</Emphasis></MarginalNote><Label>2</Label><Text>In this Act, <DefinedTermEn>Indigenous governing body</DefinedTermEn> means a council, government or other entity that is authorized to act on behalf of an Indigenous group, community or people that holds rights recognized and affirmed by section 35 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Constitution Act, 1982</XRefExternal>.</Text></Section><Heading level="1"><TitleText>National Strategy</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Development</MarginalNote><Label>3</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The Minister of Health must, in consultation with the representatives of the provincial governments responsible for health, as well as with Indigenous governing bodies, eye care professionals, patient groups and other relevant stakeholders, develop a national strategy to support universal access to eye care, vision correction and vision aids across Canada.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Contents</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The strategy must</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>identify barriers to accessing eye care services and obtaining vision correction products and visual aids in Canada; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>identify measures to improve access across Canada to the following:</Text><Subparagraph><Label>(i)</Label><Text>vision care services, such as routine eye examinations,</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph><Label>(ii)</Label><Text>devices such as eyeglasses, contact lenses and low-vision aids,</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph><Label>(iii)</Label><Text>eye care for conditions such as glaucoma, iritis and chemical burns,</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph><Label>(iv)</Label><Text>surgical eye care for conditions such as trauma, cataracts and glaucoma, and</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph><Label>(v)</Label><Text>health care services for the diagnosis and treatment of eye conditions related to other diseases, such as diabetes and arthritis.</Text></Subparagraph></Paragraph></Subsection></Section><Heading level="1"><TitleText>Reports to Parliament</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Tabling of strategy</MarginalNote><Label>4</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Within 18 months after the day on which this Act comes into force, the Minister of Health must prepare a report setting out the national strategy and cause it to be tabled in each House of Parliament on any of the first 15 days on which that House is sitting after the report is completed.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Publication</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The Minister must publish the report on the website of the Department of Health within 10 days after the day on which it is tabled in Parliament.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Report</MarginalNote><Label>5</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Within five years after the day on which the report referred to in section 4 is tabled in both Houses of Parliament, the Minister of Health must prepare a report on the effectiveness of the national strategy and on the state of access to eye care in Canada that also sets out the Minister’s conclusions and recommendations regarding the strategy.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Tabling of report</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The Minister must cause the report to be tabled in each House of Parliament on any of the first 15 days on which that House is sitting after the report is completed.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Publication</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>The Minister must publish the report on the website of the Department of Health within 10 days after the day on which it is tabled in Parliament.</Text></Subsection></Section></Body></Bill>