<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><Bill bill-origin="commons" bill-type="private-public" xml:lang="en" date-time="2024-10-08 12:02:44"><Identification><BillNumber>C-414</BillNumber><Parliament><Session>1</Session><Number>44</Number><RegnalYear><Year-s>70-71</Year-s><Monarch>Elizabeth II – 1-2-3 Charles III</Monarch></RegnalYear><Year-s>2021-2022-2023-2024</Year-s></Parliament><LongTitle>An Act to amend the Canada Health Act (mental, addictions and substance use health services)</LongTitle><ShortTitle status="unofficial" /><RunningHead>An Act to amend the Canada Health Act (mental, addictions and substance use health services)</RunningHead><BillHistory><Stages stage="first-reading-house"><Date><YYYY>2024</YYYY><MM>10</MM><DD>10</DD></Date></Stages></BillHistory><BillSponsor><Emphasis style="smallcaps">Mr. Johns</Emphasis></BillSponsor><BillRefNumber date-time="2024-10-08">441417</BillRefNumber></Identification><Introduction><Summary><TitleText>SUMMARY</TitleText><Provision><Text>This enactment amends the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Canada Health Act</XRefExternal> to add mental, addictions and substance use health services to the definition of “insured health services”.</Text></Provision></Summary><Enacts><Provision><Text>His Majesty, by and with the advice and consent <Keep>of the</Keep> Senate and House of Commons of Canada, <Keep>enacts</Keep> as follows:</Text></Provision></Enacts></Introduction><Body><Heading level="1"><MarginalNote><HistoricalNote>R.S., c. C-6</HistoricalNote></MarginalNote><TitleText>Canada Health Act</TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><Label>1</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The definition <DefinitionRef>insured health services</DefinitionRef> in section 2 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Canada Health Act</XRefExternal> is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><SectionPiece><Definition><Text><DefinedTermEn>insured health services</DefinedTermEn> means hospital services, physician services, surgical-dental services and <Ins>mental, addictions and substance use health services</Ins> provided to insured persons, but does not include any health services that a person is entitled to and eligible for under any other Act of Parliament or under any Act of the legislature of a province that relates to workers’ or workmen’s compensation; (<DefinedTermFr>services de santé assurés</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Definition></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Section 2 of the Act is amended by adding the following in alphabetical order:</Text><AmendedText><SectionPiece><Definition change="ins"><Text><DefinedTermEn>mental, addictions and substance use health services</DefinedTermEn> includes mental, addictions and substances use health services provided in community settings; (<DefinedTermFr>services de santé mentale, dépendances ou de consommation de substances</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Definition></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>2</Label><Text>Section 9 of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><Section><MarginalNote>Comprehensiveness</MarginalNote><Label>9</Label><Text>In order to satisfy the criterion respecting comprehensiveness, the health care insurance plan of a province must insure all insured health services provided by <Keep svc="1">hospitals,</Keep> medical practitioners or dentists, and where the law of the province so permits, similar or additional services rendered by other health care practitioners, <Ins>including those provided in community settings</Ins>.</Text></Section></AmendedText></Section></Body></Bill>