<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><Bill bill-origin="commons" bill-type="private-public" xml:lang="en" date-time="2024-11-20 15:04:20"><Identification><BillNumber>C-421</BillNumber><Parliament><Session>1</Session><Number>44</Number><RegnalYear><Year-s>70-71</Year-s><Monarch>Elizabeth II – 1-2-3 Charles III</Monarch></RegnalYear><Year-s>2021-2022-2023-2024</Year-s></Parliament><LongTitle>An Act to establish a national food cooperative strategy</LongTitle><ShortTitle status="unofficial" /><RunningHead>National Food Cooperative Strategy Act</RunningHead><BillHistory><Stages stage="first-reading-house"><Date><YYYY>2024</YYYY><MM>11</MM><DD>27</DD></Date></Stages></BillHistory><BillSponsor><Emphasis style="smallcaps">Mr. MacGregor</Emphasis></BillSponsor><BillRefNumber date-time="2024-11-20">441425</BillRefNumber></Identification><Introduction><Summary><TitleText>SUMMARY</TitleText><Provision><Text>This enactment provides for the development of a national strategy to facilitate the establishment of food cooperatives in Canada. It also sets out reporting requirements respecting the strategy.</Text></Provision></Summary><Preamble><Provision><MarginalNote>Preamble</MarginalNote><Text>Whereas grocery prices in Canada are increasing at the fastest rate in more than 40 years;</Text></Provision><Provision><Text>Whereas the Competition Bureau of Canada reported that Canada’s grocery industry is dominated by a small number of large corporations;</Text></Provision><Provision><Text>Whereas many Canadians are foregoing meals and using food banks, while profits in the grocery industry amounted to over $6 billion in 2023;</Text></Provision><Provision><Text>Whereas the Competition Bureau of Canada has stated that encouraging more competition in the grocery industry and expanding consumer choice would lead to lower grocery prices; </Text></Provision><Provision><Text>And whereas the establishment of more food cooperatives will lead to the creation of more community-owned and economically viable small and medium-sized businesses across Canada;</Text></Provision></Preamble><Enacts><Provision><Text>Now, therefore, His Majesty, by and with the advice and consent <Keep>of the</Keep> Senate and House of Commons of Canada, <Keep>enacts</Keep> as follows:</Text></Provision></Enacts></Introduction><Body><Heading level="1"><TitleText>Short Title</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Short title</MarginalNote><Label>1</Label><Text>This Act may be cited as the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">National Food Cooperative Strategy Act</XRefExternal>.</Text></Section><Heading level="1"><TitleText>National Food Cooperative Strategy</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Development and content</MarginalNote><Label>2</Label><Text>The Minister of Industry must, in consultation with representatives of the provincial governments responsible for industry and economic development, relevant stakeholders in those fields and representatives of Indigenous communities, develop a national strategy that contains measures to facilitate the establishment of food cooperatives in Canada in order to enable more small and medium-sized businesses to compete in Canada’s grocery industry.</Text></Section><Heading level="1"><TitleText>Report to Parliament</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Report</MarginalNote><Label>3</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Within 18 months after the day on which this Act comes into force, the Minister of Industry must prepare a report setting out the strategy.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Tabling of report</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The Minister must cause the report to be tabled in each House of Parliament on any of the first 15 days on which that House is sitting after the report is completed.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Publication</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>The Minister must publish the report on the website of the Department of Industry within 10 days after the day on which the report is tabled in both Houses of Parliament. </Text></Subsection></Section></Body></Bill>