<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!--Arbortext, Inc., 1988-2010, v.4002--><Bill bill-origin="commons" bill-type="govt-public" xml:lang="en"><Identification><BillNumber>C-66</BillNumber><Parliament><Session>1</Session><Number>44</Number><RegnalYear><Year-s>70-71</Year-s><Monarch>Elizabeth II – 1-2 Charles III</Monarch></RegnalYear><Year-s>2021-2022-2023-2024</Year-s></Parliament><LongTitle>An Act to amend the National Defence Act and other Acts</LongTitle><ShortTitle status="unofficial">Military Justice System Modernization Act</ShortTitle><RunningHead>Military Justice System Modernization Act</RunningHead><BillHistory><Stages stage="first-reading-house"><Date><YYYY>2024</YYYY><MM>3</MM><DD>21</DD></Date></Stages></BillHistory><BillSponsor>MINISTER OF NATIONAL DEFENCE</BillSponsor><BillRefNumber date-time="2024-03-19">91192</BillRefNumber></Identification><Introduction><Recommendation><TitleText>RECOMMENDATION</TitleText><Provision format-ref="section"><Text>Her Excellency the Governor General recommends to the House of Commons the appropriation of public revenue under the circumstances, in the manner and for the purposes set out in a measure entitled “<Emphasis style="italic">An Act to amend the National Defence Act and other Acts</Emphasis>”.</Text></Provision></Recommendation><Summary><TitleText>SUMMARY</TitleText><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>This enactment amends provisions of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">National Defence Act</XRefExternal> that relate to the military justice system in response to the Report of the Third Independent Review Authority to the Minister of National Defence and the Report of the Independent External Comprehensive Review of the Department of National Defence and the Canadian Armed Forces.</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>In response to those reports, the enactment amends that Act to, among other things,</Text><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>modify the process for appointing the Canadian Forces Provost Marshal, the Director of Military Prosecutions and the Director of Defence Counsel Services with a view to enhancing their independence;</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>affirm the Judge Advocate General’s respect for the independence of authorities in the military justice system in the exercise of the Judge Advocate General’s superintendence of the administration of military justice;</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>(c)</Label><Text>remove the court martial’s jurisdiction to try a person in relation to an offence under the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Criminal Code</XRefExternal> that is alleged to have been committed in Canada and that is of a sexual nature or committed for a sexual purpose;</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>(d)</Label><Text>remove the Canadian Armed Forces’ authority to investigate an offence under the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Criminal Code</XRefExternal> that is alleged to have been committed in Canada and that is of a sexual nature or committed for a sexual purpose;</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>(e)</Label><Text>expand the class of persons who are eligible to be appointed as a military judge;</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>(f)</Label><Text>expand the class of persons who may make an interference complaint and provide that a member of the military police or person performing policing duties or functions under the Canadian Forces Provost Marshal’s supervision must make such a complaint in certain circumstances; and</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>(g)</Label><Text>change the title of the Canadian Forces Provost Marshal to the Provost Marshal General.</Text></Provision></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>In addition, the enactment amends the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">National Defence Act</XRefExternal> to remove military judges from the summary hearing system and to provide that, in the context of a service offence, an individual acting on behalf of a victim may request that a victim’s liaison officer be appointed to assist them.<PageBreak /></Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>It further amends that Act to harmonize the sex offender information and publication ban provisions with the amendments made to the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Criminal Code</XRefExternal> in <XRefExternal reference-type="act">An Act to amend the Criminal Code, the Sex Offender Information Registration Act and the International Transfer of Offenders Act</XRefExternal>.</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>Finally, it amends the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Criminal Code</XRefExternal> to, among other things, provide superior courts of criminal jurisdiction with the jurisdiction to hear applications for an exemption in respect of orders to comply with the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Sex Offender Information Registration Act</XRefExternal> made under the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">National Defence Act</XRefExternal> and applications to vary the duration of such orders.</Text></Provision></Summary><Enacts><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>His Majesty, by and with the advice and consent of the Senate and House of Commons of Canada, enacts as follows:</Text></Provision></Enacts></Introduction><Body><Heading level="1"><TitleText>Short Title</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Short title</MarginalNote><Label>1</Label><Text>This Act may be cited as the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Military Justice System Modernization Act</XRefExternal>.</Text></Section><Heading level="1"><MarginalNote><HistoricalNote>R.S., c. N-5</HistoricalNote></MarginalNote><TitleText><XRefExternal reference-type="act">National Defence Act</XRefExternal></TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><Label>2</Label><Text>Section 9.2 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">National Defence Act</XRefExternal> is amended by adding the following after subsection (1):</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Subsection change="ins"><MarginalNote>Clarification — independence</MarginalNote><Label>(1.1)</Label><Text>For greater certainty, in the exercise of the Judge Advocate General’s superintendence, the Judge Advocate General respects the independence of authorities in the military justice system, including the Provost Marshal General, the Director of Military Prosecutions and the Director of Defence Counsel Services.</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>3</Label><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Paragraph 12(3)(a) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>prescribing the rates and conditions of issue of pay of military judges;</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The portion of subsection 12(4) of the Act before paragraph (a) is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Subsection><MarginalNote>Retroactive effect</MarginalNote><Label>(4)</Label><Text>Regulations made under paragraph (3)(a) may, if they so provide, have retroactive effect. However, <Ins>they</Ins> may not have effect</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Subsection></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>4</Label><Text>Subsections 18.3(1) to (4) of the Act are replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Section><MarginalNote>Appointment</MarginalNote><Label>18.3</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The <Ins>Governor in Council</Ins> may appoint an officer who has been a member of the military police for at least 10 years to be the Provost Marshal <Ins>General</Ins>.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Rank</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The Provost Marshal <Ins>General</Ins> holds a rank that is not less than <Ins>brigadier-general</Ins>.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Tenure of office</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>The Provost Marshal <Ins>General</Ins> holds office during <Ins>pleasure</Ins> for a term not exceeding four years.</Text></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>5</Label><Text>Paragraph 18.4(a) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><SectionPiece><Paragraph change="ins"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>the supervision of the performance of policing duties and functions;</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>6</Label><Text>Sections 18.5 and 18.6 of the Act are replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Section change="ins"><MarginalNote><Ins>Acting Provost Marshal General</Ins></MarginalNote><Label><Ins>18.41</Ins></Label><Text>If the Provost Marshal General is absent or unable to act or the office of Provost Marshal General is vacant, the Minister may authorize any officer who is a member of the military police to exercise the powers and perform the duties and functions of the Provost Marshal General, but that officer may act as the Provost Marshal General for a period of more than 90 days only with the approval of the Governor in Council.</Text></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Responsible to Minister</MarginalNote><Label>18.5</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The Provost Marshal <Ins>General is responsible to the Minister in the performance</Ins> of the responsibilities described in paragraphs 18.4(a) to (d).</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>General instructions or guidelines</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The <Ins>Minister</Ins> may issue general instructions or guidelines in writing in respect of the responsibilities described in paragraphs 18.4(a) to (d). The Provost Marshal <Ins>General</Ins> shall ensure that they are available to the public.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Annual report</MarginalNote><Label>18.6</Label><Text>The Provost Marshal <Ins>General</Ins> shall, within three months after the end of each fiscal year, submit to the <Ins>Minister</Ins> a report concerning the activities of the Provost Marshal <Ins>General</Ins> and the military police during the year.</Text></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>7</Label><Text>Section 70 of the Act is amended by striking out “or” at the end of paragraph (b) and by adding the following after paragraph (c):</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><SectionPiece><Paragraph change="ins"><Label>(d)</Label><Text>an offence under any of the following provisions of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Criminal Code</XRefExternal>:</Text><Subparagraph><Label>(i)</Label><Text>section 151 (sexual interference),</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph><Label>(ii)</Label><Text>section 152 (invitation to sexual touching),</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph><Label>(iii)</Label><Text>section 153 (sexual exploitation),</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph><Label>(iv)</Label><Text>section 153.1 (sexual exploitation of person with disability),</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph><Label>(v)</Label><Text>section 155 (incest),</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph><Label>(vi)</Label><Text>subsection 160(1) (bestiality),</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph><Label>(vii)</Label><Text>subsection 160(2) (compelling the commission of bestiality),</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph><Label>(viii)</Label><Text>subsection 160(3) (bestiality in presence of or by a child),</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph><Label>(ix)</Label><Text>section 162 (voyeurism),</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph><Label>(x)</Label><Text>section 162.1 (publication, etc., of an intimate image without consent),</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph><Label>(xi)</Label><Text>section 163.1 (child pornography),</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph><Label>(xii)</Label><Text>section 170 (parent or guardian procuring sexual activity),</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph><Label>(xiii)</Label><Text>section 171 (householder permitting prohibited sexual activity),</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph><Label>(xiv)</Label><Text>section 171.1 (making sexually explicit material available to child),</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph><Label>(xv)</Label><Text>section 172.1 (luring a child),</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph><Label>(xvi)</Label><Text>section 172.2 (agreement or arrangement — sexual offence against child),</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph><Label>(xvii)</Label><Text>subsection 173(2) (exposure),</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph><Label>(xviii)</Label><Text>section 271 (sexual assault),</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph><Label>(xix)</Label><Text>section 272 (sexual assault with a weapon, threats to a third party or causing bodily harm),</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph><Label>(xx)</Label><Text>section 273 (aggravated sexual assault),</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph><Label>(xxi)</Label><Text>section 273.3 (removal of a child from Canada),</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph><Label>(xxii)</Label><Text>section 279.011 (trafficking  —  person under 18 years),</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph><Label>(xxiii)</Label><Text>subsection 279.02(2) (material benefit — trafficking of person under 18 years),</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph><Label>(xxiv)</Label><Text>subsection 279.03(2) (withholding or destroying documents — trafficking of person under 18 years),</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph><Label>(xxv)</Label><Text>section 286.1 (obtaining sexual services for consideration),</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph><Label>(xxvi)</Label><Text>section 286.2 (material benefit from sexual services),</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph><Label>(xxvii)</Label><Text>section 286.3 (procuring), and</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph><Label>(xxviii)</Label><Text>section 286.4 (advertising sexual services);</Text></Subparagraph></Paragraph><Paragraph change="ins"><Label>(e)</Label><Text>an offence under the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Criminal Code</XRefExternal> — other than an offence referred to in paragraph (d) — that is of a sexual nature or that is committed for a sexual purpose;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph change="ins"><Label>(f)</Label><Text>an offence under the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Criminal Code</XRefExternal>, as it read from time to time before the day on which this paragraph comes into force, if the conduct alleged would be an offence referred to in paragraph (d) or (e) if it occurred on or after that day;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph change="ins"><Label>(g)</Label><Text>conspiring or attempting to commit an offence referred to in any of paragraphs (d) to (f) or being an accessory after the fact to such an offence; or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph change="ins"><Label>(h)</Label><Text>counselling a person to commit an offence referred to in any of paragraphs (d) to (f) if the offence is not committed.</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>8</Label><Text>The Act is amended by adding the following after section 70:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Section change="ins"><MarginalNote>No authority to investigate — certain offences</MarginalNote><Label>70.1</Label><Text>Despite any other provision of this Act and any other law, an officer or non-commissioned member does not have authority to investigate, for the purposes of the laying of a charge under paragraph 130(1)(a) or an information under the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Criminal Code</XRefExternal>, in relation to an offence referred to in any of paragraphs 70(d) to (h) that was, or is alleged to have been, committed in Canada.</Text></Section><Section change="ins"><MarginalNote>Clarification — investigative measures</MarginalNote><Label>70.2</Label><Subsection change="ins"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Nothing in section 70.1 prevents an officer or non-commissioned member from exercising their powers or performing their duties and functions, before the arrival of the civilian authority having jurisdiction in the matter, to the extent necessary to prevent the commission, continuation or repetition of an offence referred to in any of paragraphs 70(d) to (h) that, as the case may be, is being, was, or is alleged to have been committed in Canada, including</Text><Paragraph change="ins"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>making an arrest in relation to the offence in accordance with Division 3 of Part III of this Act or section 494 or 495 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Criminal Code</XRefExternal>; or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph change="ins"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>if an arrest is made under paragraph (a), conducting a search incident to the arrest.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection change="ins"><MarginalNote>Evidence relating to the offence</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Nothing in section 70.1 prevents an officer or non-commissioned member from securing or preserving any evidence of or relating to the offence referred to in subsection (1) before the arrival of the civilian authority having jurisdiction in the matter.</Text></Subsection><Subsection change="ins"><MarginalNote>Evidence otherwise secured</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>Nothing in section 70.1 prevents an officer or non-commissioned member from securing or preserving — to the extent that their powers, duties and functions under this Act, other than under subsection (1) or (2), or any other law authorize them to do so — evidence of or relating to an offence referred to in any of paragraphs 70(d) to (h) that was, or is alleged to have been, committed in Canada.</Text></Subsection><Subsection change="ins"><MarginalNote>Transfer of arrested persons and evidence</MarginalNote><Label>(4)</Label><Text>An officer or non-commissioned member shall, as soon as feasible, transfer a person arrested under paragraph (1)(a) to the custody of the civilian authority having jurisdiction in the matter and transfer to them any evidence secured or preserved under any of subsections (1) to (3).</Text></Subsection></Section><Section change="ins"><MarginalNote>Clarification — private prosecutions</MarginalNote><Label>70.3</Label><Text>Nothing in section 70.1 prevents an officer or non-commissioned member from initiating or conducting a private prosecution in relation to an offence referred to in any of paragraphs 70(d) to (h).</Text></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>9</Label><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Subsection 71.16(1) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Section><MarginalNote>Victim’s liaison officer</MarginalNote><Label>71.16</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Unless <Ins>they are</Ins> of the opinion that it is not possible to do so for operational reasons, a commanding officer shall, at the request of the victim <Ins>or an individual acting on their behalf</Ins>, appoint an officer or non-commissioned member, who satisfies the conditions established in regulations made by the Governor in Council, to be a liaison officer to assist the victim <Ins>or individual</Ins> as provided for in subsection (3). The commanding officer shall, to the extent possible, appoint the officer or non-commissioned member who has been requested by the victim <Ins>or individual</Ins> to be their liaison officer.</Text></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Paragraphs 71.16(3)(a) and (b) of the Act are replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>explaining to the victim <Ins>or individual acting on their behalf</Ins> the manner in which service offences are charged, dealt with and tried under the Code of Service Discipline; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>obtaining and transmitting to the victim <Ins>or individual acting on their behalf</Ins> information relating to a service offence that <Ins>they have</Ins> requested and to which <Ins>they have</Ins> a right under this Division.</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>10</Label><Text>Subsection 119.1(3) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Subsection><MarginalNote>Proof of certain facts by certificate</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>In proceedings under subsection (1), a certificate of a person referred to in paragraph 16(2)(b.1) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Sex Offender Information Registration Act</XRefExternal> stating that the person named in the certificate failed to report under section 4, 4.1, 4.2 or 4.3 — or provide information under section 5 or notify a person under subsection 6(1) <Ins>or (1.01)</Ins> — of that Act is evidence of the statements contained in it without proof of the signature or official character of the person appearing to have signed it.</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>11</Label><Text>The Act is amended by adding the following after section 162.5:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Section change="ins"><MarginalNote>Military judges</MarginalNote><Label>162.51</Label><Text>A military judge is not to be charged with having committed a service infraction.</Text></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>12</Label><Text>Paragraph 162.9(c) of the Act is repealed.</Text></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>13</Label><Text>Section 163 of the Act is amended by adding the following after subsection (2):</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Subsection change="ins"><MarginalNote>Military judges</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>Despite subsections (1) and (2), a military judge may not conduct a hearing.</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>14</Label><Text>Section 163.4 of the French version of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no" xml:lang="fr"><Section><MarginalNote>Prescription</MarginalNote><Label>163.4</Label><Text><Ins>L’</Ins>audience sommaire <Ins>ne peut commencer que dans les</Ins> six mois <Ins>suivant</Ins> la date de la commission présumée du manquement d’ordre militaire <Ins>auquel elle se rapporte</Ins>.</Text></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>15</Label><Text>Section 165.1 of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Section><MarginalNote>Appointment</MarginalNote><Label>165.1</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The <Ins>Governor in Council</Ins> may appoint an officer who is a barrister or advocate with at least ten years standing at the bar of a province to be the Director of Military Prosecutions.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Tenure of office</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The Director of Military Prosecutions holds office during good behaviour for a term of not more than <Ins>seven</Ins> years <Ins>but</Ins> may <Ins>be subject to remedial or disciplinary measures in accordance with section 165.101</Ins>.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Term not renewable</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>The Director of Military Prosecutions is <Ins>not</Ins> eligible to be reappointed.</Text></Subsection><Subsection change="ins"><MarginalNote>Suspension</MarginalNote><Label>(4)</Label><Text>On receipt of a request referred to in subsection 165.101(1), the Governor in Council may, if the Governor in Council is of the opinion that there are exceptional circumstances that justify it, suspend the Director of Military Prosecutions from office until the Governor in Council decides whether to impose any remedial or disciplinary measures.</Text></Subsection><Subsection change="ins"><MarginalNote>Definition of <DefinitionRef>exceptional circumstances</DefinitionRef></MarginalNote><Label>(5)</Label><Text>For the purposes of subsection (4), <DefinedTermEn>exceptional circumstances</DefinedTermEn> include circumstances in which there are allegations of serious misconduct or allegations related to a risk to occupational health and safety or to a risk of injury to international relations, national defence or national security.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section change="ins"><MarginalNote>Inquiry</MarginalNote><Label>165.101</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The Minister may request of the Governor in Council that an inquiry be held to determine whether the Director of Military Prosecutions should be subject to remedial or disciplinary measures for any reason set out in paragraphs (12)(a) to (e).</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Appointment of judge</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>On receipt of a request, the Governor in Council may appoint a judge of a superior court to conduct the inquiry.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Powers</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>The judge has all the powers, rights and privileges that are vested in a superior court, including the power to</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>issue a summons requiring any person to appear at the time and place specified in the summons in order to testify about all matters within the person’s knowledge relative to the inquiry and to produce any document or thing relative to the inquiry that the person has or controls; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>administer oaths and examine any person on oath.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Staff</MarginalNote><Label>(4)</Label><Text>The judge may engage the services of counsel and other persons having technical or specialized knowledge to assist the judge in conducting the inquiry, establish the terms and conditions of their engagement and, with the approval of the Treasury Board, fix and pay their remuneration and expenses.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Inquiry in public</MarginalNote><Label>(5)</Label><Text>Subject to subsections (6) and (7), the inquiry shall be conducted in public.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Confidentiality of inquiry</MarginalNote><Label>(6)</Label><Text>The judge may, on application, take any measures and make any order that the judge considers necessary to ensure the confidentiality of the inquiry if, after having considered all available alternative measures, the judge is satisfied that</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>there is a real and substantial risk that matters involving international relations, national defence or national security will be disclosed;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>there is a real and substantial risk to the fairness of the inquiry such that the need to prevent disclosure outweighs the societal interest that the inquiry be conducted in public; or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(c)</Label><Text>there is a serious possibility that the life, liberty or security of a person will be endangered.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Confidentiality of application</MarginalNote><Label>(7)</Label><Text>If the judge considers it appropriate, the judge may take any measures and make any order that the judge considers necessary to ensure the confidentiality of a hearing held in respect of an application under subsection (6).</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Rules of evidence</MarginalNote><Label>(8)</Label><Text>The judge is not bound by any legal or technical rules of evidence and may receive, and base a decision on, evidence presented in the proceedings that they consider credible or trustworthy in the circumstances of the case.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Intervenors</MarginalNote><Label>(9)</Label><Text>An interested party may, with leave of the judge, intervene in the inquiry on any terms and conditions that the judge considers appropriate.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Notice to Director of Military Prosecutions</MarginalNote><Label>(10)</Label><Text>The Director of Military Prosecutions shall be given reasonable notice of the subject matter of the inquiry and of the time and place of any hearing and shall be given an opportunity, in person or by counsel, to be heard at the hearing, to cross-examine witnesses and to present evidence.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Report to Minister</MarginalNote><Label>(11)</Label><Text>After the inquiry has been completed, the judge shall submit a report containing their findings and recommendations, if any, to the Minister.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Recommendations</MarginalNote><Label>(12)</Label><Text>The judge may, in the report, recommend that the Director of Military Prosecutions be suspended without pay or removed from office or that any other disciplinary measure or any remedial measure be taken if, in the judge’s opinion, the Director</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>has become incapacitated from the proper execution of that office by reason of infirmity;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>has committed misconduct;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(c)</Label><Text>has failed in the proper execution of that office;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(d)</Label><Text>has been placed, by conduct or otherwise, in a position that is incompatible with the due execution of that office; or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(e)</Label><Text>no longer satisfies the minimum standards and conditions of service applicable to officers.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Transmission of report to Governor in Council</MarginalNote><Label>(13)</Label><Text>The Minister shall send the report to the Governor in Council who may, if the Governor in Council considers it appropriate, suspend the Director of Military Prosecutions without pay, remove the Director from office or impose any other disciplinary measure or any remedial measure.</Text></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>16</Label><Text>Section 165.16 of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Section><MarginalNote>Acting Director of Military Prosecutions</MarginalNote><Label>165.16</Label><Text><Ins>If</Ins> the Director of Military Prosecutions <Ins>is absent or unable to act or the office of Director of Military Prosecutions is vacant</Ins>, the Minister <Ins>may authorize</Ins> any officer who is a barrister or advocate with standing at the bar of a province <Ins>to exercise</Ins> the powers and <Ins>perform</Ins> the duties and functions of <Ins>the Director of Military Prosecutions, but that officer may act as the Director of Military Prosecutions for a period of more than 90 days only with the approval of the Governor in Council</Ins>.</Text></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>17</Label><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Subsection 165.17(3) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Subsection><MarginalNote>Specific instructions or guidelines</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>The <Ins>Minister</Ins> may issue instructions or guidelines in writing in respect of a particular prosecution.</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Subsections 165.17(5) and (6) of the Act are replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Subsection><MarginalNote>Exception</MarginalNote><Label>(5)</Label><Text>The Director of Military Prosecutions <Ins>may, if they consider</Ins> it to be in the best interests of the administration of military justice, <Ins>delay making an</Ins> instruction or guideline <Ins>issued under subsection (3)</Ins>, or any part of it, available to the public <Ins>until the completion of the prosecution or any related prosecution</Ins>.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Copies to Minister</MarginalNote><Label>(6)</Label><Text>The Judge Advocate General shall provide the Minister with a copy of every instruction and guideline <Ins>issued</Ins> under <Ins>subsection (2)</Ins>.</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Subsection></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>18</Label><Text>Subsection 165.21(1) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Section><MarginalNote>Appointment</MarginalNote><Label>165.21</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The Governor in Council may appoint any officer <Ins>or non-commissioned member</Ins> who is a barrister or advocate of at least 10 years’ standing at the bar of a province and who has been <Ins>a member of the Canadian Forces</Ins> for at least ten years to be a military judge.</Text></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>19</Label><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The portion of subsection 165.22(1) of the Act before paragraph (a) is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Section><MarginalNote>Panel established</MarginalNote><Label>165.22</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>There is established a Reserve Force Military Judges Panel to which the Governor in Council may name any officer <Ins>or non-commissioned member</Ins> who has been <Ins>a member of the Canadian Forces</Ins> for at least 10 years and who</Text></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Subsection 165.22(2) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Subsection><MarginalNote>Reserve force military judge</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text><Ins>A member of the Canadian Forces</Ins> named to the panel is referred to in this Act as a “reserve force military judge”.</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Subsection></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>20</Label><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Subparagraph 183.5(1)(a)(i) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><SectionPiece><Subparagraph><Label>(i)</Label><Text>an offence punishable under section 130 that is an offence under section 151, 152, 153, 153.1, 155, 160, 162, <Ins>162.1</Ins>, 163.1, 170, 171, 171.1, 172, 172.1, 172.2, 173, 213, 271, 272, 273, 279.01, 279.011, 279.02, 279.03, 280, 281, 286.1, 286.2, 286.3, 346 or 347 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Criminal Code</XRefExternal>,</Text></Subparagraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Paragraphs 183.5(2)(a) and (b) of the French version of the Act are replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no" xml:lang="fr"><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>a)</Label><Text>d’aviser <Ins>dans les meilleurs délais</Ins> la victime et <Ins>tout témoin âgé</Ins> de moins de dix-huit ans de leur droit de demander l’ordonnance;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>b)</Label><Text>de rendre l’ordonnance, si le procureur de la poursuite, la victime ou <Ins>tout témoin âgé de moins de dix-huit ans</Ins> lui en fait la demande;</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(3)</Label><Text>Subsection 183.5(2) of the Act is amended by striking out “and” at the end of paragraph (a), by adding “and” at the end of paragraph (b) and by adding the following after paragraph (b):</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><SectionPiece><Paragraph change="ins"><Label>(c)</Label><Text>if an order is made, as soon as feasible, inform the victim and witness who are the subject of that order of its existence and of their right to apply to revoke or vary it.</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(4)</Label><Text>Subsection 183.5(4) of the Act is amended by striking out “and” at the end of paragraph (a), by adding “and” at the end of paragraph (b) and by adding the following after paragraph (b):</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><SectionPiece><Paragraph change="ins"><Label>(c)</Label><Text>if an order is made, as soon as feasible, inform the victim of the existence of the order and of their right to apply to revoke or vary it.</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(5)</Label><Text>Subsection 183.5(6) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Subsection change="ins"><MarginalNote>Duty to inquire</MarginalNote><Label>(5.1)</Label><Text>If the prosecutor makes an application for an order under paragraph (2)(b) or (4)(b), the military judge shall</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>if the victim or witness is present, inquire of them if they wish to be the subject of the order;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>if the victim or witness is not present, inquire of the prosecutor if, before the application was made, they determined whether the victim or witness wishes to be the subject of the order; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(c)</Label><Text>in any event, advise the prosecutor of their duty under subsection (5.2).</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection change="ins"><MarginalNote>Duty to inform</MarginalNote><Label>(5.2)</Label><Text>If the prosecutor makes the application, they shall, as soon as feasible after the military judge makes the order, inform the military judge that they have</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>informed the victim and the witness who are the subject of the order of its existence;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>determined whether they wish to be the subject of the order; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(c)</Label><Text>informed them of their right to apply to revoke or vary the order.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Limitation</MarginalNote><Label>(6)</Label><Text>An order made under this section does not apply in <Ins>either of the following circumstances</Ins>:</Text><Paragraph><Label><Ins>(a)</Ins></Label><Text>the disclosure of information is made in the course of the administration of military justice and it is made for a purpose other than to make the information known in the community; <Ins>or</Ins></Text></Paragraph><Paragraph change="ins"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>the disclosure of information is made by a person who is the subject of the order and is about that person and their particulars, in any forum and for any purpose, and they did not intentionally or recklessly reveal the identity of, or reveal particulars likely to identify, any other person whose identity is protected by an order prohibiting the publication in any document or the broadcasting or transmission in any way of information that could identify that other person.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection change="ins"><MarginalNote>Limitation — victims and witnesses</MarginalNote><Label>(7)</Label><Text>An order made under this section does not apply in respect of the disclosure of information by the victim or witness when it is not the purpose of the disclosure to make the information known to the public, including when the disclosure is made to a legal professional, a health care professional or a person in a relationship of trust with the victim or witness.</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Subsection></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>21</Label><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Subsection 183.6(4) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Subsection><MarginalNote>Limitation</MarginalNote><Label>(4)</Label><Text>An order made under this section does not apply in <Ins>either of the following circumstances</Ins>:</Text><Paragraph><Label><Ins>(a)</Ins></Label><Text>the disclosure is made in the course of the administration of military justice and it is made for a purpose other than to make the information known in the community; <Ins>or</Ins></Text></Paragraph><Paragraph change="ins"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>the disclosure of information is made by a person who is the subject of the order and is about that person and their particulars, in any forum and for any purpose, and they did not intentionally or recklessly reveal the identity of, or reveal particulars likely to identify, any other person whose identity is protected by an order prohibiting the publication in any document or the broadcasting or transmission in any way of information that could identify that other person.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection change="ins"><MarginalNote>Limitation — victims, witnesses and other participants</MarginalNote><Label>(4.1)</Label><Text>An order made under this section does not apply in respect of the disclosure of information by the victim, witness or military justice system participant when it is not the purpose of the disclosure to make the information known to the public, including when the disclosure is made to a legal professional, a health care professional or a person in a relationship of trust with the victim, witness or military justice system participant.</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Section 183.6 of the Act is amended by adding the following after subsection (6):</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Subsection change="ins"><MarginalNote>Duty to inquire</MarginalNote><Label>(6.1)</Label><Text>If the prosecutor makes an application for an order under subsection (1) or (2), the military judge shall</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>if the victim, witness or military justice system participant is present, inquire of them if they wish to be the subject of the order;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>if the victim, witness or military justice system participant is not present, inquire of the prosecutor if, before the application was made, they determined whether the victim, witness or military justice system participant wishes to be the subject of the order; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(c)</Label><Text>in any event, advise the prosecutor of their duty under subsection (9.2).</Text></Paragraph></Subsection></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(3)</Label><Text>Section 183.6 of the Act is amended by adding the following after subsection (9):</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Subsection change="ins"><MarginalNote>Supplementary duty — military judge</MarginalNote><Label>(9.1)</Label><Text>If an order is made, the military judge shall, as soon as feasible, inform the victim, witness and military justice system participant who are the subject of that order of its existence and of their right to apply to revoke or vary it.</Text></Subsection><Subsection change="ins"><MarginalNote>Duty to inform</MarginalNote><Label>(9.2)</Label><Text>If the prosecutor makes the application, they shall, as soon as feasible after the military judge makes the order, inform the military judge that they have</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>informed the victim, witness and military justice system participant who are the subject of the order of its existence;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>determined whether they wish to be the subject of the order; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(c)</Label><Text>informed them of their right to apply to revoke or vary the order.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection></AmendedText></Subsection></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>22</Label><Text>The Act is amended by adding the following after section 183.6:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Section change="ins"><MarginalNote>Application — vary or revoke</MarginalNote><Label>183.61</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>If a person who is the subject of an order made under section 183.5 or 183.6 requests that the prosecutor have it varied or revoked, the prosecutor shall, as soon as feasible, make an application to vary or revoke the order on their behalf.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Order — vary or revoke</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>If an application to vary or revoke an order made under section 183.5 or 183.6 is made by the person who is the subject of the order or by any other person, including a prosecutor, who is acting on their behalf, the military judge assigned to preside at the court martial or a military judge designated by the Chief Military Judge shall, without holding a hearing, vary or revoke the order, unless the military judge is of the opinion that to do so may affect the privacy interests of any person who is the subject of any order prohibiting the publication in any document or the broadcasting or transmission in any way of information that could identify that person.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Hearing</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>If the military judge is of the opinion that varying or revoking the order that is the subject of an application referred to in subsection (2) may affect the privacy interests of any person who is the subject of any order prohibiting the publication in any document or the broadcasting or transmission in any way of information that could identify that person, the military judge shall hold a hearing to determine whether the order should be varied or revoked.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Factor</MarginalNote><Label>(4)</Label><Text>In order to determine whether the order should be varied, the military judge shall take into account whether it is possible to do so in a manner that protects the privacy interests of any other person who is the subject of any order prohibiting the publication in any document or the broadcasting or transmission in any way of information that could identify that person.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Notice</MarginalNote><Label>(5)</Label><Text>The applicant is not required to provide notice of the application to vary or revoke the order to the accused.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Submissions</MarginalNote><Label>(6)</Label><Text>The accused shall not be permitted to make submissions in relation to the application.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Notice of change</MarginalNote><Label>(7)</Label><Text>If the order is varied or revoked, the prosecutor shall notify the accused.</Text></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>23</Label><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The definition <DefinedTermEn>designated offence</DefinedTermEn> in section 227 of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><SectionPiece><Definition><Text><DefinedTermEn>designated offence</DefinedTermEn> means a <Ins>primary</Ins> offence or a <Ins>secondary</Ins> offence. (<DefinedTermFr>infraction désignée</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Definition></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Section 227 of the Act is amended by adding the following in alphabetical order:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><SectionPiece><Definition change="ins"><Text><DefinedTermEn>primary offence</DefinedTermEn> means</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>an offence referred to in any of paragraphs (a) to (e) of the definition <DefinitionRef>primary offence</DefinitionRef> in subsection 490.011(1) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Criminal Code</XRefExternal> that is punishable under section 130 of this Act; or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>an attempt or conspiracy to commit an offence referred to in paragraph (a). (<DefinedTermFr>infraction primaire</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Paragraph></Definition><Definition change="ins"><Text><DefinedTermEn>secondary offence</DefinedTermEn> means</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>an offence referred to in paragraph (a) of the definition <DefinitionRef>secondary offence</DefinitionRef> in subsection 490.011(1) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Criminal Code</XRefExternal> that is punishable under section 130 of this Act; or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>an attempt or conspiracy to commit an offence referred to in paragraph (a). (<DefinedTermFr>infraction secondaire</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Paragraph></Definition></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>24</Label><Text>Section 227.01 of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Section><MarginalNote>Order</MarginalNote><Label>227.01</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text><Ins>Subject to subsection (5)</Ins>, when a court martial imposes a sentence on a person <Ins>in respect of a</Ins> designated offence, it shall make an order in the prescribed form requiring the person to comply with the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Sex Offender Information Registration Act</XRefExternal> if</Text><Paragraph change="ins"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>a sentence of imprisonment of two years or more is imposed for the designated offence or, if the sentence is in respect of more than one offence, the court martial is of the opinion that a sentence of imprisonment of two years or more is justified for the designated offence; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph change="ins"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>the victim of the designated offence is under the age of 18 years.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Order — previous offence or obligation</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text><Ins>Subject to subsection (5)</Ins>, when a court martial imposes a sentence on a person <Ins>in respect of</Ins> a designated offence, it shall make an order in the prescribed form <Keep svc="1">requiring</Keep> the person to comply with the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Sex Offender Information Registration Act</XRefExternal> if the prosecutor establishes that, before or after the coming into force of <Ins>paragraphs (a) and (b)</Ins>, the person</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>was previously convicted <Ins>under section 130 in respect</Ins> of <Ins>a primary</Ins> offence or <Ins>was previously convicted under</Ins> the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Criminal Code</XRefExternal> <Ins>of a <DefinitionRef>primary offence</DefinitionRef>, as defined</Ins> in subsection 490.011(1) of <Ins>that Act; or</Ins></Text></Paragraph><Paragraph change="ins"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>is or was, as a result of a conviction, subject to an order or obligation under this or another Act of Parliament to comply with the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Sex Offender Information Registration Act</XRefExternal>.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection change="ins"><MarginalNote>Order — other circumstances</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>Subject to subsection (5), when a court martial imposes a sentence on a person in respect of a designated offence in circumstances in which neither subsection (1) nor (2) applies, or when the court martial finds the person not responsible on account of mental disorder for a designated offence, it shall make an order in the prescribed form requiring the person to comply with the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Sex Offender Information Registration Act</XRefExternal> unless the court martial is satisfied that the person has established that</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>there would be no connection between making the order and the purpose of helping police services prevent or investigate crimes of a sexual nature by requiring the registration of information relating to sex offenders under that Act; or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>the impact of the order on the person, including on their privacy or liberty, would be grossly disproportionate to the public interest in protecting society through the effective prevention or investigation of crimes of a sexual nature that is to be achieved by the registration of information relating to sex offenders under that Act.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection change="ins"><MarginalNote>Factors</MarginalNote><Label>(4)</Label><Text>In determining whether to make an order under subsection (3) in respect of a person, the court martial shall consider</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>the nature and seriousness of the designated offence;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>the victim’s age and other personal characteristics;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(c)</Label><Text>the nature and circumstances of the relationship between the person and the victim;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(d)</Label><Text>the personal characteristics and circumstances of the person;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(e)</Label><Text>the person’s criminal history, including the age at which they previously committed any offence and the length of time for which they have been at liberty without committing an offence;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(f)</Label><Text>the opinions of experts who have examined the person; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(g)</Label><Text>any other factors that the court martial considers relevant.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection change="ins"><MarginalNote>Limitation — secondary offences</MarginalNote><Label>(5)</Label><Text>A court martial shall make an order under any of subsections (1) to (3) in respect of a secondary offence only if the prosecutor applies for the order and establishes beyond a reasonable doubt that the person committed the secondary offence with the intent to commit a primary offence.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Interpretation</MarginalNote><Label>(<Ins>6</Ins>)</Label><Text>For the <Ins>purposes</Ins> of paragraph (<Ins>2</Ins>)(a), a previous conviction includes a conviction for an offence</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>for which a person is given an <DefinitionRef>adult sentence</DefinitionRef>, <Ins>as defined in</Ins> subsection 2(1) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Youth Criminal Justice Act</XRefExternal>; or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>that is made in <DefinitionRef>ordinary court</DefinitionRef>, <Ins>as defined in</Ins> subsection 2(1) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Young Offenders Act</XRefExternal>, chapter Y-1 of the Revised Statutes of Canada, 1985.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>25</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The portion of subsection 227.02(2) of the Act before paragraph (c) is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Subsection><MarginalNote>Duration of order — subsection 227.01(1) or (3)</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>An order made under subsection 227.01(1) or (<Ins>3</Ins>)</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text><Ins>subject to subsections (3) and (5)</Ins>, ends 10 years after it was made if the maximum term of imprisonment for the offence in connection with which it was made is five years or less;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text><Ins>subject to subsections (3) and (5)</Ins>, ends 20 years after it was made if the maximum term of imprisonment for the offence is 10 or 14 years; and</Text></Paragraph></Subsection></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Subsections 227.02(2.1) to (5) of the Act are replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Subsection change="ins"><MarginalNote>Duration of order — offences in same proceeding</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>An order made under subsection 227.01(1) or (3) applies for life if</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>in the same proceeding, the person has been convicted of, or found not responsible on account of mental disorder for, two or more designated offences in connection with which an order under any of subsections 227.01(1) to (3) may be made; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>the court martial is satisfied that those offences demonstrate, or form part of, a pattern of behaviour showing that the person presents an increased risk of reoffending by committing a crime of a sexual nature.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection change="ins"><MarginalNote>If court martial not satisfied</MarginalNote><Label>(4)</Label><Text>If paragraph (3)(a) applies in the circumstances but the court martial is not satisfied as set out in paragraph (3)(b), the duration of the order is determined by applying paragraphs (2)(a) to (c) to the designated offence with the longest maximum term of imprisonment.</Text></Subsection><Subsection change="ins"><MarginalNote>Duration of order — other order or obligation</MarginalNote><Label>(5)</Label><Text>An order made under subsection 227.01(1) or (3) applies for life if the person</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>was previously convicted of, or previously found not responsible on account of mental disorder for, an offence under section 130 in respect of a primary offence or a <DefinitionRef>primary offence</DefinitionRef>, as defined in subsection 490.011(1) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Criminal Code</XRefExternal>, under that Act; or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>is, or was at any time, the subject of an order or obligation under this or another Act of Parliament to comply with the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Sex Offender Information Registration Act</XRefExternal>.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Duration of order</MarginalNote><Label>(<Ins>6</Ins>)</Label><Text>An order made under subsection 227.01(<Ins>2</Ins>) applies for life.</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Subsection></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>26</Label><Text>The Act is amended by adding the following after section 227.02:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Section change="ins"><MarginalNote>Reasons</MarginalNote><Label>227.021</Label><Text>The court martial shall</Text><Paragraph change="ins"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>state the designated offence that forms the basis of an order made under subsection 227.01(1) and the term of imprisonment imposed; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph change="ins"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>give reasons for a decision under subsection 227.01(3) or paragraph 227.02(3)(b).</Text></Paragraph></Section><Section change="ins"><MarginalNote>Failure to make order</MarginalNote><Label>227.022</Label><Text>If the court martial does not consider the matter under <Ins>any of subsections 227.01</Ins>(1) <Ins>to</Ins> (3) at the time the sentence is imposed, <Ins>or a finding of not responsible on account of mental disorder is made, for a primary offence</Ins>,</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>the Chief Military Judge shall cause the Court Martial Administrator to convene a Standing Court Martial to do so;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>the Court Martial Administrator shall, within 90 days after the day on which the sentence was imposed or the <Ins>finding made</Ins>, convene the court martial;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(c)</Label><Text>for greater certainty, the person continues to be liable to be dealt with under the Code of Service Discipline for that purpose; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph change="ins"><Label>(d)</Label><Text>the court martial may issue a summons in the prescribed form to compel the attendance of the person at the hearing.</Text></Paragraph></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>27</Label><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Paragraph 227.03(1)(c) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(c)</Label><Text>if 20 years have elapsed since the order was made, in the case of an order referred to in paragraph 227.02(2)(c) or subsection 227.02(3), (5) or (<Ins>6</Ins>).</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Subsection 227.03(3) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Subsection><MarginalNote>Pardon, record suspension or absolute discharge</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>Despite subsections (1) and (2), a person may apply for a termination order once they receive a pardon, a record suspension is ordered, or <Ins>they are absolutely discharged under paragraph 672.54(a) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Criminal Code</XRefExternal></Ins>.</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Subsection></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>28</Label><Text>Subsection 227.04(1) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Section><MarginalNote>Termination order</MarginalNote><Label>227.04</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The court martial shall make a termination order if it is satisfied that the person has established that</Text><Paragraph change="ins"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>there would be no connection between continuing an order or obligation and the purpose of helping police services prevent or investigate crimes of a sexual nature by requiring the registration of information relating to sex offenders under the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Sex Offender Information Registration Act</XRefExternal>; or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label><Ins>(b)</Ins></Label><Text>the impact on <Ins>the person</Ins> of continuing an order or an obligation, including on their privacy or liberty, would be grossly disproportionate to the public interest in protecting society through the effective prevention or investigation of crimes of a sexual nature <Ins>that is</Ins> to be achieved by the registration of information relating to sex offenders under <Ins>that Act</Ins>.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection change="ins"><MarginalNote>Factors</MarginalNote><Label>(1.1)</Label><Text>In determining whether to make the termination order, the court martial shall consider</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>the nature and seriousness of the offence that is the basis of an order or obligation;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>the victim’s age and other personal characteristics;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(c)</Label><Text>the nature and circumstances of the relationship between the person and the victim;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(d)</Label><Text>the personal characteristics and circumstances of the person;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(e)</Label><Text>the person’s criminal history, including the age at which they previously committed any offence and the length of time for which they have been at liberty without committing an offence;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(f)</Label><Text>the opinions of experts who have examined the person; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(g)</Label><Text>any other factors that the court martial considers relevant.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>29</Label><Text>Section 227.07 of the Act is amended by adding the following after subsection (2):</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Subsection change="ins"><MarginalNote>References</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>The reference in subsection (1) to the definition <DefinitionRef>designated offence</DefinitionRef> is a reference to that definition as it read from time to time before the day on which this subsection comes into force, the reference in paragraph (2)(c) to subsection 227.01(3) is a reference to that provision as it read from time to time before that day and the reference in that paragraph to subsection 490.012(3) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Criminal Code</XRefExternal> is a reference to that provision as it read from time to time before October 26, 2023.</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>30</Label><Text>Section 227.09 of the Act is amended by adding the following after subsection (3):</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Subsection change="ins"><MarginalNote>References</MarginalNote><Label>(4)</Label><Text>In paragraph (3)(d), the reference to the definition <DefinitionRef>designated offence</DefinitionRef> in section 227 of this Act is a reference to that definition as it read from time to time before the day on which this subsection comes into force and the reference to the definition <DefinitionRef>designated offence</DefinitionRef> in subsection 490.011(1) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Criminal Code</XRefExternal> is a reference to that definition as it read from time to time before October 26, 2023.</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>31</Label><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The portion of subsection 227.12(2) of the Act before paragraph (a) is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Subsection><MarginalNote>Time for application — single offence</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>A person may apply for a termination order if the following period has elapsed since they were sentenced, or found not responsible on account of mental disorder, for <Ins>the</Ins> offence <Ins>listed in the notice</Ins>:</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Subsections 227.12(3) and (4) of the Act are replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Subsection><MarginalNote>More than one offence</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>If more than one offence is listed in the notice, the person may apply for a termination order if 20 years have elapsed since they were sentenced, or found not responsible on account of mental disorder, for the most recent offence.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Pardon or record suspension or absolute discharge</MarginalNote><Label>(4)</Label><Text>Despite subsections (2) and (3), a person may apply for a termination order once they receive a pardon, a record suspension is ordered, or <Ins>they are absolutely discharged under paragraph 672.54(a) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Criminal Code</XRefExternal></Ins>.</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Subsection></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>32</Label><Text>Subsection 227.13(1) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Section><MarginalNote>Termination order</MarginalNote><Label>227.13</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The court martial shall make an order terminating the obligation if it is satisfied that the person has established that</Text><Paragraph change="ins"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>there would be no connection between continuing the obligation and the purpose of helping police services prevent or investigate crimes of a sexual nature by requiring the registration of information relating to sex offenders under the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Sex Offender Information Registration Act</XRefExternal>; or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label><Ins>(b)</Ins></Label><Text>the impact on <Ins>the person</Ins> of continuing the obligation, including on their privacy or liberty, would be grossly disproportionate to the public interest in protecting society through the effective prevention or investigation of crimes of a sexual nature <Ins>that is</Ins> to be achieved by the registration of information relating to sex offenders under the <Ins>that Act</Ins>.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection change="ins"><MarginalNote>Factors</MarginalNote><Label>(1.1)</Label><Text>In determining whether to make the termination order, the court martial shall consider</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>the nature and seriousness of the offence that is the basis of the obligation;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>the victim’s age and other personal characteristics;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(c)</Label><Text>the nature and circumstances of the relationship between the person and the victim;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(d)</Label><Text>the personal characteristics and circumstances of the person;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(e)</Label><Text>the person’s criminal history, including the age at which they previously committed any offence and the length of time for which they have been at liberty without committing an offence;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(f)</Label><Text>the opinions of experts who have examined the person; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(g)</Label><Text>any other factors that the court martial considers relevant.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>33</Label><Text>Paragraph 227.15(1)(b) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>appeal the legality of a decision made under <Ins>section</Ins> 227.01 <Ins>or 227.02</Ins>, subsection 227.04(1), 227.1(4) or 227.13(1) or <Ins>section 227.22 or 227.23</Ins> of this Act — or appeal a decision made under <Ins>section</Ins> 490.012 <Ins>or 490.013 or</Ins> subsection 490.016(1), 490.023(2), 490.027(1), 490.02905(2) <Ins>or (2.2), 490.029051(2) or (3)</Ins>, 490.02909(1), <Ins>490.029111(2), 490.029112(2) or (3)</Ins>, 490.02913(1), <Ins>490.04(4)</Ins> or <Ins>(5) or 490.05(4) or (5)</Ins> of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Criminal Code</XRefExternal> — within the required period;</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>34</Label><Text>Paragraph 227.18(1)(b) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>for the purpose of a proceeding under section 227.01 <Ins>or 227.02</Ins>, subsection 227.04(1), 227.1(4) or 227.13(1) or <Ins>section 227.22 or 227.23</Ins> or for the purpose of an appeal respecting the legality of a decision made under any of those provisions, whether a person who is subject to the Code of Service Discipline, or who is an officer, or non-commissioned member, of the primary reserve, is, or was at any time, required to comply with an order made under section 227.01 of this Act or section 490.012 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Criminal Code</XRefExternal> or with an obligation under section 227.06 of this Act, section 490.019 or 490.02901 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Criminal Code</XRefExternal> or section 36.1 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">International Transfer of Offenders Act</XRefExternal>;</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>35</Label><Text>The Act is amended by adding the following after section 227.21:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Heading change="ins" level="3"><TitleText>Additional Orders</TitleText></Heading><Section change="ins"><MarginalNote>Application for exemption order</MarginalNote><Label>227.22</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>A person may apply for an order exempting them from an order made under section 227.01 on or after April 15, 2011 but before the day on which this subsection comes into force.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Jurisdiction</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The application shall be made to the Chief Military Judge if the applicant is subject to the Code of Service Discipline or is an officer, or non-commissioned member, of the primary reserve at the time. In any other case, the application shall be made to a court under section 490.04 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Criminal Code</XRefExternal>.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Court martial</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>On receipt of the application, the Chief Military Judge shall cause the Court Martial Administrator to convene a Standing Court Martial to try the issue.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Limitation — exemption order</MarginalNote><Label>(4)</Label><Text>The court martial shall not make an exemption order in respect of an application made under subsection (1) if</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>the sentence for the designated offence that is the basis of the order made under section 227.01 is a term of imprisonment of two years or more — or, if the sentence is in respect of multiple offences, one of which is the designated offence, the court martial was, at the time of imposing the sentence, of the opinion that a sentence of imprisonment of two years or more was justified for the designated offence — and the victim of the designated offence was under the age of 18 years; or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>before or after the order under section 227.01 was made, the person</Text><Subparagraph><Label>(i)</Label><Text>was convicted of an offence under section 130 in respect of a primary offence — or was convicted under the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Criminal Code</XRefExternal> of a <DefinitionRef>primary offence</DefinitionRef>, as defined in subsection 490.011(1) of that Act — that is not the offence on the basis of which the order was made, or</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph><Label>(ii)</Label><Text>is or was, as a result of a conviction, subject to another order under this or another Act of Parliament to comply with the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Sex Offender Information Registration Act</XRefExternal>.</Text></Subparagraph></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Exemption order</MarginalNote><Label>(5)</Label><Text>Subject to subsection (4), the court martial shall make an exemption order if it is satisfied that the person has established that, at the time the order was made,</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>there was no connection between the order and the purpose of helping police services prevent or investigate crimes of a sexual nature by requiring the registration of information relating to sex offenders under the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Sex Offender Information Registration Act</XRefExternal>; or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>the impact of the order on the person, including on their privacy or liberty, was grossly disproportionate to the public interest in protecting society through the effective prevention or investigation of crimes of a sexual nature that is to be achieved by the registration of information relating to sex offenders under that Act.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Factors</MarginalNote><Label>(6)</Label><Text>In determining whether to make the exemption order, the court martial shall consider</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>the nature and seriousness of the offence that is the basis of the order;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>the victim’s age and other personal characteristics;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(c)</Label><Text>the nature and circumstances of the relationship between the person and the victim;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(d)</Label><Text>the personal characteristics and circumstances of the person;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(e)</Label><Text>the person’s criminal history, including the age at which they previously committed any offence and the length of time for which they have been at liberty without committing an offence;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(f)</Label><Text>the opinions of experts who have examined the person; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(g)</Label><Text>any other factors that the court martial considers relevant.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Reasons for decision</MarginalNote><Label>(7)</Label><Text>The court martial shall give reasons for its decision.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Removal of information from database</MarginalNote><Label>(8)</Label><Text>If the court martial makes an exemption order, it shall also make an order requiring the Royal Canadian Mounted Police to permanently remove from the database all information that relates to the person that was registered in the database on receipt of a copy of the order made under section 227.01.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section change="ins"><MarginalNote>Application for variation order</MarginalNote><Label>227.23</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>A person may apply for an order to vary the duration of</Text><Paragraph change="ins"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>an order made under section 227.01, if the order applies for life under subsection 227.02(2.1), as it read from time to time before the day on which this paragraph comes into force; or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph change="ins"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>an obligation under section 227.06, if the obligation applies for life under paragraph 227.09(3)(d) and none of the offences listed in the prescribed form served on the person in respect of the obligation have a maximum term of imprisonment for life.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Jurisdiction</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The application shall be made to the Chief Military Judge if the applicant is subject to the Code of Service Discipline or is an officer, or non-commissioned member, of the primary reserve at the time. In any other case, the application shall be made to a court under section 490.05 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Criminal Code</XRefExternal>.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Court martial</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>On receipt of the application, the Chief Military Judge shall cause the Court Martial Administrator to convene a Standing Court Martial to try the issue.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Variation order</MarginalNote><Label>(4)</Label><Text>The court martial shall make the variation order if it is satisfied that the person has established that the offences that are the basis of the order or obligation do not demonstrate, or do not form part of, a pattern of behaviour showing that the person presents an increased risk of reoffending by committing a crime of a sexual nature.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Variation of duration</MarginalNote><Label>(5)</Label><Text>If the court martial makes a variation order, it shall set out the duration of the order or obligation in the order, which shall be determined by applying</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>subsection 227.02(2) to the offence in question with the longest maximum term of imprisonment, in the case of an order; or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>paragraphs 227.09(3)(a) and (b) to the offence in question with the longest maximum term of imprisonment, in the case of an obligation.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Reasons for decision</MarginalNote><Label>(6)</Label><Text>The court martial shall give reasons for its decision.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Notification</MarginalNote><Label>(7)</Label><Text>The court martial shall cause the Provost Marshal to be notified of a variation order made under this section.</Text></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>36</Label><Text>Paragraph 230(g) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(g)</Label><Text>the legality of a decision made under <Ins>section</Ins> 227.01 <Ins>or 227.02</Ins>;</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>37</Label><Text>Paragraph 230.1(h) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(h)</Label><Text>the legality of a decision made under <Ins>section</Ins> 227.01 <Ins>or 227.02</Ins>;</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>38</Label><Text>Section 230.2 of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Section><MarginalNote>Appeal from order</MarginalNote><Label>230.2</Label><Text>Subject to subsection 232(3), a person who applied for an exemption order under section 227.1 <Ins>or 227.22</Ins>, a termination order under section 227.03 or 227.12 or <Ins>a variation order under section 227.23</Ins> and the Minister or counsel instructed by the Minister have the right to appeal to the Court Martial Appeal Court in respect of the legality of the decision made by the court martial.</Text></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>39</Label><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Subsections 240.5(1) and (2) of the Act are replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Section><MarginalNote>Appeal against decision</MarginalNote><Label>240.5</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>On the hearing of an appeal respecting the legality of a decision made under <Ins>section</Ins> 227.01 <Ins>or 227.02 or</Ins> subsection 227.04(1), 227.1(4) or 227.13(1) the Court Martial Appeal Court, or another court hearing the appeal, may</Text><Paragraph><Label><Ins>(a)</Ins></Label><Text>dismiss the appeal; or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label><Ins>(b)</Ins></Label><Text>allow <Ins>the appeal</Ins> and order a new hearing, quash <Ins>or amend</Ins> the order or make an order that may be made under <Ins>the applicable</Ins> provision.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection change="ins"><MarginalNote>Appeal against decision — section 227.22 or 227.23</MarginalNote><Label>(1.1)</Label><Text>On the hearing of an appeal respecting the legality of a decision made under section 227.22 or 227.23, the Court Martial Appeal Court, or another court hearing the appeal, may</Text><Paragraph change="ins"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>dismiss the appeal; or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>allow the appeal and order a new hearing, quash or amend the exemption order or variation order or make an order that may be made, as the case may be, under subsection 227.22(5) or section 227.23.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Requirements relating to notice</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>If the Court Martial Appeal Court or other court makes an order that may be made under <Ins>section</Ins> 227.01, it shall cause the requirements set out in section 227.05 to be fulfilled.</Text></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Subsections 240.5(3) and (4) of the French version of the Act are replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no" xml:lang="fr"><Subsection><MarginalNote>Avis au grand prévôt</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>Si elle rend une ordonnance en application des paragraphes 227.04(1) ou 227.13(1), la Cour d’appel de la cour martiale — <Ins>ou toute autre juridiction saisie de l’appel</Ins> — veille à ce que le grand prévôt en soit avisé.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Radiation des renseignements</MarginalNote><Label>(4)</Label><Text>Si elle rend une ordonnance de dispense en application du paragraphe 227.1(4), la Cour d’appel de la cour martiale — <Ins>ou toute autre juridiction saisie de l’appel</Ins> — rend aussi l’ordonnance prévue au paragraphe 227.1(6).</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(3)</Label><Text>Section 240.5 of the Act is amended by adding the following after subsection (4):</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Subsection change="ins"><MarginalNote>Removal of information from database</MarginalNote><Label>(5)</Label><Text>If the Court Martial Appeal Court or other court makes an exemption order that may be made under section 227.22, it shall also make the order referred to in subsection 227.22(8).</Text></Subsection><Subsection change="ins"><MarginalNote>Requirements relating to notice</MarginalNote><Label>(6)</Label><Text>If the Court Martial Appeal Court or other court quashes an exemption order made under section 227.22, it shall cause the Provost Marshal to be notified of the decision and shall cause the person who applied for the order to be informed of section 119.1 and sections 4 to 7.1 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Sex Offender Information Registration Act</XRefExternal>.</Text></Subsection><Subsection change="ins"><MarginalNote>Notice — variation order</MarginalNote><Label>(7)</Label><Text>If the Court Martial Appeal Court or other court quashes or amends a variation order made under section 227.23, or makes an order that may be made under that section, it shall cause the Provost Marshal to be notified of the decision.</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Subsection></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>40</Label><Text>Section 249.18 of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Section><MarginalNote>Appointment</MarginalNote><Label>249.18</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The <Ins>Governor in Council</Ins> may appoint an officer who is a barrister or advocate with at least ten years standing at the bar of a province to be the Director of Defence Counsel Services.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Tenure of office</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The Director of Defence Counsel Services holds office during good behaviour for a term of not more than <Ins>seven</Ins> years <Ins>but</Ins> may <Ins>be subject to remedial or disciplinary measures in accordance with section 249.181</Ins>.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Term not renewable</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>The Director of Defence Counsel Services is <Ins>not</Ins> eligible to be reappointed.</Text></Subsection><Subsection change="ins"><MarginalNote>Suspension</MarginalNote><Label>(4)</Label><Text>On receipt of a request referred to in subsection 249.181(1), the Governor in Council may, if the Governor in Council is of the opinion that there are exceptional circumstances that justify it, suspend the Director of Defence Counsel Services from office until the Governor in Council decides whether to impose any remedial or disciplinary measures.</Text></Subsection><Subsection change="ins"><MarginalNote>Definition of <DefinitionRef>exceptional circumstances</DefinitionRef></MarginalNote><Label>(5)</Label><Text>For the purposes of subsection (4), <DefinedTermEn>exceptional circumstances</DefinedTermEn> include circumstances in which there are allegations of serious misconduct or allegations related to a risk to occupational health and safety or to a risk of injury to international relations, national defence or national security.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section change="ins"><MarginalNote>Inquiry</MarginalNote><Label>249.181</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The Minister may request of the Governor in Council that an inquiry be held to determine whether the Director of Defence Counsel Services should be subject to remedial or disciplinary measures for any reason set out in paragraphs (12)(a) to (e).</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Appointment of judge</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>On receipt of a request, the Governor in Council may appoint a judge of a superior court to conduct the inquiry.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Powers</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>The judge has all the powers, rights and privileges that are vested in a superior court, including the power to</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>issue a summons requiring any person to appear at the time and place specified in the summons in order to testify about all matters within the person’s knowledge relative to the inquiry and to produce any document or thing relative to the inquiry that the person has or controls; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>administer oaths and examine any person on oath.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Staff</MarginalNote><Label>(4)</Label><Text>The judge may engage the services of counsel and other persons having technical or specialized knowledge to assist the judge in conducting the inquiry, establish the terms and conditions of their engagement and, with the approval of the Treasury Board, fix and pay their remuneration and expenses.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Inquiry in public</MarginalNote><Label>(5)</Label><Text>Subject to subsections (6) and (7), the inquiry shall be conducted in public.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Confidentiality of inquiry</MarginalNote><Label>(6)</Label><Text>The judge may, on application, take any measures and make any order that the judge considers necessary to ensure the confidentiality of the inquiry if, after having considered all available alternative measures, the judge is satisfied that</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>there is a real and substantial risk that matters involving international relations, national defence or national security will be disclosed;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>there is a real and substantial risk to the fairness of the inquiry such that the need to prevent disclosure outweighs the societal interest that the inquiry be conducted in public; or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(c)</Label><Text>there is a serious possibility that the life, liberty or security of a person will be endangered.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Confidentiality of application</MarginalNote><Label>(7)</Label><Text>If the judge considers it appropriate, the judge may take any measures and make any order that the judge considers necessary to ensure the confidentiality of a hearing held in respect of an application under subsection (6).</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Rules of evidence</MarginalNote><Label>(8)</Label><Text>The judge is not bound by any legal or technical rules of evidence and may receive, and base a decision on, evidence presented in the proceedings that they consider credible or trustworthy in the circumstances of the case.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Intervenors</MarginalNote><Label>(9)</Label><Text>An interested party may, with leave of the judge, intervene in the inquiry on any terms and conditions that the judge considers appropriate.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Notice to Director of Defence Counsel Services</MarginalNote><Label>(10)</Label><Text>The Director of Defence Counsel Services shall be given reasonable notice of the subject matter of the inquiry and of the time and place of any hearing and shall be given an opportunity, in person or by counsel, to be heard at the hearing, to cross-examine witnesses and to present evidence.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Report to Minister</MarginalNote><Label>(11)</Label><Text>After the inquiry has been completed, the judge shall submit a report containing their findings and recommendations, if any, to the Minister.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Recommendations</MarginalNote><Label>(12)</Label><Text>The judge may, in the report, recommend that the Director of Defence Counsel Services be suspended without pay or removed from office or that any other disciplinary measure or any remedial measure be taken if, in the judge’s opinion, the Director</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>has become incapacitated from the proper execution of that office by reason of infirmity;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>has committed misconduct;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(c)</Label><Text>has failed in the proper execution of that office;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(d)</Label><Text>has been placed, by conduct or otherwise, in a position that is incompatible with the due execution of that office; or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(e)</Label><Text>no longer satisfies the minimum standards and conditions of service applicable to officers.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Transmission of report to Governor in Council</MarginalNote><Label>(13)</Label><Text>The Minister shall send the report to the Governor in Council who may, if the Governor in Council considers it appropriate, suspend the Director of Defence Counsel Services without pay, remove the Director from office or impose any other disciplinary measure or any remedial measure.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section change="ins"><MarginalNote>Acting Director of Defence Counsel Services</MarginalNote><Label>249.182</Label><Text>If the Director of Defence Counsel Services is absent or unable to act or the office of Director of Defence Counsel Services is vacant, the Minister may authorize any officer who is a barrister or advocate with standing at the bar of a province to exercise the powers and perform the duties and functions of the Director of Defence Counsel Services, but that officer may act as the Director of Defence Counsel Services for a period of more than 90 days only with the approval of the Governor in Council.</Text></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>41</Label><Text>The definition <DefinedTermEn>interference complaint</DefinedTermEn> in section 250 of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><SectionPiece><Definition><Text><DefinedTermEn>interference complaint</DefinedTermEn> means a complaint made under subsection 250.19(1) <Ins>or (1.1)</Ins>. (<DefinedTermFr>plainte pour ingérence</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Definition></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>42</Label><Text>Subsection 250.19(1) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Section><MarginalNote>Obligation to make complaint</MarginalNote><Label>250.19</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Any member of the military police or <Ins>person performing policing duties or functions under the Provost Marshal General’s supervision</Ins> who believes on reasonable grounds that any officer, non-commissioned member or senior official of the Department has improperly interfered with the <Ins>performance of any of the policing duties or functions that are prescribed for the purposes of section 250.18 in regulations made by the Governor in Council shall</Ins> make a complaint about that person under this Division.</Text></Subsection><Subsection change="ins"><MarginalNote>Right to make complaint</MarginalNote><Label>(1.1)</Label><Text>If they believe on reasonable grounds that an officer, non-commissioned member or senior official of the Department has improperly interfered with the performance of any of the policing duties or functions that are prescribed for the purposes of section 250.18 in regulations made by the Governor in Council, any of the following may make a complaint about that person under this Division:</Text><Paragraph change="ins"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>a victim or other person affected by the performance of the policing duty or function; or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph change="ins"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>an individual acting on behalf of a victim referred to in paragraph (a).</Text></Paragraph></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>43</Label><Text>Subsection 250.26(2) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Subsection><MarginalNote>Complaint about Provost Marshal General</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>If a conduct complaint is about the conduct of the Provost Marshal <Ins>General</Ins>, the <Ins>Minister, or a person designated by the Minister</Ins>, is responsible for dealing with the complaint and has all the powers and duties of the Provost Marshal <Ins>General</Ins> under this Division.</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>44</Label><Text>Subsection 250.49(2) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Subsection><MarginalNote>Exception</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>If the Provost Marshal <Ins>General</Ins> is the subject of the complaint, the review shall be conducted by the <Ins>Minister</Ins>.</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>45</Label><Text>Subsection 250.5(2) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Subsection><MarginalNote>Exceptions</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>If the Chief of the Defence Staff, the Deputy Minister or <Ins>the Provost Marshal General</Ins> is the subject of the complaint, the review shall be conducted by the Minister.</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>46</Label><Text>Section 303.1 of the Act is amended by adding the following after subsection (1):</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Subsection change="ins"><MarginalNote>Prosecution — limitation</MarginalNote><Label>(1.1)</Label><Text>A prosecutor shall not commence or continue a prosecution against a person who is the subject of the order unless, in the opinion of the prosecutor,</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>the person knowingly failed to comply with the order;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>the privacy interests of another person who is the subject of any order prohibiting the publication in any document or the broadcasting or transmission in any way of information that could identify that person have been compromised; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(c)</Label><Text>a warning to the individual is not appropriate.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote>Replacement of “Canadian Forces Provost Marshal” and “Provost Marshal”</MarginalNote><Label>47</Label><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The Act is amended by replacing “Canadian Forces Provost Marshal” and “Provost Marshal” with “Provost Marshal General” in the following provisions:</Text><Paragraph type="amending"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>the heading before section 18.3;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>subsection 18.3(5);</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(c)</Label><Text>the portion of section 18.4 before paragraph (a);</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(d)</Label><Text>paragraph 215(2)(c);</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(e)</Label><Text>subsection 227.04(3);</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(f)</Label><Text>subparagraph 227.05(1)(d)(iii);</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(g)</Label><Text>subsection 227.07(1);</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(h)</Label><Text>subsection 227.08(4);</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(i)</Label><Text>section 227.11;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(j)</Label><Text>subsection 227.13(3);</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(k)</Label><Text>subsection 227.15(4);</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(l)</Label><Text>the portion of subsection 227.15(5) before paragraph (a);</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(m)</Label><Text>subsection 227.16(3);</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(n)</Label><Text>the portion of subsection 227.18(1) before paragraph (a);</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(o)</Label><Text>the portion of subsection 227.18(2) before paragraph (a);</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(p)</Label><Text>subsection 227.19(1);</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(q)</Label><Text>the portion of subsection 227.19(2) before paragraph (a);</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(r)</Label><Text>section 227.21;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(s)</Label><Text>subsection 240.5(3);</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(t)</Label><Text>subsection 250.21(1);</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(u)</Label><Text>subparagraphs 250.21(2)(c)(i) to (iii);</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(v)</Label><Text>section 250.22;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(w)</Label><Text>subsection 250.24(2);</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(x)</Label><Text>section 250.25;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(y)</Label><Text>subsection 250.26(1);</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(z)</Label><Text>section 250.261;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(z.1)</Label><Text>subsection 250.27(1);</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(z.2)</Label><Text>the portion of subsection 250.27(4) before paragraph (a);</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(z.3)</Label><Text>paragraph 250.27(6)(c);</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(z.4)</Label><Text>subsection 250.28(1);</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(z.5)</Label><Text>the portion of section 250.29 before paragraph (a);</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(z.6)</Label><Text>the portion of subsection 250.3(1) before paragraph (a);</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(z.7)</Label><Text>paragraphs 250.31(2)(a) and (b);</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(z.8)</Label><Text>subsection 250.32(3);</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(z.9)</Label><Text>subsections 250.34(2) and (3);</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(z.91)</Label><Text>subsections 250.35(1) and (3);</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(z.92)</Label><Text>paragraph 250.36(e);</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(z.93)</Label><Text>paragraph 250.37(1)(d);</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(z.94)</Label><Text>subsections 250.38(3) and (5);</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(z.95)</Label><Text>section 250.39;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(z.96)</Label><Text>paragraph 250.4(1)(b);</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(z.97)</Label><Text>section 250.48;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(z.98)</Label><Text>subsection 250.49(1); and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(z.99)</Label><Text>subsection 250.53(2).</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><MarginalNote>Replacement of “Provost Marshal” — English version</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The English version of the Act is amended by replacing “Provost Marshal” with “Provost Marshal General” in the following provisions:</Text><Paragraph type="amending"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>the portion of subsection 250.27(5) before paragraph (a);</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph type="amending"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>the portion of subsection 250.28(2) before paragraph (a);</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph type="amending"><Label>(c)</Label><Text>the portion of subsection 250.28(3) before paragraph (a); and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph type="amending"><Label>(d)</Label><Text>subsections 250.3(2) and (3).</Text></Paragraph></Subsection></Section><Heading level="1"><MarginalNote><HistoricalNote>R.S., c. C-46</HistoricalNote></MarginalNote><TitleText><XRefExternal reference-type="act">Criminal Code</XRefExternal></TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><Label>48</Label><Text>Subsection 490.02(3) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Criminal Code</XRefExternal> is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Subsection><MarginalNote>References</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>The reference in subsection (1) to the definition <DefinitionRef>designated offence</DefinitionRef> is a reference to that definition as it read from time to time before <Ins>October 26, 2023</Ins>, the reference in paragraph (2)(b) to subsection 490.012(3) is a reference to that provision as it read from time to time before that day and <Ins>the reference in that paragraph to subsection 227.01(3) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">National Defence Act</XRefExternal> is a reference to that provision as it read from time to time before</Ins> the day on which <Ins>section <XRefSection lawid="1">48</XRefSection> of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Military Justice System Modernization Act</XRefExternal></Ins> comes into force.</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>49</Label><Text>Subsection 490.022(4) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Subsection><MarginalNote>References</MarginalNote><Label>(4)</Label><Text>In paragraph (3)(d), the reference to the definition <DefinitionRef>designated offence</DefinitionRef> <Ins>in subsection 490.011(1) of this Act</Ins> is a reference to that definition as it read from time to time before <Ins>October 26, 2023 and the reference to the definition <DefinitionRef>designated offence</DefinitionRef> in section 227 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">National Defence Act</XRefExternal> is a reference to that definition as it read from time to time before</Ins> the day on which <Ins>section <XRefSection lawid="2">49</XRefSection> of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Military Justice System Modernization Act</XRefExternal></Ins> comes into force.</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>50</Label><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Paragraphs 490.04(1)(a) and (b) of the Act are replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>an order made under section 490.012 on or after April 15, 2011 but before <Ins>October 26, 2023</Ins>;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph change="ins"><Label>(a.1)</Label><Text>an order made under section 227.01 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">National Defence Act</XRefExternal> on or after April 15, 2011 but before the day on which this paragraph comes into force; or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>an obligation under section 490.02901, or under section 36.1 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">International Transfer of Offenders Act</XRefExternal>, that began before <Ins>October 26, 2023</Ins>.</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Subsection 490.04(2) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Subsection><MarginalNote>Limitation — application</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>A person is not permitted to apply under paragraph (1)(b) if, on or after <Ins>October 26, 2023</Ins>, they have made an application for an exemption order under section 490.02905 or 490.029111 in respect of the same obligation.</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(3)</Label><Text>Paragraph 490.04(3)(a) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>a superior court of criminal jurisdiction,</Text><Subparagraph><Label><Ins>(i)</Ins></Label><Text>if the application is made under paragraph (1)(a) in respect of an order made by such a court, <Ins>or</Ins></Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph change="ins"><Label>(ii)</Label><Text>if the application is made under paragraph (1)(a.1) and the Chief Military Judge does not have jurisdiction to receive the application under subsection 227.22(2) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">National Defence Act</XRefExternal>; or</Text></Subparagraph></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(4)</Label><Text>The portion of paragraph 490.04(4) of the Act before subparagraph (b)(i) is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Subsection><MarginalNote>Limitation — exemption order</MarginalNote><Label>(4)</Label><Text>The court shall not make an exemption order in respect of an application made under paragraph (1)(a) <Ins>or (a.1)</Ins> if</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text><Ins>in the case of an order referred to in paragraph (1)(a)</Ins>, the designated offence that is the basis of the order was prosecuted by indictment, the sentence for that offence is a term of imprisonment of two years or more and the victim of that offence was under the age of 18 years;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph change="ins"><Label>(a.1)</Label><Text><Ins>in the case of an order referred to in paragraph (1)(a.1)</Ins>, the sentence for the <DefinitionRef>designated offence</DefinitionRef>, as defined in section 227 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">National Defence Act</XRefExternal>, that is the basis of the order is a term of imprisonment of two years or more and the victim of that offence was under the age of 18 years; or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>before or after the order <Ins>referred to in paragraph (1)(a) or (a.1)</Ins> was made, the person</Text></Paragraph></Subsection></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(5)</Label><Text>Subsection 490.04(8) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Subsection><MarginalNote>Removal of information from database</MarginalNote><Label>(8)</Label><Text>If the court makes an exemption order, it shall also make an order requiring the Royal Canadian Mounted Police to permanently remove from the database all information that relates to the person that was registered in the database on receipt of a copy of the order made under section 490.012 <Ins>or under section 227.01 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">National Defence Act</XRefExternal></Ins>, the notice referred to in section 490.02901 or the Form 1 referred to in subparagraph 8(4)(a)(ii) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">International Transfer of Offenders Act</XRefExternal>, as the case may be.</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Subsection></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>51</Label><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Paragraph 490.05(1)(a) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>an order made under section 490.012, if the order applies for life under subsection 490.013(2.1), as it read from time to time before <Ins>October 26, 2023</Ins>;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph change="ins"><Label>(a.1)</Label><Text>an order made under section 227.01 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">National Defence Act</XRefExternal>, if the order applies for life under subsection 227.02(2.1) of that Act, as it read from time to time before the day on which this paragraph comes into force;</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Paragraphs 490.05(1)(c) and (d) of the Act are replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><SectionPiece><Paragraph change="ins"><Label>(b.1)</Label><Text>an obligation under section 227.06 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">National Defence Act</XRefExternal>, if the obligation applies for life under paragraph 227.09(3)(d) of that Act and none of the offences listed in the prescribed form served on the person under that Act in respect of the obligation have a maximum term of imprisonment for life;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(c)</Label><Text>an obligation under section 490.02901, if the obligation applies for life under paragraph 490.02904(3)(d), the obligation began before <Ins>October 26, 2023</Ins> and the condition set out in paragraph 490.029051(1)(b) is met; or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(d)</Label><Text>an obligation under section 36.1 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">International Transfer of Offenders Act</XRefExternal>, if the obligation applies for life under subsection 36.2(3) of that Act, the obligation began before <Ins>October 26, 2023</Ins> and the condition set out in paragraph 490.029112(1)(b) is met.</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(3)</Label><Text>Paragraph 490.05(3)(a) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>a superior court of criminal jurisdiction,</Text><Subparagraph><Label><Ins>(i)</Ins></Label><Text>if the application is made under paragraph (1)(a) in respect of an order made by such a court, <Ins>or</Ins></Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph change="ins"><Label>(ii)</Label><Text>if the application is made under paragraph (1)(a.1) or (b.1) and the Chief Military Judge does not have jurisdiction to receive the application under subsection 227.23(2) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">National Defence Act</XRefExternal>; or</Text></Subparagraph></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(4)</Label><Text>Subsection 490.05(5) of the Act is amended by adding the following after paragraph (a):</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><SectionPiece><Paragraph change="ins"><Label>(a.1)</Label><Text>subsection 227.02(2) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">National Defence Act</XRefExternal> to the offence in question with the longest maximum term of imprisonment, in the case of an order under section 227.01 of that Act;</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(5)</Label><Text>Subsection 490.05(5) of the Act is amended by adding the following after paragraph (b):</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><SectionPiece><Paragraph change="ins"><Label>(b.1)</Label><Text>paragraphs 227.09(3)(a) and (b) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">National Defence Act</XRefExternal> to the offence in question with the longest maximum term of imprisonment, in the case of an obligation under section 227.06 of that Act;</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>52</Label><Text>Subsection 490.06(2) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Subsection><MarginalNote>Removal of information from database</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>If an appeal court makes an exemption order, it shall also make an order requiring the Royal Canadian Mounted Police to permanently remove from the database all information that relates to the person that was registered in the database on receipt of a copy of the order made under section 490.012 <Ins>or under section 227.01 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">National Defence Act</XRefExternal></Ins>, the notice referred to in section 490.02901 or the Form 1 referred to in subparagraph 8(4)(a)(ii) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">International Transfer of Offenders Act</XRefExternal>, as the case may be.</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>53</Label><Text>The Act is amended by replacing “Canadian Forces Provost Marshal” with “Provost Marshal General” in section 5 of Form 52 of Part XXVIII.</Text></Section><Heading level="1"><MarginalNote><HistoricalNote>2013, c. 24</HistoricalNote></MarginalNote><TitleText><XRefExternal reference-type="act">Strengthening Military Justice in the Defence of Canada Act</XRefExternal></TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><Label>54</Label><Text>Section 13 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Strengthening Military Justice in the Defence of Canada Act</XRefExternal> is repealed.</Text></Section><Heading level="1"><MarginalNote><HistoricalNote>2004, c. 10</HistoricalNote></MarginalNote><TitleText>Consequential Amendments to the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Sex Offender Information Registration Act</XRefExternal></TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote>Replacement of “Canadian Forces Provost Marshal”</MarginalNote><Label>55</Label><Text>The <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Sex Offender Information Registration Act</XRefExternal> is amended by replacing “Canadian Forces Provost Marshal” with “Provost Marshal General” in the following provisions:</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>the portion of subsection 8.2(1) before paragraph (a);</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>the portion of subsection 8.2(2) before paragraph (a);</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(c)</Label><Text>subsections 8.2(3) to (5);</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(d)</Label><Text>the portion of subsection 8.2(6) before paragraph (a);</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(e)</Label><Text>the portion of subsection 8.2(7) before paragraph (a); and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(f)</Label><Text>subsection 12(2).</Text></Paragraph></Section><Heading level="1"><TitleText>Transitional Provisions</TitleText></Heading><Section type="transitional"><MarginalNote>Words and Expressions</MarginalNote><Label>56</Label><Text>The words and expressions used in sections <XRefInternal>57</XRefInternal> to <XRefInternal>65</XRefInternal> have the same meaning as in the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">National Defence Act</XRefExternal>.</Text></Section><Section type="transitional"><MarginalNote>Canadian Forces Provost Marshal</MarginalNote><Label>57</Label><Subsection type="transitional"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The person who holds office as the Canadian Forces Provost Marshal immediately before the day on which section <XRefInternal>4</XRefInternal> comes into force</Text><Paragraph type="transitional"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>continues, for the remainder of the term for which they were appointed, to hold office, but they hold office during pleasure and as the Provost Marshal General; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph type="transitional"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>is deemed, for that term, to have been appointed under subsection 18.3(1) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">National Defence Act</XRefExternal>, as amended by that section <XRefInternal>4</XRefInternal>.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection type="transitional"><MarginalNote>No compensation</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Despite the provisions of any contract, agreement or order, the person referred to in subsection (1) has no right to claim or receive any compensation, damages, indemnity or other form of relief from His Majesty in right of Canada or from any employee or agent of His Majesty due to the changes made to their appointment by that subsection.</Text></Subsection><Subsection type="transitional"><MarginalNote>Inquiry continued</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>An inquiry under subsections 18.3(3) and (4) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">National Defence Act</XRefExternal>, as they read immediately before the day on which section <XRefInternal>4</XRefInternal> comes into force, that, immediately before that day, had not been completed, is continued in accordance with those subsections except that</Text><Paragraph type="transitional"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>the inquiry committee must provide a record of the inquiry and a report of its conclusions to the Minister, who may recommend to the Governor in Council that the Provost Marshal General be removed from office; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph type="transitional"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>the Governor in Council has the power referred to in that subsection 18.3(3) to remove the Provost Marshal General from office.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection></Section><Section type="transitional"><MarginalNote>General Instructions or guidelines by Vice Chief of Defence Staff</MarginalNote><Label>58</Label><Subsection type="transitional"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>An instruction or guideline issued under subsection 18.5(2) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">National Defence Act</XRefExternal>, as it read immediately before the day on which section <XRefInternal>6</XRefInternal> comes into force, that is in effect immediately before that day is deemed to be an instruction or guideline issued by the Minister under subsection 18.5(2) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">National Defence Act</XRefExternal>, as amended by that section <XRefInternal>6</XRefInternal>.</Text></Subsection><Subsection type="transitional"><MarginalNote>Copy to Minister</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The Vice Chief of the Defence Staff must provide the Minister with a copy of every instruction or guideline referred to in subsection (1) as soon as feasible after the day on which section <XRefInternal>6</XRefInternal> comes into force.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section type="transitional"><MarginalNote>Specific Instructions or guidelines by Vice Chief of Defence Staff</MarginalNote><Label>59</Label><Text>An instruction or guideline issued under subsection 18.5(3) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">National Defence Act</XRefExternal>, as it read immediately before the day on which section <XRefInternal>6</XRefInternal> comes into force, that is in effect immediately before that day ceases to be in effect.</Text></Section><Section type="transitional"><MarginalNote>Transfer of ongoing investigations</MarginalNote><Label>60</Label><Text>As soon as feasible after the day on which section <XRefInternal>7</XRefInternal> comes into force, but no later than 60 days after that day, the Canadian Forces must transfer to the civilian authority having jurisdiction in the matter responsibility for any ongoing investigation into an offence referred to in any of paragraphs 70(d) to (h) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">National Defence Act</XRefExternal>, as enacted by that section <XRefInternal>7</XRefInternal>, that was, or is alleged to have been, committed in Canada and for which a charge has not been laid under that Act or an information has not been laid under the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Criminal Code</XRefExternal> before that day.</Text></Section><Section type="transitional"><MarginalNote>Application of <XRefExternal reference-type="act">National Defence Act</XRefExternal></MarginalNote><Label>61</Label><Text>The <XRefExternal reference-type="act">National Defence Act</XRefExternal>, as it read immediately before the day on which section <XRefInternal>7</XRefInternal> comes into force, continues to apply in respect of an offence referred to in any of paragraphs 70(d) to (h) of that Act, as enacted by that section <XRefInternal>7</XRefInternal>, that was, or is alleged to have been, committed in Canada and for which a charge has been laid under that Act or an information has been laid under the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Criminal Code</XRefExternal> before that day.</Text></Section><Section type="transitional"><MarginalNote>Military judges — service infractions</MarginalNote><Label>62</Label><Text>No charge alleging the commission of a service infraction, laid before the day on which section <XRefInternal>11</XRefInternal> comes into force, is to be proceeded with against a military judge on or after that day.</Text></Section><Section type="transitional"><MarginalNote>Director of Military Prosecutions</MarginalNote><Label>63</Label><Subsection type="transitional"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The person who holds office as the Director of Military Prosecutions immediately before the day on which section <XRefInternal>15</XRefInternal> comes into force</Text><Paragraph type="transitional"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>continues to hold office for the remainder of the term for which they were appointed;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph type="transitional"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>is deemed, for that term, to have been appointed under subsection 165.1(1) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">National Defence Act</XRefExternal>, as amended by that section <XRefInternal>15</XRefInternal>; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph type="transitional"><Label>(c)</Label><Text>is, despite subsection 165.1(3) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">National Defence Act</XRefExternal>, as amended by that section <XRefInternal>15</XRefInternal>, eligible on the expiry of that term to be appointed under that subsection 165.1(1) for a single additional term of not more than seven years.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection type="transitional"><MarginalNote>Inquiry continued</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>An inquiry under subsections 165.1(2) and (2.1) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">National Defence Act</XRefExternal>, as they read immediately before the day on which section <XRefInternal>15</XRefInternal> comes into force, that, immediately before that day, had not been completed, is continued in accordance with those subsections except that the inquiry committee must make its recommendation to the Governor in Council and that the Governor in Council has the power referred to in that subsection 165.1(2) to remove the Director of Military Prosecutions from office.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section type="transitional"><MarginalNote>Specific instructions or guidelines by Judge Advocate General</MarginalNote><Label>64</Label><Subsection type="transitional"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>An instruction or guideline issued under subsection 165.17(3) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">National Defence Act</XRefExternal>, as it read immediately before the day on which subsection <XRefInternal>17</XRefInternal>(1) comes into force, that applies in respect of a prosecution that, immediately before that day, had not been completed is deemed to be an instruction or guideline issued by the Minister under subsection 165.17(3) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">National Defence Act</XRefExternal>, as amended by that subsection <XRefInternal>17</XRefInternal>(1).</Text></Subsection><Subsection type="transitional"><MarginalNote>Availability to public</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Subsection 165.17(5) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">National Defence Act</XRefExternal>, as amended by subsection <XRefInternal>17</XRefInternal>(2), applies in respect of a specific instruction or guideline referred to in subsection (1).</Text></Subsection></Section><Section type="transitional"><MarginalNote>Director of Defence Counsel Services</MarginalNote><Label>65</Label><Subsection type="transitional"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The person who holds office as the Director of Defence Counsel Services immediately before the day on which section <XRefInternal>40</XRefInternal> comes into force</Text><Paragraph type="transitional"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>continues to hold office for the remainder of the term for which they were appointed;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph type="transitional"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>is deemed, for that term, to have been appointed under subsection 249.18(1) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">National Defence Act</XRefExternal>, as amended by that section <XRefInternal>40</XRefInternal>; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph type="transitional"><Label>(c)</Label><Text>is, despite subsection 249.18(3) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">National Defence Act</XRefExternal>, as amended by that section <XRefInternal>40</XRefInternal>, eligible on the expiry of that term to be appointed under that subsection 249.18(1) for a single additional term of not more than seven years.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection type="transitional"><MarginalNote>Inquiry continued</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>An inquiry under subsections 249.18(2) and (2.1) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">National Defence Act</XRefExternal>, as they read immediately before the day on which section <XRefInternal>40</XRefInternal> comes into force, that, immediately before that day, had not been completed, is continued in accordance with those subsections except that the inquiry committee must make its recommendation to the Governor in Council and that the Governor in Council has the power referred to in that subsection 249.18(2) to remove the Director of Defence Counsel Services from office.</Text></Subsection></Section><Heading level="1"><TitleText>Coordinating Amendments</TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote>This Act</MarginalNote><Label>66</Label><Text>On the first day on which both sections <XRefInternal>35</XRefInternal> and <XRefInternal>47</XRefInternal> of this Act are in force,</Text><Paragraph type="amending"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>subsection 227.23(7) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">National Defence Act</XRefExternal> is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Subsection><MarginalNote>Notification</MarginalNote><Label>(7)</Label><Text>The court martial shall cause the Provost Marshal General to be notified of a decision to make a variation order under this section.</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Paragraph><Paragraph type="amending"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>subsection 240.5(3) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">National Defence Act</XRefExternal> is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Subsection><MarginalNote>Notice to Provost Marshal General</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>If the Court Martial Appeal Court or other court makes an order that may be made under subsection 227.04(1) or 227.13(1), it shall cause the Provost Marshal General to be notified of the decision.</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Paragraph><Paragraph type="amending"><Label>(c)</Label><Text>subsections 240.5(6) and (7) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">National Defence Act</XRefExternal> are replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Subsection><MarginalNote>Requirements relating to notice</MarginalNote><Label>(6)</Label><Text>If the Court Martial Appeal Court or other court quashes an exemption order made under section 227.22, it shall cause the Provost Marshal General to be notified of the decision and shall cause the person who applied for the order to be informed of section 119.1 and sections 4 to 7.1 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Sex Offender Information Registration Act</XRefExternal>.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Notice — variation order</MarginalNote><Label>(7)</Label><Text>If the Court Martial Appeal Court or other court quashes a variation order made under section 227.23, it shall cause the Provost Marshal General to be notified of the decision.</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Paragraph></Section><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote>2015, c. 23</MarginalNote><Label>67</Label><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>In this section, <DefinedTermEn>other Act</DefinedTermEn> means the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Tougher Penalties for Child Predators Act</XRefExternal>, chapter 23 of the Statutes of Canada, 2015.</Text></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>If section 32 of the other Act comes into force before section <XRefInternal>10</XRefInternal> of this Act, then that section <XRefInternal>10</XRefInternal> is repealed.</Text></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(3)</Label><Text>If section <XRefInternal>10</XRefInternal> of this Act comes into force before section 32 of the other Act, then that section 32 is repealed.</Text></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(4)</Label><Text>If section 32 of the other Act comes into force on the same day as section <XRefInternal>10</XRefInternal> of this Act, then that section <XRefInternal>10</XRefInternal> is deemed never to have come into force and is repealed.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote>Bill C-291</MarginalNote><Label>68</Label><Text>If Bill C-291, introduced in the 1st session of the 44th Parliament and entitled <XRefExternal reference-type="act">An Act to amend the Criminal Code and to make consequential amendments to other Acts (child sexual abuse and exploitation material)</XRefExternal>, receives royal assent, then, on the first day on which both subsection 1(1) of that Act and section <XRefInternal>7</XRefInternal> of this Act are in force, subparagraph 70(d)(xi) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">National Defence Act</XRefExternal> is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(xi)</Label><Text>section 163.1 (child sexual abuse and exploitation material),</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Section><Heading level="1"><TitleText>Coming into Force</TitleText></Heading><Section type="CIF"><MarginalNote>Order in council</MarginalNote><Label>69</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Sections <XRefInternal>2</XRefInternal>, <XRefInternal>4</XRefInternal> to <XRefInternal>6</XRefInternal>, <XRefInternal>41</XRefInternal> to <XRefInternal>45</XRefInternal>, <XRefInternal>47</XRefInternal>, <XRefInternal>53</XRefInternal> and <XRefInternal>55</XRefInternal> come into force on a day to be fixed by order of the Governor in Council.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Order in council</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Sections <XRefInternal>3</XRefInternal>, <XRefInternal>15</XRefInternal> to <XRefInternal>17</XRefInternal>, <XRefInternal>40</XRefInternal> and <XRefInternal>54</XRefInternal> come into force on a day to be fixed by order of the Governor in Council.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>60th day after royal assent</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>Sections <XRefInternal>7</XRefInternal> and <XRefInternal>8</XRefInternal> come into force on the 60th day after the day on which this Act receives royal assent.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Order in council</MarginalNote><Label>(4)</Label><Text>Sections <XRefInternal>9</XRefInternal>, <XRefInternal>11</XRefInternal> to <XRefInternal>14</XRefInternal>, <XRefInternal>18</XRefInternal> and <XRefInternal>19</XRefInternal> come into force on a day or days to be fixed by order of the Governor in Council</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Order in council</MarginalNote><Label>(5)</Label><Text>Sections <XRefInternal>10</XRefInternal>, <XRefInternal>23</XRefInternal> to <XRefInternal>39</XRefInternal> and <XRefInternal>48</XRefInternal> to <XRefInternal>52</XRefInternal> come into force on a day to be fixed by order of the Governor in Council.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Order in council</MarginalNote><Label>(6)</Label><Text>Sections <XRefInternal>20</XRefInternal> to <XRefInternal>22</XRefInternal> and <XRefInternal>46</XRefInternal> come into force on a day to be fixed by order of the Governor in Council.</Text></Subsection></Section></Body></Bill>