<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!--Arbortext, Inc., 1988-2010, v.4002--><Bill bill-origin="senate" bill-type="govt-public" xml:lang="en"><Identification><BillNumber>S-14</BillNumber><Parliament><Session>1</Session><Number>44</Number><RegnalYear><Year-s>70-71</Year-s><Monarch>Elizabeth II 芒聙聯 1-2 Charles III</Monarch></RegnalYear><Year-s>2021-2022-2023</Year-s></Parliament><LongTitle>An Act to amend the Canada National Parks Act, the Canada National Marine Conservation Areas Act, the Rouge National Urban Park Act and the National Parks of Canada Fishing Regulations</LongTitle><ShortTitle status="official">Protecting Canada芒聙聶s Natural Wonders Act</ShortTitle><RunningHead>Protecting Canada芒聙聶s Natural Wonders Act</RunningHead><BillHistory><Stages stage="first-reading-senate"><Date><YYYY>2023</YYYY><MM>10</MM><DD>19</DD></Date></Stages></BillHistory><BillSponsor>THE HONOURABLE SENATOR GOLD, P.C</BillSponsor><BillRefNumber date-time="2023-10-12">91170</BillRefNumber></Identification><Introduction><Summary><TitleText>SUMMARY</TitleText><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>This enactment amends the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Canada National Parks Act</XRefExternal> to, among other things,</Text><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>broaden and clarify offences in relation to the discharge or deposit of substances in a national park or national park reserve;</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>expand the boundaries of seven national parks and one national park reserve;</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>(c)</Label><Text>establish the Akami-Uapishk谩碌聛芒聙聯KakKasuak芒聙聯Mealy Mountains National Park Reserve of Canada and enact provisions for its operation and administration; and</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>(d)</Label><Text>change the name of 芒聙聹Gwaii Haanas National Park Reserve of Canada芒聙聺 to 芒聙聹Gwaii Haanas National Park Reserve and Haida Heritage Site芒聙聺.</Text></Provision></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>The enactment also amends the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Canada National Marine Conservation Areas Act</XRefExternal> to establish the Tallurutiup Imanga National Marine Conservation Area and the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Rouge National Urban Park Act</XRefExternal> to broaden and clarify offences in relation to the discharge or deposit of substances in that Park and makes consequential amendments to the <XRefExternal reference-type="regulation">National Parks of Canada Fishing Regulations</XRefExternal>.</Text></Provision></Summary><TableOfProvisions label-column-width="2.5"><Heading level="1"><TitleText>TABLE OF PROVISIONS</TitleText></Heading><Heading level="1"><TitleText>An Act to amend the Canada National Parks Act, the Canada National Marine Conservation Areas Act, the Rouge National Urban Park Act and the National Parks of Canada Fishing Regulations</TitleText></Heading><Heading level="1"><TitleText>Short Title</TitleText></Heading><Label><Emphasis style="bold">1</Emphasis></Label><Text><XRefExternal reference-type="act">Protecting Canada芒聙聶s Natural Wonders Act</XRefExternal></Text><Label><Emphasis style="bold">2</Emphasis></Label><Text><XRefExternal reference-type="act">Canada National Parks Act</XRefExternal></Text><Label><Emphasis style="bold">18</Emphasis></Label><Text><XRefExternal reference-type="act">Canada National Marine Conservation Areas Act</XRefExternal></Text><Label><Emphasis style="bold">19</Emphasis></Label><Text><XRefExternal reference-type="act">Rouge National Urban Park Act</XRefExternal></Text><Label><Emphasis style="bold">22</Emphasis></Label><Text>Consequential Amendments to the <XRefExternal reference-type="regulation">National Parks of Canada Fishing Regulations</XRefExternal></Text><Heading level="1"><TitleText>Coordinating Amendments</TitleText></Heading><Label><Emphasis style="bold">23</Emphasis></Label><Text>2015, c. 38</Text><Heading level="1"><TitleText>Coming into Force</TitleText></Heading><Label><Emphasis style="bold">24</Emphasis></Label><Text>Akami-Uapishk谩碌聛芒聙聯KakKasuak芒聙聯Mealy Mountains National Park Reserve of Canada</Text><Label><Emphasis style="bold">25</Emphasis></Label><Text>Tallurutiup Imanga National Marine Conservation Area</Text><Heading level="5"><Label>SCHEDULE</Label></Heading></TableOfProvisions><Enacts><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>His Majesty, by and with the advice and consent of the Senate and House of Commons of Canada, enacts as follows:</Text></Provision></Enacts></Introduction><Body><Heading level="1"><TitleText>Short Title</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Short title</MarginalNote><Label>1</Label><Text>This Act may be cited as the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Protecting Canada芒聙聶s Natural Wonders Act</XRefExternal>.</Text></Section><Heading level="1"><MarginalNote><HistoricalNote>2000, c. 32</HistoricalNote></MarginalNote><TitleText>Canada National Parks Act</TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><Label>2</Label><Text>Paragraph 16(1)(t) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Canada National Parks Act</XRefExternal> is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(t)</Label><Text>the use, transportation and storage of pesticides and other toxic substances, <Ins>including products treated with or containing any of those substances</Ins>;</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText><ExplanatoryNote><Label><Emphasis style="italic">Clause 2</Emphasis>:</Label><ExplanatoryText>Relevant portion of subsection 16(1):</ExplanatoryText><ExistingText><Section><Label>16</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The Governor in Council may make regulations respecting</Text><Paragraph><Label>...</Label><Text>脗聽</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(t)</Label><Text>the use, transportation and temporary storage of pesticides and other toxic substances;</Text></Paragraph></Subsection></Section></ExistingText></ExplanatoryNote></Section><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote><HistoricalNote>2009, c. 14, s. 33</HistoricalNote></MarginalNote><Label>3</Label><Text>The portion of subsection 24(1) of the Act before paragraph (a) is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Section><MarginalNote>Offence</MarginalNote><Label>24</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Every person who contravenes section 13, subsection 32(1) <Ins>or (2)</Ins> or a provision of the regulations designated by regulations made under paragraph 16(1)(y) <Ins>or who fails to take measures that they are ordered to take under subsection 32(3)</Ins> is guilty of an offence and liable</Text></Subsection></Section></AmendedText><ExplanatoryNote><Label><Emphasis style="italic">Clause 3</Emphasis>:</Label><ExplanatoryText>Relevant portion of subsection 24(1):</ExplanatoryText><ExistingText><Section><Label>24</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Every person who contravenes section 13, subsection 32(1) or a provision of the regulations designated by regulations made under paragraph 16(1)(y) is guilty of an offence and liable</Text></Subsection></Section></ExistingText></ExplanatoryNote></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>4</Label><Text>Section 32 of the Act and the heading before it are replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Heading level="1"><TitleText><Ins>Discharge or Deposit of Substances</Ins></TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Protection of natural environment</MarginalNote><Label>32</Label><Subsection change="ins"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>It is prohibited to discharge or deposit a substance in a park if the discharge or deposit degrades the natural environment, injures fauna, flora or cultural resources, endangers human health or public safety or is likely to do any of those things.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Duty to notify and take measures</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text><Ins>If</Ins> the <Ins>discharge or deposit</Ins> of a <Ins>substance in a park degrades</Ins> the natural environment, <Ins>injures</Ins> fauna, flora or cultural resources, <Ins>endangers human health or public safety or is likely to do any of those things</Ins>, any person who has charge, management or control of the substance <Ins>and</Ins> any <Ins>person who caused or contributed to the discharge or deposit</Ins> shall</Text><Paragraph change="ins"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>notify the superintendent without delay; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph change="ins"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>take reasonable measures to prevent, mitigate or remediate harm and to prevent or minimize danger, as the case may be.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Powers of superintendent and Minister</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>If the superintendent of <Ins>the</Ins> park is of the opinion that a person is not taking the measures required by subsection <Ins>(2)(b)</Ins>, the superintendent may <Ins>order</Ins> the person to take those measures. If the person fails to <Ins>take the measures that they are ordered to take,</Ins> the Minister may <Ins>take the</Ins> measures on behalf of <Ins>His</Ins> Majesty in right of Canada.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Expenses of clean-up</MarginalNote><Label>(<Ins>4</Ins>)</Label><Text>A person who fails to <Ins>take the measures that they are ordered to take</Ins> is liable for the expenses reasonably incurred by <Ins>His</Ins> Majesty in right of Canada in taking the measures. Those expenses may be recovered from <Ins>the</Ins> person, with costs, in proceedings brought in the name of <Ins>His</Ins> Majesty in any court of competent jurisdiction.</Text></Subsection></Section></AmendedText><ExplanatoryNote><Label><Emphasis style="italic">Clause 4</Emphasis>:</Label><ExplanatoryText>Existing text of the heading and section 32:</ExplanatoryText><ExistingText><Heading level="1"><TitleText>Mitigation of Environmental Damage</TitleText></Heading><Section><Label>32</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Where a substance that is capable of degrading the natural environment, injuring fauna, flora or cultural resources or endangering human health is discharged or deposited in a park, any person who has charge, management or control of the substance shall take reasonable measures to prevent any degradation of the natural environment and any danger to the fauna, flora or cultural resources or to persons that may result from the discharge or deposit.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><Label>(2)</Label><Text>If the superintendent of a park is of the opinion that a person is not taking the measures required by subsection (1), the superintendent may direct the person to take those measures and, if the person fails to do so, the Minister may direct those measures to be taken on behalf of Her Majesty in right of Canada.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><Label>(3)</Label><Text>A person who fails to comply with a direction given by a superintendent under subsection (2) is liable for the expenses reasonably incurred by Her Majesty in right of Canada in taking the measures directed, and those expenses may be recovered from that person, with costs, in proceedings brought in the name of Her Majesty in any court of competent jurisdiction.</Text></Subsection></Section></ExistingText></ExplanatoryNote></Section><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote><HistoricalNote>2019, c. 29, s. 329</HistoricalNote></MarginalNote><Label>5</Label><Text>Section 39 of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Section><MarginalNote>Application of Act</MarginalNote><Label>39</Label><Text>Subject to sections 40 to <Ins>41.7</Ins>, this Act applies to a park reserve as if it were a park.</Text></Section></AmendedText><ExplanatoryNote><Label><Emphasis style="italic">Clause 5</Emphasis>:</Label><ExplanatoryText>Existing text of section 39:</ExplanatoryText><ExistingText><Section><Label>39</Label><Text>Subject to sections 40 to 41.5, this Act applies to a park reserve as if it were a park.</Text></Section></ExistingText></ExplanatoryNote></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>6</Label><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The Act is amended by adding the following after section 41.5:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Section change="ins"><MarginalNote>Akami-Uapishk谩碌聛芒聙聯KakKasuak芒聙聯Mealy Mountains National Park Reserve of Canada</MarginalNote><Label>41.6</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>For the purposes of subsections 5(1) and 6(2), leases, licences of occupation, easements, permits and other licences and authorizations relating to public lands in Akami-Uapishk谩碌聛芒聙聯KakKasuak芒聙聯Mealy Mountains National Park Reserve of Canada are deemed not to encumber or affect title to those lands, but if those lands become a park, those instruments continue in effect according to their terms and conditions.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Continuation of leases and licences of occupation</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Existing leases and licences of occupation in or on Akami-Uapishk谩碌聛芒聙聯KakKasuak芒聙聯Mealy Mountains National Park Reserve of Canada are continued under this Act in accordance with their terms and conditions, which prevail over this Act to the extent of any inconsistency between them.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Renewals 芒聙聰 leases and licences of occupation</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>Those leases and licences of occupation may be renewed in accordance with their terms and conditions. If a lease or licence of occupation does not provide for its renewal, then it may be renewed in accordance with this Act.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Leases or licences 芒聙聰 cabins</MarginalNote><Label>(4)</Label><Text>The Minister may enter into leases of public lands in Akami-Uapishk谩碌聛芒聙聯KakKasuak芒聙聯Mealy Mountains National Park Reserve of Canada for the personal use or occupation of cabins, or may issue licences for the personal use or occupation of cabins on those lands, and may renew or approve the assignment of those leases or licences.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Leases or licences 芒聙聰 tilts</MarginalNote><Label>(5)</Label><Text>The Minister may enter into leases of public lands in Akami-Uapishk谩碌聛芒聙聯KakKasuak芒聙聯Mealy Mountains National Park Reserve of Canada for the establishment or personal use or occupation of tilts, or may issue licences for the establishment, personal use or occupation of tilts on those lands, and may renew or approve the assignment of those leases or licences.</Text></Subsection><Subsection change="ins"><MarginalNote>Authorizations 芒聙聰 cabins or tilts</MarginalNote><Label>(6)</Label><Text>The superintendent of Akami-Uapishk谩碌聛芒聙聯KakKasuak芒聙聯Mealy Mountains National Park Reserve of Canada may authorize the personal use or occupation of cabins on public lands in the park reserve, or the establishment, personal use or occupation of tilts on those lands, and may renew or approve the assignment of those authorizations.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section change="ins"><MarginalNote>Activities 芒聙聰 Akami-Uapishk谩碌聛芒聙聯KakKasuak芒聙聯Mealy Mountains National Park Reserve</MarginalNote><Label>41.7</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>A traditional land user who has in their possession a document issued by the superintendent that confirms that status may, subject to the following requirements, conditions and restrictions, carry on a traditional activity on public lands in Akami-Uapishk谩碌聛芒聙聯KakKasuak芒聙聯Mealy Mountains National Park Reserve of Canada:</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>the requirements set out in or imposed under the provisions of this Act or the regulations, other than the provisions that do not apply in respect of that activity under subsection (3); and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>any conditions or restrictions imposed by the superintendent for the purposes of</Text><Subparagraph><Label>(i)</Label><Text>conservation, sustainable use or public health or safety, or</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph><Label>(ii)</Label><Text>implementing any provision of a land claims agreement that requires, directly or indirectly, that commercial trapping by all, or by a class of, traditional land users be prohibited or restricted.</Text></Subparagraph></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection change="ins"><MarginalNote>Obligation to issue document</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>If, on application, the superintendent is satisfied that an individual is a traditional land user, the superintendent must issue a document confirming that status. The superintendent may subsequently revoke the document if the superintendent determines that the individual is no longer, or never was, a traditional land user.</Text></Subsection><Subsection change="ins"><MarginalNote>Exemptions 芒聙聰 traditional activities</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>The following provisions do not apply in respect of the following traditional activities that are carried on under subsection (1):</Text><Paragraph change="ins"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>paragraph 3(1)(a) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="regulation">National Parks of Canada Fishing Regulations</XRefExternal> in respect of fishing, including ice fishing;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph change="ins"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>paragraph 41(1)(a) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="regulation">National Parks Highway Traffic Regulations</XRefExternal> in respect of the use of over-snow vehicles to access cabins or carry on other traditional activities;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph change="ins"><Label>(c)</Label><Text>section 10 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="regulation">National Parks General Regulations</XRefExternal> in respect of berry picking, the gathering of medicinal plants and the cutting of wood for personal use;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph change="ins"><Label>(d)</Label><Text>section 21 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="regulation">National Parks General Regulations</XRefExternal> in respect of motor boating;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph change="ins"><Label>(e)</Label><Text>section 3 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="regulation">National Parks of Canada Camping Regulations</XRefExternal> in respect of camping;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph change="ins"><Label>(f)</Label><Text>subsection 4(1) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="regulation">National Parks of Canada Fire Protection Regulations</XRefExternal> in respect of the use of fires to heat food or beverages;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph change="ins"><Label>(g)</Label><Text>paragraphs 4(1)(a) and (c) and section 19 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="regulation">National Parks Wildlife Regulations</XRefExternal> in respect of the hunting of ducks, geese, ptarmigan, grouse and porcupine, trapping, including for commercial purposes, and the snaring of snowshoe hare and ptarmigan;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph change="ins"><Label>(h)</Label><Text>subsections 20(1), (5) and (6) and paragraph 21(b) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="regulation">National Parks Wildlife Regulations</XRefExternal> in respect of the hunting of ducks, geese, ptarmigan, grouse and porcupine, trapping, including for commercial purposes, and the transport and use of firearms for personal safety, hunting and trapping; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph change="ins"><Label>(i)</Label><Text>subsection 20(5) and paragraph 21(b) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="regulation">National Parks Wildlife Regulations</XRefExternal> in respect of the snaring of snowshoe hare and ptarmigan.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Inuit harvesting activities</MarginalNote><Label>(4)</Label><Text>Despite any other provision of this Act or the regulations, Inuit referred to in section 12.13.10 of the Agreement may carry on the harvesting activities permitted by that section, in the portion of Akami-Uapishk谩碌聛芒聙聯KakKasuak芒聙聯Mealy Mountains National Park Reserve of Canada that overlaps the area set out in the Map Atlas referred to in that section, if those activities are carried on in accordance with the Agreement and the laws of Newfoundland and Labrador, including the orders and regulations referred to in paragraph 1 of schedule 12-F to the Agreement.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Application of provincial laws</MarginalNote><Label>(5)</Label><Text>The laws of Newfoundland and Labrador apply to Inuit referred to in subsection (4), with respect to the harvesting activities referred to in that subsection that are carried on in the portion of Akami-Uapishk谩碌聛芒聙聯KakKasuak芒聙聯Mealy Mountains National Park Reserve of Canada referred to in that subsection, if the effect of those laws is to implement schedule 12-F to the Agreement.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Exception</MarginalNote><Label>(6)</Label><Text>Subsection (5) does not apply in respect of Inuit referred to in subsection (4) who are carrying on traditional activities under subsection (1).</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Aircraft access</MarginalNote><Label>(7)</Label><Text>Despite any other provision of this Act or the regulations, a person may conduct a take-off or landing of an <DefinitionRef>aircraft</DefinitionRef>, as defined in subsection 3(1) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Aeronautics Act</XRefExternal>, on public lands in Akami-Uapishk谩碌聛芒聙聯KakKasuak芒聙聯Mealy Mountains National Park Reserve of Canada if they conduct it in accordance with an authorization provided by the superintendent.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Considerations 芒聙聰 authorizations</MarginalNote><Label>(8)</Label><Text>The superintendent must have regard to considerations of public health and safety and the sustainable use and conservation of Akami-Uapishk谩碌聛芒聙聯KakKasuak芒聙聯Mealy Mountains National Park Reserve of Canada when authorizing a take-off or landing.</Text></Subsection><Subsection change="ins"><MarginalNote>Fishing</MarginalNote><Label>(9)</Label><Text>In the <XRefExternal reference-type="regulation">National Parks of Canada Fishing Regulations</XRefExternal>,</Text><Paragraph change="ins"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>any reference to Gros Morne National Park of Canada, except in Schedules IV and V to those Regulations, is deemed to include a reference to Akami-Uapishk谩碌聛芒聙聯KakKasuak芒聙聯Mealy Mountains National Park Reserve of Canada;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph change="ins"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>the text set out in item 48, column 1, of Schedule II to those Regulations is deemed to include a reference to the waters referred to in Schedule I to the <XRefExternal reference-type="regulation">Newfoundland and Labrador Fishery Regulations</XRefExternal> that are wholly or partially located in Akami-Uapishk谩碌聛芒聙聯KakKasuak芒聙聯Mealy Mountains National Park Reserve of Canada and the open season for those waters is, despite the text set out in column III, deemed to be June 15 to September 15;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph change="ins"><Label>(c)</Label><Text>the open season for all other waters that are located in Akami-Uapishk谩碌聛芒聙聯KakKasuak芒聙聯Mealy Mountains National Park Reserve of Canada is, despite the text set out in item 49, column III, of Schedule II to those Regulations, deemed to be February 1 to September 15; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph change="ins"><Label>(d)</Label><Text>items 1 and 2, column II, of Schedule V to those Regulations are deemed to include a reference to the waters referred to in Schedule I to the <XRefExternal reference-type="regulation">Newfoundland and Labrador Fishery Regulations</XRefExternal> that are wholly or partially located in Akami-Uapishk谩碌聛芒聙聯KakKasuak芒聙聯Mealy Mountains National Park Reserve of Canada.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Definitions</MarginalNote><Label>(10)</Label><Text>The following definitions apply in this section.</Text><Definition><Text><DefinedTermEn>Agreement</DefinedTermEn>芒聙聜means the land claims agreement signed on behalf of Inuit of Labrador, Her Majesty the Queen in right of Newfoundland and Labrador and Her Majesty the Queen in right of Canada on January 22, 2005, including any amendments made to it.芒聙聜(<DefinedTermFr>Accord</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Definition><Definition><Text><DefinedTermEn>common-law partner</DefinedTermEn>, in relation to an individual, means another individual who has been cohabiting with the individual in a conjugal relationship for at least one year.芒聙聜(<DefinedTermFr>conjoint de fait</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Definition><Definition><Text><DefinedTermEn>designated area</DefinedTermEn>芒聙聜means the public lands located in Akami-Uapishk谩碌聛芒聙聯KakKasuak芒聙聯Mealy Mountains National Park Reserve of Canada, all lands within a 50 km wide perimeter surrounding the park reserve and the community of Happy Valley-Goose Bay.芒聙聜(<DefinedTermFr>zone d脙漏sign脙漏e</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Definition><Definition><Text><DefinedTermEn>superintendent</DefinedTermEn>芒聙聜means the superintendent of Akami-Uapishk谩碌聛芒聙聯KakKasuak芒聙聯Mealy Mountains National Park Reserve of Canada.芒聙聜(<DefinedTermFr>directeur</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Definition><Definition><Text><DefinedTermEn>traditional activity</DefinedTermEn>芒聙聜means any of the following activities:</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>the use of an <DefinitionRef>over-snow vehicle</DefinitionRef>, as defined in section 2 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="regulation">National Parks Highway Traffic Regulations</XRefExternal>, to access cabins or carry on other traditional activities;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>fishing, including ice fishing;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(c)</Label><Text>berry picking;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(d)</Label><Text>motor boating;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(e)</Label><Text>the gathering of medicinal plants;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(f)</Label><Text>the use of fires to heat food or beverages;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(g)</Label><Text>the hunting of ducks, geese, ptarmigan, grouse and porcupine;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(h)</Label><Text>trapping, including for commercial purposes;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(i)</Label><Text>the snaring of snowshoe hare and ptarmigan;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(j)</Label><Text>the transport and use of firearms and ammunition for personal safety, hunting and trapping;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(k)</Label><Text>the cutting of wood for personal use; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(l)</Label><Text>camping.芒聙聜(<DefinedTermFr>activit脙漏 traditionnelle</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Paragraph></Definition><Definition><Text><DefinedTermEn>traditional land user</DefinedTermEn>芒聙聜means </Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>a <DefinitionRef>beneficiary</DefinitionRef>, as defined in section 1.1.1 of the Agreement;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>an individual who is a member of NunatuKavut Community Council Inc., a corporation without share capital incorporated under the laws of Newfoundland and Labrador;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(c)</Label><Text>an individual who was born in the designated area;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(d)</Label><Text>an individual who was born to a biological parent who, at the time of the individual芒聙聶s birth, was ordinarily resident in the designated area;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(e)</Label><Text>an individual who was legally adopted by a parent who, at the time the adoption took effect, was ordinarily resident in the designated area;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(f)</Label><Text>an individual who was or has been ordinarily resident in the designated area for at least 10 consecutive years; or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(g)</Label><Text>a child, spouse or common-law partner of an individual described in any of paragraphs (a) to (f).芒聙聜(<DefinedTermFr>utilisateur traditionnel des terres</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Paragraph></Definition></Subsection></Section><Section change="ins"><MarginalNote>Application to park</MarginalNote><Label>41.8</Label><Text>Sections 41.6 and 41.7 continue to apply, with any adaptations that may be necessary, to any public lands in Akami-Uapishk谩碌聛芒聙聯KakKasuak芒聙聯Mealy Mountains National Park Reserve of Canada that become a park.</Text></Section></AmendedText><ExplanatoryNote><Label><Emphasis style="italic">Clause 6</Emphasis>: (1)</Label><ExplanatoryText>New.</ExplanatoryText></ExplanatoryNote></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Subsections 41.7(7) and (8) of the Act are repealed.</Text></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(3)</Label><Text>Subsection 41.7(9) of the Act is repealed.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>7</Label><Text>The description of Grasslands National Park of Canada in Part 3 of Schedule 1 to the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text>In the Province of Saskatchewan, all those lands more particularly described as:</Text></Provision><Group><GroupHeading format-ref="group3-subdivision"><TitleText>East Block</TitleText></GroupHeading><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text>The Northwest and Southwest Quarters of Section 6, the Northwest and Southwest Quarters of Section 7, a portion of the Northeast Quarter of Section 7, being Parcel A shown on Plan No. 111566 in the Canada Lands Surveys Records and No. 101933467 in the Saskatchewan Land Surveys Directory, Legal Subdivisions 12 &amp; 13 of Section 17, Sections 18, 19, a portion of the West half of Section 20, being Parcel A shown on Plan No. 83810 in the Canada Lands Surveys Records and No. 00MJ06487 in the Saskatchewan Land Surveys Directory, Legal Subdivisions 4 &amp; 5 of Section 29 and Sections 30 and 31, all in Township 1, Range 4, West of the Third Meridian as shown on Plan No. 73407 in the Canada Lands Surveys Records;</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text>Sections 1, 2, 11 to 15, the Northeast Quarter of Section 16, the Northeast and Southeast Quarters of Section 21, Sections 22 to 27, the Northeast and Southeast Quarters of Section 28 and Section 36, all in Township 1, Range 5, West of the Third Meridian as shown on Plan No. 73409 in the Canada Lands Surveys Records;</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text>Sections 1 to 36, all in Township 1, Range 6, West of the Third Meridian as shown on Plan No. 73410 in the Canada Lands Surveys Records;</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text>Sections 1, 12, 13, 24, 25 and 36, all in Township 1, Range 7, West of the Third Meridian as shown on Plan No. 73411 in the Canada Lands Surveys Records;</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text>The Southwest Quarter of Section 5, the Southeast and Southwest Quarters of Section 6 and the Northwest and Southwest Quarters of Section 18, all in Township 2, Range 4, West of the Third Meridian as shown on Plan No. 73408 in the Canada Lands Surveys Records;</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text>The Southeast and Southwest Quarters of Section 2, the Southeast and Southwest Quarters of Section 3, Sections 4 to 9 and 13 to 15, all in Township 2, Range 5, West of the Third Meridian as shown on Plan No. 94784 in the Canada Lands Surveys Records;</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text>Sections 1, 2, the Southeast and Southwest Quarters of Section 3, Sections 4 to 9, the Northwest and Northeast Quarters of Section 14, Sections 18, 19, the Northeast, Southeast and Southwest Quarters of Section 23 and Sections 30 to 33, all in Township 2, Range 6, West of the Third Meridian as shown on Plan No. 94827 in the Canada Lands Surveys Records;</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text>Sections 1, 12, 13, 24, 25, 36, all in Township 2, Range 7, West of the Third Meridian as shown on Plan No. 95040 in the Canada Lands Surveys Records;</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text>The Northeast Quarter of Section 3, Section 5 and Sections 8 to 11, all in Township 3, Range 6, West of the Third Meridian as shown on Plan No. 94828 in the Canada Lands Surveys Records; and</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text>All interior Statutory Road Allowances, intervening within the above lands:</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text>Excepting the North-South statutory road allowance (surface) immediately adjacent to the West boundary of Section 6, Township 2, Range 5, West of the Third Meridian; and</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text>Excepting the East-West statutory road allowance (surface) immediately adjacent to the South boundary of Section 5, Township 3, Range 6, West of the Third Meridian.</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text>All beds of bodies of water traversing the above lands.</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text>All lands described above include mines and minerals.</Text></Provision></Group><Group><GroupHeading format-ref="group3-subdivision"><TitleText>West Block</TitleText></GroupHeading><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text>Section 31 in Township 1, Range 9, West of the Third Meridian as shown on Plan No. 111593 in the Canada Lands Surveys Records;</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text>Sections 1 to 23, the Southwest, Northeast and Northwest Quarters of Section 24 and Sections 25 to 36, all in Township 1, Range 10, West of the Third Meridian as shown on Plan No. 73412 in the Canada Lands Surveys Records;</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text>Sections 1, 2, 11 to 16, the Northeast and Northwest Quarters of Section 17, Sections 20 to 29 and 32 to 36, all in Township 1, Range 11, West of the Third Meridian as shown on Plan No. 73414 in the Canada Lands Surveys Records;</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text>Sections 6, 7, 18, 19, 30 and the Southeast and Southwest Quarters of Section 31, all in Township 2, Range 9, West of the Third Meridian as shown on Plan No. 94515 in the Canada Lands Surveys Records;</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text>Sections 1 to 24 and the Northeast and Southeast Quarters of Section 25, all in Township 2, Range 10, West of the Third Meridian as shown on Plan No. 73413 in the Canada Lands Surveys Records;</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text>Sections 1 to 24, the Southwest and Northwest Quarters of Section 25, Sections 26 to 35 and the Southwest and Northwest Quarters of Section 36, all in Township 2, Range 11, West of the Third Meridian as shown on Plan No. 73415 in the Canada Lands Surveys Records;</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text>The Northeast and Northwest Quarters of Section 1, the Northeast Quarter of Section 2, the Northeast Quarter of Section 9, the Northeast and Northwest Quarters of Section 10, Sections 11 to 15, the Northeast and Southeast Quarters of Section 16, the Northeast and Northwest Quarters of Section 18 and Sections 19 to 36, all in Township 2, Range 12, West of the Third Meridian as shown on Plan No. 97665 in the Canada Lands Surveys Records;</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text>Section 13, the Northeast and Northwest Quarters of Section 23, Sections 24 to 26, Section 28, the Northeast, Southeast and Northwest Quarters of Section 32 and Sections 33 to 36, all in Township 2, Range 13, West of the Third Meridian as shown on Plan No. 97414 in the Canada Lands Surveys Records:</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text>Excepting out of the Northwest Quarter of Section 32 and the Southeast and Southwest Quarters of Section 13 the road right-of-way (surface) shown on Plan No. 87805 in the Canada Lands Surveys Records and No. 91SC00331 in the Saskatchewan Land Surveys Directory;</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text>The Southwest Quarter of Section 3, Sections 4 to 9, the Southeast and Southwest Quarters of Section 16, the Southeast and Southwest Quarters of Section 17 and Section 18, all in Township 3, Range 11, West of the Third Meridian as shown on Plan No. 95890 in the Canada Lands Surveys Records;</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text>Sections 1 to 18, all in Township 3, Range 12, West of the Third Meridian as shown on Plan No. 97667 in the Canada Lands Surveys Records;</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text>Sections 1 to 5, the Southeast Quarter of Section 8, the Southeast and Southwest Quarters of Section 9 and Sections 11 to 14, all in Township 3, Range 13, West of the Third Meridian as shown on Plan No. 97416 in the Canada Lands Surveys Records</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text>Excepting out of the Northeast Quarter of Section 4, Parcel A (surface and subsurface) shown on Plan No. 101705981 in the Saskatchewan Land Surveys Directory; and</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text>Excepting out of the Southwest and Northwest Quarters of Section 5 the road right-of-way (surface) shown on Plan No. 87808 in the Canada Lands Surveys Records and No. 71SC08602 in the Saskatchewan Land Surveys Directory; and</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text>All interior Statutory Road Allowances, intervening within the above lands.</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text>All beds of bodies of water traversing the above lands.</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text>All lands described above include mines and minerals.</Text></Provision></Group></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>8</Label><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The portion of the description of Riding Mountain National Park of Canada in Part 4 of Schedule 1 to the Act that begins with 芒聙聹(b) sections 25, 26, 27芒聙聺 and ends with 芒聙聹subdivisions 13, 14, 15 and 16 of Section 27;芒聙聺 is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>the northwest quarter of Section 22;</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>(c)</Label><Text>The northeast, southeast, southwest quarters, and south half of the northwest quarter Section 28;</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>(d)</Label><Text>sections 25, 26, 27, legal subdivisions 13 and 14 of Section 28, sections 29 to 36 inclusive;</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>(e)</Label><Text>all that portion of the original Dominion Government Road Allowance adjoining the north boundary of Section 19, described as follows: commencing at a point on the north boundary of Section 19, a distance of 34 feet (10.36 metres) easterly from the northwest corner of Section 19; thence easterly along said north boundary 400 feet (121.92 metres); thence northerly at right angles with said north boundary 66 feet (20.12 metres) to the northerly limit of said original Dominion Government Road Allowance; thence westerly along the northerly limit of said road allowance 382 feet (116.43 metres); thence southwesterly in a straight line to the point of commencement;</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>(f)</Label><Text>all that portion of the original Dominion Government Road Allowance between sections 29 and 30, lying north of the westerly production of the south boundary of southwest quarter Section 29;</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>(g)</Label><Text>all that portion of the original Dominion Government Road Allowance between sections 31 and 32, lying south of the southerly shoreline of Clear Lake;</Text><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text>the last two mentioned road allowances are as shown on Plan 30750 in said records;</Text></Provision></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>(6)</Label><Text>in Township 19, Range 19:</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>sections 25, 26, 34, 35 and 36, the east half of Section 33, the northeast quarter of Section 24 and legal subdivisions 13, 14, 15 and 16 of Section 27;</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>the northwest quarter of Section 24;</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>(c)</Label><Text>legal subdivisions 1 and 8, and the east half of legal subdivision 2 in Section 23;</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>(d)</Label><Text>legal subdivision 9, east half of legal subdivision 10, south half of legal subdivisions 15 and 16, and the north half of the east half of legal subdivision 16 in Section 23;</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>(e)</Label><Text>the southeast and southwest quarters, the south half of the northeast quarter, and legal subdivisions 11 and 12 in Section 27;</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>(f)</Label><Text>the northwest quarter and the west half of the northeast quarter of Section 14;</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>(g)</Label><Text>legal subdivision 4 and the west half of legal subdivision 5 in Section 23;</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>(h)</Label><Text>Parcels A and B, as shown on Plan 30230 in the west half of Section 33, filed in the Land Titles Office at Neepawa, a copy of which is recorded in the Canada Lands Surveys Records at Ottawa as 75834, excepting out of Parcel A all that portion taken for a public road as shown on Plan 40477, registered in said Land Titles Office, and as Plan 111596 in said records;</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>(i)</Label><Text>the northwest and southwest quarters of Section 28, excepting out of said quarters firstly: all that portion taken for a public road as shown on Plan 5110, registered in the Land Titles Office at Neepawa, a copy of which is recorded in the Canada Lands Surveys Records at Ottawa as 111598, and secondly: the easterly 9.912 metres of the westerly 14.941 metres;</Text></Provision></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><MarginalNote><HistoricalNote>SOR/2003芒聙聯345, s. 1(2)</HistoricalNote></MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The last paragraph of the description of Riding Mountain National Park of Canada in Part 4 of Schedule 1 to the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text>Said lands containing together about 2 980 square kilometres.</Text></Provision></AmendedText></Subsection></Section><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote><HistoricalNote>SOR/2022芒聙聯244, s. 1(1)</HistoricalNote></MarginalNote><Label>9</Label><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The first, second and third paragraphs of the description of Thousand Islands National Park of Canada in Part 5 of Schedule 1 to the Act are replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text>In the Province of Ontario, Municipalities of the Township of Leeds and the Thousand Islands, and the Township of Front of Yonge, and the City of Brockville, County of Leeds and Grenville, more particularly described as follows:</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text>All those parcels of land being more particularly described under Firstly to Twenty-ninthly as follows:</Text></Provision></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The portion of the description of Thousand Islands National Park of Canada in Part 5 of Schedule 1 to the French version of the Act that begins with 芒聙聹Neuvi脙篓mement芒聙聺 and ends with 芒聙聹ladite partie refermant environ 0,40 hectare芒聙聺 is amended by replacing 芒聙聹concession de Broken Front芒聙聺 with 芒聙聹interrompue en front芒聙聺.</Text></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><MarginalNote><HistoricalNote>SOR/2022芒聙聯244, s. 1(2)</HistoricalNote></MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>The last paragraph of the description of Thousand Islands National Park of Canada in Part 5 of Schedule 1 to the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text>Twenty-thirdly</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text>Parcel 1, Plan 108349 in the Canada Lands Surveys Records at Ottawa, being part of the road allowance between Lots 12 and 13, Broken Front Concession and part of the road allowance between Lots 12 and 13 Concession 1, Geographic Township of Yonge, containing about 1.04 hectares.</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text>Twenty-fourthly</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text>Parcel 1, Plan 108347 in the Canada Lands Surveys Records, being part of the road allowance between Lots 18 and 19, Broken Front Concession Geographic Township of Yonge, containing about 0.717 hectares.</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text>Twenty-fifthly</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text>Parcel 1, Plan 108350 in the Canada Lands Surveys Records, being part of the road allowance between Lots 6 and 7, Concession 1, Geographic Township of Yonge, containing about 1.16 hectares.</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text>Twenty-sixthly</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text>Parcel 1, Plan 108348 in the Canada Lands Surveys Records, being part of Lot 15, Broken Front Concession, Geographic Township of Yonge, containing about 0.470 hectares.</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text>Twenty-seventhly</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text>Parcel 1, Plan 108346 in the Canada Lands Surveys Records, being part of Lot 25, Broken Front Concession Geographic Township of Yonge, containing about 0.493 hectares.</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text>Twenty-eighthly</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text>Parcel 2, Plan 109998 in the Canada Lands Surveys Records, being part of Lot 8, Concession 1 Geographic Township of Lansdowne, containing about 28.6 hectares.</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text>Twenty-ninthly</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text>Victoria Island, Plan 2220 in the Canada Lands Surveys Records, lying and being in the St. Lawrence River, opposite Lot 15 in the first Concession Geographic Township of Elizabethtown, containing about 0.202 hectares.</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text>The whole from Firstly to Twenty-ninthly containing about 1 888.831 hectares (18.888 square kilometres).</Text></Provision></AmendedText></Subsection></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>10</Label><Text>The description of Point Pelee National Park of Canada in Part 5 of Schedule 1 to the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text>In the Province of Ontario, County of Essex, Geographic Township of Mersea and the Municipality of the Township of Pelee;</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text>All those parcels of land being more particularly described under Firstly and Secondly as follows:</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text>Firstly</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text>All that parcel of land known as Point Pelee, and being comprised of the Naval Reserve at said Point Pelee as shown on a plan of said Naval Reserve, signed by Alexander Baird, Provincial Land Surveyor, at Leamington on February 17, 1883, a copy of which is recorded in the Canada Lands Surveys Records at Ottawa as Plan 52325;</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text>Said parcel containing about 1 500 hectares.</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text>Secondly</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text>All that parcel of land being Middle Island in Lake Erie;</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text>Said parcel containing about 20 hectares.</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text>Said parcels described under Firstly and Secondly containing together about 1 520 hectares.</Text></Provision></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>11</Label><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The first paragraph of the description of Prince Edward Island National Park of Canada in Part 9 of Schedule 1 to the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text>All those parcels along the northerly coast of Prince Edward Island, described as follows:</Text></Provision></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The last paragraph of the description of Prince Edward Island National Park of Canada in Part 9 of Schedule 1 to the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text>All that lot, piece, or parcel of land, and lands covered by water, situate, lying and being at Greenwich, partly in the Township 40, in the County of Kings, in the Province of Prince Edward Island and more particularly described as follows:</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text>Parcel 11 as shown on 芒聙聹Compiled Plan of Parcels 11, 12, 13, 15, 16, 17, 18, and 19, Lands of Her Majesty the Queen in Right of Canada, Greenwich, County of Kings, Province of Prince Edward Island芒聙聺 prepared by David R.J. Morris, C.L.S., signed June 14, 2017. The said plan was recorded in the Canada Lands Surveys Records (CLSR) at Ottawa, Ontario on June 26, 2017, under number 106359 CLSR, said Parcel 11 containing 328.1 hectares, more or less.</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text>All those lots, pieces, or parcels of land, and lands covered by water, situate, lying and being at Greenwich, entirely in the Township 40, in the County of Kings, in the Province of Prince Edward Island and more particularly described as follows:</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text>The following parcels are all as shown on 芒聙聹Compiled Plan of Parcels 11, 12, 13, 15, 16, 17, 18, and 19, Lands of Her Majesty the Queen in Right of Canada, Greenwich, County of Kings, Province of Prince Edward Island芒聙聺 prepared by David R.J. Morris, C.L.S., signed June 14, 2017. The said plan was recorded in the Canada Lands Surveys Records (CLSR) at Ottawa, Ontario on June 26, 2017, under number 106359 CLSR.</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text>Parcel 12 containing 24.4 hectares, more or less.</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text>Parcel 13 containing 196.7 hectares, more or less. Said Parcel 13 being subject to a 12.19 metre (40 foot) wide right-of-way granted to St. Peter芒聙聶s Estates Ltd. by deed made August 15, 1995, between the Government of Prince Edward Island (Grantor) and St. Peter芒聙聶s Estates Ltd. (Grantee) and registered on August 15, 1995, in the Office of the Registrar of Deeds for Kings County at Charlottetown, Prince Edward Island in Book 312 at Page 50. Said right-of-way containing 8 383 square metres, more or less and shown on said Plan 106359 CLSR.</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text>Parcel 15 containing 34.5 hectares, more or less.</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text>Parcel 16 containing 3.4 hectares, more or less.</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text>Parcel 17 containing 1.3 hectares, more or less.</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text>Parcel 18 containing 0.35 hectares, more or less.</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text>Parcel 19 containing 0.25 hectares, more or less.</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text>Said parcels containing together about 2 738.8 hectares (27.39 square kilometres).</Text></Provision></AmendedText></Subsection></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>12</Label><Text>The description of Tuktut Nogait National Park of Canada in Part 12 of Schedule 1 to the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text>In the Northwest Territories;</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text>In the Inuvialuit Settlement Region and Sahtu Settlement Area;</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text>All geographic coordinates are North American Datum of 1927:</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>1)</Label><Text>Commencing at a point of intersection of the southerly boundary of the Inuvialuit Settlement Region with the easterly boundary of the Sahtu Settlement Area, as that boundary is defined in Appendix A, Volume 1 of the Sahtu Dene and Metis Comprehensive Land Claim Agreement, said point being at latitude 68脗掳00芒聙虏00芒聙鲁 north and longitude 120脗掳40芒聙虏51芒聙鲁 west;</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>2)</Label><Text>Thence southeasterly along the boundary of the said Sahtu Settlement Area to its intersection with latitude 67脗掳45芒聙虏00芒聙鲁 north at approximate longitude 119脗掳42芒聙虏39芒聙鲁 west;</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>3)</Label><Text>Thence west along the parallel of said latitude to a point at latitude 67脗掳45芒聙虏00芒聙鲁 north and longitude 121脗掳27芒聙虏00芒聙鲁 west;</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>4)</Label><Text>Thence northwesterly along a geodesic line to a point at latitude 68脗掳00芒聙虏00芒聙鲁 north and longitude 122脗掳05芒聙虏00芒聙鲁 west, said point being on the southerly boundary of the Inuvialuit Settlement Region;</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>5)</Label><Text>Thence northwesterly in a straight line to a point having a latitude of 68脗掳30芒聙虏00芒聙鲁 north and longitude 123脗掳20芒聙虏00芒聙鲁 west;</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>6)</Label><Text>Thence north along longitude 123脗掳20芒聙虏00芒聙鲁 west to its intersection with the surveyed boundary of the Paulatuk 7(1)(b) lands at approximate latitude 69脗掳00芒聙虏00芒聙鲁 north;</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>7)</Label><Text>Thence easterly along the surveyed boundary of said Paulatuk lands to the surveyed corner at approximate latitude 69脗掳00芒聙虏00芒聙鲁 north and approximate longitude 123脗掳10芒聙虏00芒聙鲁 west;</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>8)</Label><Text>Thence northerly along the surveyed boundary of the Paulatuk 7(1)(b) and 7(1)(a) lands to the surveyed corner of the Paulatuk 7(1)(b) lands at approximate latitude 69脗掳19芒聙虏00芒聙鲁 north and approximate longitude 123脗掳10芒聙虏00芒聙鲁 west;</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>9)</Label><Text>Thence easterly, northerly, northeasterly, easterly and southeasterly along the surveyed boundary of the Paulatuk 7(1)(b) lands to its intersection with the middle thread of the Outwash River at approximate latitude 69脗掳27芒聙虏46芒聙鲁 north and approximate longitude 120脗掳51芒聙虏51芒聙鲁 west;</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>10)</Label><Text>Thence northerly and easterly along the middle thread of the Outwash River to its intersection with the shoreline of Amundsen Gulf and the mouth of the Outwash River at an approximate longitude 120脗掳40芒聙虏51芒聙鲁 west, being a corner of the Inuvialuit Settlement Region as described in Annex A-1 of the Agreement referred to in the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Western Arctic (Inuvialuit) Claims Settlement Act</XRefExternal> (S.C. 1984, c. 24);</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>11)</Label><Text>Thence generally southerly, following the limit of the said Inuvialuit Settlement Region to the point of commencement.</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text>Said parcel containing an area of approximately 18 180 square kilometres.</Text></Provision></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote><HistoricalNote>2017, c. 26, s. 38(F)</HistoricalNote></MarginalNote><Label>13</Label><Text>The description of Quttinirpaaq National Park of Canada in Part 13 of Schedule 1 to the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text>The geographic coordinates below refer to the North American Datum of 1927;</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text>In Nunavut;</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text>On Ellesmere Island;</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text>All topographic features being according to the Gazetteer of Canada (Northwest Territories) First Edition, Ottawa 1980 and to National Topographic Series Maps, (120 C&amp;D Lady Franklin Bay), (120 E Robeson Channel), (120 F&amp;G Clements Markham Inlet), (340 E&amp;H M芒聙聶Clintock Inlet) and (340 D Tanquary Fiord) produced at a scale of 1:250,000 by the Department of Energy, Mines and Resources at Ottawa;</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text>All that part of said Ellesmere Island, including a part of the Arctic Ocean, the bays, the fiords, Discovery Harbour, the inlets, the rivers, the lakes, the islands and all the streams that lie within the boundaries which may be more particularly described as follows:</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text>Commencing at the summit of Mount Thompson located at approximate latitude 81脗掳15芒聙虏 north and approximate longitude 76脗掳57芒聙虏 west;</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text>Thence southeasterly to the summit of Mount Koch at approximate latitude 81脗掳11芒聙虏 north and approximate longitude 75脗掳20芒聙虏 west;</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text>Thence easterly to the summit of Mount Neville at approximate latitude 81脗掳10芒聙虏 north and approximate longitude 70脗掳33芒聙虏 west;</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text>Thence easterly to a point on the ordinary low water mark of Beatrix Bay at the mouth of an unnamed stream that flows into Beatrix Bay at approximate latitude 81脗掳11芒聙虏 north and approximate longitude 70脗掳12芒聙虏 west;</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text>Thence generally northeasterly following the ordinary low water mark along the north side of Beatrix Bay and Archer Fiord to the most easterly point of the promontory on the southwest side of Simmons Bay at approximate latitude 81脗掳14芒聙虏 north and approximate longitude 69脗掳18芒聙虏 west;</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text>Thence northeasterly across Simmons Bay to the most southerly point on the ordinary low water mark on the north side of Archer Fiord at approximate latitude 81脗掳15芒聙虏 north and approximate longitude 69脗掳09芒聙虏 west;</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text>Thence generally northeasterly following the ordinary low water mark along the northern side of Archer Fiord to its most northeasterly point at Keppel Head at approximate latitude 81脗掳31芒聙虏 north and approximate longitude 66脗掳37芒聙虏 west;</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text>Thence northeasterly across Lady Franklin Bay to the most southerly point on the ordinary low water mark at Distant Cape at approximate latitude 81脗掳43芒聙虏 north and approximate longitude 64脗掳27芒聙虏 west;</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text>Thence generally northeasterly following the ordinary low water mark along Watercourse Bay on the northern side of Robeson Channel to its most easterly point at Cape Murchison at approximate latitude 81脗掳46芒聙虏 north and approximate longitude 64脗掳06芒聙虏 west;</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text>Thence northeasterly across St. Patrick Bay to the most southerly point on the ordinary low water mark near Cartmel Point at approximate latitude 81脗掳47芒聙虏 north and approximate longitude 64脗掳02芒聙虏 west;</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text>Thence generally northeasterly following the ordinary low water mark along the northern side of Robeson Channel to a point at the entrance of Wrangel Bay at approximate latitude 81脗掳58芒聙虏30芒聙鲁 north and approximate longitude 62脗掳32芒聙虏 west;</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text>Thence northwesterly to a point at latitude 82脗掳03芒聙虏00芒聙鲁 north and longitude 63脗掳01芒聙虏00芒聙鲁 west being approximately 990.5 metres on an approximate azimuth of 231脗掳14芒聙虏31芒聙鲁 from an unnamed peak having an elevation of about 655 metres at approximate latitude 82脗掳03芒聙虏 north and approximate longitude 62脗掳58芒聙虏 west;</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text>Thence northwesterly to an unnamed peak having an elevation of about 732 metres at approximate latitude 82脗掳09芒聙虏 north and approximate longitude 63脗掳35芒聙虏 west;</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text>Thence northwesterly to the summit of Mount Eugene at approximate latitude 82脗掳25芒聙虏 north and approximate longitude 66脗掳47芒聙虏 west;</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text>Thence northwesterly to a point on the ordinary low water mark on the south side of Clements Markham Inlet at longitude 68脗掳00芒聙虏00芒聙鲁 west and approximate latitude 82脗掳39芒聙虏 north;</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text>Thence due north along said longitude 68脗掳00芒聙虏00芒聙鲁 west and across Clements Markham Inlet to a point on the ordinary low water mark on the north side of Clements Markham Inlet at approximate latitude 82脗掳42芒聙虏 north;</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text>Thence generally northeasterly following the ordinary low water mark along the northern side of Clements Markham Inlet to its most northerly point at Cape Colan at approximate latitude 82脗掳55芒聙虏 north and approximate longitude 66脗掳20芒聙虏 west;</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text>Thence northwesterly in the Arctic Ocean to the intersection of latitude 83脗掳09芒聙虏00芒聙鲁 north and longitude 70脗掳00芒聙虏00芒聙鲁 west;</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text>Thence westerly in the Arctic Ocean to the intersection of latitude 83脗掳09芒聙虏00芒聙鲁 north and longitude 74脗掳20芒聙虏00芒聙鲁 west;</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text>Thence southwesterly in the Arctic Ocean to the intersection of latitude 83脗掳05芒聙虏00芒聙鲁 north and longitude 77脗掳10芒聙虏00芒聙鲁 west;</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text>Thence southwesterly to the most northerly point on the ordinary low water mark at the entrance of M芒聙聶Clintock Inlet near Borup Point at approximate latitude 82脗掳56芒聙虏 north and approximate longitude 77脗掳47芒聙虏 west;</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text>Thence southerly to the summit of Mount Ayles at approximate latitude 82脗掳43芒聙虏 north and approximate longitude 77脗掳18芒聙虏 west;</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text>Thence southerly to an unnamed peak having an elevation of about 1829 metres at approximate latitude 82脗掳31芒聙虏 north and approximate longitude 77脗掳04芒聙虏 west;</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text>Thence due south to an unnamed peak having an elevation of about 1676 metres at approximate latitude 81脗掳49芒聙虏 north and approximate longitude 77脗掳04芒聙虏 west;</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text>Thence southwesterly to an unnamed peak having an elevation of about 1524 metres at approximate latitude 81脗掳34芒聙虏 north and approximate longitude 79脗掳03芒聙虏 west;</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text>Thence southeasterly to triangulation station number 629232 (established by the Geodetic Survey Division of the Earth Sciences Sector, Natural Resources Canada at Ottawa, the geographic coordinates of said station being at latitude 81脗掳18芒聙虏38.8738芒聙鲁 north and longitude 78脗掳07芒聙虏09.4867芒聙鲁 west according to the 1975 Arctic Islands Adjustment, North American Datum of 1927);</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text>Thence southeasterly along the production of the last aforesaid mentioned line to its intersection with the ordinary low water mark on the northwest side of Tanquary Fiord at approximate latitude 81脗掳18芒聙虏 north and approximate longitude 78脗掳07芒聙虏 west;</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text>Thence easterly across Tanquary Fiord to a point on the ordinary low water mark on the most southwesterly limit of Fishhook Point at approximate longitude 77脗掳37芒聙虏00芒聙鲁 west and approximate latitude 81脗掳19芒聙虏 north;</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text>Thence southeasterly to the point of commencement;</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text>The above described lands containing about 37 800 square kilometres.</Text></Provision></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote><HistoricalNote>2017, c. 26, s. 39(1)(F) and (2)</HistoricalNote></MarginalNote><Label>14</Label><Text>The description of Mingan Archipelago National Park Reserve of Canada in Schedule 2 to the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text>In the Province of Quebec:</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text>All those lands being the whole and entire Fief and Seigneurie of the Isles and Islets of Mingan, situate and being on the coast of the North shore of the St. Lawrence River, in the Province of Quebec, the said Fief and Seigneurie consisting of the Isles and Islets which being on the said North shore of the St. Lawrence River from Perroquets Island, longitude 64脗掳12芒聙虏40芒聙鲁 following continuation to the mouth of the River Aguanish, longitude 62脗掳05芒聙虏00芒聙鲁 in such manner as the said Fief and Seigneurie with its rights is more amply conceded and designated by the title of concession granted to Jacques de Lalande and Louis Joliet.</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text>Some of the Isles and Islets forming part of the Fief and Seigneurie of the Isles and Islets of Mingan are now known and designated as being lots 5 338 113 to 5 338 121, 6 504 068 and 6 504 185 to 6 504 187 of the cadastre of Quebec. The other Isles and Islets, forming part of the Fief and Seigneurie of the Isles and Islets of Mingan, are without cadastral designation.</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text>Notwithstanding the generality of the foregoing, the following Isles and Islets forming part of the Fief and Seigneurie of the Isles and Islets of Mingan are not included in the present description, namely: Maison Island, Wreck Island (without cadastral designation), Havre de Mingan Island designated as being lot 6 504 191 of the cadastre of Quebec and part of Firmin Island designated as being lot 5 338 112 of the cadastre of Quebec.</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text>Those lands included in the present description containing about 97.7 square kilometres exclude the lands situated below the ordinary high-water mark of the said Isles and Islets.</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text>The longitudes mentioned above were scaled from the 1:250,000 map sheets 12L and 22I of the national topographic series.</Text></Provision></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>15</Label><Text>Schedule 2 to the Act is amended by adding the following after the description of Sable Island National Park Reserve of Canada:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Group><GroupHeading format-ref="group1-part"><TitleText>Akami-Uapishk谩碌聛芒聙聯KakKasuak芒聙聯Mealy Mountains National Park Reserve of Canada</TitleText></GroupHeading><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text>All that lot, piece or parcel of land situated in the electoral districts of Cartwright-L芒聙聶Anse au Clair, Torngat Mountains and Lake Melville, in the Province of Newfoundland and Labrador, described in Chapter 1 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="other">Land Description Report for the Proposed National Park Reserve in the Mealy Mountains Region of Labrador</XRefExternal> recorded in the Canada Lands Survey Records as FB40974 CLSR on January 7, 2016, and shown on the plan prepared by the Atlantic Regional Office of the Surveyor General Branch, Natural Resources Canada, dated between December 22 and 24, 2015, entitled 芒聙聹Descriptive Map Plan showing the Boundary of the Proposed National Park Reserve in the Mealy Mountains Region of Labrador芒聙聺. A copy of the said plan was recorded in the Registry of Crown Titles in St. John芒聙聶s, Newfoundland and Labrador, as Special Plan SP 478R. A copy of the said plan was also recorded in the Canada Lands Surveys Records in Ottawa, Ontario, under number 104838 CLSR on January 7, 2016.</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text>The said National Park Reserve contains an area of approximately 10 700 square kilometres.</Text></Provision></Group></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>16</Label><Text>Schedule 5 to the Act is amended by deleting the description of the Mount Agassiz Ski Area and the heading before it.</Text></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>17</Label><Text>The Act is amended by replacing 芒聙聹Gwaii Haanas National Park Reserve of Canada芒聙聺 with 芒聙聹Gwaii Haanas National Park Reserve and Haida Heritage Site芒聙聺 in the following provisions:</Text><Paragraph type="amending"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>section 41; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph type="amending"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>the heading 芒聙聹Gwaii Haanas National Park Reserve of Canada芒聙聺 in Schedule 2.</Text></Paragraph></Section><Heading level="1"><MarginalNote><HistoricalNote>2002, c. 18</HistoricalNote></MarginalNote><TitleText>Canada National Marine Conservation Areas Act</TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><Label>18</Label><Text>Schedule 1 to the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Canada National Marine Conservation Areas Act</XRefExternal> is amended by adding, after the heading of that Schedule, the text set out in the schedule to this Act.</Text></Section><Heading level="1"><MarginalNote><HistoricalNote>2015, c. 10</HistoricalNote></MarginalNote><TitleText>Rouge National Urban Park Act</TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><Label>19</Label><Text>Section 17 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Rouge National Urban Park Act</XRefExternal> and the heading before it are replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Heading level="1"><TitleText><Ins>Discharge or Deposit of Substances</Ins></TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Protection of natural environment</MarginalNote><Label>17</Label><Subsection change="ins"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>It is prohibited to discharge or deposit a substance in the Park if the discharge or deposit degrades the natural environment, injures natural or cultural resources, endangers human health or public safety or is likely to do any of those things.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Duty to notify and take reasonable measures</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text><Ins>If the discharge</Ins> or <Ins>deposit</Ins> of <Ins>a substance in</Ins> the <Ins>Park degrades the</Ins> natural environment, <Ins>injures</Ins> natural <Ins>or</Ins> cultural resources, <Ins>endangers human health or public safety or is likely</Ins> to <Ins>do</Ins> any <Ins>of those things</Ins>, any person who has charge, management or control of the substance and any person who caused or contributed to the <Ins>discharge</Ins> or <Ins>deposit must</Ins></Text><Paragraph change="ins"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>notify the superintendent without delay; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph change="ins"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>take reasonable measures to prevent, mitigate or remediate harm and to prevent or minimize danger, as the case may be.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Powers of superintendent and Minister</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>If the superintendent is of the opinion that a person is not taking the required measures, the superintendent may order the person to take those measures. If the person fails to <Ins>take the measures that they are ordered to take,</Ins> the Minister may take <Ins>the</Ins> measures on behalf of <Ins>His</Ins> Majesty in right of Canada.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Expenses of clean-up</MarginalNote><Label>(<Ins>4</Ins>)</Label><Text>A person who fails to <Ins>take</Ins> the <Ins>measures</Ins> that <Ins>they are ordered to take</Ins> is liable for the expenses reasonably incurred by <Ins>His</Ins> Majesty in right of Canada in taking the measures. Those expenses may be recovered from <Ins>the</Ins> person, with costs, in proceedings brought in the name of <Ins>His</Ins> Majesty in any court of competent jurisdiction.</Text></Subsection></Section></AmendedText><ExplanatoryNote><TitleText>Rouge National Urban Park Act</TitleText><Label><Emphasis style="italic">Clause 19</Emphasis>:</Label><ExplanatoryText>Existing text of the heading and section 17:</ExplanatoryText><ExistingText><Heading level="1"><TitleText>Pollution Clean-up</TitleText></Heading><Section><Label>17</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>If a substance that is capable of degrading the natural environment, injuring natural or cultural resources or endangering human health is discharged or deposited in the Park, any person who has charge, management or control of the substance and any person who caused or contributed to the discharge or deposit must take reasonable measures to prevent any degradation of the natural environment and any danger to natural or cultural resources or to human health that may result from the discharge or deposit.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><Label>(2)</Label><Text>If the superintendent is of the opinion that a person is not taking the required measures, the superintendent may order the person to take those measures and, if the person fails to do so, the Minister may take those measures on behalf of Her Majesty in right of Canada.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><Label>(3)</Label><Text>A person who fails to comply with an order given by the superintendent is liable for the expenses reasonably incurred by Her Majesty in right of Canada in taking the measures, and those expenses may be recovered from that person, with costs, in proceedings brought in the name of Her Majesty in any court of competent jurisdiction.</Text></Subsection></Section></ExistingText></ExplanatoryNote></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>20</Label><Text>Section 19 of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Section><MarginalNote>For greater certainty</MarginalNote><Label>19</Label><Text>For greater certainty, subsections 17(1) <Ins>and (2)</Ins> and 18(2) do not prevent the carrying out of agricultural activities by a lessee of public lands in the Park in accordance with their lease.</Text></Section></AmendedText><ExplanatoryNote><Label><Emphasis style="italic">Clause 20</Emphasis>:</Label><ExplanatoryText>Existing text of section 19:</ExplanatoryText><ExistingText><Section><Label>19</Label><Text>For greater certainty, subsections 17(1) and 18(2) do not prevent the carrying out of agricultural activities by a lessee of public lands in the Park in accordance with their lease.</Text></Section></ExistingText></ExplanatoryNote></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>21</Label><Text>The portion of subsection 33(1) of the Act before paragraph (a) is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Section><MarginalNote>Offence</MarginalNote><Label>33</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Every person who contravenes subsection 17(1) <Ins>or (2) or who fails to take measures that they are ordered to take under subsection 17(3)</Ins> is guilty of an offence and liable</Text></Subsection></Section></AmendedText><ExplanatoryNote><Label><Emphasis style="italic">Clause 21</Emphasis>:</Label><ExplanatoryText>Relevant portion of subsection 33(1):</ExplanatoryText><ExistingText><Section><Label>33</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Every person who contravenes subsection 17(1) is guilty of an offence and liable</Text></Subsection></Section></ExistingText></ExplanatoryNote></Section><Heading level="1"><MarginalNote><HistoricalNote>C.R.C., c. 1120; SOR/2003芒聙聯54, s. 1</HistoricalNote></MarginalNote><TitleText>Consequential Amendments to the <XRefExternal reference-type="regulation">National Parks of Canada Fishing Regulations</XRefExternal></TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><Label>22</Label><Text>The <XRefExternal reference-type="regulation">National Parks of Canada Fishing Regulations</XRefExternal> are amended by replacing 芒聙聹Gwaii Haanas National Park Reserve of Canada芒聙聺 with 芒聙聹Gwaii Haanas National Park Reserve and Haida Heritage Site芒聙聺 in the following provisions:</Text><Paragraph type="amending"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>section 2.6; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph type="amending"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>item 15 of Schedule IV.</Text></Paragraph></Section><Heading level="1"><TitleText>Coordinating Amendments</TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote>2015, c. 38</MarginalNote><Label>23</Label><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>In this section, <DefinedTermEn>other Act</DefinedTermEn> means the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Lake Superior National Marine Conservation Area Act</XRefExternal>.</Text></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>If section 4 of the other Act comes into force before section <XRefInternal>18</XRefInternal> of this Act, that section <XRefInternal>18</XRefInternal> is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Section type="amending"><Label><XRefInternal>18</XRefInternal></Label><Text>Schedule 1 to the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Canada National Marine Conservation Areas Act</XRefExternal> is amended by adding, after the description of Lake Superior National Marine Conservation Area of Canada, the text set out in the schedule to this Act.</Text></Section></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(3)</Label><Text>If section <XRefInternal>18</XRefInternal> of this Act comes into force before section 4 of the other Act, the portion of that section 4 preceding the title 芒聙聹Lake Superior National Marine Conservation Area of Canada芒聙聺 is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Section type="amending"><Label>4</Label><Text>Schedule 1 to the Act is amended by adding the following after the heading of that Schedule:</Text></Section></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(4)</Label><Text>If section 4 of the other Act comes into force on the same day as section <XRefInternal>18</XRefInternal> of this Act, then that section 4 is deemed to have come into force before that section <XRefInternal>18</XRefInternal> and subsection (2) applies as a consequence.</Text></Subsection></Section><Heading level="1"><TitleText>Coming into Force</TitleText></Heading><Section type="CIF"><MarginalNote>Akami-Uapishk谩碌聛芒聙聯KakKasuak芒聙聯Mealy Mountains National Park Reserve of Canada</MarginalNote><Label>24</Label><Subsection type="CIFnobold"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Subsection <XRefInternal>6</XRefInternal>(2) comes into force on the day on which regulations made under the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Canada National Parks Act</XRefExternal> respecting access by air to Akami-Uapishk谩碌聛芒聙聯KakKasuak芒聙聯Mealy Mountains National Park Reserve of Canada, or to any future national park that replaces all or part of that park reserve, come into force.</Text></Subsection><Subsection type="CIFnobold"><MarginalNote>Regulations respecting recreational fishing</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Subsection <XRefInternal>6</XRefInternal>(3) comes into force on the day on which regulations made under the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Canada National Parks Act</XRefExternal> respecting recreational fishing in Akami-Uapishk谩碌聛芒聙聯KakKasuak芒聙聯Mealy Mountains National Park Reserve of Canada, or in any future national park that replaces all or part of that park reserve, come into force.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section type="CIF"><MarginalNote>Tallurutiup Imanga National Marine Conservation Area</MarginalNote><Label>25</Label><Text>Section <XRefInternal>18</XRefInternal> comes into force on the day on which a notice is published in the <XRefExternal reference-type="other">Canada Gazette</XRefExternal> confirming that an interim management plan for the Tallurutiup Imanga National Marine Conservation Area has been approved by the <DefinitionRef>Aulattiqatigiit Board</DefinitionRef>, as defined in section 2.2 of the Tallurutiup Imanga National Marine Conservation Area Inuit Impact and Benefit Agreement signed on behalf of Inuit of the Qikiqtani Region of Nunavut and Her Majesty the Queen in Right of Canada on August 1, 2019.</Text></Section></Body><Schedule bilingual="no" spanlanguages="no"><ScheduleFormHeading><Label>SCHEDULE</Label><OriginatingRef>(Section <XRefInternal>18</XRefInternal>)</OriginatingRef></ScheduleFormHeading><DocumentInternal><Group><GroupHeading format-ref="group1-part"><TitleText>Tallurutiup Imanga National Marine Conservation Area</TitleText></GroupHeading><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text>All topographic features hereinafter referred to being derived from the CANVEC dataset edition 9.</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text>The boundary is graphically illustrated on a sketch recorded in the Canada Lands Surveys Records as 111760 CLSR.</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text>Select points have a unique number in brackets that can be cross-referenced with the above-noted sketch.</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text>Commencing at a point where longitude 72脗掳33芒聙虏00芒聙鲁 West meets the ordinary high water mark at approximate latitude 71脗掳39芒聙虏36芒聙鲁 North on Cape Hunter, on Baffin Island; [1]</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text>Thence beginning southerly and generally westerly along the sinuosity of the ordinary high water mark of Baffin Island to a point where latitude 71脗掳48芒聙虏52芒聙鲁 North meets the same at approximate longitude 74脗掳30芒聙虏09芒聙鲁 West on the east side of Feachem Bay; [2]</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text>Thence easterly in a straight line and inland to a point at latitude 71脗掳48芒聙虏23芒聙鲁 North and longitude 74脗掳25芒聙虏27芒聙鲁 West; [3]</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text>Thence easterly in a straight line to a point at latitude 71脗掳50芒聙虏00芒聙鲁 North and longitude 74脗掳15芒聙虏00芒聙鲁 West; [4]</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text>Thence northerly in a straight line to a point at latitude 71脗掳52芒聙虏10芒聙鲁 North and longitude 74脗掳11芒聙虏00芒聙鲁 West; [5]</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text>Thence easterly in a straight line to a point on the ordinary high water mark of Baffin Island where latitude 71脗掳52芒聙虏06芒聙鲁 North meets the same at approximate longitude 74脗掳10芒聙虏17芒聙鲁 West; [6]</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text>Thence generally northwesterly along the sinuosity of the ordinary high water mark of Baffin Island to a point where the eastern boundary of P.C. O.I.C. 1984芒聙聬972 meets the same at approximate latitude 72脗掳42芒聙虏59芒聙鲁 North and approximate longitude 77脗掳46芒聙虏23芒聙鲁 West; [7]</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text>Thence westerly in a straight line, perpendicular to the general direction of the shore, for a distance of 100 metres to a point within Eclipse Sound at approximate latitude 72脗掳43芒聙虏01芒聙鲁 North and approximate longitude 77脗掳46芒聙虏32芒聙鲁 West; [8]</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text>Thence generally southwesterly, along a line running 100 metres perpendicularly distant offshore from the sinuosity of the ordinary high water mark of Baffin Island, to a point where longitude 77脗掳56芒聙虏13芒聙鲁 West meets the same at approximate latitude 72脗掳42芒聙虏12芒聙鲁 North; [9]</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text>Thence northwesterly in a straight line to a point at latitude 72脗掳43芒聙虏03芒聙鲁 North and longitude 77脗掳58芒聙虏07芒聙鲁 West; [10]</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text>Thence southwesterly in a straight line to a point at latitude 72脗掳42芒聙虏37芒聙鲁 North and longitude 78脗掳01芒聙虏37芒聙鲁 West; [11]</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text>Thence southwesterly in a straight line to a point at latitude 72脗掳41芒聙虏42芒聙鲁 North and longitude 78脗掳03芒聙虏46芒聙鲁 West; [12]</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text>Thence southeasterly in a straight line to a point on a line running 100 metres perpendicularly distant offshore from the sinuosity of the ordinary high water mark of Baffin Island where latitude 72脗掳40芒聙虏43芒聙鲁 North meets the same at approximate longitude 78脗掳01芒聙虏39芒聙鲁 West; [13]</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text>Thence southwesterly along a line running 100 metres perpendicularly distant offshore from the sinuosity of the ordinary high water mark of Baffin Island, to the point of intersection with a straight line drawn northwesterly from and perpendicular to the general direction of the ordinary high water mark where the western boundary of P.C. O.I.C. 1984芒聙聬972 meets the same at approximate latitude 72脗掳39芒聙虏26芒聙鲁 North and approximate longitude 78脗掳10芒聙虏04芒聙鲁 West; [14]</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text>Thence southeasterly in a straight line to the point on the ordinary high water mark of Baffin Island where the said western boundary of P.C. O.I.C. 1984芒聙聬972 meets the same at approximate latitude 72脗掳39芒聙虏23芒聙鲁 North and approximate longitude 78脗掳09芒聙虏59芒聙鲁 West; [15]</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text>Thence generally southwesterly along the sinuosity of the ordinary high water mark of Baffin Island to a point where the western boundary of Sirmilik National Park of Canada meets the same near point 177PI, as shown on Administrative Plan of Sirmilik National Park of Canada in the Canada Lands Surveys Records at Ottawa as 104419 and filed in the Land Titles Office for Nunavut as 4575, at approximate latitude 72脗掳24芒聙虏08芒聙鲁 North and approximate longitude 78脗掳27芒聙虏18芒聙鲁 West; [16]</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text>Thence southwesterly along the northwestern boundary of said Sirmilik National Park of Canada to the ordinary high water mark of the northerly extremity of the promontory known as Oorbignaluk Headland at approximate latitude 72脗掳22芒聙虏02芒聙鲁 North and approximate longitude 78脗掳36芒聙虏12芒聙鲁 West; [17]</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text>Thence generally southwesterly along the sinuosity of the ordinary high water mark of Baffin Island to a point on the eastern side of Milne Inlet where latitude 72脗掳00芒聙虏00芒聙鲁 North meets the same at approximate longitude 80脗掳38芒聙虏59芒聙鲁 West; [18]</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text>Thence westerly following the line of latitude 72脗掳00芒聙虏00芒聙鲁 North across said Milne Inlet to the western side thereof where latitude 72脗掳00芒聙虏00芒聙鲁 North meets the ordinary high water mark at approximate longitude 80脗掳48芒聙虏17芒聙鲁 West; [19]</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text>Thence generally northwesterly along the sinuosity of the ordinary high water mark of Baffin Island to a point where longitude 84脗掳29芒聙虏10芒聙鲁 West meets the same at approximate latitude 73脗掳03芒聙虏58芒聙鲁 North near Nanisivik; [20]</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text>Thence northerly in a straight line to a point at latitude 73脗掳05芒聙虏04芒聙鲁 North and longitude 84脗掳28芒聙虏32芒聙鲁 West within Strathcona Sound; [21]</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text>Thence westerly in a straight line to a point at latitude 73脗掳05芒聙虏29芒聙鲁 North and longitude 84脗掳35芒聙虏53芒聙鲁 West within Strathcona Sound; [22]</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text>Thence southerly in a straight line to a point on the ordinary high water mark of Baffin Island where longitude 84脗掳36芒聙虏32芒聙鲁 West meets the same at approximate latitude 73脗掳04芒聙虏22芒聙鲁 North; [23]</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text>Thence westerly along the sinuosity of the ordinary high water mark of Baffin Island to a point where the eastern boundary of P.C. O.I.C. 1993芒聙聬785 meets the same at approximate latitude 73脗掳06芒聙虏20芒聙鲁 North and approximate longitude 84脗掳55芒聙虏59芒聙鲁 West; [24]</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text>Thence northerly along the projection of the said eastern boundary of P.C. O.I.C. 1993芒聙聬785 to the point of intersection with a line running 100 metres perpendicularly distant offshore from the sinuosity of the ordinary high water mark of Baffin Island at approximate latitude 73脗掳06芒聙虏24芒聙鲁 North and approximate longitude 84脗掳54芒聙虏59芒聙鲁 West; [25]</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text>Thence generally southwesterly along a line running 100 metres perpendicularly distant offshore from the sinuosity of the ordinary high water mark of Baffin Island, to a point where latitude 73脗掳04芒聙虏29芒聙鲁 North meets the same at approximate longitude 85脗掳09芒聙虏24芒聙鲁 West in Victor Bay; [26]</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text>Thence westerly in a straight line to a point on a line running 100 metres perpendicularly distant offshore from the sinuosity of the ordinary high water mark of Baffin Island where latitude 73脗掳04芒聙虏08芒聙鲁 North meets the same at approximate longitude 85脗掳14芒聙虏56芒聙鲁 West; [27]</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text>Thence northwesterly along a line running 100 metres perpendicularly distant offshore from the sinuosity of the ordinary high water mark of Baffin Island, to a point on the projection of the western boundary of P.C. O.I.C. 1993芒聙聬785 at approximate latitude 73脗掳08芒聙虏36芒聙鲁 North and approximate longitude 85脗掳24芒聙虏29芒聙鲁 West; [28]</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text>Thence southerly along the said projection of the western boundary of P.C. O.I.C. 1993芒聙聬785 to a point on the ordinary high water mark of Baffin Island at approximate latitude 73脗掳08芒聙虏32芒聙鲁 North and approximate longitude 85脗掳24芒聙虏29芒聙鲁 West; [29]</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text>Thence southerly along the sinuosity of the ordinary high water mark of Baffin Island to a point where the western boundary of P.C. O.I.C. 1993芒聙聬785 meets the same at approximate latitude 73脗掳01芒聙虏37芒聙鲁 North and approximate longitude 85脗掳24芒聙虏59芒聙鲁 West; [30]</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text>Thence southerly along the projection of the said western boundary of P.C. O.I.C. 1993芒聙聬785 to the point of intersection with a line running 100 metres perpendicularly distant offshore from the sinuosity of the ordinary high water mark of Baffin Island at approximate latitude 73脗掳01芒聙虏33芒聙鲁 North and approximate longitude 85脗掳24芒聙虏59芒聙鲁 West; [31]</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text>Thence generally easterly along a line running 100 metres perpendicularly distant offshore from the sinuosity of the ordinary high water mark of Baffin Island, to a point where latitude 73脗掳00芒聙虏33芒聙鲁 North meets the same at approximate longitude 85脗掳08芒聙虏54芒聙鲁 West in Arctic Bay; [32]</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text>Thence easterly in a straight line to a point on a line running 100 metres perpendicularly distant offshore from the sinuosity of the ordinary high water mark of Baffin Island where latitude 73脗掳00芒聙虏33芒聙鲁 North meets the same at approximate longitude 85脗掳04芒聙虏12芒聙鲁 West; [33]</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text>Thence generally southeasterly along a line running 100 metres perpendicularly distant offshore from the sinuosity of the ordinary high water mark of Baffin Island, to the point of intersection with the projection of the eastern boundary of P.C. O.I.C. 1993芒聙聬785 at approximate latitude 72脗掳58芒聙虏30芒聙鲁 North and approximate longitude 84脗掳54芒聙虏59芒聙鲁 West; [34]</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text>Thence northerly along the said projection of the eastern boundary of P.C. O.I.C. 1993芒聙聬785 to a point on the ordinary high water mark of Baffin Island at approximate latitude 72脗掳58芒聙虏35芒聙鲁 North and approximate longitude 84脗掳54芒聙虏59芒聙鲁 West; [35]</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text>Thence beginning southeasterly and generally northwesterly and following the sinuosity of the ordinary high water mark of Baffin Island to a point on Brodeur Peninsula where latitude 73脗掳49芒聙虏59芒聙鲁 North meets the same at approximate longitude 86脗掳48芒聙虏05芒聙鲁 West; [36]</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text>Thence westerly in a straight line to a point on the ordinary high water mark of Somerset Island, near Cape Clarence, where latitude 73脗掳53芒聙虏49芒聙鲁 North meets the same at approximate longitude 90脗掳09芒聙虏53芒聙鲁 West; [37]</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text>Thence generally westerly along the sinuosity of the ordinary high water mark of Somerset Island to a point where latitude 73脗掳56芒聙虏56芒聙鲁 North meets the same at approximate longitude 95脗掳19芒聙虏13芒聙鲁 West; [38]</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text>Thence westerly in a straight line to a point at latitude 73脗掳55芒聙虏52芒聙鲁 North and longitude 95脗掳58芒聙虏10芒聙鲁 West within Peel Sound; [39]</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text>Thence northerly in a straight line to a point at latitude 74脗掳53芒聙虏57芒聙鲁 North and longitude 96脗掳06芒聙虏56芒聙鲁 West within Resolute Passage; [40]</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text>Thence easterly in a straight line to a point on the ordinary high water mark of Cornwallis Island where latitude 74脗掳53芒聙虏56芒聙鲁 North meets the same at approximate longitude 96脗掳01芒聙虏29芒聙鲁 West; [41]</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text>Thence generally southeasterly along the sinuosity of the ordinary high water mark of Cornwallis Island to a point where the western boundary of P.C. O.I.C. 1983芒聙聬1086 meets the same at approximate latitude 74脗掳45芒聙虏19芒聙鲁 North and approximate longitude 95脗掳05芒聙虏10芒聙鲁 West; [42]</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text>Thence southerly along the projection of the said western boundary of P.C. O.I.C. 1983芒聙聬1086 to a point measured 100 metres perpendicular to the sinuosity of the ordinary high water mark of Cornwallis Island within Allen Bay at approximate latitude 74脗掳45芒聙虏15芒聙鲁 North and approximate longitude 95脗掳05芒聙虏10芒聙鲁 West; [43]</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text>Thence generally southerly along a line running 100 metres perpendicularly distant offshore from the sinuosity of the ordinary high water mark of Cornwallis Island, to a point where latitude 74脗掳43芒聙虏40芒聙鲁 North meets the same at approximate longitude 95脗掳02芒聙虏59芒聙鲁 West; [44]</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text>Thence westerly in a straight line to a point at latitude 74脗掳43芒聙虏56芒聙鲁 North and longitude 95脗掳07芒聙虏01芒聙鲁 West; [45]</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text>Thence southwesterly in a straight line to a point at latitude 74脗掳41芒聙虏27芒聙鲁 North and longitude 95脗掳09芒聙虏40芒聙鲁 West; [46]</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text>Thence easterly in a straight line to a point on a line running 100 metres perpendicularly distant offshore from the sinuosity of the ordinary high water mark of Cornwallis Island where latitude 74脗掳41芒聙虏23芒聙鲁 North meets the same at approximate longitude 95脗掳05芒聙虏37芒聙鲁 West; [47]</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text>Thence generally southeasterly along a line running 100 metres perpendicularly distant offshore from the sinuosity of the ordinary high water mark of Cornwallis Island, to a point where longitude 94脗掳53芒聙虏26芒聙鲁 West meets the same at approximate latitude 74脗掳40芒聙虏16芒聙鲁 North, near Resolute Bay; [48]</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text>Thence easterly in a straight line to a point on a line running 100 metres perpendicularly distant offshore from the sinuosity of the ordinary high water mark of Cornwallis Island where latitude 74脗掳39芒聙虏54芒聙鲁 North meets the same at approximate longitude 94脗掳48芒聙虏09芒聙鲁 West; [49]</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text>Thence generally southeasterly along a line running 100 metres perpendicularly distant offshore from the sinuosity of the ordinary high water mark of Cornwallis Island, to a point on the projection of the eastern boundary of P.C. O.I.C. 1983芒聙聬1086 at approximate latitude 74脗掳37芒聙虏54芒聙鲁 North and approximate longitude 94脗掳38芒聙虏05芒聙鲁 West; [50]</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text>Thence northerly along the projection of the said eastern boundary of P.C. O.I.C. 1983芒聙聬1086 to a point on the ordinary high water mark of Cornwallis Island at approximate latitude 74脗掳37芒聙虏57芒聙鲁 North and approximate longitude 94脗掳38芒聙虏02芒聙鲁 West; [51]</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text>Thence generally northeasterly along the sinuosity of the ordinary high water mark of Cornwallis Island to a point where latitude 75脗掳02芒聙虏05芒聙鲁 North meets the same at approximate longitude 93脗掳30芒聙虏19芒聙鲁 West; [52]</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text>Thence easterly in a straight line to a point at latitude 75脗掳03芒聙虏54芒聙鲁 North and longitude 92脗掳49芒聙虏18芒聙鲁 West within Wellington Channel; [53]</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text>Thence easterly in a straight line to a point on the ordinary high water mark of Devon Island where latitude 75脗掳02芒聙虏24芒聙鲁 North meets the same at approximate longitude 92脗掳13芒聙虏54芒聙鲁 West near Bowden Point; [54]</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text>Thence generally southeasterly along the sinuosity of the ordinary high water mark of Devon Island to a point where latitude 74脗掳38芒聙虏40芒聙鲁 North meets the same at approximate longitude 91脗掳22芒聙虏44芒聙鲁 West at the entrance to Gascoyne Inlet; [55]</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text>Thence southeasterly in a straight line to a point on the ordinary high water mark of Devon Island where latitude 74脗掳37芒聙虏43芒聙鲁 North meets the same at approximate longitude 91脗掳18芒聙虏05芒聙鲁 West near Cape Ricketts; [56]</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text>Thence easterly along the sinuosity of the ordinary high water mark of Devon Island to a point where longitude 91脗掳11芒聙虏41芒聙鲁 West meets the same at approximate latitude 74脗掳37芒聙虏29芒聙鲁 North near Cape Liddon; [57]</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text>Thence northerly in a straight line and inland to a point at latitude 74脗掳37芒聙虏42芒聙鲁 North and longitude 91脗掳11芒聙虏37芒聙鲁 West; [58]</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text>Thence easterly in a straight line to a point at latitude 74脗掳37芒聙虏48芒聙鲁 North and longitude 91脗掳07芒聙虏58芒聙鲁 West; [59]</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text>Thence northeasterly in a straight line to a point at latitude 74脗掳38芒聙虏22芒聙鲁 North and longitude 91脗掳07芒聙虏13芒聙鲁 West; [60]</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text>Thence easterly in a straight line to a point on the ordinary high water mark of Devon Island where latitude 74脗掳38芒聙虏22芒聙鲁 North meets the same at approximate longitude 91脗掳06芒聙虏34芒聙鲁 West near Cape Liddon; [61]</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text>Thence generally easterly along the sinuosity of the ordinary high water mark of Devon Island to a point where latitude 74脗掳28芒聙虏25芒聙鲁 North meets the same at approximate longitude 86脗掳58芒聙虏37芒聙鲁 West on the east side of Hobhouse Inlet; [62]</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text>Thence easterly in a straight line and inland to a point at latitude 74脗掳28芒聙虏23芒聙鲁 North and longitude 86脗掳57芒聙虏20芒聙鲁 West; [63]</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text>Thence southerly in a straight line to a point at latitude 74脗掳27芒聙虏53芒聙鲁 North and longitude 86脗掳57芒聙虏20芒聙鲁 West; [64]</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text>Thence easterly in a straight line to a point at latitude 74脗掳28芒聙虏06芒聙鲁 North and longitude 86脗掳38芒聙虏26芒聙鲁 West; [65]</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text>Thence southeasterly in a straight line to a point on the ordinary high water mark of Devon Island where longitude 86脗掳37芒聙虏33芒聙鲁 West meets the same at approximate latitude 74脗掳27芒聙虏59芒聙鲁 North; [66]</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text>Thence generally easterly, northerly and northwesterly along the sinuosity of the ordinary high water mark of Devon Island to a point where longitude 81脗掳40芒聙虏40芒聙鲁 West meets the same at approximate latitude 75脗掳48芒聙虏32芒聙鲁 North; [67]</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text>Thence northeasterly in a straight line to a point on the ordinary high water mark of Ellesmere Island where longitude 81脗掳03芒聙虏56芒聙鲁 West meets the same at approximate latitude 76脗掳08芒聙虏00芒聙鲁 North, at King Edward Point; [68]</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text>Thence generally northeasterly along the sinuosity of the ordinary high water mark of Ellesmere Island to a point where latitude 76脗掳35芒聙虏16芒聙鲁 North meets the same at approximate longitude 78脗掳07芒聙虏21芒聙鲁 West; [69]</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text>Thence southeasterly in a straight line to a point at latitude 76脗掳30芒聙虏12芒聙鲁 North and longitude 77脗掳53芒聙虏42芒聙鲁 West in Baffin Bay; [70]</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text>Thence southeasterly in a straight line to a point at latitude 76脗掳24芒聙虏13芒聙鲁 North and longitude 77脗掳50芒聙虏20芒聙鲁 West in Baffin Bay; [71]</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text>Thence southerly in a straight line to a point at latitude 75脗掳25芒聙虏54芒聙鲁 North and longitude 78脗掳06芒聙虏41芒聙鲁 West in Baffin Bay; [72]</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text>Thence southeasterly in a straight line to a point at latitude 74脗掳56芒聙虏17芒聙鲁 North and longitude 77脗掳03芒聙虏02芒聙鲁 West in Baffin Bay; [73]</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text>Thence southeasterly in a straight line to a point at latitude 74脗掳33芒聙虏47芒聙鲁 North and longitude 75脗掳35芒聙虏49芒聙鲁 West in Baffin Bay; [74]</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text>Thence southeasterly in a straight line to a point at latitude 74脗掳05芒聙虏26芒聙鲁 North and longitude 74脗掳26芒聙虏29芒聙鲁 West in Baffin Bay; [75]</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text>Thence southeasterly in a straight line to the point of commencement.</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text>Containing an area of approximately 108 000 square kilometres as measured on the Albers Equal Area Projection;</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text>Save and except all islands, rocks and shoals that are 400 hectares in area or larger as measured from the ordinary high water mark;</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text>Save and except the Nirjutiqarvik National Wildlife Area as defined in the <XRefExternal reference-type="regulation">Wildlife Area Regulations</XRefExternal> pursuant to the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Canada Wildlife Act</XRefExternal>;</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text>Save and except the Prince Leopold Island Bird Sanctuary as defined in the <XRefExternal reference-type="regulation">Migratory Bird Sanctuary Regulations</XRefExternal> pursuant to the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Migratory Birds Convention Act, 1994</XRefExternal>;</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text>Save and except all Inuit Owned Lands that are wholly or partially within the hereinbefore described Tallurutiup Imanga National Marine Conservation Area;</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text>References to straight lines mean points joined directly on the NAD83 ellipsoid by geodesics;</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text>Coordinates referenced hereon are geodetic and referenced to the North American Datum of 1983 (NAD83), Canadian Spatial Reference System (CSRS).</Text></Provision></Group></DocumentInternal></Schedule></Bill>