<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!--Arbortext, Inc., 1988-2010, v.4002--><Bill bill-origin="senate" bill-type="govt-public" xml:lang="en"><Identification><BillNumber>S-2</BillNumber><Parliament><Session>1</Session><Number>44</Number><RegnalYear><Year-s>70</Year-s><Monarch>Elizabeth II</Monarch></RegnalYear><Year-s>2021</Year-s></Parliament><LongTitle>An Act to amend the Parliament of Canada Act and to make consequential and related amendments to other Acts</LongTitle><ShortTitle status="unofficial">An Act to amend the Parliament of Canada Act and to make consequential and related amendments to other Acts</ShortTitle><RunningHead>An Act to amend the Parliament of Canada Act and to make consequential and related amendments to other Acts</RunningHead><BillHistory><Stages stage="third-reading-senate"><Date><YYYY>2021</YYYY><MM>12</MM><DD>7</DD></Date></Stages></BillHistory><BillRefNumber date-time="2021-11-23">91040</BillRefNumber></Identification><Introduction><Summary><TitleText>SUMMARY</TitleText><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>This enactment amends the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Parliament of Canada Act</XRefExternal> and makes consequential and related amendments to other Acts to, among other things,</Text><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>change the additional annual allowances that are paid to senators who occupy certain positions so that the government’s representatives and the Opposition in the Senate are eligible for the allowances for five positions each and the three other recognized parties or parliamentary groups in the Senate with the greatest number of members are eligible for the allowances for four positions each;</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>provide that the Leader of the Government in the Senate or Government Representative in the Senate, the Leader of the Opposition in the Senate and the Leader or Facilitator of every other recognized party or parliamentary group in the Senate are to be consulted on the appointment of certain officers and agents of Parliament; and</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>(c)</Label><Text>provide that the Leader of the Government in the Senate or Government Representative in the Senate, the Leader of the Opposition in the Senate and the Leader or Facilitator of every other recognized party or parliamentary group in the Senate may change the membership of the Standing Senate Committee on Internal Economy, Budgets and Administration.</Text></Provision></Provision></Summary><Enacts><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>Her Majesty, by and with the advice and consent of the Senate and House of Commons of Canada, enacts as follows:</Text></Provision></Enacts></Introduction><Body><Heading level="1"><MarginalNote><HistoricalNote>R.S., c. P-1</HistoricalNote></MarginalNote><TitleText>Parliament of Canada Act</TitleText></Heading><Heading level="2"><TitleText>Amendments to the Act</TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote><HistoricalNote>1991, c. 20, s. 1</HistoricalNote></MarginalNote><Label>1</Label><Text>Subsection 19.1(3) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Parliament of Canada Act</XRefExternal> is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Subsection><MarginalNote>Composition of Committee</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>The Leader of the Government in the Senate or Government Representative in the Senate, or his or her nominee, the Leader of the Opposition in the Senate, or his or her nominee, and the Leader or Facilitator of every other recognized party or parliamentary group in the Senate, or his or her nominee, may, in accordance with the rules of the Senate, change the membership of the Committee from time to time, including during periods of prorogation or dissolution.</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote><HistoricalNote>2004, c. 7, s. 2</HistoricalNote></MarginalNote><Label>2</Label><Text>Section 20.1 of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Section><MarginalNote>Appointment</MarginalNote><Label>20.1</Label><Text>The Governor in Council shall, by commission under the Great Seal, appoint a Senate Ethics Officer after consultation with the Leader of the Government in the Senate or Government Representative in the Senate, the Leader of the Opposition in the Senate and the Leader or Facilitator of every other recognized party or parliamentary group in the Senate and after approval of the appointment by resolution of the Senate.</Text></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>3</Label><Text>The Act is amended by adding the following after section 62.3:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Heading level="2"><TitleText>Additional Annual Allowances of Senators Beginning on July 1, 2022</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Additional annual allowances — senators</MarginalNote><Label>62.4</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Despite section 62.3, beginning on July 1, 2022 there shall be paid to the following senators the following additional annual allowances:</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>the senator occupying the position of Leader of the Government in the Senate or Government Representative in the Senate, unless he or she is in receipt of a salary under the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Salaries Act</XRefExternal>, $90,500;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>the senator occupying the position of Leader of the Opposition in the Senate, $42,800;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(c)</Label><Text>the senator occupying the position of Leader or Facilitator of the recognized party or parliamentary group in the Senate that consists of the greatest number of senators, other than the recognized party or parliamentary group to which a senator referred to in paragraph (a) or (b) belongs, $42,800;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(d)</Label><Text>the senator occupying the position of Leader or Facilitator of the recognized party or parliamentary group in the Senate that consists of the second greatest number of senators, other than the recognized party or parliamentary group to which a senator referred to in paragraph (a) or (b) belongs, $21,300;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(e)</Label><Text>the senator occupying the position of Leader or Facilitator of the recognized party or parliamentary group in the Senate that consists of the third greatest number of senators, other than the recognized party or parliamentary group to which a senator referred to in paragraph (a) or (b) belongs, $21,300;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(f)</Label><Text>the senator occupying the position of Deputy Leader of the Government in the Senate or Legislative Deputy to the Government Representative in the Senate, $42,800;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(g)</Label><Text>the senator occupying the position of Deputy Leader of the Opposition in the Senate, $27,000;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(h)</Label><Text>the senator occupying the position of Deputy Leader or Deputy Facilitator to the senator referred to in paragraph (c), $27,000;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(i)</Label><Text>the senator occupying the position of Deputy Leader or Deputy Facilitator to the senator referred to in paragraph (d), $13,400;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(j)</Label><Text>the senator occupying the position of Deputy Leader or Deputy Facilitator to the senator referred to in paragraph (e), $13,400;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(k)</Label><Text>the senator occupying the position of Government Whip in the Senate or Government Liaison in the Senate, $12,900;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(l)</Label><Text>the senator occupying the position of Opposition Whip in the Senate, $7,400;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(m)</Label><Text>the senator occupying the position of Whip or Liaison of the recognized party or parliamentary group in the Senate whose Leader or Facilitator is referred to in paragraph (c), $7,400;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(n)</Label><Text>the senator occupying the position of Whip or Liaison of the recognized party or parliamentary group in the Senate whose Leader or Facilitator is referred to in paragraph (d), $3,700;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(o)</Label><Text>the senator occupying the position of Whip or Liaison of the recognized party or parliamentary group in the Senate whose Leader or Facilitator is referred to in paragraph (e), $3,700;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(p)</Label><Text>the senator occupying the position of Chair of the Caucus of the Government in the Senate, $7,400;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(q)</Label><Text>the senator occupying the position of Chair of the Caucus of the Opposition in the Senate, $6,400;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(r)</Label><Text>the senator occupying the position of Deputy Whip or Deputy Liaison of the recognized party or parliamentary group in the Senate whose Leader or Facilitator is referred to in paragraph (c), $3,200;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(s)</Label><Text>the senator occupying the position of Deputy Whip or Deputy Liaison of the recognized party or parliamentary group in the Senate whose Leader or Facilitator is referred to in paragraph (d), $1,500;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(t)</Label><Text>the senator occupying the position of Deputy Whip or Deputy Liaison of the recognized party or parliamentary group in the Senate whose Leader or Facilitator is referred to in paragraph (e), $1,500;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(u)</Label><Text>the senator occupying the position of Deputy Government Whip in the Senate or Deputy Government Liaison in the Senate, $6,400; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(v)</Label><Text>the senator occupying the position of Deputy Opposition Whip in the Senate, $3,200.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Subsequent fiscal years</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Despite section 62.3, the additional annual allowance that shall be paid for each fiscal year after March 31, 2023 to a senator referred to in subsection (1) is the additional annual allowance for the previous fiscal year plus the amount obtained by multiplying that additional annual allowance by the index described in section 67.1 for the previous calendar year.</Text></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote><HistoricalNote>2005, c. 16, s. 7; 2017, c. 15, s. 44</HistoricalNote></MarginalNote><Label>4</Label><Text>Sections 67 and 67.1 of the Act are replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Section><MarginalNote>Rounding of amounts</MarginalNote><Label>67</Label><Text>The salaries and allowances payable to members of the Senate and the House of Commons under sections 55.1 and 62.1 to 62.4 of this Act and section 4.1 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Salaries Act</XRefExternal> shall be rounded down to the nearest hundred dollars.</Text></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Index</MarginalNote><Label>67.1</Label><Text>The index referred to in paragraph 55.1(2)(b) and subsections 62.1(2), 62.2(2), 62.3(2) and (4) and 62.4(2) for a calendar year is the index of the average percentage increase in base-rate wages for the calendar year, resulting from major settlements negotiated with bargaining units of 500 or more employees in the private sector in Canada, as published by the Department of Employment and Social Development within three months after the end of that calendar year.</Text></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote><HistoricalNote>2005, c. 16, s. 10</HistoricalNote></MarginalNote><Label>5</Label><Text>The portion of subsection 71.1(1) of the Act before paragraph (a) is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Section><MarginalNote>Entitlement</MarginalNote><Label>71.1</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>A member of the Senate or the House of Commons who resigns by reason of disability may elect to receive an annual disability allowance equal to 70% of their annual salaries and allowances under sections 55.1 and 62.1 to 62.4 of this Act and section 4.1 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Salaries Act</XRefExternal>, on the date of resignation, if at the time of their resignation, the member</Text></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote><HistoricalNote>2017, c. 20, s. 128</HistoricalNote></MarginalNote><Label>6</Label><Text>Paragraph 79.1(1)(a) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>the Leader of the Government in the Senate or Government Representative in the Senate, the Leader of the Opposition in the Senate and the Leader or Facilitator of every other recognized party or parliamentary group in the Senate; and</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Section><Heading level="2"><MarginalNote><HistoricalNote>R.S., c. M-5</HistoricalNote></MarginalNote><TitleText>Consequential Amendment to the Members of Parliament Retiring Allowances Act</TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote><HistoricalNote>2005, c. 16, s. 14(1)</HistoricalNote></MarginalNote><Label>7</Label><Text>The definition <DefinedTermEn>annual allowance</DefinedTermEn> in subsection 2(1) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Members of Parliament Retiring Allowances Act</XRefExternal> is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><SectionPiece><Definition><Text><DefinedTermEn>annual allowance</DefinedTermEn> means an annual allowance payable to a member under section 62, 62.3 or 62.4 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Parliament of Canada Act</XRefExternal> or payable to a member under an appropriation Act as Deputy Chair or Assistant Deputy Chair of a committee. (<DefinedTermFr>indemnité annuelle</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Definition></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Section><Heading level="1"><TitleText>Related Amendments</TitleText></Heading><Heading level="2"><MarginalNote><HistoricalNote>R.S., c. A-1</HistoricalNote></MarginalNote><TitleText>Access to Information Act</TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote><HistoricalNote>2006, c. 9, s. 109(1)</HistoricalNote></MarginalNote><Label>8</Label><Text>Subsection 54(1) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Access to Information Act</XRefExternal> is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Section><MarginalNote>Appointment</MarginalNote><Label>54</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The Governor in Council shall, by commission under the Great Seal, appoint an Information Commissioner after consultation with the Leader of the Government in the Senate or Government Representative in the Senate, the Leader of the Opposition in the Senate, the Leader or Facilitator of every other recognized party or parliamentary group in the Senate and the leader of every recognized party in the House of Commons and approval of the appointment by resolution of the Senate and House of Commons.</Text></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Section><Heading level="2"><MarginalNote><HistoricalNote>R.S., c. A-17</HistoricalNote></MarginalNote><TitleText>Auditor General Act</TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote><HistoricalNote>2006, c. 9, s. 110(1)</HistoricalNote></MarginalNote><Label>9</Label><Text>Subsection 3(1) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Auditor General Act</XRefExternal> is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Section><MarginalNote>Appointment</MarginalNote><Label>3</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The Governor in Council shall, by commission under the Great Seal, appoint an Auditor General of Canada after consultation with the Leader of the Government in the Senate or Government Representative in the Senate, the Leader of the Opposition in the Senate, the Leader or Facilitator of every other recognized party or <Keep svc="1">parliamentary</Keep> group in the Senate and the leader of every recognized party in the House of Commons and approval of the appointment by resolution of the Senate and House of Commons.</Text></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Section><Heading level="2"><MarginalNote><HistoricalNote>R.S., c. P-21</HistoricalNote></MarginalNote><TitleText>Privacy Act</TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote><HistoricalNote>2006, c. 9, s. 118(1)</HistoricalNote></MarginalNote><Label>10</Label><Text>Subsection 53(1) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Privacy Act</XRefExternal> is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Section><MarginalNote>Appointment</MarginalNote><Label>53</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The Governor in Council shall, by commission under the Great Seal, appoint a Privacy Commissioner after consultation with the Leader of the Government in the Senate or Government Representative in the Senate, the Leader of the Opposition in the Senate, the Leader or Facilitator of every other recognized party or parliamentary group in the Senate and the leader of every recognized party in the House of Commons and approval of the appointment by resolution of the Senate and House of Commons.</Text></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Section><Heading level="2"><MarginalNote><HistoricalNote>R.S., c. 22 (4th Supp.)</HistoricalNote></MarginalNote><TitleText>Emergencies Act</TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><Label>11</Label><Text>Subsection 62(2) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Emergencies Act</XRefExternal> is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Subsection><MarginalNote>Membership</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The Parliamentary Review Committee shall include at least one member of the House of Commons from each party that has a recognized membership of 12 or more persons in that House and at least the Leader of the Government in the Senate or Government Representative in the Senate, or his or her nominee, the Leader of the Opposition in the Senate, or his or her nominee, and the Leader or Facilitator who is referred to in any of paragraphs 62.4(1)(c) to (e) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Parliament of Canada Act</XRefExternal>, or his or her nominee.</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Section><Heading level="2"><MarginalNote><HistoricalNote>R.S., c. 31 (4th Supp.)</HistoricalNote></MarginalNote><TitleText>Official Languages Act</TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote><HistoricalNote>2006, c. 9, s. 111(1)</HistoricalNote></MarginalNote><Label>12</Label><Text>Subsection 49(1) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Official Languages Act</XRefExternal> is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Section><MarginalNote>Appointment</MarginalNote><Label>49</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The Governor in Council shall, by commission under the Great Seal, appoint a Commissioner of Official Languages for Canada after consultation with the Leader of the Government in the Senate or Government Representative in the Senate, the Leader of the Opposition in the Senate, the Leader or Facilitator of every other recognized party or parliamentary group in the Senate and the leader of every recognized party in the House of Commons and approval of the appointment by resolution of the Senate and House of Commons.</Text></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Section><Heading level="2"><MarginalNote><HistoricalNote>R.S., c. 44 (4th Supp.); 2006, c. 9, s. 66</HistoricalNote></MarginalNote><TitleText>Lobbying Act</TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote><HistoricalNote>2006, c. 9, s. 68</HistoricalNote></MarginalNote><Label>13</Label><Text>Subsection 4.1(1) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Lobbying Act</XRefExternal> is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Section><MarginalNote>Commissioner of Lobbying</MarginalNote><Label>4.1</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The Governor in Council shall, by commission under the Great Seal, appoint a Commissioner of Lobbying after consultation with the Leader of the Government in the Senate or Government Representative in the Senate, the Leader of the Opposition in the Senate, the Leader or Facilitator of every other recognized party or parliamentary group in the Senate and the leader of every recognized party in the House of Commons and approval of the appointment by resolution of the Senate and House of Commons.</Text></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Section><Heading level="2"><MarginalNote><HistoricalNote>2005, c. 46</HistoricalNote></MarginalNote><TitleText>Public Servants Disclosure Protection Act</TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote><HistoricalNote>2006, c. 9, s. 119(1)</HistoricalNote></MarginalNote><Label>14</Label><Text>Subsection 39(1) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Public Servants Disclosure Protection Act</XRefExternal> is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Section><MarginalNote>Appointment</MarginalNote><Label>39</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The Governor in Council shall, by commission under the Great Seal, appoint a Public Sector Integrity Commissioner after consultation with the Leader of the Government in the Senate or Government Representative in the Senate, the Leader of the Opposition in the Senate, the Leader or Facilitator of every other recognized party or parliamentary group in the Senate and the leader of every recognized party in the House of Commons and approval of the appointment by resolution of the Senate and House of Commons.</Text></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Section><Heading level="2"><MarginalNote><HistoricalNote>2017, c. 15</HistoricalNote></MarginalNote><TitleText>National Security and Intelligence Committee of Parliamentarians Act</TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><Label>15</Label><Text>Subsection 5(2) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">National Security and Intelligence Committee of Parliamentarians Act</XRefExternal> is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Subsection><MarginalNote>Consultation</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>A member of the Senate may be appointed to the Committee only after the Prime Minister has consulted with the Leader of the Government in the Senate or Government Representative in the Senate, the Leader of the Opposition in the Senate and the Leader or Facilitator of every other recognized party or parliamentary group in the Senate.</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Section><Heading level="2"><MarginalNote><HistoricalNote>2019, c. 13, s. 2</HistoricalNote></MarginalNote><TitleText>National Security and Intelligence Review Agency Act</TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><Label>16</Label><Text>Paragraphs 4(2)(a) and (b) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">National Security and Intelligence Review Agency Act</XRefExternal> are replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>the Leader of the Government in the Senate or Government Representative in the Senate and the Leader of the Opposition in the Senate;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>the Leader or Facilitator of every recognized party or parliamentary group in the Senate;</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Section><Heading level="1"><TitleText>Coming into Force</TitleText></Heading><Section type="transitional"><MarginalNote>Order in council</MarginalNote><Label>17</Label><Subsection type="transitional"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Subject to subsection (2), this Act comes into force on a day to be fixed by order of the Governor in Council.</Text></Subsection><Subsection type="transitional"><MarginalNote>Royal recommendation</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>No order may be made under subsection (1) unless the appropriation of moneys for the purposes of this Act has been recommended by the Governor General and the moneys have been appropriated by Parliament.</Text></Subsection></Section></Body></Bill>