<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><Bill bill-origin="senate" bill-type="private-public" xml:lang="en" date-time="2021-10-19 11:47:02"><Identification><BillNumber>S-204</BillNumber><Parliament><Session>1</Session><Number>44</Number><RegnalYear><Year-s>70</Year-s><Monarch>Elizabeth II</Monarch></RegnalYear><Year-s>2021</Year-s></Parliament><LongTitle>An Act to amend the Customs Tariff (goods from Xinjiang)</LongTitle><ShortTitle status="unofficial">Xinjiang Manufactured Goods Importation Prohibition Act</ShortTitle><RunningHead> Xinjiang Manufactured Goods Importation Prohibition Act</RunningHead><BillHistory><Stages stage="first-reading-senate"><Date><YYYY>2021</YYYY><MM>11</MM><DD>24</DD></Date></Stages></BillHistory><BillSponsor>Senator Housakos</BillSponsor><BillRefNumber date-time="">4412121</BillRefNumber></Identification><Introduction><Summary><TitleText>SUMMARY</TitleText><Provision><Text>This enactment amends the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Customs Tariff</XRefExternal> to prohibit the importation of goods manufactured in the Xinjiang Uyghur Autonomous Region of the People's Republic of China.</Text></Provision></Summary><Preamble><Provision><MarginalNote>Preamble</MarginalNote><Text>Whereas the Chinese Communist Party is engaged in a series of human rights abuses as part of an ongoing genocide against Uyghur and Turkic Muslims and other ethnic and religious minorities in the Xinjiang Uyghur Autonomous
Region of the People’s Republic of China;</Text></Provision><Provision><Text>Whereas these actions have been recognized as a genocide by numerous international bodies and jurisdictions including the United States of America and the United Kingdom;</Text></Provision><Provision><Text>Whereas the House of Commons has recognized the ongoing human rights abuses committed against Uyghur and Turkic Muslims as genocide;</Text></Provision><Provision><Text>Whereas the Senate has called for Magnitsky sanctions against officials of the Chinese Communist Party for their involvement in these genocidal actions;</Text></Provision><Provision><Text>And whereas Canada is a nation built on the rule of law, freedom of religion and the principles of basic human rights;</Text></Provision></Preamble><Enacts><Provision><Text>Now, therefore, Her Majesty, by and with the advice and consent of the Senate and House of Commons of Canada, enacts as follows:</Text></Provision></Enacts></Introduction><Body><Heading level="1"><TitleText>Short Title</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Short title</MarginalNote><Label>1</Label><Text>This Act may be cited as the <Emphasis style="italic">Xinjiang Manufactured Goods Importation Prohibition Act</Emphasis>.</Text></Section><Heading level="1"><MarginalNote><HistoricalNote>1997, c. 36</HistoricalNote></MarginalNote><TitleText><XRefExternal reference-type="act">Customs Tariff</XRefExternal></TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><Label>2</Label><Text>The <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Customs Tariff</XRefExternal> is amended by adding the following after section 136:</Text><AmendedText change="ins"><Section><MarginalNote>Prohibited imports</MarginalNote><Label>136.1</Label><Text>Despite anything in this Act, the importation of goods manufactured or produced wholly or in part in the Xinjiang Uyghur Autonomous Region of the People’s Republic of China is prohibited.</Text></Section></AmendedText><ExplanatoryNote><TitleText><XRefExternal reference-type="act">Customs Tariff</XRefExternal></TitleText><Label><Emphasis style="italic">Clause 2</Emphasis>:</Label><ExplanatoryText>New.</ExplanatoryText></ExplanatoryNote></Section><Heading level="1"><TitleText>Coming into Force</TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote>First anniversary of royal assent</MarginalNote><Label>3</Label><Text>This Act comes into force on the first anniversary of the day on which it receives royal assent.</Text></Section></Body></Bill>