<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><Bill bill-origin="senate" bill-type="private-public" xml:lang="en" date-time="2021-11-17 11:02:01"><Identification><BillNumber>S-209</BillNumber><Parliament><Session>1</Session><Number>44</Number><RegnalYear><Year-s>70-71</Year-s><Monarch>Elizabeth II – 1-2 Charles III</Monarch></RegnalYear><Year-s>2021-2022-2023-2024</Year-s></Parliament><LongTitle>An Act respecting Pandemic Observance Day</LongTitle><ShortTitle status="unofficial">Pandemic Day Act</ShortTitle><RunningHead>Pandemic Day Act</RunningHead><BillHistory><Stages stage="assented-to"><Date><YYYY>2024</YYYY><MM>4</MM><DD>30</DD></Date></Stages></BillHistory><Chapter><ConsolidatedNumber /><AnnualStatuteId><AnnualStatuteNumber>7</AnnualStatuteNumber><YYYY>2024</YYYY></AnnualStatuteId></Chapter><BillRefNumber date-time="">4412124</BillRefNumber></Identification><Introduction><Summary><TitleText>SUMMARY</TitleText><Provision><Text>This enactment designates March 11th in each and every year as “Pandemic Observance Day”.</Text></Provision></Summary><Preamble><Provision pointsize="10" topmarginspacing="-6" language-align="yes"><MarginalNote>Preamble</MarginalNote><Text>Whereas, on March 11, 2020, the World Health Organization characterized the coronavirus disease (COVID-19) epidemic as a global pandemic;</Text></Provision><Provision><Text>Whereas March 11, 2021, was designated — by order in council on March 8, 2021, and by proclamation on March 31, 2021 — as a “National Day of Observance” to honour those who have died of COVID-19, to recognize those working on the front lines and to acknowledge COVID-19’s serious effects on the health of Canada's population;</Text></Provision><Provision><Text>Whereas it is important to acknowledge the multidimensional effects of the pandemic on every person in Canada;</Text></Provision><Provision><Text>Whereas this pandemic has worsened the various forms of inequality in Canada and has had a disproportionate impact on the vulnerable people within society and members of historically disadvantaged groups;</Text></Provision><Provision><Text>And whereas it is fitting that March 11 of each year be officially designated as “Pandemic Observance Day” in order to give the Canadian public an opportunity to commemorate the efforts to get through the pandemic, to remember its effects and to reflect on ways to prepare for any future pandemics;</Text></Provision></Preamble><Enacts><Provision language-align="yes"><Text>Now, therefore, His Majesty, by and with the advice and consent of the Senate and House of Commons of Canada, enacts as follows:
</Text></Provision></Enacts></Introduction><Body><Heading level="1"><TitleText>Short Title</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Short title</MarginalNote><Label>1</Label><Text>This Act may be cited as the <Emphasis style="italic">Pandemic Day Act</Emphasis>.</Text></Section><Heading level="1"><TitleText>Pandemic Observance Day</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Pandemic Observance Day</MarginalNote><Label>2</Label><Text>Throughout Canada, in each and every year, the 11th day of March is to be known as “Pandemic Observance Day”.</Text></Section></Body></Bill>