<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><Bill bill-origin="senate" bill-type="private-public" xml:lang="en" date-time="2021-06-04 15:12:27"><Identification><BillNumber>S-215</BillNumber><Parliament><Session>1</Session><Number>44</Number><RegnalYear><Year-s>70</Year-s><Monarch>Elizabeth II</Monarch></RegnalYear><Year-s>2021</Year-s></Parliament><LongTitle>An Act respecting measures in relation to the financial stability of post-secondary institutions</LongTitle><ShortTitle status="unofficial">Post-Secondary Institutions Bankruptcy Protection Act</ShortTitle><RunningHead>Post-Secondary Institutions Bankruptcy Protection Act</RunningHead><BillHistory><Stages stage="first-reading-senate"><Date><YYYY>2021</YYYY><MM>11</MM><DD>24</DD></Date></Stages></BillHistory><BillSponsor>Senator Moncion</BillSponsor><BillRefNumber date-time="">4412112</BillRefNumber></Identification><Introduction><Summary><TitleText>SUMMARY</TitleText><Provision><Text>This enactment provides for the development of a proposal for federal initiatives designed to ensure the financial stability of post-secondary institutions. It also amends the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Bankruptcy and Insolvency Act</XRefExternal> and the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Companies’ Creditors Arrangement Act</XRefExternal> to exclude post-secondary educational institutions from the definitions of <DefinitionEnOnly>corporation</DefinitionEnOnly> and <DefinitionEnOnly>company</DefinitionEnOnly> under those Acts, respectively.</Text></Provision></Summary><Enacts><Provision><Text>Her Majesty, by and with the advice and consent of the Senate and House of Commons of Canada, enacts as follows:</Text></Provision></Enacts></Introduction><Body><Heading level="1"><TitleText>Short Title</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Short title</MarginalNote><Label>1</Label><Text>This Act may be cited as the <Emphasis style="italic">Post-Secondary Institutions Bankruptcy Protection Act</Emphasis>.</Text></Section><Heading level="1"><TitleText>Interpretation</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Interpretation</MarginalNote><Label>2</Label><Text>The following definitions apply in this Act.</Text><Definition><Text><DefinedTermEn>institution</DefinedTermEn> means an educational institution set out in any of the following:</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>the <XRefExternal reference-type="other">Master List of Designated Educational Institutions</XRefExternal> published by the Government of Canada on its website;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>the <XRefExternal reference-type="other">Master List of Certified Educational Institutions</XRefExternal> published by the Government of Canada on its website;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(c)</Label><Text>the <XRefExternal reference-type="other">Directory of Educational Institutions and Programs</XRefExternal> published by the Government of Quebec on its website. (<DefinedTermFr>établissement</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Paragraph></Definition><Definition><Text><DefinedTermEn>Minister</DefinedTermEn> means the member of the Queen’s Privy Council for Canada designated by the Governor in Council as the Minister for the purposes of this Act. (<DefinedTermFr>ministre</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Definition></Section><Heading level="1"><TitleText>Designation of Minister</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Power of Governor in Council</MarginalNote><Label>3</Label><Text>The Governor in Council may designate a member of the Queen’s Privy Council for Canada to be the Minister for the purposes of this Act.</Text></Section><Heading level="1"><TitleText>Proposal</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Proposal</MarginalNote><Label>4</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The Minister must develop a proposal for federal initiatives designed to</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>reduce the risk that an institution becomes bankrupt or insolvent;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>protect students, faculty and staff in the event that an institution becomes bankrupt or insolvent; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(c)</Label><Text>support communities that would be impacted by an institution becoming bankrupt or insolvent.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Consultation</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The proposal under subsection (1) must be developed in consultation with representatives from</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>institutions;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>provincial and municipal governments;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(c)</Label><Text>groups and associations of — or advocating on behalf of — students, faculty and staff of institutions.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Inclusion</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>The proposal must include both a list of legislative amendments that the Government of Canada intends to introduce and a timeline for their introduction in order to achieve the objectives described in paragraphs (1)(a) to (c).</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Time limit</MarginalNote><Label>(4)</Label><Text>The development of the proposal must be completed as soon as practicable, but no later than one year after the day on which this section comes into force. </Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Tabling in Parliament</MarginalNote><Label>(5)</Label><Text>The Minister must cause the proposal to be tabled in each House of Parliament as soon as practicable after it has been developed.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Action plan made public</MarginalNote><Label>(6)</Label><Text>After the proposal is tabled, the Minister must make it public.</Text></Subsection></Section><Heading level="1"><MarginalNote><HistoricalNote>R.S., c. B-3</HistoricalNote></MarginalNote><TitleText><XRefExternal reference-type="other">Bankruptcy and Insolvency Act</XRefExternal></TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><Label>5</Label><Text>The definition <DefinedTermEn>corporation</DefinedTermEn> in section 2 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Bankruptcy and Insolvency Act</XRefExternal> is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><SectionPiece><Definition><Text><DefinedTermEn>corporation</DefinedTermEn> means <Ins>any</Ins> company, <Ins>corporation</Ins> or legal person incorporated by or under an Act of Parliament or of the legislature of a province, <Ins>any</Ins> incorporated company <Ins>having assets or doing</Ins> business in Canada, wherever incorporated, <Ins>and any</Ins> income trust, but does not include</Text><Paragraph change="ins"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>post-secondary educational institutions that receive from a government or a municipality funds that are paid for the purpose of assisting them in the ongoing provision of educational services to the general public,</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label><Ins>(b)</Ins></Label><Text><DefinitionEnOnly>banks</DefinitionEnOnly> <Ins>and</Ins> <DefinitionEnOnly>authorized foreign banks</DefinitionEnOnly> within the meaning of section 2 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Bank Act</XRefExternal>,</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label><Ins>(c)</Ins></Label><Text>insurance companies, <Ins>and</Ins></Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label><Ins>(d)</Ins></Label><Text>companies <Ins>to which the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Trust and Loan Companies Act</XRefExternal> applies</Ins>; (<DefinedTermFr>personne morale</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Paragraph></Definition></SectionPiece></AmendedText><ExplanatoryNote><TitleText><XRefExternal reference-type="other">Bankruptcy and Insolvency Act</XRefExternal></TitleText><Label><Emphasis style="italic">Clause 5</Emphasis>:</Label><ExplanatoryText>Existing text of the definition:</ExplanatoryText><ExistingText><SectionPiece><Definition><Text><DefinedTermEn>corporation</DefinedTermEn> means a company or legal person that is incorporated by or under an Act of Parliament or of the legislature of a province, an incorporated company, wherever incorporated, that is authorized to carry on business in Canada or has an office or property in Canada or an income trust, but does not include banks, authorized foreign banks within the meaning of section 2 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Bank Act</XRefExternal>, insurance companies, trust companies or loan companies; <DefinedTermFr>(personne morale</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Definition></SectionPiece></ExistingText></ExplanatoryNote></Section><Heading level="1"><MarginalNote><HistoricalNote>R.S., c. C-36</HistoricalNote></MarginalNote><TitleText><XRefExternal reference-type="act">Companies’ Creditors Arrangement Act</XRefExternal></TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><Label>6</Label><Text>The definition <DefinedTermEn>company</DefinedTermEn> in section 2 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Companies’ Creditors Arrangement Act</XRefExternal> is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><SectionPiece><Definition><Text><DefinedTermEn>company</DefinedTermEn> means any company, corporation or legal person incorporated by or under an Act of Parliament or of the legislature of a province, any incorporated company having assets or doing business in Canada, wherever incorporated, and any income trust, but does not include</Text><Paragraph change="ins"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>post-secondary educational institutions that receive from a government or a municipality funds that are paid for the purpose of assisting them in the ongoing provision of educational services to the general public,</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label><Ins>(b)</Ins></Label><Text><DefinitionEnOnly>banks</DefinitionEnOnly> <Ins>and</Ins> <DefinitionEnOnly>authorized foreign banks</DefinitionEnOnly> within the meaning of section 2 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Bank Act</XRefExternal>,</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label><Ins>(c)</Ins></Label><Text>telegraph companies,</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label><Ins>(d)</Ins></Label><Text>insurance companies, and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label><Ins>(e)</Ins></Label><Text>companies to which the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Trust and Loan Companies Act</XRefExternal> applies; (<DefinedTermFr>compagnie</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Paragraph></Definition></SectionPiece></AmendedText><ExplanatoryNote><TitleText><XRefExternal reference-type="act">Companies’ Creditors Arrangement Act</XRefExternal></TitleText><Label><Emphasis style="italic">Clause 6</Emphasis>:</Label><ExplanatoryText>Existing text of the definition:</ExplanatoryText><ExistingText><SectionPiece><Definition><Text><DefinedTermEn>company</DefinedTermEn> means any company, corporation or legal person incorporated by or under an Act of Parliament or of the legislature of a province, any incorporated company having assets or doing business in Canada, wherever incorporated, and any income trust, but does not include banks, authorized foreign banks within the meaning of section 2 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Bank Act</XRefExternal>, telegraph companies, insurance companies and companies to which the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Trust and Loan Companies Act</XRefExternal> applies; (<DefinedTermFr>compagnie</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Definition></SectionPiece></ExistingText></ExplanatoryNote></Section><Heading level="1"><TitleText>Coming into Force</TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote>Order in council</MarginalNote><Label>7</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Sections 5 and 6 come into force on a day or days to be fixed by order of the Governor in Council, on recommendation of the Minister.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Recommendation</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The Minister may only make a recommendation under subsection (1) if the Minister considers that doing so is consistent with the proposal developed under section 4.</Text></Subsection></Section></Body></Bill>