<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><Bill bill-origin="senate" bill-type="private-public" xml:lang="en" date-time="2018-03-19 15:13:11"><Identification><BillNumber>S-214</BillNumber><Parliament><Session>1</Session><Number>44</Number><RegnalYear><Year-s>70-71</Year-s><Monarch>Elizabeth II 芒聙聯 1 Charles III</Monarch></RegnalYear><Year-s>2021-2022-2023</Year-s></Parliament><LongTitle>An Act to establish International Mother Language Day</LongTitle><ShortTitle status="unofficial">International Mother Language Day Act</ShortTitle><RunningHead>International Mother Language Day Act</RunningHead><BillHistory><Stages stage="assented-to"><Date><YYYY>2023</YYYY><MM>4</MM><DD>27</DD></Date></Stages></BillHistory><Chapter><ConsolidatedNumber /><AnnualStatuteId><AnnualStatuteNumber>5</AnnualStatuteNumber><YYYY>2023</YYYY></AnnualStatuteId></Chapter><BillRefNumber date-time="">4411716</BillRefNumber></Identification><Introduction><Summary><TitleText>SUMMARY</TitleText><Provision><Text>This enactment designates the 21st day of February in each and every year as 芒聙聹International Mother Language Day芒聙聺.</Text></Provision></Summary><Preamble><Provision pointsize="10" topmarginspacing="-6" language-align="yes"><MarginalNote>Preamble</MarginalNote><Text>Whereas English and French are Canada芒聙聶s official languages;</Text></Provision><Provision><Text>Whereas more than 60 different Aboriginal languages are spoken in Canada;</Text></Provision><Provision><Text>Whereas Canadians speak a multitude of languages that greatly enrich Canada and its culture;</Text></Provision><Provision><Text>Whereas, in November 1999, International Mother Language Day was proclaimed by the General Conference of the United Nations Educational, Scientific and Cultural Organization;</Text></Provision><Provision><Text>Whereas, in May 2007, the United Nations General Assembly called upon Member States 芒聙聹to promote the preservation and protection of all languages used by peoples of the world芒聙聺;</Text></Provision><Provision><Text>Whereas some Canadian provinces and cities already recognize International Mother Language Day;</Text></Provision><Provision><Text>And whereas the Parliament of Canada wishes to <Keep>recognize</Keep> the value of linguistic and cultural diversity;</Text></Provision></Preamble><Enacts><Provision><Text>Now, therefore, His Majesty, by and with the advice and consent of the Senate and House of Commons of Canada, enacts as follows:</Text></Provision></Enacts></Introduction><Body><Heading level="1"><TitleText>Short Title</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Short Title</MarginalNote><Label>1</Label><Text>This Act may be cited as the <Emphasis style="italic">International Mother Language Day Act</Emphasis>.</Text></Section><Heading level="1"><TitleText>International Mother Language Day</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>International Mother Language Day</MarginalNote><Label>2</Label><Text>Throughout Canada, in each and every year, the 21st day of February is to be known as 芒聙聹International Mother Language Day芒聙聺.</Text></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Not a legal holiday</MarginalNote><Label>3</Label><Text>For greater certainty, International Mother Language Day is not a legal holiday or a non-juridical day.</Text></Section></Body></Bill>