<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><Bill bill-origin="senate" bill-type="private-public" xml:lang="en" date-time="2020-01-23 14:57:01"><Identification><BillNumber>S-218</BillNumber><Parliament><Session>1</Session><Number>44</Number><RegnalYear><Year-s>70</Year-s><Monarch>Elizabeth II</Monarch></RegnalYear><Year-s>2021</Year-s></Parliament><LongTitle>An Act to amend the Department for Women and Gender Equality Act </LongTitle><ShortTitle status="unofficial" /><RunningHead>An Act to amend the Department for Women and Gender Equality Act</RunningHead><BillHistory><Stages stage="first-reading-senate"><Date><YYYY>2021</YYYY><MM>11</MM><DD>24</DD></Date></Stages></BillHistory><BillSponsor>Senator M<Emphasis style="smallcaps">c</Emphasis>Callum</BillSponsor><BillRefNumber date-time="">4411922</BillRefNumber></Identification><Introduction><Summary><TitleText>SUMMARY</TitleText><Provision><Text>This enactment amends the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Department for Women and Gender Equality Act</XRefExternal> to require the Minister for Women and Gender Equality to examine the potential effects of certain bills and amendments on women and to report to Parliament accordingly.</Text></Provision></Summary><Enacts><Provision><Text>Her Majesty, by and with the advice and consent of the Senate and House of Commons of Canada, <Keep>enacts</Keep> as follows:</Text></Provision></Enacts></Introduction><Body><Heading level="1"><MarginalNote><HistoricalNote>2018, c. 27, s. 661</HistoricalNote></MarginalNote><TitleText>Department for Women and Gender Equality Act</TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><Label>1</Label><Text>The <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Department for Women and Gender Equality Act</XRefExternal> is amended by adding the following after section 5:</Text><AmendedText change="ins"><Heading level="1"><TitleText>Duty to Examine Bills for Their Effects on Women</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Examination of Government Bills</MarginalNote><Label>5.1</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The Minister must examine every Bill introduced in either House of Parliament by a minister or other representative of the Crown and cause to be tabled, in the House in which the Bill originates, a statement that sets out potential effects of the Bill on women, particularly Indigenous women.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Tabling of statement</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The Minister must cause the statement to be tabled no later than two sitting days after the day on which the Bill is introduced.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Examination of other Bills</MarginalNote><Label>5.2</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>If a Bill that was not examined under subsection 5.1(1) is referred to a committee of the House in which the Bill originates, the Minister must examine the Bill and cause to be tabled in that House a statement setting out potential effects of the Bill on women, and particularly on  Indigenous women.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Tabling of statement</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The Minister must cause the statement to be tabled no later than 10 sitting days after the day on which the Bill is referred to a committee. </Text></Subsection></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Examination of amendments</MarginalNote><Label>5.3</Label><Text>If a Bill is amended by the House in which it originates and that Bill is received by the other House, the Minister must cause to be tabled in that House, no later than seven sitting days after that House receives the Bill,  a statement setting out potential effects of amendments made by the House in which the Bill originates on women, and particularly on Indigenous women.</Text></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Publication of each  statement</MarginalNote><Label>5.4</Label><Text>The Minister must publish every statement on the departmental website no later than the day after the day on which it is tabled.</Text></Section></AmendedText><ExplanatoryNote><TitleText>Department for Women and Gender Equality Act</TitleText><Label><Emphasis style="italic">Clause 1</Emphasis>:</Label><ExplanatoryText>New.</ExplanatoryText></ExplanatoryNote></Section><Heading level="1" type="transitional"><TitleText>Transitional Provision</TitleText></Heading><Section type="transitional"><Label>2</Label><Text>Sections 5.1 to 5.4 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Department for Women and Gender Equality Act</XRefExternal> apply only in respect of a Bill introduced in Parliament on or after the day that is six months after the day on which this Act receives royal assent.</Text></Section></Body></Bill>