<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><Bill bill-origin="senate" bill-type="private-public" xml:lang="en" date-time="2021-05-03 09:19:29"><Identification><BillNumber>S-238</BillNumber><Parliament><Session>1</Session><Number>44</Number><RegnalYear><Year-s>70-71</Year-s><Monarch>Elizabeth II</Monarch></RegnalYear><Year-s>2021-2022</Year-s></Parliament><LongTitle>An Act to amend the Criminal Code and the Canadian Victims Bill of Rights (information about the victim)</LongTitle><ShortTitle status="unofficial"> Véronique Barbe Act</ShortTitle><RunningHead> Véronique Barbe Act</RunningHead><BillHistory><Stages stage="first-reading-senate"><Date><YYYY>2022</YYYY><MM>2</MM><DD>24</DD></Date></Stages></BillHistory><BillSponsor>Senator Boisvenu</BillSponsor><BillRefNumber date-time="">4412111</BillRefNumber></Identification><Introduction><Summary><TitleText>SUMMARY</TitleText><Provision><Text>This enactment amends provisions of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Criminal Code</XRefExternal> in order to provide for the possibility of ordering an accused, defendant, offender or other person to refrain from publishing, distributing, transmitting or making available on the Internet any information concerning victims and, in some cases, other persons.</Text></Provision><Provision language-align="yes"><Text>It also amends the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Canadian Victims Bill of Rights</XRefExternal> by adding a right to have reasonable measures taken in order to prohibit an offender from publishing, distributing, transmitting or making available on the Internet any information concerning victims.</Text></Provision></Summary><Enacts><Provision><Text>Her Majesty, by and with the advice and consent of the Senate and House of Commons of Canada, enacts as follows:</Text></Provision></Enacts></Introduction><Body><Heading level="1"><TitleText>Short Title</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Short title</MarginalNote><Label>1</Label><Text>This Act may be cited as the <Emphasis style="italic">Véronique Barbe Act</Emphasis>.</Text></Section><Heading level="1"><MarginalNote><HistoricalNote>R.S., c. C-46</HistoricalNote></MarginalNote><TitleText>Criminal Code</TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><Label>2</Label><Text>Subsection 501(3) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Criminal Code</XRefExternal> is amended by adding the following after paragraph (d):</Text><AmendedText change="ins"><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(d.1)</Label><Text>abstain from publishing, distributing, transmitting or making accessible on the Internet any information concerning the victim of the offence in question;</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText><ExplanatoryNote><TitleText>Criminal Code</TitleText><Label><Emphasis style="italic">Clause 2</Emphasis>:</Label><ExplanatoryText>New.</ExplanatoryText></ExplanatoryNote></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>3</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Subsection 515(4) of the Act is amended by adding the following after paragraph (d):</Text><AmendedText change="ins"><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(d.1)</Label><Text>abstain from publishing, distributing, transmitting or making accessible on the Internet any information concerning the victim of the offence in question;</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Subsection 515(4.2) of the Act is amended by adding the following after paragraph (a):</Text><AmendedText change="ins"><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(a.01)</Label><Text>that the accused abstain from publishing, distributing, transmitting or making accessible on the Internet any information concerning the victim of the offence in question;</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText><ExplanatoryNote><Label><Emphasis style="italic">Clause 3</Emphasis>: (1) and (2)</Label><ExplanatoryText>New.</ExplanatoryText></ExplanatoryNote></Subsection><Subsection><Label>(3)</Label><Text>Subsection 515(12) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><Subsection><MarginalNote>Order re no communication</MarginalNote><Label>(12)</Label><Text>A justice who orders that an accused be detained in custody under this section may include in the order a direction that the accused must abstain from <Ins>either or both of the following:</Ins></Text><Paragraph><Label><Ins>(a)</Ins></Label><Text>communicating, directly or indirectly, with any victim, witness or other person identified in the order, except in accordance with such conditions specified in the order as the justice considers necessary<Ins>; or</Ins></Text></Paragraph><Paragraph change="ins"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>publishing, distributing, transmitting or making accessible on the Internet any information concerning the victim of the offence in question.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection></AmendedText></Subsection><ExplanatoryNote><Label>(3)</Label><ExplanatoryText>Existing text of subsection 514(12):</ExplanatoryText><ExistingText><Subsection><Label>(12)</Label><Text>A justice who orders that an accused be detained in custody under this section may include in the order a direction that the accused abstain from communicating, directly or indirectly, with any victim, witness or other person identified in the order, except in accordance with such conditions specified in the order as the justice considers necessary.</Text></Subsection></ExistingText></ExplanatoryNote></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>4</Label><Text>Subsection 516(2) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><Subsection><MarginalNote>Detention pending bail hearing</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>A justice who remands an accused to custody under subsection (1) or subsection 515(11) may order that the accused abstain from <Ins>either or both of the following:</Ins></Text><Paragraph><Label><Ins>(a)</Ins></Label><Text>communicating, directly or indirectly, with any victim, witness or other person identified in the order, except in accordance with any conditions specified in the order that the justice considers necessary<Ins>; or</Ins></Text></Paragraph><Paragraph change="ins"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>publishing, distributing, transmitting or making accessible on the Internet any information concerning the victim of the offence in question.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection></AmendedText><ExplanatoryNote><Label><Emphasis style="italic">Clause 4</Emphasis>:</Label><ExplanatoryText>Existing text of subsection 516(2):</ExplanatoryText><ExistingText><Subsection><Label>(2)</Label><Text>A justice who remands an accused to custody under subsection (1) or subsection 515(11) may order that the accused abstain from communicating, directly or indirectly, with any victim, witness or other person identified in the order, except in accordance with any conditions specified in the order that the justice considers necessary.</Text></Subsection></ExistingText></ExplanatoryNote></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>5</Label><Text>Subsection 522(2.1) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><Subsection><MarginalNote>Order re no communication</MarginalNote><Label>(2.1)</Label><Text>A judge referred to in subsection (2) who orders that an accused be detained in custody under this section may include in the order a direction that the accused <Ins>must</Ins> abstain from <Ins>either or both of the following:</Ins></Text><Paragraph><Label><Ins>(a)</Ins></Label><Text>communicating, directly or indirectly, with any victim, witness or other person identified in the order, except in accordance with such conditions specified in the order as the judge considers necessary<Ins>; or</Ins></Text></Paragraph><Paragraph change="ins"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>publishing, distributing, transmitting or making accessible on the Internet any information concerning the victim of the offence in question.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection></AmendedText><ExplanatoryNote><Label><Emphasis style="italic">Clause 5</Emphasis>:</Label><ExplanatoryText>Existing text of subsection 522(2.1):</ExplanatoryText><ExistingText><Subsection><Label>(2.1)</Label><Text>A judge referred to in subsection (2) who orders that an accused be detained in custody under this section may include in the order a direction that the accused abstain from communicating, directly or indirectly, with any victim, witness or other person identified in the order except in accordance with such conditions specified in the order as the judge considers necessary.</Text></Subsection></ExistingText></ExplanatoryNote></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>6</Label><Text>Section 672.542 of the Act is amended by striking out “or” at the end of paragraph (a) and by adding the following after paragraph (a):</Text><AmendedText change="ins"><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(a.1)</Label><Text>abstain from publishing, distributing, transmitting or making accessible on the Internet any information concerning the victim of the offence for which the offender is being sentenced; or</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText><ExplanatoryNote><Label><Emphasis style="italic">Clause 6</Emphasis>:</Label><ExplanatoryText>New.</ExplanatoryText></ExplanatoryNote></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>7</Label><Text>Subsection 732.1(3) of the Act is amended by adding the following after paragraph (a.1):</Text><AmendedText change="ins"><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(a.2)</Label><Text>abstain from publishing, distributing, transmitting or making accessible on the Internet any information concerning the victim of the offence for which the offender is being sentenced;</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText><ExplanatoryNote><Label><Emphasis style="italic">Clause 7</Emphasis>:</Label><ExplanatoryText>New.</ExplanatoryText></ExplanatoryNote></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>8</Label><Text>Subsection 742.3(2) of the Act is amended by adding the following after paragraph (a.3):</Text><AmendedText change="ins"><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(a.4)</Label><Text>abstain from publishing, distributing, transmitting or making accessible on the Internet any information concerning the victim of the offence for which the offender is being sentenced;</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText><ExplanatoryNote><Label><Emphasis style="italic">Clause 8</Emphasis>:</Label><ExplanatoryText>New.</ExplanatoryText></ExplanatoryNote></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>9</Label><Text>Subsection 743.21(1) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><Section><MarginalNote>Non-communication order</MarginalNote><Label>743.21</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The sentencing judge may order that the <Ins>accused must abstain from either or both of the following:</Ins></Text><Paragraph><Label><Ins>(a)</Ins></Label><Text>communicating, directly or indirectly, with any victim, witness or other person identified in the order, except in accordance with <Ins>such</Ins> conditions specified in the order <Ins>as the justice</Ins> considers necessary<Ins>; or</Ins></Text></Paragraph><Paragraph change="ins"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>publishing, distributing, transmitting or making accessible on the Internet any information concerning the victim of the offence for which the offender is being sentenced.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection></Section></AmendedText><ExplanatoryNote><Label><Emphasis style="italic">Clause 9</Emphasis>:</Label><ExplanatoryText>Existing text of subsection 743.21(1):</ExplanatoryText><ExistingText><Section><Label>743.21</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The sentencing judge may issue an order prohibiting the offender from communicating, directly or indirectly, with any victim, witness or other person identified in the order during the custodial period of the sentence, except in accordance with any conditions specified in the order that the sentencing judge considers necessary.</Text></Subsection></Section></ExistingText></ExplanatoryNote></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>10</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The portion of subsection 810(3.2) of the Act before paragraph (a) is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><Subsection><MarginalNote>Conditions in recognizance</MarginalNote><Label>(3.2)</Label><Text>Before making an order under subsection (3), the justice or the summary conviction court shall consider whether it is desirable, in the interests of the safety of the
informant, of the person on whose behalf the information was laid or of that person’s intimate partner or child, as the case may be, to add <Ins>any</Ins> of the following conditions to the recognizance<Ins>:</Ins></Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Subsection 810(3.2) of the Act is amended by striking out “or” at the end of paragraph (a), by adding “or” after paragraph (b) and by adding the following after paragraph (b):</Text><AmendedText change="ins"><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(c)</Label><Text>a condition prohibiting the defendant from publishing, distributing, transmitting or making accessible on the Internet any information concerning the person on whose behalf the information was laid or that person’s intimate partner or child.</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText><ExplanatoryNote><Label><Emphasis style="italic">Clause 10</Emphasis>:</Label><ExplanatoryText>Existing text of subsection 810(3.2):</ExplanatoryText><ExistingText><Subsection><Label>(3.2)</Label><Text>Before making an order under subsection (3), the justice or the summary conviction court shall consider whether it is desirable, in the interests of the safety of the informant, of the person on whose behalf the information was laid or of that person’s intimate partner or child, as the case may be, to add either or both of the following conditions to the recognizance,</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>a condition prohibiting the defendant from being at, or within a distance specified in the recognizance from, a place specified in the recognizance where the person on whose behalf the information was laid or that person’s intimate partner or child, as the case may be, is regularly found; or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label><Emphasis style="bold">(b)</Emphasis></Label><Text>a condition prohibiting the defendant from communicating, in whole or in part, directly or indirectly, with the person on whose behalf the information was laid or that person’s intimate partner or child, as the case may be.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection></ExistingText></ExplanatoryNote></Subsection></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>11</Label><Text>Subsection 810.02(6) of the Act is amended by adding the following after paragraph (d):</Text><AmendedText change="ins"><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(d.1)</Label><Text>prohibit the defendant from publishing, distributing, transmitting or making accessible on the Internet any information concerning any person identified in the recognizance;</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText><ExplanatoryNote><Label><Emphasis style="italic">Clause 11</Emphasis>:</Label><ExplanatoryText>New.</ExplanatoryText></ExplanatoryNote></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>12</Label><Text>Subsection 810.1(3.02) of the Act is amended by adding the following after paragraph (b.1):</Text><AmendedText change="ins"><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(b.2)</Label><Text>prohibit the defendant from publishing, distributing, transmitting or making accessible on the Internet any information concerning any person identified in the recognizance;</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText><ExplanatoryNote><Label><Emphasis style="italic">Clause 12</Emphasis>:</Label><ExplanatoryText>New.</ExplanatoryText></ExplanatoryNote></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>13</Label><Text>Paragraph (q) of Form 32 of Part XXVIII of the Act after the heading “<Emphasis style="italic">List of Conditions</Emphasis>” is amended by replacing “– abstains from communicating, directly or indirectly, with victim, witness or other specified person except in accordance with conditions specified by judge, provincial court judge or justice; and” with the following:</Text><AmendedText><FormGroup><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1" list-item="no" language-align="no"><Label>–</Label><Text>abstains from communicating, directly or indirectly, with victim, witness or other specified person except in accordance with conditions specified by judge, provincial court judge or justice;</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1" list-item="no" language-align="no" change="ins"><Label>–</Label><Text>abstains from publishing, distributing, transmitting or making accessible on the Internet any information concerning the victim or other specified person; and</Text></Provision></FormGroup></AmendedText><ExplanatoryNote><Label><Emphasis style="italic">Clause 13</Emphasis>:</Label><ExplanatoryText>Existing text of relevant portions of <Emphasis style="italic">List of Conditions</Emphasis> in Form 32:</ExplanatoryText><ExistingText><FormGroup><Provision format-ref="centered" list-item="no" language-align="yes" pointsize="8"><Text><Emphasis style="italic">List of Conditions</Emphasis></Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1" list-item="no" language-align="no" pointsize="8"><Label>. . .</Label><Text /></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1" list-item="no" language-align="no" pointsize="8"><Label>(q)</Label><Text>any other reasonable conditions, including:</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1" list-item="no" language-align="no" pointsize="8"><Label /><Text>. . .</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1" list-item="no" language-align="no" pointsize="8"><Label>–</Label><Text>abstains from communicating, directly or indirectly, with victim, witness or other specified person except in accordance with conditions specified by judge, provincial court judge or justice; and</Text><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1" list-item="no" language-align="no" pointsize="8"><Label /><Text>. . .</Text></Provision></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1" list-item="no" language-align="no" pointsize="8"><Text /></Provision></FormGroup></ExistingText></ExplanatoryNote></Section><Heading level="1"><MarginalNote><HistoricalNote>2015, c. 13, s. 2</HistoricalNote></MarginalNote><TitleText><XRefExternal reference-type="act">Canadian Victims Bill of Rights</XRefExternal></TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><Label>14</Label><Text>The <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Canadian Victims Bill of Rights</XRefExternal> is amended by adding the following after section 11:</Text><AmendedText change="ins"><Section><MarginalNote>Publication or distribution of information concerning the victim</MarginalNote><Label>11.1</Label><Text>Every victim has the right to have reasonable and necessary measures taken by the appropriate authorities in the criminal justice system to prevent the offender from publishing, distributing, transmitting or making accessible on the Internet any information concerning the victim.</Text></Section></AmendedText><ExplanatoryNote><TitleText><XRefExternal reference-type="act">Canadian Victims Bill of Rights</XRefExternal></TitleText><Label><Emphasis style="italic">Clause 14</Emphasis>:</Label><ExplanatoryText>New.</ExplanatoryText></ExplanatoryNote></Section><Heading level="1"><TitleText>Coordinating Amendment</TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote>Bill S-205</MarginalNote><Label>15</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Subsection (2) applies if Bill S-205, introduced in the 1st session of the 44th Parliament and entitled <Emphasis style="italic">An Act to amend the Criminal Code and to make consequential amendments to another Act (interim release and domestic violence recognizance orders</Emphasis> (in this section referred to as the “other Act”), receives royal assent.</Text></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>On the first day on which both section 11 of this Act and section 3 of the other Act are in force, subsection 810.03(7) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Criminal Code</XRefExternal> is amended by adding the following after paragraph (e):</Text><AmendedText change="ins"><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(e.1)</Label><Text>to abstain from publishing, distributing, transmitting or making accessible on the Internet any information concerning their child or concerning the person on whose behalf the information was laid or that person’s intimate partner or child, as the case may be.</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection></Section></Body></Bill>