<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><Bill bill-origin="senate" bill-type="private-public" xml:lang="en" date-time="2023-02-17 09:32:00"><Identification><BillNumber>S-259</BillNumber><Parliament><Session>1</Session><Number>44</Number><RegnalYear><Year-s>70-71</Year-s><Monarch>Elizabeth II – 1 Charles III</Monarch></RegnalYear><Year-s>2021-2022-2023</Year-s></Parliament><LongTitle>An Act to designate the month of March as Hellenic Heritage Month</LongTitle><ShortTitle status="unofficial">Hellenic Heritage Month Act</ShortTitle><RunningHead>Hellenic Heritage Month Act</RunningHead><BillHistory><Stages stage="first-reading-senate"><Date><YYYY>2023</YYYY><MM>3</MM><DD>29</DD></Date></Stages></BillHistory><BillSponsor>Senator LOFFREDA</BillSponsor><BillRefNumber date-time="">4412228</BillRefNumber></Identification><Introduction><Summary><TitleText>SUMMARY</TitleText><Provision><Text>
This enactment designates the month of March as “Hellenic Heritage Month”.</Text></Provision></Summary><Preamble><Provision pointsize="10" topmarginspacing="-6" language-align="yes"><MarginalNote>Preamble</MarginalNote><Text>Whereas over 260,000 Canadians are of Greek descent and numerous Greek communities exist across the country;</Text></Provision><Provision><Text>
Whereas Greek Canadians have made meaningful and lasting contributions to Canada’s political, economic, scientific, legal, medical, cultural and social fabric, and in numerous other areas of value and significance;
</Text></Provision><Provision><Text>
Whereas the origins of Canadian democracy can be traced back to the ancient Greek city-state of Athens;</Text></Provision><Provision><Text>
Whereas the month of March is culturally and spiritually significant for the Greek community, as it was on March 25, 1821, on the Great Feast of the Annunciation, that Greece commenced its war of independence from the Ottoman Empire, leading to the creation of the modern state of Greece;</Text></Provision><Provision><Text>And whereas the celebration of Hellenic Heritage Month would encourage Greek Canadians to promote their culture and traditions and share them with their fellow Canadians;</Text></Provision></Preamble><Enacts><Provision><Text>His Majesty, by and with the advice and consent of the Senate and House of Commons of Canada, enacts as follows:</Text></Provision></Enacts></Introduction><Body><Heading level="1"><TitleText>Short Title</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Short title</MarginalNote><Label>1</Label><Text>This Act may be cited as the <Emphasis style="italic">Hellenic Heritage Month Act</Emphasis>.</Text></Section><Heading level="1"><TitleText>Hellenic Heritage Month</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Designation</MarginalNote><Label>2</Label><Text>Throughout Canada, in each and every year, the month of March is to be known as “Hellenic Heritage Month”.</Text></Section></Body></Bill>