<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><Bill bill-origin="senate" bill-type="private-public" xml:lang="en" date-time="2023-09-20 08:04:22"><Identification><BillNumber>S-278</BillNumber><Parliament><Session>1</Session><Number>44</Number><RegnalYear><Year-s>70-71</Year-s><Monarch>Elizabeth II â 1-2 Charles III</Monarch></RegnalYear><Year-s>2021-2022-2023</Year-s></Parliament><LongTitle>An Act to amend the Special Economic Measures Act (disposal of foreign state assets)</LongTitle><ShortTitle status="unofficial" /><RunningHead>An Act to amend the Special Economic Measures Act (disposal of foreign state assets)</RunningHead><BillHistory><Stages stage="first-reading-senate"><Date><YYYY>2023</YYYY><MM>10</MM><DD>4</DD></Date></Stages></BillHistory><BillSponsor>Senator Omidvar</BillSponsor><BillRefNumber date-time="">4412327</BillRefNumber></Identification><Introduction><Summary><TitleText>SUMMARY</TitleText><Provision><Text>This enactment amends the <XRefExternal reference-type="act" reference-level="federal">Special Economic Measures Act</XRefExternal> to allow the Governor in Council to dispose of a foreign stateâs <Keep>assets</Keep> seized under the Act if the seizure occurred without a judicial order.</Text></Provision></Summary><Enacts><Provision><Text>His Majesty, by and with the advice and consent of the Senate and House of Commons of Canada, enacts as follows:</Text></Provision></Enacts></Introduction><Body><Heading level="1"><MarginalNote><HistoricalNote>1992, c. 17</HistoricalNote></MarginalNote><TitleText><XRefExternal reference-type="act" reference-level="federal">Special Economic Measures Act</XRefExternal></TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><Label>1</Label><Text>Section 5 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Special Economic Measures Act</XRefExternal> is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><Section><MarginalNote>Costs</MarginalNote><Label>5</Label><Text>Any costs incurred by or on behalf of <Ins>His</Ins> Majesty in right of Canada in relation to the seizure or restraint of property under an order made under paragraph 4(1)(b) or the disposal of property forfeited under section 5.4 <Ins>or 5.41</Ins> are the liability of the owner of the property and constitute a debt due to <Ins>His</Ins> Majesty in right of Canada that may be recovered in any court of competent jurisdiction.</Text></Section></AmendedText><ExplanatoryNote><TitleText><XRefExternal reference-type="act" reference-level="federal">Special Economic Measures Act</XRefExternal></TitleText><Label><Emphasis style="italic">Clause 1</Emphasis>:</Label><ExplanatoryText>Text of section 5:</ExplanatoryText><ExistingText><Section><Label>5</Label><Text>Any costs incurred by or on behalf of Her Majesty in right of Canada in relation to the seizure or restraint of property under an <Keep>order</Keep> made under paragraph 4(1)(b) or the disposal of property forfeited under section 5.4 are the liability of the owner of the property and constitute a debt due to Her Majesty in right of Canada that may be recovered in any court of competent jurisdiction.</Text></Section></ExistingText></ExplanatoryNote></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>2</Label><Text>Paragraph 5.2(b) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>the property is forfeited to <Ins>His</Ins> Majesty in right of Canada under section 5.4 <Ins>or 5.41</Ins>.</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText><ExplanatoryNote><Label><Emphasis style="italic">Clause 2</Emphasis>:</Label><ExplanatoryText>Text of relevant portions of section 5.2:</ExplanatoryText><ExistingText><Section><Label>5.2</Label><Text>All secured and unsecured rights and interests in any property that is the subject of an order made under paragraph 4(1)(b) that are held by a person are entitled to the same ranking that they would have been entitled to had the order not been made, unless</Text><Paragraph><Label>. . .</Label><Text /></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>the property is forfeited to Her Majesty in right of Canada under section 5.4.</Text></Paragraph></Section></ExistingText></ExplanatoryNote></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>3</Label><Text>The Act is amended by adding the following <Keep>after</Keep> subsection 5.4(1):</Text><AmendedText change="ins"><Subsection><MarginalNote>Exception</MarginalNote><Label>(1.1)</Label><Text>An order made under subsection (1) cannot relate to property that is owned, held or controlled, directly or indirectly, by a foreign state.</Text></Subsection></AmendedText><ExplanatoryNote><Label><Emphasis style="italic">Clause 3</Emphasis>:</Label><ExplanatoryText>New.</ExplanatoryText></ExplanatoryNote></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>4</Label><Text>The Act is amended by adding the following <Keep>after</Keep> section 5.4:</Text><AmendedText change="ins"><Section><MarginalNote>Forfeiture of foreign state assets</MarginalNote><Label>5.41</Label><Text>The Governor in Council may, by order, have any property that is the subject of an order made under paragraph 4(1)(b) and that is owned â or that is held or controlled directly or indirectly â by a foreign state to be forfeited to His Majesty in right of Canada.</Text></Section></AmendedText><ExplanatoryNote><Label><Emphasis style="italic">Clause 4</Emphasis>:</Label><ExplanatoryText>New.</ExplanatoryText></ExplanatoryNote></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>5</Label><Text>The portion of section 5.6 of the Act before paragraph (a) is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><Section><MarginalNote>Payment out of Proceeds Account</MarginalNote><Label>5.6</Label><Text>After consulting with the Minister of Finance and the Minister of Foreign Affairs, the Minister may â at the times and in the manner, and on any terms and conditions, that the Minister considers appropriate â pay out of the <DefinitionRef>Proceeds Account</DefinitionRef>, as defined in section 2 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act" reference-level="federal">Seized Property Management Act</XRefExternal>, amounts not exceeding the net proceeds from the disposition of property <Keep>forfeited</Keep> under section 5.4 <Ins>or 5.41</Ins>, but only for any of the following purposes:</Text></Section></AmendedText><ExplanatoryNote><Label><Emphasis style="italic">Clause 5</Emphasis>:</Label><ExplanatoryText>Text of relevant portion of section 5.6:</ExplanatoryText><ExistingText><Section><Label>5.6</Label><Text>After consulting with the Minister of Finance and the Minister of Foreign Affairs, the Minister may â at the times and in the manner, and on any terms and conditions, that the Minister considers appropriate â pay out of the <DefinitionRef>Proceeds Account</DefinitionRef>, as defined in section 2 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act" reference-level="federal">Seized Property Management Act</XRefExternal>, amounts not exceeding the net proceeds from the disposition of property forfeited under section 5.4, but only for any of the following purposes:</Text></Section></ExistingText></ExplanatoryNote></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>6</Label><Text>Subsection 6.2(1) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text></Section><Section><MarginalNote>RCMP</MarginalNote><Label>6.2</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The Commissioner of the Royal Canadian Mounted Police may assist the Minister in matters related to the making of an order under paragraph 4(1)(b), the seizure or restraint of any property that is the subject of such an order<Ins>,</Ins> the making of an application for forfeiture of the property under section 5.4 <Ins>or the making of an order under section 5.41</Ins> and, for that purpose, may collect information from and disclose information to the persons referred to in section 6.1.</Text></Subsection><ExplanatoryNote><Label><Emphasis style="italic">Clause 6</Emphasis>:</Label><ExplanatoryText>Text of subsection 6.2(1):</ExplanatoryText><ExistingText><Section><Label>6.2</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The Commissioner of the Royal Canadian Mounted Police may assist the Minister in matters related to the making of an order under paragraph 4(1)(b), the seizure or restraint of any property that is the subject of such an order or the making of an application for <Keep>forfeiture</Keep> of the property under section 5.4 and, for that purpose, may collect information from and disclose information to the persons referred to in section 6.1.</Text></Subsection></Section></ExistingText></ExplanatoryNote></Section></Body></Bill>