<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><Bill bill-origin="senate" bill-type="private-public" xml:lang="en" date-time="2024-10-07 15:44:03"><Identification><BillNumber>S-289</BillNumber><Parliament><Session>1</Session><Number>44</Number><RegnalYear><Year-s>70-71</Year-s><Monarch>Elizabeth II 芒聙聯 1-2-3 Charles III</Monarch></RegnalYear><Year-s>2021-2022-2023-2024</Year-s></Parliament><LongTitle>An Act to amend the National Capital Act (Gatineau Park)</LongTitle><ShortTitle status="unofficial">Gatineau Park Act</ShortTitle><RunningHead>Gatineau Park Act</RunningHead><BillHistory><Stages stage="first-reading-senate"><Date><YYYY>2024</YYYY><MM>10</MM><DD>10</DD></Date></Stages></BillHistory><BillSponsor>Senator GALVEZ</BillSponsor><BillRefNumber date-time="">4412406</BillRefNumber></Identification><Introduction><Summary><TitleText>SUMMARY</TitleText><Provision><Text>The bill amends the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">National Capital Act</XRefExternal> to, among other things,</Text></Provision><Provision first-line-indent="1" subsequent-line-indent="1" language-align="yes"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>establish the boundaries of Gatineau Park;</Text></Provision><Provision first-line-indent="1" subsequent-line-indent="1" language-align="yes"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>prioritize the ecological integrity of the park in its management by the National Capital Commission (NCC);</Text></Provision><Provision first-line-indent="1" subsequent-line-indent="1" language-align="yes"><Label>(c)</Label><Text>prohibit the sale of public lands located within the park, with certain exceptions;</Text></Provision><Provision first-line-indent="1" subsequent-line-indent="1" language-align="yes"><Label>(d)</Label><Text>strengthen consultation and collaboration between the NCC, the Algonquin Anishinabeg Nation and neighbouring municipalities;</Text></Provision><Provision first-line-indent="1" subsequent-line-indent="1" language-align="yes"><Label>(e)</Label><Text>promote the use of services from businesses and workers of the Algonquin Anishinabeg Nation for maintenance and conservation activities in Gatineau Park;</Text></Provision><Provision first-line-indent="1" subsequent-line-indent="1" language-align="yes"><Label>(f)</Label><Text>allow the NCC to negotiate a preemptive right agreement (right of first refusal) with private landowners in the park; and</Text></Provision><Provision first-line-indent="1" subsequent-line-indent="1" language-align="yes"><Label>(g)</Label><Text>authorize the creation of regulations to oversee activities in the park and set corresponding fees.</Text></Provision></Summary><TableOfProvisions><Heading level="1"><TitleText>TABLE OF PROVISIONS</TitleText></Heading><Heading level="1"><TitleText>An Act to amend the National Capital Act (Gatineau Park)</TitleText></Heading><Label /><Text>Preamble</Text><Heading level="1"><TitleText>Short Title</TitleText></Heading><Label>1</Label><Text><Emphasis style="italic">Gatineau Park Act</Emphasis></Text><Heading level="1"><TitleText><XRefExternal reference-type="act" reference-level="federal">National Capital Act</XRefExternal></TitleText></Heading><Label>2</Label><Text>Defnitions</Text><Label>3</Label><Text>Amendments</Text><Heading level="1"><TitleText>Consequential Amendments</TitleText></Heading><Label>10</Label><Text>References</Text><Heading level="1"><TitleText>Coordinating Amendments</TitleText></Heading><Label>11</Label><Text>Bill S-13</Text><Label>12</Label><Text>Bill C-399</Text><Label>13</Label><Text>Bill C-20</Text><Label>14</Label><Text>Bill C-27</Text><Heading level="1"><Label>SCHEDULE</Label></Heading></TableOfProvisions><Preamble><Provision pointsize="10" topmarginspacing="-6" language-align="yes"><MarginalNote>Preamble</MarginalNote><Text>Whereas Parliament recognizes that it is essential to ensure that the natural environment of the National Capital Region, and especially Gatineau Park, is preserved for the enjoyment of all Canadians;</Text></Provision><Provision><Text>Whereas Gatineau Park is located on the unceded traditional lands of the Algonquin Anishinabeg Nation;</Text></Provision><Provision><Text>Whereas it is important to connect Canadians with the natural and cultural heritage of the National Capital Region and with the history of its early Indigenous inhabitants, consistent with the <XRefExternal reference-type="act" reference-level="federal">United Nations Declaration on the Rights of Indigenous Peoples Act</XRefExternal>, and of others who have shaped its landscapes;</Text></Provision><Provision><Text>Whereas the National Capital Commission requires the legislative and regulatory tools necessary to effectively manage Gatineau Park;</Text></Provision><Provision><Text>Whereas Gatineau Park is a regional and national treasure promoting recreational activities respectful of the environment and must be acknowledged and defined as such;</Text></Provision><Provision><Text>Whereas Gatineau Park is home to diverse natural ecosystems and a significant number of plant and animal species at risk;</Text></Provision><Provision><Text>Whereas Parliament recognizes the importance of preserving the ecological integrity of Gatineau Park;</Text></Provision><Provision><Text>And whereas strengthening the effective management of protected areas is a commitment made by the government of Canada under the Kunming-Montreal Global Biodiversity Framework, adopted by the United Nations Biodiversity Conference in Montreal on December 19, 2022;</Text></Provision></Preamble><Enacts><Provision><Text>Now, therefore, His Majesty, by and with the advice and consent of the Senate and House of Commons of Canada, enacts as follows:</Text></Provision></Enacts></Introduction><Body><Heading level="1"><TitleText>Short Title</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Short title</MarginalNote><Label>1</Label><Text>This Act may be cited as the <Emphasis style="italic">Gatineau Park Act</Emphasis>.</Text></Section><Heading level="1"><MarginalNote><HistoricalNote>R.S., c. N-4</HistoricalNote></MarginalNote><TitleText><XRefExternal reference-type="act" reference-level="federal">National Capital Act</XRefExternal></TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote>Definitions</MarginalNote><Label>2</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The definition <DefinedTermEn>National Capital Region</DefinedTermEn> in section 2 of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><SectionPiece><Definition><Text><DefinedTermEn>National Capital Region</DefinedTermEn> means the seat of the Government of Canada and its surrounding area, more particularly described in <Ins>Schedule 1</Ins>; (<DefinedTermFr>r脙漏gion de la capitale nationale</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Definition></SectionPiece></AmendedText><ExplanatoryNote><TitleText><XRefExternal reference-type="act" reference-level="federal">National Capital Act</XRefExternal></TitleText><Label><Emphasis style="italic">Clause 2</Emphasis>: (1)</Label><ExplanatoryText>Text of the definition:</ExplanatoryText><ExistingText><SectionPiece><Definition><Text><DefinedTermEn>National Capital Region</DefinedTermEn>芒聙聜means the seat of the Government of Canada and its surrounding area, more particularly described in the schedule;芒聙聜<DefinedTermFr>(r脙漏gion de la capitale nationale</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Definition></SectionPiece></ExistingText></ExplanatoryNote></Subsection><Subsection><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Section 2 of the Act is amended by adding the following in alphabetical order:</Text><AmendedText change="ins"><SectionPiece><Definition><Text><DefinedTermEn>ecological integrity</DefinedTermEn> means, with respect to a park, a condition that is determined to be characteristic of its natural region and likely to persist, including abiotic components and the composition and abundance of native species and biological communities, rates of change and supporting processes; (<DefinedTermFr>int脙漏grit脙漏 脙漏cologique</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Definition><Definition><Text><DefinedTermEn>enforcement officer</DefinedTermEn> means a person designated under section 10.09 or belonging to a class of persons so designated; (<DefinedTermFr>agent de l芒聙聶autorit脙漏</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Definition><Definition><Text><DefinedTermEn>Gatineau Park</DefinedTermEn> means the area whose boundaries are named and described in Schedule 2; (<DefinedTermFr>parc de la Gatineau</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Definition></SectionPiece></AmendedText><ExplanatoryNote><Label>(2)</Label><ExplanatoryText>New.</ExplanatoryText></ExplanatoryNote></Subsection></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>3</Label><Text>The Act is amended by adding the following after section 2:</Text><AmendedText change="ins"><Section><MarginalNote>Rights of Indigenous peoples of Canada</MarginalNote><Label>2.1</Label><Text>This Act is to be construed as upholding the Aboriginal and treaty rights of Indigenous peoples recognized and affirmed by section 35 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act" reference-level="otherNation">Constitution Act, 1982</XRefExternal>, and not as abrogating or derogating from them.</Text></Section></AmendedText><ExplanatoryNote><Label><Emphasis style="italic">Clause 3</Emphasis>:</Label><ExplanatoryText>New.</ExplanatoryText></ExplanatoryNote></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>4</Label><Text>The Act is amended by adding the following after section 10:</Text><AmendedText change="ins"><Heading level="1"><TitleText>Gatineau Park</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Park dedicated to public</MarginalNote><Label>10.01</Label><Text>Gatineau Park is dedicated to the people of Canada, including the Algonquin Anishinabeg Nation, for their benefit, education and enjoyment, subject to this Act and the regulations, and the Park shall be maintained and made use of 芒聙聰 and its ecological integrity protected 芒聙聰 so as to leave it unimpaired for the enjoyment of future generations.</Text></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Ecological integrity</MarginalNote><Label>10.02</Label><Text>Maintenance of ecological integrity, through the protection of natural resources and natural processes, shall be the first priority of the Commission when considering all aspects of the management of Gatineau Park.</Text></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Enlarging Gatineau Park</MarginalNote><Label>10.03</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The Governor in Council may, by order, amend Schedule 2 for the purpose of enlarging Gatineau Park if the Governor in Council is satisfied that His Majesty has title to the lands that can be included in Gatineau Park, regardless of whether there are any charges on title.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Judicial finding as to title</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>If a court of competent jurisdiction finds that His Majesty does not have title to the lands referred to in subsection (1), the Governor in Council may, by order, amend Schedule 2 by altering the description of Gatineau Park to remove those lands from the Park.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>No reduction of park area</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>Except as provided by subsection (2), no amendment may be made by the Governor in Council to Schedule 2 for the purpose of removing any portion of Gatineau Park.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Master Plan</MarginalNote><Label>10.04</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Within 10 years after the day on which this section comes into force, the Commission shall prepare a Gatineau Park Master Plan containing a long-term ecological vision for the park, a set of ecological integrity objectives and indicators, and provisions for resource protection and restoration, zoning, visitor use, public awareness and performance evaluation, and shall cause the plan to be tabled in each House of Parliament.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Review of Master Plan by Commission</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The Commission shall review the Master Plan for Gatineau Park at least every 10 years and shall cause any amendments to the plan to be tabled in each House of Parliament.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Consultation 芒聙聰 public and Anishinabeg Nation</MarginalNote><Label>10.05</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The Commission shall provide opportunities for public participation at the national, regional and local levels 芒聙聰 including participation by Algonquin Anishinabeg Nation and the residents of Gatineau Park 芒聙聰 in the development of regulations relating to Gatineau Park, the formulation of Master Plans, land use planning and any other matters that the Commission considers relevant.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Consultation</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The Commission must be able to demonstrate, in a report published on its website, that it has consulted both the cities and municipalities adjacent to Gatineau Park and the Algonquin Anishinabeg governing bodies of the region and has considered their recommendations.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Prohibition on disposing of public land</MarginalNote><Label>10.06</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Despite any other provision of this Act and subject to subsection (2), no person shall dispose of or grant a right or interest in any public lands in Gatineau Park.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Authority to dispose</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Public lands or a right or interest in public lands in Gatineau Park may be disposed of to</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>an Algonquin Anishinabeg organization or governing body of the region, if the disposal is necessary for the establishment of health care, social services, or cultural services for the Anishinabeg Nation; or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>a federal, provincial or municipal authority, if the disposal is required for the purpose of installing or maintaining public health care establishments or public infrastructure 芒聙聰 including public utilities or transportation corridors. </Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Reversion</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>Public lands in the Gatineau Park revert to the Commission if those lands cease to be used for the purpose for which they were disposed of or the rights or interests were granted.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Interdiction 芒聙聰 use of public lands</MarginalNote><Label>10.07</Label><Text>Subject to regulations made under subsection 20(1.1), no person shall use or occupy public lands in Gatineau Park except as permitted by the Commission.</Text></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Right of first refusal agreements</MarginalNote><Label>10.08</Label><Text>The Commission is authorized to negotiate with an owner of real property located within Gatineau Park an agreement granting it a right of first refusal, allowing the Commission to acquire the property before it is disposed of by that owner. In the absence of such an agreement, any owner intending to dispose of their real property must notify the Commission of their intention, unless the purchaser is a 芒聙聹person related芒聙聺, within the meaning of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act" reference-level="federal">Income Tax Act</XRefExternal>, to the owner.</Text></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Designation of enforcement officers</MarginalNote><Label>10.09</Label><Text>The Minister may designate persons or classes of persons employed in the federal public administration or by a provincial, municipal or local authority or an Algonquin Anishinabeg governing body, whose duties include law enforcement, to be enforcement officers for the purpose of enforcing the provisions of this Act or the regulations in relation to Gatineau Park. For that purpose, enforcement officers have the same powers and are entitled to the same protections provided by law to peace officers within the meaning of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act" reference-level="federal">Criminal Code</XRefExternal>.</Text></Section><Section><MarginalNote><XRefExternal reference-type="act" reference-level="federal">Contraventions Act</XRefExternal></MarginalNote><Label>10.1</Label><Text>The Minister may designate persons or classes of persons employed in the federal public administration or by a provincial, municipal or local authority or by an Algonquin Anishinabeg governing body for the purpose of enforcing this Act or the regulations for Gatineau Park with respect to offences that have been designated as contraventions under the <XRefExternal reference-type="act" reference-level="federal">Contraventions Act</XRefExternal>.</Text></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Maintenance and conservation work</MarginalNote><Label>10.11</Label><Text>The Commission must also consider calling upon the services of businesses and workers from the Algonquin Anishinabeg Nation of the region for part of Gatineau Park芒聙聶s maintenance and conservation work.</Text></Section></AmendedText><ExplanatoryNote><Label><Emphasis style="italic">Clause 4</Emphasis>:</Label><ExplanatoryText>New.</ExplanatoryText></ExplanatoryNote></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>5</Label><Text>Subsection 16(3) of the French version of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><Subsection><MarginalNote><Language xml:lang="fr">Parc de la Gatineau</Language></MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text><Language xml:lang="fr">La Commission peut verser aux autorit脙漏s comp脙漏tentes, pour ceux de ses biens immeubles situ脙漏s dans le <Ins>parc</Ins> de la Gatineau, des subventions n芒聙聶exc脙漏dant pas, dans une ann脙漏e fiscale donn脙漏e, les montants qu芒聙聶elle estime suffisants pour indemniser ces autorit脙漏s des pertes de revenu de taxes municipales et scolaires subies par elles pendant l芒聙聶ann脙漏e en question du fait de l芒聙聶acquisition de ces biens par la Commission.</Language></Text></Subsection></AmendedText><ExplanatoryNote><Label><Emphasis style="italic">Clause 5</Emphasis>:</Label><ExplanatoryText>Text of subsection 16(3):</ExplanatoryText><ExistingText><Subsection><Label>(3)</Label><Text>The Commission may pay grants to the appropriate authorities in respect of real property of the Commission situated in Gatineau Park not exceeding in any tax year the amounts estimated by the Commission to be sufficient to compensate such authorities for the loss of tax revenue during that tax year in respect of municipal and school taxes by reason of the acquisition of the property by the Commission.</Text></Subsection></ExistingText></ExplanatoryNote></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>6</Label><Text>Section 20 of the Act is amended by adding the following after subsection (1):</Text><AmendedText change="ins"><Subsection><MarginalNote>Regulations 芒聙聰 Gatineau Park</MarginalNote><Label>(1.1)</Label><Text>The Governor in Council may also make regulations respecting</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>the restriction or prohibition of activities in and the control of the use of Gatineau Park resources and facilities;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>the determination of fees, rates, rents and other charges for the use of Gatineau Park resources and facilities, the provision of works, services and improvements, and the issuance and amendment of permits, licences and other authorizing instruments; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(c)</Label><Text>the management of ecological integrity of Gatineau Park.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection></AmendedText><ExplanatoryNote><Label><Emphasis style="italic">Clause 6</Emphasis>:</Label><ExplanatoryText>New.</ExplanatoryText></ExplanatoryNote></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>7</Label><Text>Subsection 20(2) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><Subsection><MarginalNote>Punishment</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text><Ins>Within the limits</Ins> set out in subsection 787(1) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act" reference-level="federal">Criminal Code</XRefExternal><Ins>, the</Ins> Governor in Council may<Ins>,</Ins> by regulation<Ins>,</Ins> prescribe the punishment that may be imposed on summary conviction for the contravention of any regulation <Ins>referred to in</Ins> subsection (1) <Ins>or (1.1)</Ins>.</Text></Subsection></AmendedText><ExplanatoryNote><Label><Emphasis style="italic">Clause 7</Emphasis>:</Label><ExplanatoryText>Text of subsection 20(2):</ExplanatoryText><ExistingText><Subsection><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The Governor in Council may by regulation prescribe the punishment that may be imposed on summary conviction for the contravention of any regulation made under subsection (1), but the punishment so prescribed shall not exceed that set out in subsection 787(1) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act" reference-level="federal">Criminal Code</XRefExternal>.</Text></Subsection></ExistingText></ExplanatoryNote></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>8</Label><Text>The schedule to the Act is renumbered Schedule 1.</Text></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>9</Label><Text>The Act is amended by adding after Schedule 1 the Schedule 2 set out in the schedule to this Act.</Text></Section><Heading level="1"><TitleText>Consequential Amendments</TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote>References</MarginalNote><Label>10</Label><Text>Unless the context requires otherwise, the expression 芒聙聹the schedule to the <XRefExternal reference-type="act" reference-level="federal">National Capital Act</XRefExternal>芒聙聺 is replaced by 芒聙聹Schedule 1 to the <XRefExternal reference-type="act" reference-level="federal">National Capital Act</XRefExternal>芒聙聺 in any Act of Parliament, and more particularly wherever it occurs in the following provisions:</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>subsection 52(2) and section 60 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Access to Information Act</XRefExternal>;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>subsection 4(1) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act" reference-level="federal">Administrative Tribunals Support Service of Canada Act</XRefExternal>;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(c)</Label><Text>subsection 50(1) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act" reference-level="federal">Broadcasting Act</XRefExternal>;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(d)</Label><Text>section 7 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act" reference-level="federal">Budget Implementation Act, 1997</XRefExternal>;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(e)</Label><Text>section 4 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act" reference-level="federal">Canada Border Services Agency Act</XRefExternal>;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(f)</Label><Text>subsection 2(1) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="regulation" reference-level="federal">Canada Elections Act</XRefExternal>;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(g)</Label><Text>subsection 38.11(1.1) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act" reference-level="federal">Canada Evidence Act</XRefExternal>;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(h)</Label><Text>subsection 10.1(1) and section 13 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act" reference-level="federal">Canada Labour Code</XRefExternal>;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(i)</Label><Text>subsection 3(2) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act" reference-level="federal">Canada School of Public Service Act</XRefExternal>;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(j)</Label><Text>subsections 18(1) and (2) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act" reference-level="federal">Canada Transportation Act</XRefExternal>;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(k)</Label><Text>section 13 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act" reference-level="federal">Canadian Centre on Substance Abuse Act</XRefExternal>;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(l)</Label><Text>section 112 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act" reference-level="federal">Canadian Environmental Assessment Act</XRefExternal>;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(m)</Label><Text>section 9 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act" reference-level="federal">Canadian Food Inspection Agency Act</XRefExternal>;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(n)</Label><Text>subsection 34(1) and sections 48.5 and 48.7 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act" reference-level="federal">Canadian Human Rights Act</XRefExternal>;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(o)</Label><Text>section 11 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act" reference-level="federal">Canadian International Trade Tribunal Act</XRefExternal>;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(p)</Label><Text>subsections 10(1) and 10.1(1) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act" reference-level="federal">Canadian Radio-television and Telecommunications Commission Act</XRefExternal>;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(q)</Label><Text>subsection 3(2) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act" reference-level="federal">Canadian Security Intelligence Service Act</XRefExternal>;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(r)</Label><Text>subsection 13(1) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act" reference-level="federal">Canadian Transportation Accident Investigation and Safety Board Act</XRefExternal>;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(s)</Label><Text>section 7 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act" reference-level="federal">College of Patent Agents and Trademark Agents Act</XRefExternal>;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(t)</Label><Text>subsection 7(1) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act" reference-level="federal">Communications Security Establishment Act</XRefExternal>;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(u)</Label><Text>subsections 6(2) and 148(1) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act" reference-level="federal">Corrections and Conditional Release Act</XRefExternal>;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(v)</Label><Text>subsection 4(1) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act" reference-level="federal">Courts Administration Service Act</XRefExternal>;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(w)</Label><Text>subsection 462.48(12) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act" reference-level="federal">Criminal Code</XRefExternal>;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(x)</Label><Text>subsections 27(1) and 60(1) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act" reference-level="federal">Department of Employment and Social Development Act</XRefExternal>;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(y)</Label><Text>subsection 6(1) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act" reference-level="federal">Energy Supplies Emergency Act</XRefExternal>;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(z)</Label><Text>subsection 17(1) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act" reference-level="federal">Export Development Act</XRefExternal>;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(z.1)</Label><Text>section 11 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act" reference-level="federal">Farm Products Agencies Act</XRefExternal>;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(z.2)</Label><Text>subsection 7(1) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act" reference-level="federal">Federal Courts Act</XRefExternal>;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(z.3)</Label><Text>sections 7 and 13 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act" reference-level="federal">Federal Public Sector Labour Relations and Employment Board Act</XRefExternal>;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(z.4)</Label><Text>subsection 26(2) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act" reference-level="federal">First Nations Fiscal Management Act</XRefExternal>;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(z.5)</Label><Text>subsection 25(2) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act" reference-level="federal">First Nations Jurisdiction over Education in British Columbia Act</XRefExternal>;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(z.6)</Label><Text>subsection 157(1) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act" reference-level="federal">Immigration and Refugee Protection Act</XRefExternal>;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(z.7)</Label><Text>section 164 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act" reference-level="federal">Impact Assessment Act</XRefExternal>;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(z.8)</Label><Text>section 22 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act" reference-level="federal">Indigenous Languages Act</XRefExternal>;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(z.9)</Label><Text>section 12 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act" reference-level="federal">Law Commission of Canada Act</XRefExternal>;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(z.10)</Label><Text>subsection 9(1) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act" reference-level="federal">National Arts Centre Act</XRefExternal>;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(z.11)</Label><Text>subsection 24(3) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act" reference-level="federal">National Security and Intelligence Committee of Parliamentarians Act</XRefExternal>;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(z.12)</Label><Text>subsection 3(1) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act" reference-level="federal">Official Languages Act</XRefExternal>;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(z.13)</Label><Text>subsection 5(1) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act" reference-level="federal">Official Residences Act</XRefExternal>;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(z.14)</Label><Text>section 17 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act" reference-level="federal">Parks Canada Agency Act</XRefExternal>;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(z.15)</Label><Text>paragraph 80(1)(a) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act" reference-level="federal">Parliament of Canada Act</XRefExternal>;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(z.16)</Label><Text>subsection 95(1) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act" reference-level="federal">Patent Act</XRefExternal>;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(z.17)</Label><Text>subsection 52(1) and section 61 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act" reference-level="federal">Privacy Act</XRefExternal>;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(z.18)</Label><Text>subsections 48(1), 60(14), 60.1(13) and 60.3(13) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act" reference-level="federal">Proceeds of Crime (Money Laundering) and Terrorist Financing Act</XRefExternal>;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(z.19)</Label><Text>subsection 3(4) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act" reference-level="federal">Public Sector Pension Investment Board Act</XRefExternal>;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(z.20)</Label><Text>subsection 6(2) and section 8 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act" reference-level="federal">Public Service Employment Act</XRefExternal>;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(z.21)</Label><Text>subsection 38.3(2) and paragraph 38.3(3)(c) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act" reference-level="federal">Countering Foreign Interference Act</XRefExternal>;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(z.22)</Label><Text>subsection 3(3) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act" reference-level="federal">Royal Canadian Mint Act</XRefExternal>;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(z.23)</Label><Text>section 13 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act" reference-level="federal">Shared Services Canada Act</XRefExternal>;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(z.24)</Label><Text>section 10 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act" reference-level="federal">Standards Council of Canada Act</XRefExternal>;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(z.25)</Label><Text>sections 8 and 14 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act" reference-level="federal">Supreme Court Act</XRefExternal>;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(z.26)</Label><Text>subsection 6(1) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act" reference-level="federal">Tax Court of Canada Act</XRefExternal>; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(z.27)</Label><Text>section 9 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act" reference-level="federal">Transportation Appeal Tribunal of Canada Act</XRefExternal>.</Text></Paragraph></Section><Heading level="1"><TitleText>Coordinating Amendments</TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote>Bill S-13</MarginalNote><Label>11</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Subsections (2) to (4) apply if Bill S-13, introduced in the 1st session of the 44th Parliament and entitled <Emphasis style="italic">An Act to amend the Interpretation Act and to make related amendments to other Acts</Emphasis> (referred to in this section as the 芒聙聹other Act芒聙聺), receives royal assent.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><Label>(2)</Label><Text>If section 3 of this Act comes into force before section 1 of the other Act, then on the day on which that section 1 comes into force, section 2.1 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act" reference-level="federal">National Capital Act</XRefExternal> is repealed.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><Label>(3)</Label><Text>If section 1 of the other Act comes into force before section 3 of this Act, then that section 3 is deemed never to have come into force and is repealed.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><Label>(4)</Label><Text>If section 1 of the other Act comes into force on the same day as section 3 of this Act, then that section 3 is deemed never to have come into force and is repealed.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote>Bill C-399</MarginalNote><Label>12</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Subsections (2) and (3) apply if Bill C-399, introduced in the 1st session of the 44th Parliament and entitled the <Emphasis style="italic">Department of Citizenship and Immigration Ombud Act</Emphasis> (referred to in this section as the 芒聙聹other Act芒聙聺), receives royal assent.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><Label>(2)</Label><Text>If section 10 of this Act comes into force before section 9 of the other Act, then on the day on which that section 9 comes into force, the expression 芒聙聹the schedule芒聙聺 in that section 9 is replaced by 芒聙聹Schedule 1芒聙聺.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><Label>(3)</Label><Text>If section 10 of this Act comes into force on the same day as section 9 of the other Act, then that section 9 is deemed to have come into force before that section 10.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote>Bill C-20</MarginalNote><Label>13</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Subsections (2) and (3) apply if Bill C-20, introduced in the 1st session of the 44th Parliament and entitled the <Emphasis style="italic">Public Complaints and Review Commission Act</Emphasis> (referred to in this section as the 芒聙聹other Act芒聙聺), receives royal assent.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><Label>(2)</Label><Text>If section 10 of this Act comes into force before subsection 6(1) of the other Act, then on the day on which that subsection 6(1) comes into force, the expression 芒聙聹the schedule芒聙聺 in that subsection 6(1) is replaced by 芒聙聹Schedule 1芒聙聺.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><Label>(3)</Label><Text>If section 10 of this Act comes into force on the same day as subsection 6(1) of the other Act, then that subsection 6(1) is deemed to have come into force before that section 10.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote>Bill C-27</MarginalNote><Label>14</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Subsections (2) and (3) apply if Bill C-27, introduced in the 1st session of the 44th Parliament and entitled the <Emphasis style="italic">Digital Charter Implementation Act, 2022</Emphasis> (referred to in this section as the 芒聙聹other Act芒聙聺), receives royal assent.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><Label>(2)</Label><Text>If section 10 of this Act comes into force before section 37 of the other Act, then on the day on which that section 37 comes into force, the expression 芒聙聹the schedule芒聙聺 in section 13 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act" reference-level="federal">Personal Information and Data Protection Tribunal Act</XRefExternal> is replaced by 芒聙聹Schedule 1芒聙聺.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><Label>(3)</Label><Text>If section 10 of this Act comes into force on the same day as section 37 of the other Act, then that section 37 is deemed to have come into force before that section 10.</Text></Subsection></Section></Body><Schedule><ScheduleFormHeading><Label>
SCHEDULE</Label><OriginatingRef><Emphasis style="bold">(Section 9)</Emphasis></OriginatingRef></ScheduleFormHeading><Schedule>

<ScheduleFormHeading>
<Label>SCHEDULE 2</Label>
<OriginatingRef>(Sections 2 and 10.3)</OriginatingRef>


<TitleText>Description of Gatineau Park Boundaries</TitleText>
</ScheduleFormHeading>
<BillPiece><Heading level="1"><TitleText>1 芒聙聰 Purpose</TitleText></Heading></BillPiece><Provision>
<Text>The boundaries of Gatineau Park are within the registration divisions of Hull, Gatineau and Pontiac, Province of Quebec, are located in the municipalities of Chelsea, La P脙陋che, Pontiac and the City of Gatineau, and form part of the cadastres of the Township of Aldfield, the Township of Eardley, the Township of Hull, the Township of Masham, the Township of Onslow and the Cadastre du Qu脙漏bec. Included within these boundaries are, in particular, the lots described below.</Text>
</Provision>


<BillPiece><Heading level="1"><TitleText>2 芒聙聰 Description</TitleText></Heading><Heading level="2"><TitleText>2.1 Section 1</TitleText></Heading></BillPiece><Provision>
<Text>This portion of Gatineau Park, described in Section芒聙炉1, is included in the registration divisions of Gatineau and Hull, located in the City of Gatineau, and forms part of the cadastre of the Township of Hull and the Cadastre du Qu脙漏bec.</Text>
</Provision>

<BillPiece><Heading level="3"><TitleText>City of Gatineau</TitleText></Heading></BillPiece><Provision justification="justify">
<Text>Commencing at the north corner of lot 3 557 256, thence in a general southeasterly direction, following the southwest boundary of boulevard de la Cit脙漏-des-Jeunes comprising lots 1 090 869, 3 557 257, 1 090 833, 1 090 817, 3 690 369, 1 345 137, 1 345 120, 1 345 121, 1 345 115, 1 345 101, 1 345 114, 1 344 870 and 1 814 247, to the intersection of the division line between lots 3 119 481 and 4 158 497 to the west boundary of lot 1 814 247; thence, westerly, following the division line between lots 4 158 496 and 4 158 497 to the northwest corner of lot 4 158 496; thence, in a general westerly direction, following the division line between lot 4 158 497 and lots 2 744 929, 2 744 928, 2 744 927, 2 744 926, 2 744 925, 2 744 924, 2 744 923, 2 744 922, 2 744 921, 2 744 920, 2 481 516, 2 481 515, 2 481 514, 2 481 513 and 1 794 609, to the northwest corner of lot 1 794 609; thence, southerly, following the division line between lots 4 158 497 and 1 794 609, to the northeast corner of lot 1 795 143 (rue des F脙漏es); thence, westerly, following the division line between lot 4 158 497 and lots 1 795 143 and 1 794 577, to the northwest corner of lot 1 794 577; thence, southerly, following the division line between lot 4 158 497 and lots 1 794 577, 1 794 575, 1 794 573, 2 401 402 (rue des Lutins), 1 794 568, 1 794 569, 2 401 400 (rue Merlin), 1 794 565, 1 794 564, 2 401 398 (rue des Feux-Follets), to the southwest corner of lot 2 401 398 (rue des Feux-Follets ); thence, northeasterly, following the division line between lots 4 158 497 and 2 401 398 (rue des Feux-Follets) to the most westerly corner of lot 1 794 567; thence, southeasterly, following the division line between lots 4 158 497 and 1 794 567, to the most southerly corner of lot 1 794 567; thence, northeasterly, following the division line between lots 4 158 497 and 1 794 567, to the most easterly corner of lot 1 794 567; thence, northwesterly, following the division line between lots 4 158 497 and 1 794 567, to the southwest corner of lot 1 794 580; thence, easterly, following the division line between lot 4 158 497 and lots 1 794 580 and 1 794 582, to the northwest corner of lot 1 794 585;thence, southerly, following the division line between lot 4 158 497 and lots 1 794 585, 1 795 137 (rue des Farfadets), 1 794 670 and 1 794 673, to the southwest corner of lot 1 794 673; thence, southerly, following the extension of the division line between lots 1 794 673 and 4 158 497, crossing lots 1 814 190 (rue Gamelin) and 3 754 072, to a point located on the division line between lots 3 754 072 and 4 139 221; thence, northeasterly, following the division line between lots 3 754 072 and 4 139 221 to a southwest corner of lot 1 814 190 (rue Gamelin); thence, northeasterly, following the division line between lots 1 814 190 (rue Gamelin) and 4 139 221, to the easterly corner of lot 1 814 190 (rue Gamelin), a distance of 60.96 m; thence, northeasterly, following the division line between lots 3 754 073 and 4 139 221, to the northeast corner of lot 4 139 221; thence, in a general southerly direction, following the division line between lots 4 139 220 and 4 139 221; 4 139 216 and 4 139 217; 4 139 218 and 4 139 219; 4 139 215 and 4 139 216; 4 139 211 and 4 139 212; 4 139 213 and 4 139 214; 4 139 209 and 4 139 211, to a southwest corner of lot 4 139 211; thence, easterly following the division line between lots 4 139 209 and 4 139 211 to the northwest corner of lot 1 288 391; thence, southerly, following the division line between lots 4 139 209 and lot 1 288 391, to the southwest corner of lot 1 288 391; thence, easterly, following the division line between lot 4 139 209 and lots 1 288 391 and 1 288 388, to the northwest corner of lot 1 288 387; thence, southerly, following the division line between lot 4 139 209 and lots 1 288 387, 1 288 386, 1 288 385 and 4 139 210, to the southwest corner of lot 4 139 210; thence, easterly, following the division line between lots 4 139 209 and 4 139 210, to the southeast corner of lot 4 139 210; thence, southerly, following the division line between lots 4 139 209 and lot 3 620 965, to the southwest corner of lot 3 620 965; thence, easterly, following the division line between lots 4 139 209 and 3 620 965, to the northwest corner of lot 1 286 748; thence, southerly, following the division line between lot 4 139 209 and lots 1 286 748, 1 288 419, 1 286 749 and 1 288 383, to the most westerly corner of lot 1 288 383; thence, southeasterly, following the division line between lot 4 139 209 and lots 1 288 383, 1 286 750, 2 555 266, 2 555 265, 1 288 381, 1 288 379, 1 288 380 and 1 286 746; to the southwest corner of lot 1 286 746; thence, westerly, following the division line between lots 4 139 209 and 4 045 687, to the northwest corner of lot 4 045 687; thence, northerly, following the division line between lots 4 139 209 and 1 286 685, to the northeast corner of lot 1 286 685; thence, westerly, following the division line between lots 4 139 209 and 1 286 685, to the northwest corner of lot 1 286 685, a distance of 41.16 m; thence, northwesterly, following the northeast boundary of rue Boucherville, the division line between lot 4 139 209 and lots 1 288 281 and 1 288 280, to the northwest corner of lot 1 288 280 (rue Boucherville); thence, southerly, following the division line between lot 1 288 280 (rue Boucherville) and lots 4 139 214, 1 288 549 and 1 288 157, to the southeast corner of lot 1 288 157; thence, westerly, crossing lot 1 286 450, to the southeast corner of lot 1 288 158, a distance of 65.63 m; thence, southerly, following the division line between lots 4 160 587 and lot 1 286 450, to the northeast corner of lot 1 286 553; thence, northwesterly, following the division line between lot 4 160 587 and lots 1 286 553, 1 286 552, 1 286 906 and 1 286 451, to the north corner of lot 1 286 451; thence, westerly, following the division line between lot 4 160 587 and lots 1 286 451, 1 286 449, 1 286 448 and 1 286 447, to the north corner of lot 1 286 447; thence, westerly, following the division line between lot 4 160 587 and lots 1 286 447, 1 286 446, 1 286 445 and 1 286 444, to the northwest corner of lot 1 286 444; thence, northerly, following the division line between lots 4 160 587 and 1 286 443, to the northeast corner of lot 1 286 443; thence, westerly, following the division line between lots 4 160 587 and 1 286 443, to the northwest corner of lot 1 286 443; thence, southerly, following the division line between lots 4 160 587 and 1 286 443, to the southwest corner of lot 1 286 443; thence, southerly, following the lines between lot 4 160 587 and lots 1 288 289 (rue Augustin-Thibeault), 1 288 294 (rue Hormidas-Dupuis), to the southwest corner of lot 1 288 294 (rue Hormidas-Dupuis); thence, in a general southeasterly direction, following the division line between lots 4 160 587 and 1 288 295 (rue Hormidas-Dupuis), to a point located at the northeast corner of lot 4 160 586; thence, westerly, following the division line between lots 4 160 586 and 4 160 587, to a point located at the northwest corner of lot 4 160 586; thence, northerly, following the division line between lot 4 160 587 and lots 1 876 616, 1 876 615 and 1 286 289, to the northeast corner of lot 1 286 289; thence, westerly, following the division line between lots 4 160 587 and 1 286 289, to a point located at the intersection of the east boundary of lot 3 558 336; thence, northerly, following the division line between lot 4 160 587 and lots 3 558 336, 3 558 337 and 1 286 192, to the northeast corner of lot 1 286 192; thence, westerly, following the division line between lots 4 160 587 and 1 286 192, to a point located at the tangent point of a curve 24.80 m in radius, a distance of 12.29 m; thence, northeasterly, northerly and northwesterly, following the division line between lots 4 160 587 and 1 288 296 (rue Gendron), to the southerly corner of lot 1 286 239; thence, northwesterly, following the division line between lots 1 288 296 (rue Gendron) and 1 286 239, to the southeast corner of lot 1 286 238; thence, northeasterly, following the division line between lots 1 286 238 and 1 286 239, a distance of 4.21 m, to the southeast corner of lot 1 286 238; thence, northerly, following the division line between lots 1 286 238 and 1 286 239, to the northwest corner of lot 1 286 239; thence, westerly, following the division line between lot 4 160 587 and lots 1 286 238 and 1 286 237, to the northwest corner of lot 1 286 237; thence, northerly, following the division line between lots 4 160 587 and 1 286 442, to the northeast corner of lot 1 286 442; thence, northwesterly, following the division line between lots 1 286 442 and 1 286 441, to the north corner of lot 1 286 442; thence, northwesterly, following the division line between lots 1 286 442 and 1 286 441, to the northwest corner of lot 1 286 442; thence, northeasterly, to a point located at the intersection of the northeast boundary of lot 1 286 441, a distance of 50.05 m; thence, northwesterly, following the division line between lots 1 286 441 and 1 288 534, to the west corner of lot 1 288 534, a distance of 80.36 m; thence, westerly, following the division line between lots 1 086 216 and 1 286 441, to the northwest corner of lot 1 286 441; thence, southerly, following the division line between lot 4 160 640 and lots 1 286 441, 1 286 440 and 1 286 441, to the southeast corner of lot 4 160 640; thence, westerly, following the division line between lots 4 160 639 and 4 160 640, to the northwest corner of lot 4 160 639; thence, northerly, following the division line between lot 4 160 640 and lots 1 794 544, 1 794 546, 1 794 547, 1 794 549, 1 795 107 (rue Des Pr脙漏s) and 1 794 551, to the northeast corner of lot 1 794 551; thence, westerly, following the division line between lot 4 160 640 and lots 1 794 551, 1 794 550 and 1 794 542, to the northwest corner of lot 1 794 542; thence, westerly, following the division line between lots 3 119 485 (boulevard Saint-Raymond) and 1 795 133 (boulevard Saint-Raymond), to the southwest corner of lot 3 119 485 (boulevard Saint-Raymond); thence, northerly, following the division line between lot 1 795 165 (boulevard Saint-Raymond) and lots 3 119 485 (boulevard Saint-Raymond) and 4 160 640, to a point located at a distance of 317.65 m; thence, northerly, crossing lot 1 795 165 (boulevard Saint-Raymond), a distance of 117.04 m, to the southeast corner of lot 3 119 490; thence, in a general northwesterly direction, following the line between lots 3 119 490 and 3 119 488, to the southeast corner of lot 1 814 268 (rue des Conif脙篓res); thence, northerly, following the division line between lots 1 795 163 (rue des Conif脙篓res) and 1 814 268 (rue des Conif脙篓res), to the northeast corner of lot 1 814 268 (rue des Conif脙篓res); thence, in a general northerly direction, following the line between lots 3 119 481 (boulevard Saint-Raymond) and 4 158 497 (boulevard Saint-Raymond), at successive distances of 58.55 m, 39.74 m and 37.32 m; thence, northerly, crossing lot 3 119 481 (boulevard Saint-Raymond) and lot 3 119 478 (chemin Pink), to a point located at the division line between lots 3 119 478 (chemin Pink) and 3 119 479, a distance of 167.17 m; thence, northwesterly, following the division line between lots 3 119 478 (Pink Road) and 3 119 479, to the west corner of lot 3 119 479; thence, in a general northwesterly and westerly direction, following the division line between lots 1 344 862 (chemin Pink) and 1 341 362, to the southeast corner of lot 1 344 861 (chemin de la Montagne nord); thence, northwesterly, following the division line between lots 1 341 362 and 1 344 861 (chemin de la Montagne nord), at successive distances of 72.92 m and 10.50 m, to the northwest corner of lot 1 344 861 (chemin de la Montagne nord); thence, on an azimuth bearing of 314脣職09', following the northeast boundary of chemin de la Montagne nord (as shown on the original cadastral plan), a distance of 101.11 m; thence, on an azimuth bearing of 314脣職00', following the northeast boundary of chemin de la Montagne nord (as shown on the original cadastral plan), a distance of 69.40 m; thence, on an azimuth bearing of 313脣職48', following the northeast boundary of chemin de la Montagne nord (as shown on the original cadastral plan), a distance of 51.31 m; thence, on an azimuth bearing of 312脣職49', following the northeast boundary of chemin de la Montagne nord (as shown on the original cadastral plan), a distance of 61.49 m; thence, on an azimuth bearing of 303脣職50', following the northeast boundary of chemin de la Montagne nord (as shown on the original cadastral plan), a distance of 39.68 m; thence, on an azimuth bearing of 305脣職36', following the northeast boundary of chemin de la Montagne nord (as shown on the original cadastral plan), a distance of 75.58 m; thence, on an azimuth bearing of 301脣職35', following the northeast boundary of chemin de la Montagne nord (as shown on the original cadastral plan), a distance of 64.99 m; thence, on an azimuth bearing of 305脣職41', following the northeast boundary of chemin de la Montagne nord (as shown on the original cadastral plan), a distance of 41.19 m; thence, on an azimuth bearing of 315脣職15', following the northeast boundary of chemin de la Montagne nord (as shown on the original cadastral plan), a distance of 35.86 m; thence, on an azimuth bearing of 319脣職27', following the northeast boundary of chemin de la Montagne nord (as shown on the original cadastral plan), a distance of 58.37 m; thence, on an azimuth bearing of 317脣職24', following the northeast boundary of chemin de la Montagne nord (as shown on the original cadastral plan), a distance of 30.36 m; thence, on an azimuth bearing of 313脣職20', following the northeast boundary of chemin de la Montagne nord (as shown on the original cadastral plan), a distance of 54.89 m; thence, on an azimuth bearing of 308脣職49', following the northeast boundary of chemin de la Montagne nord (as shown on the original cadastral plan), a distance of 44.32 m; thence, on an azimuth bearing of 303脣職33', following the northeast boundary of chemin de la Montagne nord (as shown on the original cadastral plan), a distance of 34.20 m; thence, on an azimuth bearing of 294脣職05', following the northeast boundary of chemin de la Montagne nord (as shown on the original cadastral plan), a distance of 39.18 m; thence, on an azimuth bearing of 288脣職49', following the north boundary of chemin de la Montagne nord (as shown on the original cadastral plan), a distance of 67.92 m; thence, on an azimuth bearing of 286脣職18', following the north boundary of chemin de la Montagne nord (as shown on the original cadastral plan), a distance of 56.40 m; thence, on an azimuth bearing of 280脣職45', following the north boundary of chemin de la Montagne nord (as shown on the original cadastral plan), a distance of 32.00 m; thence, on an azimuth bearing of 277脣職34', following the north boundary of chemin de la Montagne nord (as shown on the original cadastral plan), a distance of 136.62 m; thence, on an azimuth bearing of 279脣職59', following the north boundary of chemin de la Montagne nord (as shown on the original cadastral plan), a distance of 22.28 m; thence, on an azimuth bearing of 282脣職07', following the north boundary of chemin de la Montagne nord (as shown on the original cadastral plan), a distance of 37.99 m; thence, on an azimuth bearing of 287脣職33', following the north boundary of chemin de la Montagne nord (as shown on the original cadastral plan), a distance of 21.87 m; thence, on an azimuth bearing of 294脣職55', following the northeast boundary of chemin de la Montagne nord (as shown on the original cadastral plan), a distance of 34.39 m; thence, on an azimuth bearing of 304脣職04', following the northeast boundary of chemin de la Montagne nord (as shown on the original cadastral plan), a distance of 66.77 m; thence, on an azimuth bearing of 307脣職52', following the northeast boundary of chemin de la Montagne nord (as shown on the original cadastral plan), a distance of 28.36 m; thence, on an azimuth bearing of 316脣職49', following the northeast boundary of chemin de la Montagne nord (as shown on the original cadastral plan), a distance of 37.89 m; thence, on an azimuth bearing of 322脣職11', following the northeast boundary of chemin de la Montagne nord (as shown on the original cadastral plan), a distance of 24.17 m; thence, on an azimuth bearing of 320脣職04', following the northeast boundary of chemin de la Montagne nord (as shown on the original cadastral plan), a distance of 32.61 m; thence, on an azimuth bearing of 316脣職01', following the northeast boundary of chemin de la Montagne nord (as shown on the original cadastral plan), to a point located at the intersection of the said boundary and the division line between lots 12 and 13B, range 5, cadastre of the Township of Hull, a distance of 63.76 m; thence, on an azimuth bearing of 316脣職03', following the northeast boundary of chemin de la Montagne nord (as shown on the original cadastral plan), a distance of 79.76 m; thence, on an azimuth bearing of 317脣職30', following the northeast boundary of chemin de la Montagne nord (as shown on the original cadastral plan), a distance of 80.13 m; thence, on an azimuth bearing of 317脣職48', following the northeast boundary of chemin de la Montagne nord (as shown on the original cadastral plan), a distance of 38.15 m; thence, on an azimuth bearing of 315脣職06', following the northeast boundary of chemin de la Montagne nord (as shown on the original cadastral plan), a distance of 36.10 m; thence, on an azimuth bearing of 310脣職22' , following the northeast boundary of chemin de la Montagne nord (as shown on the original cadastral plan), a distance of 42.66 m; thence, on an azimuth bearing of 312脣職00', following the northeast boundary of chemin de la Montagne nord (as shown on the original cadastral plan), a distance of 109.83 m; thence, on an azimuth bearing of 315脣職25', following the northeast boundary of chemin de la Montagne nord (as shown on the original cadastral plan), a distance of 21.00 m; thence, on an azimuth bearing of 321脣職07', following the northeast boundary of chemin de la Montagne nord (as shown on the original cadastral plan), a distance of 25.17 m; thence, on an azimuth bearing of 324脣職21', following the northeast boundary of chemin de la Montagne nord (as shown on the original cadastral plan), a distance of 48.12 m; thence, on an azimuth bearing of 326脣職52', following the northeast boundary of chemin de la Montagne nord (as shown on the original cadastral plan), to a point located at the intersection of the said boundary and the division line between lots 13B and 13A, range 5, cadastre of the Township of Hull, a distance of 51.01 m; thence, on an azimuth bearing of 336脣職12', following the northeast boundary of chemin de la Montagne nord (as shown on the original cadastral plan), a distance of 33.62 m; thence, on an azimuth bearing of 337脣職26', following the northeast boundary of chemin de la Montagne nord (as shown on the original cadastral plan), a distance of 27.89 m; thence, on an azimuth bearing of 327脣職38', following the northeast boundary of chemin de la Montagne nord (as shown on the original cadastral plan), a distance of 27.49 m; thence, on an azimuth bearing of 316脣職30', following the northeast boundary of chemin de la Montagne nord (as shown on the original cadastral plan), a distance of 25.42 m; thence, on an azimuth bearing of 305脣職46', following the northeast boundary of chemin de la Montagne nord (as shown on the original cadastral plan), a distance of 25.96 m; thence, on an azimuth bearing of 291脣職37', following the north boundary of chemin de la Montagne nord (as shown on the original cadastral plan), a distance of 22.70 m; thence, on an azimuth bearing of 280脣職05', following the north boundary of chemin de la Montagne nord (as shown on the original cadastral plan), a distance of 22.05 m; thence, on an azimuth bearing of 277脣職26', following the north boundary of chemin de la Montagne nord (as shown on the original cadastral plan), a distance of 30.31 m; thence, on an azimuth bearing of 277脣職08', following the north boundary of chemin de la Montagne nord (as shown on the original cadastral plan), a distance of 44.27 m; thence, on an azimuth bearing of 276脣職24', following the north boundary of chemin de la Montagne nord (as shown on the original cadastral plan), to a point located at the intersection of the said boundary and the division line between lots 13A and 14A, range 5, cadastre of the Township of Hull, a distance of 28.13 m; thence, on an azimuth bearing of 276脣職32', following the north boundary of chemin de la Montagne nord (as shown on the original cadastral plan), a distance of 52.12 m; thence, on an azimuth bearing of 280脣職11', following the north boundary of chemin de la Montagne nord (as shown on the original cadastral plan), a distance of 30.81 m; thence, on an azimuth bearing of 285脣職57', following the north boundary of chemin de la Montagne nord (as shown on the original cadastral plan), a distance of 39.13 m; thence, on an azimuth bearing of 285脣職13', following the north boundary of chemin de la Montagne nord (as shown on the original cadastral plan), a distance of 59.80 m; thence, on an azimuth bearing of 287脣職08', following the north boundary of chemin de la Montagne nord (as shown on the original cadastral plan), a distance of 19.48 m; thence, on an azimuth bearing of 292脣職50', following the northeast boundary of chemin de la Montagne nord (as shown on the original cadastral plan), to a point located at the intersection of the said boundary and the division line between lots 14A, range 5, and lot 14, range 6, all part of the cadastre of the Township of Hull, a distance of 26.87 m; thence, on an azimuth bearing of 293脣職14', following the northeast boundary of chemin de la Montagne nord (as shown on the original cadastral plan), a distance of 68.54 m; thence, on an azimuth bearing of 292脣職28', following the north boundary of chemin de la Montagne nord (as shown on the original cadastral plan), a distance of 55.88 m; thence, on an azimuth bearing of 294脣職43', following the northeast boundary of chemin de la Montagne nord (as shown on the original cadastral plan), a distance of 92.77 m; thence, on an azimuth bearing of 290脣職42', following the north boundary of chemin de la Montagne nord (as shown on the original cadastral plan), a distance of 53.02 m; thence, on an azimuth bearing of 285脣職18', following the north boundary of chemin de la Montagne nord (as shown on the original cadastral plan), a distance of 44.21 m; thence, on an azimuth bearing of 277脣職16', following the north boundary of chemin de la Montagne nord (as shown on the original cadastral plan), to a point located at the intersection of the said boundary and the division line between lots 14 and 15, range 6, cadastre of the Township of Hull, a distance of 18.50 m; thence, on an azimuth bearing of 270脣職54', following the north boundary of chemin de la Montagne nord (as shown on the original cadastral plan), a distance of 21.73 m; thence, on an azimuth bearing of 259脣職54', following the north boundary of chemin de la Montagne nord (as shown on the original cadastral plan), a distance of 36.79 m; thence, on an azimuth bearing of 257脣職18', following the north boundary of chemin de la Montagne nord (as shown on the original cadastral plan), a distance of 43.29 m; thence, on an azimuth bearing of 262脣職56', following the north boundary of chemin de la Montagne nord (as shown on the original cadastral plan), a distance of 28.82 m; thence, on an azimuth bearing of 274脣職39', following the north boundary of chemin de la Montagne nord (as shown on the original cadastral plan), a distance of 23.87 m; thence, on an azimuth bearing of 284脣職08', following the north boundary of chemin de la Montagne nord (as shown on the original cadastral plan), a distance of 20.68 m; thence, on an azimuth bearing of 297脣職25', following the northeast boundary of chemin de la Montagne nord (as shown on the original cadastral plan), a distance of 16.22 m; thence, on an azimuth bearing of 297脣職28', following the northeast boundary of chemin de la Montagne nord (as shown on the original cadastral plan), a distance of 105.55 m; thence, on an azimuth bearing of 302脣職41', following the northeast boundary of chemin de la Montagne nord (as shown on the original cadastral plan), a distance of 27.53 m; thence, on an azimuth bearing of 314脣職58', following the northeast boundary of chemin de la Montagne nord (as shown on the original cadastral plan), a distance of 17.80 m; thence, on an azimuth bearing of 316脣職03', following the northeast boundary of chemin de la Montagne nord (as shown on the original cadastral plan), a distance of 39.62 m; thence, on an azimuth bearing of 310脣職41', following the northeast boundary of chemin de la Montagne nord (as shown on the original cadastral plan), a distance of 27.14 m; thence, on an azimuth bearing of 307脣職17', following the northeast boundary of chemin de la Montagne nord (as shown on the original cadastral plan), a distance of 54.95 m; thence, on an azimuth bearing of 308脣職33', following the northeast boundary of chemin de la Montagne nord (as shown on the original cadastral plan) and the southwest boundary of Skyridge Road (lot 15-4, range 6, cadastre of the Township of Hull), a distance of 32.01 m; thence, on an azimuth bearing of 301脣職39', following the northeast boundary of chemin de la Montagne nord (as shown on the original cadastral plan), a distance of 40.33 m; thence, on an azimuth bearing of 285脣職25', following the north boundary of chemin de la Montagne nord (as shown on the original cadastral plan), a distance of 66.57 m; thence, on an azimuth bearing of 280脣職13', following the north boundary of chemin de la Montagne nord (as shown on the original cadastral plan), to a point located at the intersection of the division line between lots 15 and 16C, range 6, cadastre of the Township of Hull, a distance of 39.26 m; thence, on an azimuth bearing of 276脣職25', following the north boundary of chemin de la Montagne nord (as shown on the original cadastral plan), a distance of 33.10 m; thence, on an azimuth bearing of 285脣職47', following the north boundary of chemin de la Montagne nord (as shown on the original cadastral plan), a distance of 21.80 m; thence, on an azimuth bearing of 292脣職13', following the north boundary of chemin de la Montagne nord (as shown on the original cadastral plan), a distance of 20.77 m; thence, on an azimuth bearing of 296脣職10', following the northeast boundary of chemin de la Montagne nord (as shown on the original cadastral plan), a distance of 25.71 m; thence, on an azimuth bearing of 297脣職07', following the northeast boundary of chemin de la Montagne nord (as shown on the original cadastral plan), a distance of 101.29 m; thence, on an azimuth bearing of 296脣職21', following the northeast boundary of chemin de la Montagne nord (as shown on the original cadastral plan), a distance of 69.42 m; thence, on an azimuth bearing of 303脣職30', following the northeast boundary of chemin de la Montagne nord (as shown on the original cadastral plan), a distance of 129.60 m; thence, on an azimuth bearing of 302脣職10', following the northeast boundary of chemin de la Montagne nord (as shown on the original cadastral plan), a distance of 59.21 m; thence, northwesterly, following the northeast boundary of chemin de la Montagne nord (as shown on the original cadastral plan), 29.15 m following the arc of a circle 75.65 m in radius; thence, on an azimuth bearing of 324脣職15', following the northeast boundary of chemin de la Montagne nord (as shown on the original cadastral plan), a distance of 34.06 m; thence, northwesterly, following the northeast boundary of chemin de la Montagne nord (as shown on the original cadastral plan), 61.46 m following the arc of a circle 99.70 m in radius; thence, on an azimuth bearing of 286脣職04', following the north boundary of chemin de la Montagne nord (as shown on the original cadastral plan), a distance of 40.03 m; thence, on an azimuth bearing of 288脣職56', following the north boundary of chemin de la Montagne nord (as shown on the original cadastral plan), a distance of 40.00 m; thence, on an azimuth bearing of 278脣職29', following the north boundary of chemin de la Montagne nord (as shown on the original cadastral plan), to a point located at the intersection of the division line between lots 16C and 17, range 6, cadastre of the Township of Hull, a distance of 20.34 m; thence, on an azimuth bearing of 288脣職38', following the north boundary of chemin de la Montagne nord (as shown on the original cadastral plan), a distance of 62.53 m; thence, on an azimuth bearing of 303脣職48', following the northeast boundary of chemin de la Montagne nord (as shown on the original cadastral plan), a distance of 21.43 m; thence, on an azimuth bearing of 311脣職14', following the northeast boundary of chemin de la Montagne nord (as shown on the original cadastral plan), a distance of 41.42 m; thence, on an azimuth bearing of 315脣職58', following the northeast boundary of chemin de la Montagne nord (as shown on the original cadastral plan), a distance of 42.52 m; thence, on an azimuth bearing of 316脣職39', following the northeast boundary of chemin de la Montagne nord (as shown on the original cadastral plan), a distance of 48.57 m; thence, on an azimuth bearing of 316脣職04', following the northeast boundary of chemin de la Montagne nord (as shown on the original cadastral plan), a distance of 35.96 m; thence, on an azimuth bearing of 301脣職20', following the northeast boundary of chemin de la Montagne nord (as shown on the original cadastral plan), a distance of 19.48 m; thence, on an azimuth bearing of 295脣職17', following the northeast boundary of chemin de la Montagne nord (as shown on the original cadastral plan), a distance of 22.45 m; thence, on an azimuth bearing of 290脣職56', following the north boundary of chemin de la Montagne nord (as shown on the original cadastral plan), a distance of 53.54 m; thence, on an azimuth bearing of 289脣職43', following the north boundary of chemin de la Montagne nord (as shown on the original cadastral plan), a distance of 68.60 m; thence, on an azimuth bearing of 281脣職52', following the north boundary of chemin de la Montagne nord (as shown on the original cadastral plan), a distance of 26.85 m; thence, on an azimuth bearing of 272脣職32', following the north boundary of chemin de la Montagne nord (as shown on the original cadastral plan), a distance of 31.55 m; thence, on an azimuth bearing of 270脣職47', following the north boundary of chemin de la Montagne nord (as shown on the original cadastral plan), a distance of 77.11 m; thence, on an azimuth bearing of 268脣職26', following the north boundary of chemin de la Montagne nord (as shown on the original cadastral plan), a distance of 41.15 m; thence, on an azimuth bearing of 265脣職19', following the north boundary of chemin de la Montagne nord (as shown on the original cadastral plan), a distance of 34.02 m; thence, on an azimuth bearing of 262脣職41', following the north boundary of chemin de la Montagne nord (as shown on the original cadastral plan), a distance of 78.44 m; thence, on an azimuth bearing of 262脣職13', following the north boundary of chemin de la Montagne nord (as shown on the original cadastral plan), a distance of 27.43 m; thence, on an azimuth bearing of 262脣職27', following the north boundary of chemin de la Montagne nord (as shown on the original cadastral plan), a distance of 59.96 m; thence, on an azimuth bearing of 262脣職24', following the north boundary of chemin de la Montagne nord (as shown on the original cadastral plan), a distance of 190.90 m; thence, on an azimuth bearing of 261脣職37', following the north boundary of chemin de la Montagne nord (as shown on the original cadastral plan), a distance of 65.23 m; thence, on an azimuth bearing of 263脣職50', following the north boundary of chemin de la Montagne nord (as shown on the original cadastral plan), to a point located at the intersection of the division line between lots 18 and 19A, range 6, cadastre of the Township of Hull, a distance of 112.25 m; thence, on an azimuth bearing of 267脣職22', following the north boundary of chemin de la Montagne nord (as shown on the original cadastral plan), a distance of 101.16 m; thence, on an azimuth bearing of 266脣職28', following the north boundary of chemin de la Montagne nord (as shown on the original cadastral plan), a distance of 96.29 m; thence, on an azimuth bearing of 272脣職26', following the north boundary of chemin de la Montagne nord (as shown on the original cadastral plan), a distance of 72.29 m; thence, on an azimuth bearing of 280脣職29', following the north boundary of chemin de la Montagne nord (as shown on the original cadastral plan), a distance of 48.24 m; thence, on an azimuth bearing of 282脣職48', following the north boundary of chemin de la Montagne nord (as shown on the original cadastral plan), a distance of 47.43 m; thence, on an azimuth bearing of 283脣職31', following the north boundary of chemin de la Montagne nord (as shown on the original cadastral plan), a distance of 73.12 m; thence, on an azimuth bearing of 284脣職40', following the north boundary of chemin de la Montagne nord (as shown on the original cadastral plan), a distance of 45.35 m; thence, on an azimuth bearing of 287脣職50', following the north boundary of chemin de la Montagne nord (as shown on the original cadastral plan), a distance of 34.74 m; thence, on an azimuth bearing of 293脣職56', following the northeast boundary of chemin de la Montagne nord (as shown on the original cadastral plan), a distance of 18.26 m; thence, on an azimuth bearing of 297脣職21', following the northeast boundary of chemin de la Montagne nord (as shown on the original cadastral plan), to a point located at the intersection of the division line between lots 19A and 20A, range 6, cadastre of the Township of Hull, a distance of 22.00 m; thence, on an azimuth bearing of 303脣職31', following the northeast boundary of chemin de la Montagne nord (as shown on the original cadastral plan), a distance of 51.72 m; thence, on an azimuth bearing of 288脣職45', following the north boundary of chemin de la Montagne nord (as shown on the original cadastral plan), a distance of 45.53 m; thence, on an azimuth bearing of 286脣職26', following the north boundary of chemin de la Montagne nord (as shown on the original cadastral plan), a distance of 34.92 m; thence, on an azimuth bearing of 297脣職34', following the northeast boundary of chemin de la Montagne nord (as shown on the original cadastral plan), a distance of 28.82 m; thence, on an azimuth bearing of 308脣職26', following the northeast boundary of chemin de la Montagne nord (as shown on the original cadastral plan), a distance of 26.29 m; thence, on an azimuth bearing of 311脣職05', following the northeast boundary of chemin de la Montagne nord (as shown on the original cadastral plan), a distance of 70.68 m; thence, on an azimuth bearing of 312脣職45', following the northeast boundary of chemin de la Montagne nord (as shown on the original cadastral plan), a distance of 93.11 m; thence, on an azimuth bearing of 311脣職56', following the northeast boundary of chemin de la Montagne nord (as shown on the original cadastral plan), a distance of 44.83 m; thence, on an azimuth bearing of 310脣職44', following the northeast boundary of chemin de la Montagne nord (as shown on the original cadastral plan), a distance of 106.35 m; thence, on an azimuth bearing of 305脣職12', following the northeast boundary of chemin de la Montagne nord (as shown on the original cadastral plan), a distance of 38.47 m; thence, on an azimuth bearing of 304脣職20', following the northeast boundary of chemin de la Montagne nord (as shown on the original cadastral plan), a distance of 62.26 m; thence, on an azimuth bearing of 308脣職42', following the northeast boundary of chemin de la Montagne nord (as shown on the original cadastral plan), a distance of 33.63 m; thence, on an azimuth bearing of 311脣職04', following the northeast boundary of chemin de la Montagne nord (as shown on the original cadastral plan), a distance of 50.27 m; thence, on an azimuth bearing of 315脣職14芒聙聶, following the northeast boundary of chemin de la Montagne nord (as shown on the original cadastral plan), a distance of 37.19 m; thence, on an azimuth bearing of 317脣職26芒聙聶, following the northeast boundary of chemin de la Montagne nord (as shown on the original cadastral plan), to a point located at the intersection of the division line between lots 20 and 21, range 7, cadastre of the Township of Hull, a distance of 6.20 m; thence, on an azimuth bearing of 317脣職26芒聙聶, following the northeast boundary of chemin de la Montagne nord (as shown on the original cadastral plan), a distance of 89.64 m; thence, on an azimuth bearing of 319脣職45芒聙聶, following the northeast boundary of chemin de la Montagne nord (as shown on the original cadastral plan), a distance of 145.42 m; thence, on an azimuth bearing of 319脣職17芒聙聶, following the northeast boundary of chemin de la Montagne nord (as shown on the original cadastral plan), a distance of 83.89 m; thence, on an azimuth bearing of 318脣職39芒聙聶, following the northeast boundary of chemin de la Montagne nord (as shown on the original cadastral plan), a distance of 29.39 m; thence, on an azimuth bearing of 315脣職12芒聙聶, following the northeast boundary of chemin de la Montagne nord (as shown on the original cadastral plan), a distance of 31.51 m; thence, on an azimuth bearing of 311脣職03芒聙聶, following the northeast boundary of chemin de la Montagne nord (as shown on the original cadastral plan), a distance of 69.43 m; thence, on an azimuth bearing of 312脣職55芒聙聶, following the northeast boundary of chemin de la Montagne nord (as shown on the original cadastral plan), a distance of 33.54 m; thence, on an azimuth bearing of 319脣職53芒聙聶, following the northeast boundary of chemin de la Montagne nord (as shown on the original cadastral plan), a distance of 58.23 m; thence, on an azimuth bearing of 328脣職34芒聙聶, following the northeast boundary of chemin de la Montagne nord (as shown on the original cadastral plan), a distance of 66.81 m; thence, on an azimuth bearing of 328脣職01芒聙聶, following the northeast boundary of chemin de la Montagne nord (as shown on the original cadastral plan), a distance of 115.41 m; thence, on an azimuth bearing of 325脣職14芒聙聶, following the northeast boundary of chemin de la Montagne nord (as shown on the original cadastral plan), a distance of 133.25 m; thence, on an azimuth bearing of 326脣職35芒聙聶, following the northeast boundary of chemin de la Montagne nord (as shown on the original cadastral plan), to a point located at the intersection of the division line between lots 21 and 22, range 7, cadastre of the Township of Hull, a distance of 119.94 m; thence, on an azimuth bearing of 325脣職40芒聙聶, following the northeast boundary of chemin de la Montagne nord (as shown on the original cadastral plan), a distance of 33.57 m; thence, on an azimuth bearing of 320脣職24芒聙聶, following the northeast boundary of chemin de la Montagne nord (as shown on the original cadastral plan), a distance of 35.04 m; thence, on an azimuth bearing of 312脣職03芒聙聶, following the northeast boundary of chemin de la Montagne nord (as shown on the original cadastral plan), a distance of 104.08 m; thence, on an azimuth bearing of 314脣職10芒聙聶, following the northeast boundary of chemin de la Montagne nord (as shown on the original cadastral plan), a distance of 54.26 m; thence, on an azimuth bearing of 318脣職29芒聙聶, following the northeast boundary of chemin de la Montagne nord (as shown on the original cadastral plan), a distance of 35.35 m; thence, on an azimuth bearing of 320脣職33芒聙聶, following the northeast boundary of chemin de la Montagne nord (as shown on the original cadastral plan), a distance of 110.86 m; thence, on an azimuth bearing of 322脣職14芒聙聶, following the northeast boundary of chemin de la Montagne nord (as shown on the original cadastral plan), a distance of 81.36 m; thence, on an azimuth bearing of 324脣職16芒聙聶, following the northeast boundary of chemin de la Montagne nord (as shown on the original cadastral plan), a distance of 33.47 m; thence, on an azimuth bearing of 331脣職58芒聙聶, following the northeast boundary of chemin de la Montagne nord (as shown on the original cadastral plan), a distance of 60.65 m; thence, on an azimuth bearing of 340脣職13芒聙聶, following the east boundary of chemin de la Montagne nord (as shown on the original cadastral plan), a distance of 33.32 m; thence, on an azimuth bearing of 356脣職47芒聙聶, following the east boundary of chemin de la Montagne nord (as shown on the original cadastral plan), a distance of 28.69 m; thence, on an azimuth bearing of 3脣職27芒聙聶, following the east boundary of chemin de la Montagne nord (as shown on the original cadastral plan), a distance of 126.46 m; thence, on an azimuth bearing of 358脣職40芒聙聶, following the east boundary of chemin de la Montagne nord (as shown on the original cadastral plan), a distance of 25.67 m; thence, on an azimuth bearing of 350脣職44芒聙聶, following the east boundary of chemin de la Montagne nord (as shown on the original cadastral plan), a distance of 15.95 m; thence, on an azimuth bearing of 348脣職11芒聙聶, following the east boundary of chemin de la Montagne nord (as shown on the original cadastral plan), a distance of 31.70 m; thence, on an azimuth bearing of 319脣職05芒聙聶, following the northeast boundary of chemin de la Montagne nord (as shown on the original cadastral plan), a distance of 35.36 m; thence, on an azimuth bearing of 323脣職06芒聙聶, following the northeast boundary of chemin de la Montagne nord (as shown on the original cadastral plan), a distance of 27.24 m; thence, on an azimuth bearing of 319脣職53芒聙聶, following the northeast boundary of chemin de la Montagne nord (as shown on the original cadastral plan), a distance of 31.04 m; thence, on an azimuth bearing of 317脣職38芒聙聶, following the northeast boundary of chemin de la Montagne nord (as shown on the original cadastral plan), a distance of 23.45 m; thence, on an azimuth bearing of 314脣職51芒聙聶, following the northeast boundary of chemin de la Montagne nord (as shown on the original cadastral plan), to a point located at the intersection of the division line between lot 22, range 7, cadastre of the Township of Hull and lot 2 635 271, Cadastre du Qu脙漏bec, a distance of 9.68 m.</Text>
</Provision>
<BillPiece><Heading level="2"><TitleText>2.2 Section 2</TitleText></Heading></BillPiece><Provision>
<Text>This portion of Gatineau Park, described in Section芒聙炉2, is included in the registration division of Gatineau, located in the Municipality of Chelsea, and forms part of the Cadastre du Qu脙漏bec.</Text>
</Provision><BillPiece><Heading level="3"><TitleText>Municipality of Chelsea</TitleText></Heading></BillPiece><Provision topmarginspacing="-.75">
<Text>
Beginning at the southeast corner of lot <Keep>2芒聙炉636芒聙炉632</Keep> (chemin de la Montagne nord), northwesterly, following the division lines between lots <Keep>2芒聙炉636芒聙炉632</Keep> (chemin de la Montagne nord) and <Keep>2芒聙炉635芒聙炉271</Keep>, to the west corner of lot <Keep>2芒聙炉635芒聙炉271</Keep>; thence, northwesterly, following the division lines between lots <Keep>2芒聙炉636芒聙炉632</Keep> (chemin de la Montagne nord) and <Keep>2芒聙炉635芒聙炉272</Keep>, to the west corner of lot <Keep>2芒聙炉635芒聙炉272</Keep>; thence, in a general northwesterly direction, following the division lines between lots <Keep>2芒聙炉636芒聙炉632</Keep> (chemin de la Montagne nord) and <Keep>2芒聙炉635芒聙炉270</Keep>, to the west corner of lot <Keep>2芒聙炉635芒聙炉270</Keep>; thence, westerly, following the division line between lots <Keep>2芒聙炉636芒聙炉632</Keep> (chemin de la Montagne nord) and <Keep>2芒聙炉635芒聙炉272</Keep>, to the west corner of lot <Keep>2芒聙炉635芒聙炉272</Keep>; thence, westerly, following the division lines between lot <Keep>2芒聙炉636芒聙炉632</Keep> (chemin de la Montagne nord) and lots <Keep>2芒聙炉635芒聙炉270</Keep>, <Keep>2芒聙炉635芒聙炉272</Keep> and <Keep>2芒聙炉635芒聙炉273</Keep>, to the northwest corner of lot <Keep>2芒聙炉636芒聙炉632</Keep> (chemin de la Montagne nord); thence, westerly, following the division lines between lots <Keep>2芒聙炉735芒聙炉412</Keep> (chemin de la Montagne nord) and <Keep>2芒聙炉635芒聙炉273</Keep>, to the southeast corner of lot <Keep>2芒聙炉635芒聙炉259</Keep>; thence, in a general westerly direction, following the division lines between lots <Keep>2芒聙炉735芒聙炉412</Keep> (chemin de la Montagne nord) and <Keep>2芒聙炉635芒聙炉259</Keep>, to the northwest corner of lot <Keep>2芒聙炉735芒聙炉412</Keep>; thence, westerly, following the division lines between lots <Keep>2芒聙炉735芒聙炉411</Keep> (chemin de la Montagne nord) and <Keep>2芒聙炉635芒聙炉259</Keep>, to the southwest corner of lot <Keep>2芒聙炉635芒聙炉259</Keep>; thence, in a general westerly direction, following the division lines between lots <Keep>2芒聙炉735芒聙炉411</Keep> (chemin de la Montagne nord) and <Keep>2芒聙炉635芒聙炉273</Keep>, to the northwest corner of lot <Keep>2芒聙炉735芒聙炉411</Keep>; thence, northwesterly, following the division lines between lots <Keep>2芒聙炉735芒聙炉408</Keep> (chemin de la Montagne nord) and <Keep>2芒聙炉635芒聙炉273</Keep>, to the north corner of lot <Keep>2芒聙炉735芒聙炉408</Keep>; thence, in a general northwesterly direction, following the division lines between lots <Keep>2芒聙炉735芒聙炉407</Keep> (chemin de la Montagne nord) and <Keep>2芒聙炉635芒聙炉273</Keep>, to the northwest corner of lot <Keep>2芒聙炉735芒聙炉407</Keep>; thence, westerly, following the division lines between lots <Keep>2芒聙炉636芒聙炉633</Keep> (chemin de la Montagne nord) and <Keep>2芒聙炉635芒聙炉273</Keep>, to the northwest corner of lot <Keep>2芒聙炉636芒聙炉633</Keep>; thence, in a general westerly direction, following the division lines between lots <Keep>2芒聙炉735芒聙炉406</Keep> (chemin de la Montagne nord) and <Keep>2芒聙炉635芒聙炉273</Keep>, to the southeast corner of lot <Keep>2芒聙炉635芒聙炉406</Keep>; thence, northwesterly, following the division lines between lots <Keep>2芒聙炉735芒聙炉404</Keep> (chemin de la Montagne nord) and <Keep>2芒聙炉635芒聙炉406</Keep>, to the north corner of lot <Keep>2芒聙炉735芒聙炉404</Keep>; thence, northwesterly, following the division line between lot <Keep>2芒聙炉735芒聙炉403</Keep> (chemin de la Montagne nord) and lots <Keep>2芒聙炉635芒聙炉406</Keep> and <Keep>2芒聙炉635芒聙炉074</Keep>, to the north corner of lot <Keep>2芒聙炉735芒聙炉403</Keep>; thence, in a general northwesterly direction, following the division lines between lots <Keep>2芒聙炉735芒聙炉402</Keep> (chemin de la Montagne nord) and <Keep>2芒聙炉635芒聙炉074</Keep>, to the northwest corner of lot <Keep>2芒聙炉735芒聙炉402</Keep>; thence, westerly, following the division lines between lots <Keep>2芒聙炉636芒聙炉634</Keep> (chemin de la Montagne nord) and <Keep>2芒聙炉635芒聙炉074</Keep>, to the northwest corner of lot <Keep>2芒聙炉636芒聙炉634</Keep>; thence, westerly, following the lines between lot <Keep>2芒聙炉735芒聙炉399</Keep> (chemin de la Montagne nord) and lots <Keep>2芒聙炉635芒聙炉074</Keep>, <Keep>2芒聙炉635芒聙炉020</Keep> and <Keep>2芒聙炉635芒聙炉074</Keep>, to the northwest corner of lot <Keep>2芒聙炉735芒聙炉399</Keep>; thence, westerly, following the division lines between lots <Keep>2芒聙炉636芒聙炉635</Keep> (chemin de la Montagne nord) and <Keep>2芒聙炉635芒聙炉074</Keep>, to the northwest corner of lot <Keep>2芒聙炉636芒聙炉635</Keep>; thence, westerly, following the division lines between lots <Keep>2芒聙炉735芒聙炉398</Keep> (chemin de la Montagne nord) and <Keep>2芒聙炉635芒聙炉074</Keep>, to the northwest corner of lot <Keep>2芒聙炉735芒聙炉398</Keep>.</Text>
</Provision>
<BillPiece><Heading level="2"><TitleText>2.3 Section 3</TitleText></Heading></BillPiece><Provision>
<Text>This portion of Gatineau Park, described in Section芒聙炉3, is included in the registration divisions of Gatineau and Pontiac, located in the Municipalities of Pontiac and La P脙陋che and forms part of the cadastres of the Township of Aldfield, the Township of Eardley, the Township of Masham, the Township of Onslow and the Cadastre du Qu脙漏bec.</Text>
</Provision><BillPiece><Heading level="3"><TitleText>Municipality of Pontiac</TitleText></Heading></BillPiece>
<Provision>
<Text>Beginning at the southeast corner of lot 2 684 171, westerly and then northwesterly, following the division lines between lots 2 756 027 (chemin de la Montagne nord) and 2 684 171, to the northwest corner of lot 2 756 027; thence, in a general northwesterly direction, following the division lines between lots 2 756 028 (chemin de la Montagne nord) and 2 684 171, to the northwest corner of lot 2 684 171; thence, easterly, following the division line between lots 2 684 171 and 2 750 617, to the most southwesterly corner of lot 2 683 938, a distance of 20.77 m; thence, easterly, following the division line between lots 2 683 938 and 2 750 617, to a point located at a distance of 31.44 m; thence, northeasterly, following the division line between lots 2 683 938 and 2 750 617, to a point located at a distance of 16.83 m; thence, in a general northerly-northwesterly direction, following the division lines between lots 2 683 938 and 2 750 617, to a point located at the northwest corner of lot 2 750 617; thence, westerly and northwesterly, following the division line between lots 2 683 938 and 2 683 923, to a point located at the northwest corner of lot 2 683 923; thence, northwesterly, northerly and westerly, following the division lines between lots 2 683 937 and 2 683 938, to a point located at the northeast corner of lot 2 683 821; thence, westerly, following the division line between lots 2 683 821 and 2 683 938, to a point located at the northwest corner of lot 2 683 821; thence, westerly, following the division line between lots 2 683 820 and 2 683 938, to a point located at the northwest corner of lot 2 683 820; thence, in a general northwesterly direction, following the division line between lots 2 683 819 and 2 683 938, to a point located at the northwest corner of lot 2 683 819; thence, northwesterly, following the division line between lots 2 683 938 and 2 683 818, to the north corner of lot 2 683 818; thence, westerly, following the division line between lots 2 683 818 and 2 683 822, to a point located at a distance of approximately 103 m; thence, on an azimuth bearing of 350脣職53', to a point located at 287.90 m; thence, on an azimuth bearing of 315脣職35', to a point located at 3.85 m; thence, on an azimuth bearing of 263脣職05', to a point located at the intersection of the east boundary of lot 2 683 751; thence, northerly, following the division line between lots 2 683 751 and 2 683 822, to a point located at the northeast corner of lot 2 683 751; thence, westerly, following the division lines between lots 2 683 751 and 2 683 822, to a point located at the northwest corner of lot 2 683 751; thence, westerly, following the division lines between lots 2 755 775 and 2 683 822, to a point located at the southeast corner of lot 2 683 558; thence, northerly, following the division line between lots 2 683 558 and 2 683 822, to a point located at the northeast corner of lot 2 683 558; thence, westerly, following the division lines between lots 2 683 558 and 2 683 822, to a point located at the northwest corner of lot 2 683 558; thence, southwesterly, following the division lines between lots 2 755 775 and 2 683 822, to a point located at distances of 32.50 m and 35.65 m; thence, westerly, following the division line between lots 2 755 775 and 2 683 822, to a point located at the northwest corner of lot 2 755 775; thence, southerly, following the division line between lots 2 683 822 and 2 755 775, to the northeast corner of lot 2 683 557; thence, westerly, following the division line between lots 2 683 822 and 2 683 557, to a point located at the northwest corner of lot 2 683 557; thence, northerly, following the division line between lots 2 683 822 and 2 683 556, to a point located at the northeast corner of lot 2 683 556; thence, westerly, following the division lines between lots 2 683 822 and 2 683 556, to a point located at the northwest corner of lot 2 683 556; thence, westerly, following the division line between lot 2 683 822 and lots 2 755 747 and 2 755 746 to a point located at the northwest corner of lot 2 755 746; thence, northwesterly, crossing lot 2 683 464, to a point located at the southeast corner of lot 2 750 624; thence, northwesterly, crossing lot 2 750 624, to a point located at the northwest corner of lot 2 750 624; thence, northerly, following the division line between lots 2 750 622 and 2 864 183 (Chemin de l芒聙聶H脙麓tel-de-Ville), to a point located at the northeast corner of lot 2 864 183 (Chemin de l芒聙聶H脙麓tel-de-Ville); thence, westerly, following the division line between lots 2 750 622 and 2 864 183 (Chemin de l芒聙聶H脙麓tel-de-Ville), to a point located at the southeast corner of lot 2 750 623; thence, westerly, following the division line between lots 2 750 623 and 2 864 183 (Chemin de l芒聙聶H脙麓tel-de-Ville), to a point located at the southwest corner of lot 2 750 623; thence, westerly, following the division line between lots 2 889 768 and 2 864 182 (Chemin de l芒聙聶H脙麓tel-de-Ville), to a point located at the southeast corner of lot 2 683 360; thence, northerly, following the division line between lots 2 889 768 and 2 683 360, to a point located at the northwest corner of lot 2 889 768; thence, in a westerly, northerly and westerly directions, following the division line between lots 2 683 360 and 2 750 622, to a point located at the intersection of the east boundary of lot 2 682 401; thence, northerly, following the division line between lot 2 750 622 and lots 2 682 401 and 2 683 356, to a point located at the northeast corner of lot 2 683 356; thence, westerly, following the division line between lot 2 750 622 and lots 2 683 356, 2 755 693 and 2 683 351, to a point located at the intersection of the east boundary of lot 2 683 347; thence, northerly, northwesterly and southwesterly, following the division line between lots 2 750 622 and 2 683 347, to a point located at the northwest corner of lot 2 683 347; thence, northerly, following the division line between lot 2 750 622 and lots 2 683 100, 2 864 184, 2 683 102, 2 683 141, 2 683 140, 2 683 142 and 2 683 143, to a point located at the east corner of lot 2 683 143; thence, northwesterly, following the division line between lot 2 750 622 and lots 2 683 143, 2 683 144 and 2 683 138, to a point located at the northwest corner of lot 2 750 622; thence, westerly, following the division line between lot 2 756 039 and lots 2 683 138, 2 683 129 and 2 683 128, to a point located at the northwest corner of lot 2 683 128; thence, northerly, following the division line between lots 2 756 039 and 2 683 117, to a point located at the northeast corner of lot 2 683 117; thence, northwesterly, following the division line between lots 2 756 039 and 2 683 117, to a point located at the northwest corner of lot 2 683 117; thence, northwesterly, following the division line between lots 2 756 039 and 2 683 103, to a point located at the northwest corner of lot 2 683 103; thence, northwesterly, following the division line between lots 2 756 039 and 2 872 193, to a point located at the north corner of lot 2 872 193; thence, in a general northwesterly direction, following the division lines between lots 2 756 039 and 2 750 627, to a point located at the northwest corner of lot 2 750 627; thence, southerly, following the division line between lots 2 750 627 and 2 750 628, to a point located at the southwest corner of lot 2 750 627; thence, westerly, following the division line between lot 2 750 628 and lots 2 682 987, 2 755 643, 2 682 904, 2 750 709, 2 682 899, 2 682 896 and 2 864 191, to a point located at the southwest corner of lot 2 750 628; thence, westerly, crossing lots 2 682 908 and 2 682 889, to a point located at the southeast corner of lot 2 682 670; thence, westerly, following the division lines between lots 2 682 666 and 2 682 670, to a point located at the southwest corner of lot 2 682 670; thence, on an azimuth bearing of 295脣職24芒聙聶, to a point located at a distance of 72.02 m; thence, on an azimuth bearing of 350脣職47芒聙聶, to a point located at a distance of 283.68 m; thence, northwesterly, crossing lots 2 682 669, 2 750 682, 2 682 667 and 2 872 186, to a point located at the intersection of the division line between lots 2 756 041 and 2 872 186, at an approximate distance of 677 m. This point is also located at an approximate distance of 235 m easterly of the northwest corner of lot 2 682 507; thence, westerly, following the division line between lot 2 756 041 and lots 2 872 186, 2 682 507, 2 750 676 and 2 750 675, to a point located at the northwest corner of lot 2 750 675; thence, westerly, crossing lot 2 864 194, to a point located at the northeast corner of lot 2 750 674; thence, westerly, following the division line between lots 2 682 498 and 2 750 674, to the southwest corner of lot 2 682 498; thence, northerly, following the division line between lots 2 682 498 and 2 872 178, and then following the division line between lots 2 682 499 and 2 872 179, to the northwest corner of lot 2 682 499; thence, westerly, following the division line between lots 2 682 501 and 2 872 179, to the northwest corner of lot 2 872 179; thence, westerly, following the division lines between lot 2 750 673 and lots 2 682 501 and 2 750 633, to the northwest corner of lot 2 750 673; thence, westerly, following the division line between lot 2 864 199 and lots 2 682 500 and 2 682 472, to a point located at an approximate distance of 521.6 m; thence, northerly, to a point located at the intersection of the south boundary of lot 3 964 882, at an approximate distance of 403.1 m; thence, westerly, following the deflections of the division line between lot 3 964 882 and 2 682 472, to the southwest corner of lot 3 964 882, at distances of 122.30 m and 192.75 m; thence, northerly, following the division line between lots 2 682 472 and 3 964 882, to the northeast corner of lot 2 682 472; thence, westerly, following the division line between lots 2 682 472 and 3 964 882, to the northwest corner of lot 2 682 472; thence, in a general northeasterly direction, following the deflections of the east and southeast boundaries of chemin Eardley-Masham, namely, the division lines between lots 3 754 086 and 3 964 882; 3 754 087 and 3 964 882; 3 754 088 and 2 682 471, to the northeast corner of lot 3 754 088 (chemin Eardley-Masham); thence, westerly, following the division line between lots 3 754 088 and 3 754 089, to the west corner of lot 3 754 089; thence, westerly, following the division line between lots 2 750 634 and 2 682 469, to the northwest corner of lot 2 682 469; thence, westerly, following the deflections of the division line between lots 2 682 402 and 2 750 634, to the northwest corner of lot 2 682 402; thence, westerly, crossing lot 2 682 400 in a straight line and then lot 2 872 173, to the southeast corner of lot 2 889 747; thence, westerly, following the deflections of the division line between lot 2 889 747 and lots 2 682 399 and 2 682 398, to the southwest corner of lot 2 889 747; thence, on an azimuth bearing of 257脣職19'29" to a point located on the division line between lots 28C and 28B, range 6, cadastre of the Township of Onslow, a distance of 270.87 m; thence, on an azimuth bearing of 281脣職17'52" to a point located on the division line between lots 28B and 27C, range 6, cadastre of the Township of Onslow, a distance of 268.35 m; thence, on an azimuth bearing of 311脣職05'59" to a point located at a distance of 229.29 m; thence, on an azimuth bearing of 264脣職51'24", to a point located at a distance of 204.61 m; thence, on an azimuth bearing of 266脣職55'21", to a point located on the division line between lots 27A and 26C, range 6, cadastre of the Township of Onslow, a distance of 156.85 m; thence, on an azimuth bearing of 262脣職08'55", to a point located on the division line between lots 26C and 26B, range 6, cadastre of the Township of Onslow, a distance of 262.26 m; thence, on an azimuth bearing of 288脣職35'18", to a point located on the division line between lots 26B and 25B, range 6, cadastre of the Township of Onslow, a distance of 282.32 m; thence, on an azimuth bearing of 321脣職07'40" to a point located on the division line between the ranges 6 and 7, cadastre of the Township of Onslow, a distance of 164.54 m; thence, following the division line between the ranges 6 and 7, cadastre of the Township of Onslow, on an azimuth bearing of 265脣職18'24" to the east boundary of chemin Wilson a distance of 418.49 m; thence, on an azimuth bearing of 295脣職30'01", to a point located at a distance of 12.63 m; thence, on an azimuth bearing of 265脣職33'46", to a point located on the division line between lots 24A and 23B, range 7, cadastre of the Township of Onslow, a distance of 516.54 m; thence, on an azimuth bearing of 260脣職51'03", to a point located at a distance of 18.97 m; thence, on an azimuth bearing of 224脣職48'09", to a point located at a distance of 64.20 m; thence, on an azimuth bearing of 243脣職04'58", to a point located at a distance of 53.53 m; thence, on an azimuth bearing of 259脣職54'37", to a point located at a distance of 32.50 m; thence, on an azimuth bearing of 266脣職24'48", to a point located at a distance of 100.18 m; thence, on an azimuth bearing of 272脣職34'10", to a point located on the division line between lots 23B and 22B, range 7, cadastre of the Township of Onslow, a distance of 274.02 m; thence, on an azimuth bearing of 357脣職37'00" to a point located at the southwest corner of lot 23A, range 7, cadastre of the Township of Onslow, a distance of 28.99 m; thence, on an azimuth bearing of 268脣職33'20", to a point located at the southwest corner of lot 22A, range 7, cadastre of the Township of Onslow, a distance of 537.48 m; thence, on an azimuth bearing of 268脣職02'14", to a point located at a distance of 251.05 m; thence, on an azimuth bearing of 5脣職09'19", to a point located at a distance of 59.28 m; thence, on an azimuth bearing of 280脣職48'18", to a point located at a distance of 213.14 m; thence, on an azimuth bearing of 316脣職27'24", to a point located at a distance of 181.95 m; thence, on an azimuth bearing of 296脣職49'22", to a point located at a distance of 74.39 m; thence, on an azimuth bearing of 292脣職01'21", to a point located at a distance of 128.91 m; thence, on an azimuth bearing of 280脣職31'18", to a point located at a distance of 71.10 m; thence, on an azimuth bearing of 296脣職11'22", to a point located at a distance of 87.77 m; thence, on an azimuth bearing of 292脣職53'21", to a point located at a distance of 72.23 m; thence, on an azimuth bearing of 289脣職25'20", to a point located at a distance of 191.35 m; thence, on an azimuth bearing of 283脣職52'19", to a point located on the division line between lots 20A and 19A, range 7, cadastre of the Township of Onslow, a distance of 110.65 m; thence, on an azimuth bearing of 255脣職44'08", to a point located at a distance of 231.75 m; thence, on an azimuth bearing of 281脣職16'18", to a point located at a distance of 131.35 m; thence, on an azimuth bearing of 261脣職34'11", to a point located on the division line between lots 19A and 18A, range 7, cadastre of the Township of Onslow, a distance of 221.49 m; thence, on an azimuth bearing of 267脣職03'13", to a point located at a distance of 376.93 m; thence, on an azimuth bearing of 274脣職28'23", to a point located on the division line between lots 18A and 17A, range 7, cadastre of the Township of Onslow, a distance of 107.71 m; thence, on an azimuth bearing of 269脣職16'22", to a point located on the division line between lots 17A and 16C, range 7, cadastre of the Township of Onslow, a distance of 534.44 m; thence, on an azimuth bearing of 258脣職19'17", to a point located on the division line between lots 16B and 15A, range 7, cadastre of the Township of Onslow, a distance of 533.21 m; thence, on an azimuth bearing of 274脣職56'23", to a point located at a distance of 257.29 m; thence, on an azimuth bearing of 277脣職08'36", to a point located on the division line between lots 15A and 14B, range 7, cadastre of the Township of Onslow, a distance of 276.49 m; thence, on an azimuth bearing of 258脣職06'34", to a point located at a distance of 462.20 m; thence, on an azimuth bearing of 257脣職34'34", to a point located on the division line between lots 13C and 12B, range 7, cadastre of the Township of Onslow, a distance of 578.97 m; thence, on an azimuth bearing of 245脣職26'38", to a point located at a distance of 281.55 m; thence, on an azimuth bearing of 266脣職34'34", to a point located at a distance of 169.05 m; thence, on an azimuth bearing of 276脣職18'36", to a point located at a distance of 239.01 m; thence, on an azimuth bearing of 261脣職08'34", to a point located at a distance of 286.52 m; thence, on an azimuth bearing of 284脣職26'40", to a point located on the division line between lots 11B and 10A, range 7, cadastre of the Township of Onslow, a distance of 132.77 m; thence, on an azimuth bearing of 268脣職21'12", to a point located on the division line between lots 10A and 9B, range 7, cadastre of the Township of Onslow, a distance of 545.37 m; thence, on an azimuth bearing of 252脣職55'35", to a point located on the division line between lots 8B and 9B, range 7, cadastre of the Township of Onslow, a distance of 524.27 m; thence, northerly following the division line between lots 8A and 9A, range 7, cadastre of the Township of Onslow, a distance of 474.68 m; thence, northerly following the division line between lots 8A and 9A, range 7, cadastre of the Township of Onslow, a distance of 730.13 m; thence, northerly following the division line between lots 8A and 9A, range 7, then lots 8B and 9A, range 8, then lots 8D and 9C, range 8, all in the cadastre of the Township of Onslow, a distance of 992.58 m; thence, northerly following the division line between lots 8D and 9C, range 8, to the southwest corner of lot 9A, range 9, all in the cadastre of the Township of Onslow, a distance of 752.24 m; thence, northerly, following the division line between lot 8A from lots 9A and 9B, range 9, then following the division line between lot 8B from lots 9C and 9D, range 9, to the northwest corner of lot 9D, range 9, all in the cadastre of the Township of Onslow; thence, northerly following the division line between lot 8B from lots 9A and 9B, range 10, to the northwest corner of lot 9B, range 10, all in the cadastre of the Township of Onslow; thence, northerly following the division line between lots 8 and 9, range 11, to the northwest corner of lot 9, range 11, all in the cadastre of the Township of Onslow; thence, northerly, following the division line between lot 8A from lots 9A and 9B, range 12, then following the division line between lot 8B from lots 9B and 9C, range 12, to the northwest corner of lot 9C, range 12, all in the cadastre of the Township of Onslow; thence, northerly following the division line between lot 8C from lots 9A and 9B, range 13, to the northwest corner of lot 9B, range 13, cadastre of the Township of Onslow, located on the division line between the Townships of Aldfield and Onslow; thence, easterly following the division line between the Townships of Aldfield and Onslow to a point located at the northwest corner of lot 10C, range 13, cadastre of the Township of Onslow; thence, easterly following the division line between the Townships of Aldfield and Onslow, to a point located at a distance of 1,432.50 m; thence, easterly following the division line between the Townships of Aldfield and Onslow, to a point located at the northeast corner of lot 15B, range 13, cadastre of the Township of Onslow, a distance of 1,695.73 m; thence, easterly following the division line between the Townships of Aldfield and Onslow, to a point located at the northwest corner of lot 17C, range 13, cadastre of the Township of Onslow, a distance of 525.87 m; thence, easterly following the division line between the Townships of Aldfield and Onslow, to a point located on the west boundary of chemin Gauvin, a distance of 12.92 m; thence, southwesterly, following the northwest boundary of chemin Gauvin, at distances of 27.71 and 16.44 m; thence, southerly, following the west boundary of chemin Gauvin, at distances of 106.63 m and 29.67 m; thence, southeasterly, following the southwest boundary of chemin Gauvin, at distances of 29.95 m, 39.95 m, 27.98 m, 26.75 m and 25.99 m; thence, easterly following the south boundary of the chemin Gauvin, a distance of 136.53 m; thence, southeasterly, crossing chemin du Lac-La-P脙陋che, following the southwest boundary of chemin Gauvin, a distance of 15.55 m; thence, southeasterly, following the southwest boundary of chemin Gauvin, at distances of 11.65 m, 34.05 m and 13.04 m; thence, easterly, following the south boundary of chemin Gauvin, at distances of 10.07 m, 21.72 m, 13.51 m and 10.88 m; thence, southeasterly, following the southwest boundary of chemin Gauvin, a distance of 29.84 m; thence, easterly, following the south boundary of chemin Gauvin, at distances of 30.55 m, 81.02 m, 41.05 m, 32.62 m and 28.89 m; thence, northeasterly, following the southeast boundary of chemin Gauvin, a distance of 22.30 m; thence, easterly, following the south boundary of chemin Gauvin, at distances of 11.99 m, 35.90 m, 27.85 m, 40.14 m, 22.33 m and 9.07 m; thence, northeasterly, following the southeast boundary of chemin Gauvin, at distances of 12.51 m and 28.00 m; thence, following the southwest shore of ruisseau du Lac-des-Loups to the intersection of the division line between lots 18A and 18B, range 13, cadastre of the Township of Onslow; thence, northerly following the division line between lots 18A and 18B, range 13, cadastre of the Township of Onslow, towards the intersection of the division line between the Townships of Aldfield and Onslow, also known as the northwest corner of lot 18B, range 13, cadastre of the Township of Onslow; thence, easterly, following the division line between the Townships of Aldfield and Onslow, towards the southwest corner of lot 12, range 1, cadastre of the Township of Aldfield, a distance of 1,760.22 m.</Text>
</Provision>
<BillPiece><Heading level="3"><TitleText>Municipality of La P脙陋che</TitleText></Heading></BillPiece>

<Provision>
<Text>Beginning at the southwest corner of lot芒聙炉12, range芒聙炉1, cadastre of the Township of Aldfield; thence, northerly following the division line between lots芒聙炉12 and芒聙炉<Keep>13A</Keep>, range芒聙炉1, Township of Aldfield, towards the intersection at the south boundary of <Keep>Route芒聙炉366</Keep> (chemin Pontbriand), a distance of 422.88芒聙炉m; thence, easterly following the south boundary of <Keep>Route芒聙炉366</Keep> (chemin Pontbriand), at distances of 79.58芒聙炉m, 82.18芒聙炉m and 43.03芒聙炉m; thence, southeasterly, following the southwest boundary of <Keep>Route芒聙炉366</Keep> (chemin Pontbriand), at distances of 41.52芒聙炉m, 75.96芒聙炉m and 45.06芒聙炉m; thence, easterly following the South boundary of <Keep>Route芒聙炉366</Keep> (chemin Pontbriand), a distance of 52.42芒聙炉m; thence, southeasterly, following the southwest boundary of <Keep>Route芒聙炉366</Keep> (chemin Pontbriand), at distances of 51.22芒聙炉m, 54.54芒聙炉m, 100.89芒聙炉m and 45.93芒聙炉m; thence, easterly following the south boundary of <Keep>Route芒聙炉366</Keep> (chemin Pontbriand), a distance of 49.17芒聙炉m; thence, easterly following the south boundary of <Keep>Route芒聙炉366</Keep> (chemin Pontbriand), to the intersection of the division line between lots芒聙炉<Keep>9A</Keep> and芒聙炉10, range芒聙炉1, cadastre of the Township of Aldfield, a distance of 141.82芒聙炉m; thence, southerly following the division line between lots芒聙炉<Keep>9A</Keep> and芒聙炉10, range芒聙炉1, cadastre of the Township of Aldfield, towards the southeast corner of lot芒聙炉10, range芒聙炉1, cadastre of the Township of Aldfield.</Text>
</Provision>


<BillPiece><Heading level="3"><TitleText>Municipality of Pontiac</TitleText></Heading></BillPiece><Provision>
<Text>Beginning at the southeast corner of lot芒聙炉10, range芒聙炉1, cadastre of the Township of Aldfield; thence, easterly following the division line between the Townships of Aldfield and Onslow, to the intersection of the south boundary of <Keep>Route芒聙炉366</Keep>, a distance of 78.41芒聙炉m; thence, southeasterly, following the southwest boundary of <Keep>Route芒聙炉366</Keep>, at distances of 216.83芒聙炉m, 78.78芒聙炉m, 135.30芒聙炉m, 56.26芒聙炉m, 61.53芒聙炉m, 22.15芒聙炉m, 85.68芒聙炉m and 47.32芒聙炉m; thence, easterly following the southwest of <Keep>Route芒聙炉366</Keep>, at distances of 28.49芒聙炉m, 33.10芒聙炉m, 47.66芒聙炉m, 35.82芒聙炉m, 122.39芒聙炉m, 113.79芒聙炉m, 29.34芒聙炉m, 30.78芒聙炉m, 49.76芒聙炉m and 158.29芒聙炉m; thence, southeasterly, following the southwest boundary of <Keep>Route芒聙炉366</Keep>, to the intersection of the division line between lots芒聙炉<Keep>25B</Keep> and芒聙炉<Keep>26B</Keep>, range芒聙炉13, cadastre of the Township of Onslow, a distance of 19.68芒聙炉m; thence, southerly to the intersection of the division line between the ranges芒聙炉12 and芒聙炉13 and the division line between lots芒聙炉<Keep>25B</Keep> and <Keep>26A</Keep>, range芒聙炉12, all in the Township of Onslow, a distance of 1,139.03芒聙炉m; thence, easterly following the division line between the ranges芒聙炉12 and芒聙炉13, cadastre of the Township of Onslow, at distances of芒聙炉263.87 m, 259.55芒聙炉m, 265.33芒聙炉m and 261.51芒聙炉m; thence, southerly, following the division line between lots <Keep>27C</Keep> and <Keep>28B</Keep>, range芒聙炉12, then lots芒聙炉<Keep>27B</Keep> and <Keep>28A</Keep>, range芒聙炉12, to the southeast corner of lot芒聙炉<Keep>27B</Keep>, range芒聙炉12, all in the cadastre of the said Township, a distance of 1,714.29芒聙炉m; thence, easterly following the division line between the ranges芒聙炉11 and芒聙炉12, to the northeast corner of lot芒聙炉28, range芒聙炉11, all in the cadastre of the Township of Onslow, a distance of 114.88芒聙炉m; thence, southerly following the division line between the Township of Masham and the Township of Onslow, towards the southeast corner of lot芒聙炉28, range芒聙炉11, cadastre of the Township of Onslow, a distance of 1,701.74芒聙炉m; thence, southerly following the division line between the Township of Masham and the Township of Onslow, towards the northwest corner of lot <Keep>2芒聙炉755芒聙炉996</Keep> (Cadastre du Qu脙漏bec), a distance of 1,235.70芒聙炉m.</Text>
</Provision>
<BillPiece><Heading level="3"><TitleText>Municipality of La P脙陋che</TitleText></Heading></BillPiece>


<Provision>
<Text>Beginning at the northwest corner of lot <Keep>2芒聙炉755芒聙炉996</Keep> (Cadastre du Qu脙漏bec), following segments of the north boundary of said lot, to the northeast corner of lot <Keep>2芒聙炉755芒聙炉996</Keep>; thence, easterly and crossing chemin Eardley-Masham, to the northwest corner of lot <Keep>2芒聙炉755芒聙炉995</Keep>; thence, easterly following the north boundary of lots <Keep>2芒聙炉755芒聙炉995</Keep>, <Keep>3芒聙炉117芒聙炉982</Keep>, <Keep>3芒聙炉117芒聙炉981</Keep>, <Keep>2芒聙炉755芒聙炉994</Keep> and <Keep>3芒聙炉117芒聙炉980</Keep>, to the northeast corner of lot <Keep>3芒聙炉117芒聙炉980</Keep>; thence, southerly following the east boundary of lot <Keep>3芒聙炉117芒聙炉980</Keep>, to the southeast corner of said lot; thence, easterly following the north boundary of lots <Keep>2芒聙炉755芒聙炉991</Keep> and <Keep>2芒聙炉755芒聙炉990</Keep> and following segments of the north boundary of lot <Keep>2芒聙炉684芒聙炉840</Keep>, to the intersection with the southeast corner of lot <Keep>2芒聙炉685芒聙炉155</Keep>; thence, northerly following the division line between lots <Keep>2芒聙炉685芒聙炉155</Keep> and <Keep>2芒聙炉685芒聙炉822</Keep>, to the northeast corner of lot <Keep>2芒聙炉685芒聙炉155</Keep>; thence, easterly following the south boundaries of lots <Keep>2芒聙炉685芒聙炉203</Keep> and <Keep>2芒聙炉685芒聙炉402</Keep>, to the southeast corner of lot <Keep>2芒聙炉685芒聙炉402</Keep>; thence, northerly following the division line between lots <Keep>2芒聙炉685芒聙炉402</Keep> and <Keep>2芒聙炉685芒聙炉822</Keep>, to the southwest corner of lot <Keep>2芒聙炉685芒聙炉406</Keep>; thence, easterly following the south boundary of lot <Keep>2芒聙炉685芒聙炉406</Keep>, to the southeast corner of said lot; thence, southeasterly, to the intersection at the northwest corner of lot <Keep>2芒聙炉685芒聙炉428</Keep> and the southwest boundary of lot <Keep>2芒聙炉864芒聙炉213</Keep> (chemin de la Prairie); thence, southeasterly, easterly, northeasterly, easterly, southeasterly and easterly following the south boundary of lots <Keep>2芒聙炉864芒聙炉213</Keep>, <Keep>2芒聙炉864芒聙炉212</Keep> and <Keep>2芒聙炉864芒聙炉211</Keep> (chemin de la Prairie), to the northeast corner of lot <Keep>2芒聙炉756芒聙炉053</Keep>; thence, northerly crossing chemin de la Prairie, to the southeast corner of lot <Keep>2芒聙炉685芒聙炉601</Keep>; thence, northerly following the division line between lots <Keep>2芒聙炉685芒聙炉601</Keep> and <Keep>2芒聙炉685芒聙炉822</Keep>, the division line between lots <Keep>2芒聙炉685芒聙炉600</Keep> and <Keep>2芒聙炉685芒聙炉822</Keep>, then the division line between lots <Keep>2芒聙炉685芒聙炉430</Keep> and <Keep>2芒聙炉685芒聙炉822</Keep>, towards the southwest corner of lot <Keep>2芒聙炉685芒聙炉608</Keep>; thence, easterly following the south boundary of lot <Keep>2芒聙炉685芒聙炉608</Keep>, to the southeast corner of said lot; thence, northerly following the east boundary of lot <Keep>2芒聙炉685芒聙炉608</Keep>, to the northeast corner of said lot; thence, northerly crossing chemin Schnob, to the southwest corner of lot <Keep>2芒聙炉756芒聙炉050</Keep>; thence, northerly following the west boundary of lot <Keep>2芒聙炉756芒聙炉050</Keep>, to the intersection at the northwest corner of said lot and the south shore of Rivi脙篓re la P脙陋che (Undivided territory); thence, in a general easterly direction, following the south shore of Rivi脙篓re la P脙陋che (Undivided territory), to the intersection with the southerly extension of the west boundary of lot <Keep>2芒聙炉756芒聙炉119</Keep>; thence, northerly, crossing Rivi脙篓re la P脙陋che (Undivided territory) and following the west boundary of lot <Keep>2芒聙炉756芒聙炉119</Keep>, to the northwest corner of said lot; thence, easterly following the north boundary of lot <Keep>2芒聙炉756芒聙炉119</Keep>, to the northeast corner of said lot, also located on the west boundary of lot <Keep>2芒聙炉864芒聙炉223</Keep> (chemin Brazeau); thence, southerly and southeasterly following the east boundary of lot <Keep>2芒聙炉756芒聙炉119</Keep>, to the intersection at the north shore of Rivi脙篓re la P脙陋che (Undivided territory), being the southeast corner of lot <Keep>2芒聙炉756芒聙炉119</Keep>; thence, southeasterly, crossing Rivi脙篓re la P脙陋che (Undivided territory), to the northeast corner of lot <Keep>2芒聙炉756芒聙炉050</Keep>; thence, following the division line between the south shore of Rivi脙篓re la P脙陋che (Undivided territory) and following the north boundaries of lots <Keep>3芒聙炉274芒聙炉668</Keep> (chemin Brazeau), <Keep>2芒聙炉685芒聙炉630</Keep>, <Keep>2芒聙炉685芒聙炉633</Keep>, <Keep>2芒聙炉685芒聙炉824</Keep>, <Keep>3芒聙炉579芒聙炉542</Keep>, <Keep>3芒聙炉389芒聙炉947</Keep> and <Keep>3芒聙炉389芒聙炉948</Keep>, to the intersection of the southerly extension of the division line between lots <Keep>3芒聙炉389芒聙炉960</Keep> and <Keep>3芒聙炉654芒聙炉717</Keep>; thence, northerly crossing Rivi脙篓re la P脙陋che (Undivided territory) to the intersection of the division line between lots <Keep>3芒聙炉389芒聙炉960</Keep> and <Keep>3芒聙炉654芒聙炉717</Keep> and the north shore of said River; thence, northerly following the division line between lots <Keep>3芒聙炉654芒聙炉717</Keep> and <Keep>3芒聙炉389芒聙炉960</Keep>, a distance of 77.57芒聙炉m; thence, northeasterly following the division line between lots <Keep>3芒聙炉654芒聙炉717</Keep> and <Keep>3芒聙炉389芒聙炉960</Keep>, a distance of 20.42芒聙炉m; thence, northeasterly crossing lots <Keep>3芒聙炉654芒聙炉717</Keep> and <Keep>3芒聙炉389芒聙炉949</Keep>, to the southwest corner of lot <Keep>3芒聙炉390芒聙炉091</Keep>; thence, easterly following the north boundary of lot <Keep>3芒聙炉389芒聙炉949</Keep>, to the southeast corner of lot <Keep>3芒聙炉390芒聙炉090</Keep>; thence, easterly following the division line between lots <Keep>3芒聙炉389芒聙炉949</Keep> and <Keep>3芒聙炉389芒聙炉950</Keep>, then the division line between lots <Keep>3芒聙炉389芒聙炉950</Keep> and <Keep>3芒聙炉654芒聙炉718</Keep>, towards the southeast corner of lot <Keep>3芒聙炉389芒聙炉950</Keep>; thence, northerly following the division line between lots <Keep>3芒聙炉389芒聙炉950</Keep> and <Keep>3芒聙炉654芒聙炉718</Keep>, at a northwest corner of lot <Keep>3芒聙炉654芒聙炉718</Keep>; thence, southeasterly following the southwest boundary of <Keep>Route芒聙炉366</Keep> (Principale est), being lots <Keep>3芒聙炉654芒聙炉734</Keep>, <Keep>3芒聙炉654芒聙炉218</Keep> and <Keep>3芒聙炉654芒聙炉220</Keep>, towards the northwest corner of lot <Keep>3芒聙炉654芒聙炉223</Keep>; thence, southeasterly following the southwest boundary of <Keep>Route芒聙炉366</Keep> (Principale est), being lot <Keep>3芒聙炉654芒聙炉223</Keep>, towards the south corner of lot <Keep>3芒聙炉654芒聙炉223</Keep>; thence, southeasterly following the southwest and west boundary of <Keep>Route芒聙炉366</Keep> (Principale est), being lot <Keep>3芒聙炉654芒聙炉253</Keep>, at successive distances of 216.74芒聙炉m, 73.18芒聙炉m, 103.09芒聙炉m, then southerly, following the west boundary of <Keep>Route芒聙炉366</Keep> (Principale est), distances of 99.00芒聙炉m and 30.00芒聙炉m; thence, easterly, crossing lots <Keep>3芒聙炉654芒聙炉223</Keep>, <Keep>3芒聙炉654芒聙炉253</Keep>, <Keep>3芒聙炉654芒聙炉256</Keep>, <Keep>3芒聙炉654芒聙炉257</Keep> <Keep>(Route芒聙炉366</Keep> (Principale est)) and <Keep>3芒聙炉654芒聙炉259</Keep> <Keep>(Autoroute芒聙炉5)</Keep>, to the northwest corner of lot <Keep>3芒聙炉391芒聙炉737</Keep>; thence, easterly following the division line between lots <Keep>3芒聙炉391芒聙炉737</Keep> and <Keep>3芒聙炉389芒聙炉951</Keep>, to the far southwest corner of lot <Keep>3芒聙炉391芒聙炉738</Keep>, at distances of 63.10芒聙炉m, 74.88芒聙炉m, 9.58芒聙炉m, 17.51芒聙炉m and 9.35芒聙炉m; thence, easterly, following the division line between lots <Keep>3芒聙炉389芒聙炉951</Keep> and <Keep>3芒聙炉391芒聙炉738</Keep>, a distance of 10.55芒聙炉m; thence, northeasterly, following the division line between lots <Keep>3芒聙炉389芒聙炉951</Keep> and <Keep>3芒聙炉391芒聙炉738</Keep>, to the northeast corner of lot <Keep>3芒聙炉391芒聙炉738</Keep>, at distances of 9.72芒聙炉m, 13.84芒聙炉m, 62.31芒聙炉m, 40.90芒聙炉m, 21.09芒聙炉m, 23.10芒聙炉m, 45.26芒聙炉m and 2.35芒聙炉m; thence, northeasterly, following the division line between lots <Keep>3芒聙炉389芒聙炉951</Keep> and <Keep>3芒聙炉391芒聙炉732</Keep>, to the northwestern corner of lot <Keep>3芒聙炉391芒聙炉732</Keep>, at distances of 6.25芒聙炉m, 13.60芒聙炉m, 61.77芒聙炉m and 27.73芒聙炉m; thence, easterly, following the division line between lots <Keep>3芒聙炉389芒聙炉951</Keep> and <Keep>3芒聙炉391芒聙炉732</Keep>, to the northwest corner of lot <Keep>3芒聙炉391芒聙炉736</Keep>, a distance of 246.25芒聙炉m; thence, southerly, following the division line between lots <Keep>3芒聙炉391芒聙炉736</Keep> and <Keep>3芒聙炉391芒聙炉732</Keep>, to the southwest corner of lot <Keep>3芒聙炉391芒聙炉736</Keep>; thence, easterly, following the division line between lots <Keep>3芒聙炉391芒聙炉736</Keep> and <Keep>3芒聙炉391芒聙炉732</Keep>, to the southeast corner of lot <Keep>3芒聙炉391芒聙炉736</Keep>; thence, southerly, following the division line between lots <Keep>3芒聙炉391芒聙炉670</Keep> and <Keep>3芒聙炉391芒聙炉732</Keep>, to the southwest corner of lot <Keep>3芒聙炉391芒聙炉670</Keep>; thence, easterly, following the division line between lots <Keep>3芒聙炉391芒聙炉670</Keep> and <Keep>3芒聙炉391芒聙炉732</Keep>, to the south corner of lot <Keep>3芒聙炉391芒聙炉670</Keep>; thence, northeasterly, following the division line between lots <Keep>3芒聙炉391芒聙炉732</Keep> and <Keep>3芒聙炉391芒聙炉670</Keep>, to the northeast corner of lot <Keep>3芒聙炉391芒聙炉732</Keep>, a distance of 1.95芒聙炉m; thence, southerly, following the division line between lots <Keep>3芒聙炉391芒聙炉675</Keep> and <Keep>3芒聙炉391芒聙炉732</Keep>, to the intersection of the north shore of the Rivi脙篓re la P脙陋che (Undivided territory); thence, southerly, crossing Rivi脙篓re la P脙陋che (Undivided territory), to a point located at the intersection of the south shore of said river and the division line between lots <Keep>3芒聙炉391芒聙炉748</Keep> and <Keep>3芒聙炉364芒聙炉796</Keep>; thence, southerly, following the division line between lots <Keep>3芒聙炉391芒聙炉748</Keep> and <Keep>3芒聙炉654芒聙炉796</Keep>, to a point located at the intersection of the north boundary of lot <Keep>3芒聙炉654芒聙炉317</Keep> (chemin Mill); thence, crossing lot <Keep>3芒聙炉654芒聙炉317</Keep> (chemin Mill), to a point located at the intersection of the south boundary of said chemin Mill and the division line between lots <Keep>3 391 750</Keep> and <Keep>3 391 773</Keep>; thence, southerly, following the division line between lots <Keep>3芒聙炉391芒聙炉773</Keep> and <Keep>3芒聙炉391芒聙炉750</Keep>, to the southwest corner of lot <Keep>3芒聙炉391芒聙炉750</Keep>; thence, westerly following the division line between lots <Keep>3芒聙炉391芒聙炉773</Keep> and <Keep>3芒聙炉654芒聙炉775</Keep>, to the north corner of lot <Keep>3芒聙炉654芒聙炉775</Keep>, at successive distances of 45.15芒聙炉m, 214.92芒聙炉m and 27.92芒聙炉m; thence, southwesterly, following the division line between lots <Keep>3芒聙炉391芒聙炉773</Keep> and <Keep>3芒聙炉654芒聙炉775</Keep>, a distance of 203.89芒聙炉m; thence, westerly following the division line between lots <Keep>3芒聙炉391芒聙炉773</Keep> and <Keep>3芒聙炉654芒聙炉775</Keep>, to the intersection with the southeast boundary of lot <Keep>3芒聙炉654芒聙炉244</Keep> (chemin Mill), successive distances of 84.42芒聙炉m and 93.58芒聙炉m; thence, southwesterly following the southeast boundary of lot <Keep>3芒聙炉654芒聙炉244</Keep> (chemin Mill), at distances of 25.93芒聙炉m and 18.49芒聙炉m, then westerly, a distance of 20.71芒聙炉m, then to the southwest, a distance of 6.94芒聙炉m, to the northwest corner of lot <Keep>3芒聙炉391芒聙炉769</Keep>; thence, westerly, crossing <Keep>Autoroute芒聙炉5</Keep>, being lot <Keep>3芒聙炉654芒聙炉238</Keep>, to the northeast corner of lot <Keep>3芒聙炉654芒聙聣100</Keep>, following the south boundary of the old chemin Mill; thence, westerly, to the northwest corner of lot <Keep>3芒聙聣654芒聙聣100</Keep> at successive distances of 28.76芒聙炉m and 17.13芒聙炉m; thence, in a general southeasterly direction, following the southwest boundary of the proposed <Keep>Autoroute芒聙炉5</Keep>, being lots <Keep>3芒聙聣654芒聙聣100</Keep> and <Keep>3芒聙聣391芒聙聣986</Keep>, to the southwest corner of lot <Keep>3芒聙聣391芒聙聣986</Keep>; thence, in a general southeasterly direction, following the southwest boundary of the proposed <Keep>Autoroute芒聙炉5</Keep> and crossing lot <Keep>3芒聙聣389芒聙聣945</Keep>, to the northwest corner of lot <Keep>3芒聙聣391芒聙聣995</Keep>; thence, in a general southeasterly direction, following the southwest boundary of the proposed <Keep>Autoroute芒聙炉5</Keep>, being lot <Keep>3芒聙聣391芒聙聣997</Keep>, to the east corner of lot <Keep>3芒聙聣391芒聙聣995</Keep>.</Text>
</Provision>
<BillPiece><Heading level="2"><TitleText>2.4 Section 4</TitleText></Heading></BillPiece><Provision>
<Text>This portion of Gatineau Park, described in Section芒聙炉4, is included in the registration division of Gatineau, located in the Municipality of Chelsea, and forms part of the Cadastre du Qu脙漏bec.</Text>
</Provision><BillPiece><Heading level="3"><TitleText>Municipality of Chelsea</TitleText></Heading></BillPiece>
<Provision>
<Text>Beginning at the east corner of lot <Keep>3芒聙炉391芒聙炉995</Keep>, in a general southeasterly direction, following the southwest boundary of the proposed Autoroute芒聙炉5, being lots <Keep>4芒聙炉138芒聙炉880</Keep>, <Keep>3芒聙炉264芒聙炉820</Keep>, <Keep>3芒聙炉264芒聙炉830</Keep>, <Keep>3芒聙炉264芒聙炉860</Keep>, <Keep>3芒聙炉264芒聙炉906</Keep> and <Keep>3芒聙炉264芒聙炉908</Keep>; thence, in a general southeasterly direction, following the southwest boundary of Autoroute芒聙炉5, being lots <Keep>3芒聙炉264芒聙炉970</Keep>, <Keep>3芒聙炉265芒聙炉005</Keep>, <Keep>3芒聙炉265芒聙炉028</Keep>, <Keep>3芒聙炉265芒聙炉027</Keep>, <Keep>3芒聙炉265芒聙炉072</Keep>, <Keep>3芒聙炉265芒聙炉073</Keep> and <Keep>2芒聙炉924芒聙炉035</Keep>, to the intersection of the south boundary of lot <Keep>2 924 035</Keep> (Autoroute芒聙炉5) and of the west boundary of lot <Keep>2芒聙炉924芒聙炉014</Keep> (chemin Scott); thence, in a general southerly direction, following the west boundaries of <Keep>2芒聙炉924芒聙炉014</Keep>, <Keep>2芒聙炉735芒聙炉360</Keep>, <Keep>2芒聙炉735芒聙炉361</Keep>, <Keep>2芒聙炉636芒聙炉730</Keep>, <Keep>2芒聙炉735芒聙炉385</Keep> and <Keep>2芒聙炉636芒聙炉729</Keep> (chemin Scott), to the southeast corner of lot <Keep>3芒聙炉754芒聙炉061</Keep>; thence, southerly, crossing lots <Keep>2芒聙炉924芒聙炉047</Keep> and <Keep>2芒聙炉636芒聙炉722</Keep> (chemin Old Chelsea), to the northwest corner of lot <Keep>2芒聙炉635芒聙炉548</Keep>; thence, southerly, following the division line between lot <Keep>2芒聙炉635芒聙炉548</Keep> and lots <Keep>2芒聙炉924芒聙炉048</Keep> and <Keep>4芒聙炉138芒聙炉881</Keep>, to the southwest corner of lot <Keep>2芒聙炉635芒聙炉548</Keep>; thence, easterly, following the division line between lot <Keep>4芒聙炉138芒聙炉881</Keep> and lots <Keep>2芒聙炉635芒聙炉548</Keep> and <Keep>2芒聙炉635芒聙炉547</Keep>, to the southwest corner of lot <Keep>2芒聙炉635 芒聙炉547</Keep>, a distance of 42.98芒聙炉m; thence, southerly, following the division line between lots <Keep>2芒聙炉635芒聙炉547</Keep> and <Keep>4芒聙炉138芒聙炉881</Keep>, to the southwest corner of lot <Keep>2芒聙炉635芒聙炉547</Keep>, a distance of 26.82芒聙炉m; thence, easterly, following the division line between lots <Keep>2芒聙炉635芒聙炉547</Keep> and <Keep>4芒聙炉138芒聙炉881</Keep>, to the southeast corner of lot <Keep>2芒聙炉635芒聙炉547</Keep>, a distance of 14.30芒聙炉m; thence, northerly, following the division line between lots <Keep>2芒聙炉635芒聙炉547</Keep> and <Keep>4芒聙炉138芒聙炉881</Keep>, to the southeast corner of lot <Keep>2芒聙炉635芒聙炉547</Keep>, a distance of 26.82芒聙炉m; thence, easterly, following the division line between lots <Keep>2芒聙炉635芒聙炉547</Keep> and <Keep>4芒聙炉138芒聙炉881</Keep>, to the southeast corner of lot <Keep>2芒聙炉635芒聙炉547</Keep>, a distance of 6.55芒聙炉m; thence, northerly, following the division line between lots <Keep>2芒聙炉635芒聙炉547</Keep> and <Keep>4芒聙炉138芒聙炉881</Keep>, to the northeast corner of lot <Keep>2芒聙炉635芒聙炉547</Keep>, a distance of 42.15芒聙炉m; thence, easterly, following the division line between lots <Keep>2芒聙炉635芒聙炉551</Keep> and <Keep>4芒聙炉138芒聙炉881</Keep>, to the southeast corner of lot <Keep>2芒聙炉635芒聙炉551</Keep>, a distance of 10.83芒聙炉m; thence, northerly, following the division line between lots <Keep>2芒聙炉635芒聙炉551</Keep> and <Keep>4芒聙炉138芒聙炉881</Keep>, to the northeast corner of lot <Keep>2芒聙炉635芒聙炉551</Keep>, a distance of 18.23芒聙炉m; thence, easterly, following the division line between lots <Keep>2芒聙炉924芒聙炉049</Keep> and <Keep>4芒聙炉138芒聙炉881</Keep>, to the northwest corner of lot <Keep>4芒聙炉138芒聙炉882</Keep>; thence, southerly, to the southwest corner of lot <Keep>4芒聙炉138芒聙炉882</Keep>, a distance of 65.87芒聙炉m; thence, easterly, to the southwest corner of lot <Keep>2芒聙炉635芒聙炉573</Keep>, a distance of 76.01芒聙炉m; thence, easterly, following the division line between lots <Keep>2芒聙炉635芒聙炉573</Keep> and <Keep>4芒聙炉138芒聙炉881</Keep>, to the southeast corner of lot <Keep>2芒聙炉635芒聙炉573</Keep>; thence, southerly, following the division line between lots <Keep>2芒聙炉635芒聙炉585</Keep> and <Keep>4芒聙炉138芒聙炉881</Keep>, to the southwest corner of lot <Keep>2芒聙炉635芒聙炉585</Keep>; thence, westerly, following the division line between lots <Keep>2芒聙聣635芒聙聣583</Keep> and <Keep>4芒聙炉138芒聙炉881</Keep>, to the southwest corner of lot <Keep>2芒聙炉635芒聙炉583</Keep>; thence, southerly, following the division line between lots <Keep>2芒聙炉635芒聙炉583</Keep> and <Keep>4芒聙炉138芒聙炉881</Keep>, to the southeast corner of lot <Keep>4芒聙炉138芒聙炉881</Keep>; thence, northwesterly, following the division line between lots <Keep>2芒聙炉635芒聙炉493</Keep> and <Keep>4芒聙炉138芒聙炉881</Keep>, to the north corner of lot <Keep>2芒聙炉635芒聙炉493</Keep>; thence, northwesterly, following the division line between lots <Keep>2芒聙炉635芒聙炉533</Keep> and <Keep>4芒聙炉138芒聙炉881</Keep>, to the northeast corner of lot <Keep>2芒聙炉635芒聙炉533</Keep>; thence, westerly, following the division line between lots <Keep>4芒聙炉138芒聙炉881</Keep> and <Keep>2芒聙炉635芒聙炉533</Keep>, to the intersection of the eastern boundary of lot <Keep>2芒聙炉735芒聙炉434</Keep> (chemin Kingsmere); thence, westerly, following the extension of the division line between lots <Keep>2芒聙炉635芒聙炉533</Keep> and <Keep>4芒聙炉138芒聙炉881</Keep>, crossing lot <Keep>2芒聙炉735芒聙炉434</Keep> (chemin Kingsmere), to the intersection of the west boundary of said lot <Keep>2芒聙炉735芒聙炉434</Keep>, a distance of 12.24芒聙炉m; thence, southerly, following the west boundary of lot <Keep>2芒聙炉735芒聙炉434</Keep> (chemin Kingsmere), to the southwest corner of lot <Keep>2芒聙炉735芒聙炉434</Keep>; thence, southwesterly, following the northwest boundary of lot <Keep>2芒聙炉636芒聙炉668</Keep> (chemin Kingsmere), to the southwest corner of said lot <Keep>2芒聙炉636芒聙炉668</Keep>; thence, southwesterly, crossing lot <Keep>2芒聙炉735芒聙炉441</Keep> (chemin Kingsmere), to the northwest corner of lot <Keep>2芒聙炉735芒聙炉433</Keep> (chemin Notch); thence, southerly, following the west boundary of chemin Notch, being lots <Keep>2芒聙炉735芒聙炉433</Keep>, <Keep>2芒聙炉735芒聙炉431</Keep>, <Keep>2芒聙炉735芒聙炉464</Keep>, <Keep>2芒聙炉735芒聙炉463</Keep> and <Keep>2芒聙炉636芒聙炉667</Keep>, to the southwest corner of lot <Keep>2芒聙炉636芒聙炉667</Keep>; thence, easterly, following the division line between lot <Keep>2芒聙炉636芒聙炉667</Keep> (chemin Notch) and lots <Keep>2芒聙炉635芒聙炉407</Keep> and <Keep>2芒聙炉735芒聙炉329</Keep> (chemin Notch), to the southeast corner of lot <Keep>2芒聙炉636芒聙炉667</Keep> (chemin Notch); thence, easterly, then southerly, following the division line between lots <Keep>2芒聙炉735芒聙炉342</Keep> (chemin de la Mine) and <Keep>2芒聙炉735芒聙炉329</Keep> (chemin Notch), to the northwest corner of lot <Keep>2芒聙炉635芒聙炉425</Keep>; thence, in a general southeasterly direction, following the southwest boundary of chemin de la Mine, being lots <Keep>2芒聙炉735芒聙炉342</Keep>, <Keep>2芒聙炉735芒聙炉341</Keep>, <Keep>2芒聙炉636芒聙炉585</Keep> and <Keep>2芒聙炉735芒聙炉338</Keep>, <Keep>2芒聙炉735芒聙炉336</Keep>, <Keep>2芒聙炉735芒聙炉333</Keep>, <Keep>2芒聙炉636芒聙炉583</Keep>, <Keep>2芒聙炉735芒聙炉331</Keep>, <Keep>2芒聙炉735芒聙炉330</Keep>, which becomes the boulevard de la Cit脙漏-des-Jeunes, lot <Keep>2芒聙炉636芒聙炉582</Keep>, to the north corner of lot <Keep>3芒聙炉557芒聙炉256</Keep>, to the point of commencement.</Text>
</Provision><BillPiece><Heading level="1"><TitleText>3 芒聙聰 System of Measurement</TitleText></Heading></BillPiece><Provision>
<Text>In this description, measurements are in metres (SI) and bearings are in reference of the geodetic system of plane coordinates of Quebec (SCOPQ).</Text>
</Provision>
</Schedule></Schedule><Schedule><ScheduleFormHeading><Label />
<OriginatingRef><Emphasis style="bold" /></OriginatingRef>
</ScheduleFormHeading></Schedule>
</Bill>