<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><Bill bill-origin="senate" bill-type="private-public" xml:lang="en" date-time="2023-08-23 15:31:14"><Identification><BillNumber>S-286</BillNumber><Parliament><Session>1</Session><Number>44</Number><RegnalYear><Year-s>70-71</Year-s><Monarch>Elizabeth II – 1-2 Charles III</Monarch></RegnalYear><Year-s>2021-2022-2023-2024</Year-s></Parliament><LongTitle>An Act respecting National Immigration Month</LongTitle><ShortTitle status="unofficial">National Immigration Month Act</ShortTitle><RunningHead>National Immigration Month Act</RunningHead><BillHistory><Stages stage="first-reading-senate"><Date><YYYY>2024</YYYY><MM>6</MM><DD>19</DD></Date></Stages></BillHistory><BillSponsor>Senator GERBA</BillSponsor><BillRefNumber date-time="">4412329</BillRefNumber></Identification><Introduction><Summary><TitleText>SUMMARY</TitleText><Provision><Text>This enactment designates the month of November as “National Immigration Month”.</Text></Provision></Summary><Preamble><Provision pointsize="10" topmarginspacing="-6" language-align="yes"><MarginalNote>Preamble</MarginalNote><Text>Whereas Canada has greatly benefited from the arrival of immigrants from all backgrounds who today make up a vital part of its population;</Text></Provision><Provision><Text>Whereas Canada has greatly benefited from immigrants’ contributions to its social and cultural development, economic prosperity and global outreach;</Text></Provision><Provision><Text>Whereas Canada has already recognized many days, weeks and months to celebrate the heritage of diverse communities and ethnic groups in Canada;</Text></Provision><Provision><Text>Whereas it is very important to educate children and future generations about the role played by immigration in building Canada;</Text></Provision><Provision><Text>Whereas Canada already celebrates the National Francophone Immigration Week in November;</Text></Provision><Provision><Text>Whereas the <XRefExternal reference-type="act" reference-level="federal">Immigration and Refugee Protection Act</XRefExternal>, which establishes principles and fundamental norms related to immigration and refugee protection, received royal assent on November 1, 2001;</Text></Provision><Provision><Text>And whereas it is desirable to establish a period when Canadians can recognize and celebrate immigrants’ contributions to Canadian society;</Text></Provision></Preamble><Enacts><Provision><Text>Now, therefore, His Majesty, by and with the advice and consent of the Senate and House of Commons of Canada, enacts as follows:</Text></Provision></Enacts></Introduction><Body><Heading level="1"><TitleText>Short Title</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Short title</MarginalNote><Label>1</Label><Text>This Act may be cited as the <Emphasis style="italic">National Immigration Month Act</Emphasis>.</Text></Section><Heading level="1"><TitleText>National Immigration Month</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>National Immigration Month</MarginalNote><Label>2</Label><Text>Throughout Canada, in each and every year, the month of November is to be known as “National Immigration Month”.</Text></Section></Body></Bill>