<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><Bill bill-origin="senate" bill-type="private-public" xml:lang="en" date-time="2024-09-13 14:51:44"><Identification><BillNumber>S-288</BillNumber><Parliament><Session>1</Session><Number>44</Number><RegnalYear><Year-s>70-71</Year-s><Monarch>Elizabeth II – 1-2-3 Charles III</Monarch></RegnalYear><Year-s>2021-2022-2023-2024</Year-s></Parliament><LongTitle>An Act respecting Inherited Blood Disorders Awareness Day</LongTitle><ShortTitle status="unofficial">Inherited Blood Disorders Awareness Day Act</ShortTitle><RunningHead>Inherited Blood Disorders Awareness Day Act</RunningHead><BillHistory><Stages stage="first-reading-senate"><Date><YYYY>2024</YYYY><MM>9</MM><DD>19</DD></Date></Stages></BillHistory><BillSponsor>Senator CORDY</BillSponsor><BillRefNumber date-time="">4412405</BillRefNumber></Identification><Introduction><Summary><TitleText>SUMMARY</TitleText><Provision><Text>This enactment designates October 18th in each and every year as “Inherited Blood Disorders Awareness Day”.</Text></Provision></Summary><Preamble><Provision pointsize="10" topmarginspacing="-6" language-align="yes"><MarginalNote>Preamble</MarginalNote><Text>Whereas inherited blood disorders affect both the cellular and non-cellular components of blood;</Text></Provision><Provision><Text>Whereas cellular blood disorders affect red cells and platelets and may also affect cellular and non-cellular blood proteins, including clotting factors;</Text></Provision><Provision><Text>Whereas, while inherited blood disorders are observed in all ethnic groups, some blood disorders may be more prevalent within certain groups of Canadians;</Text></Provision><Provision><Text>Whereas it is important to expand efforts in Canada that advance new and innovative treatments for <Keep>inherited</Keep> blood disorders;</Text></Provision><Provision><Text>Whereas it is also important to advance advocacy <Keep>initiatives</Keep> to meet the needs of Canadians living with inherited blood disorders and to ensure their equal access to health care services no matter where they live in Canada;</Text></Provision><Provision><Text>Whereas bringing otherwise separate and unique rare inherited blood disorders under one umbrella will maximize visibility and advocacy for patients, many of whom belong to marginalized communities that do not have adequate access to medical care;</Text></Provision><Provision><Text>Whereas raising awareness will promote better care, treatment, research, capacity-building and education across Canada in relation to inherited blood disorders;</Text></Provision><Provision><Text>And whereas recognizing a inherited blood disorders awareness day will make Canada a world leader;</Text></Provision></Preamble><Enacts><Provision><Text>Now, therefore, His Majesty, by and with the advice and consent of the Senate and House of Commons of Canada, enacts as follows:</Text></Provision></Enacts></Introduction><Body><Heading level="1"><TitleText>Short Title</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Short title</MarginalNote><Label>1</Label><Text>This Act may be cited as the <Emphasis style="italic">Inherited Blood Disorders Awareness Day Act</Emphasis>.</Text></Section><Heading level="1"><TitleText>Inherited Blood Disorders Awareness Day</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Inherited Blood Disorders Awareness Day</MarginalNote><Label>2</Label><Text>Throughout Canada, in each and every year, the 18th day of October is to be known as “Inherited Blood <Keep>Disorders</Keep> Awareness Day”.</Text></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Not a legal holiday</MarginalNote><Label>3</Label><Text>For greater certainty, Inherited Blood Disorders Awareness Day is not a legal holiday or a non-juridical day.</Text></Section></Body></Bill>