<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><Bill bill-origin="senate" bill-type="private-public" xml:lang="en" date-time="2024-02-15 15:24:34"><Identification><BillNumber>S-285</BillNumber><Parliament><Session>1</Session><Number>44</Number><RegnalYear><Year-s>70-71</Year-s><Monarch>Elizabeth II – 1-2 Charles III</Monarch></RegnalYear><Year-s>2021-2022-2023-2024</Year-s></Parliament><LongTitle>An Act to amend the Canada Business Corporations Act (purpose of a corporation)</LongTitle><ShortTitle status="unofficial">21st-Century Business Act</ShortTitle><RunningHead>An Act to amend the Canada Business Corporations Act (purpose of a corporation)</RunningHead><BillHistory><Stages stage="first-reading-senate"><Date><YYYY>2024</YYYY><MM>5</MM><DD>23</DD></Date></Stages></BillHistory><BillSponsor>Senator MIVILLE-DECHÊNE</BillSponsor><BillRefNumber date-time="">4412334</BillRefNumber></Identification><Introduction><Summary><TitleText>SUMMARY</TitleText><Provision><Text>This enactment amends the <XRefExternal reference-type="act" reference-level="federal">Canada Business Corporations Act</XRefExternal> to provide that a corporation’s purpose is to pursue its best <Keep>interests</Keep> while also operating in a manner that</Text></Provision><Provision first-line-indent="1" subsequent-line-indent="1"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>benefits the wider society and the environment in a manner proportionate to its size and the nature of its operations; and</Text></Provision><Provision first-line-indent="1" subsequent-line-indent="1"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>minimizes any harm that the corporation causes to the wider society and the environment, with the objective of eliminating such harm.</Text></Provision><Provision language-align="yes"><Text>It also makes related amendments.</Text></Provision></Summary><Preamble><Provision pointsize="10" topmarginspacing="-6" language-align="yes"><MarginalNote>Preamble</MarginalNote><Text>Whereas Parliament recognizes that a review of the purpose of a corporation is required as a result of the social and environmental challenges of the 21st century;</Text></Provision><Provision><Text>Whereas corporations should focus on producing profitable solutions for the problems of people and the planet and not on profiting from creating problems;</Text></Provision><Provision><Text>Whereas directors and officers have historically had a fiduciary duty to act only in the best interests of their corporations and this has resulted in social and environmental factors being regularly considered as either risks or opportunities for those corporations’ <Keep>operations</Keep> and profitability, not in relation to those corporations’ impacts on broader society and the <Keep>environment</Keep>;</Text></Provision><Provision><Text>Whereas Parliament considers it essential for corporations to have a purpose that encompasses both the pursuit of their best interests and benefits to the wider society and the environment; and</Text></Provision><Provision><Text>Whereas Parliament considers it essential that corporations periodically disclose information to the public about these impacts and benefits;</Text></Provision></Preamble><Enacts><Provision><Text>Now, therefore, His Majesty, by and with the advice and consent of the Senate and House of Commons of Canada, enacts as follows:</Text></Provision></Enacts></Introduction><Body><Heading level="1"><TitleText>Short Title</TitleText></Heading><Section type="normal"><MarginalNote>Short title</MarginalNote><Label>1</Label><Text>This Act may be cited as the <Emphasis style="italic">21st-Century Business Act</Emphasis>.</Text></Section><Heading level="1"><MarginalNote><HistoricalNote>R.S., c. C-44</HistoricalNote></MarginalNote><TitleText><XRefExternal reference-type="act" reference-level="federal">Canada Business Corporations Act</XRefExternal></TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><Label>2</Label><Text>The <XRefExternal reference-type="act" reference-level="federal">Canada Business Corporations Act</XRefExternal> is amended by adding the following after subsection 6(1):</Text><AmendedText change="ins"><Subsection><MarginalNote>Purpose of corporation</MarginalNote><Label>(1.1)</Label><Text>The articles may set out the purpose of the corporation, provided that the purpose is consistent with section 14.1.</Text></Subsection></AmendedText><ExplanatoryNote><TitleText><XRefExternal reference-type="act" reference-level="federal">Canada Business Corporations Act</XRefExternal></TitleText><Label><Emphasis style="italic">Clause 2</Emphasis>:</Label><ExplanatoryText>New.</ExplanatoryText></ExplanatoryNote></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>3</Label><Text>The Act is amended by adding the following <Keep>after</Keep> section 14:</Text><AmendedText change="ins"><Heading level="1"><Label>PART II.1</Label><TitleText>Purpose of a Corporation</TitleText></Heading><Section type="normal"><MarginalNote>Purpose of corporation</MarginalNote><Label>14.1</Label><Text>The purpose of a corporation is to pursue its best interests while also operating in a manner that</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>benefits the wider society and the environment in a manner proportionate to its size and the nature of its operations; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>minimizes any harm that the corporation causes to the wider society and the environment, with the objective of eliminating such harm.</Text></Paragraph></Section></AmendedText><ExplanatoryNote><Label><Emphasis style="italic">Clause 3</Emphasis>:</Label><ExplanatoryText>New.</ExplanatoryText></ExplanatoryNote></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>4</Label><Text>Subsections 122(1) and (1.1) of the Act are <Keep>replaced</Keep> by the following:</Text><AmendedText><Section><MarginalNote>Directors and officers — duty to pursue purpose of corporation</MarginalNote><Label>122</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Every director and officer of a corporation<Ins>,</Ins> in exercising their powers and discharging their duties<Ins>,</Ins> shall act honestly and in good faith</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>with a view to the best interests of the corporation; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text><Ins>to pursue those interests while ensuring that the corporation operates in a manner that</Ins></Text><Subparagraph change="ins"><Label>(i)</Label><Text>benefits the wider society and the environment in a manner proportionate to its size and the <Keep>nature</Keep> of its operations, and</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph change="ins"><Label>(ii)</Label><Text>minimizes any harm that it causes to the wider society and the environment, with the objective of eliminating such harm.</Text></Subparagraph></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Directors and officers — duty of care</MarginalNote><Label>(1.1)</Label><Text><Ins>Every director and officer</Ins> of <Ins>a</Ins> corporation<Ins>, in exercising their powers and discharging their duties, shall <Keep>exercise</Keep> the care, diligence and skill that a reasonably prudent person would exercise in comparable circumstances, including towards</Ins></Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>shareholders<Ins>;</Ins></Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>employees<Ins>;</Ins></Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(c)</Label><Text> retirees and pensioners<Ins>;</Ins></Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(d)</Label><Text>creditors<Ins>;</Ins></Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(e)</Label><Text>consumers<Ins>;</Ins></Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(f)</Label><Text>governments<Ins>;</Ins></Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(g)</Label><Text>the environment; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(h)</Label><Text>the <Ins>corporation’s</Ins> long-term interests.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection></Section></AmendedText><ExplanatoryNote><Label><Emphasis style="italic">Clause 4</Emphasis>:</Label><ExplanatoryText>Text of subsections 122(1) and (1.1):</ExplanatoryText><ExistingText><Section><Label>122</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Every director and officer of a corporation in exercising their powers and discharging their duties shall</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>act honestly and in good faith with a view to the best interests of the corporation; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>exercise the care, diligence and skill that a reasonably prudent person would exercise in comparable circumstances.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><Label>(1.1)</Label><Text>When acting with a view to the best interests of the corporation under paragraph (1)(a), the directors and officers of the corporation may consider, but are not limited to, the following factors:</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>the interests of</Text><Subparagraph><Label>(i)</Label><Text>shareholders,</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph><Label>(ii)</Label><Text>employees,</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph><Label>(iii)</Label><Text>retirees and pensioners,</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph><Label>(iv)</Label><Text>creditors,</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph><Label>(v)</Label><Text>consumers, and</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph><Label>(vi)</Label><Text>governments;</Text></Subparagraph></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>the environment; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(c)</Label><Text>the long-term interests of the corporation.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection></Section></ExistingText></ExplanatoryNote></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>5</Label><Text>The portion of subsection 123(5) before paragraph (a) is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><Section><MarginalNote>Defence — good faith</MarginalNote><Label>123</Label><Subsection><Label>(5)</Label><Text>A director has complied with his or her duties under <Ins>paragraph 122(1)(a) and</Ins> subsection <Ins>122(1.1)</Ins> if the director relied in good faith on</Text></Subsection></Section></AmendedText><ExplanatoryNote><Label><Emphasis style="italic">Clause 5</Emphasis>:</Label><ExplanatoryText>Text of relevant poriton of subsection 123(5):</ExplanatoryText><ExistingText><Section><Label>123</Label><Subsection><Label>(5)</Label><Text>A director has complied with his or her duties under subsection 122(1) if the director relied in good faith on</Text></Subsection></Section></ExistingText></ExplanatoryNote></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>6</Label><Text>Paragraph 124(3)(a) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>acted honestly and in good faith <Ins>to advance the purpose</Ins> of the corporation or, as the case may be, to <Ins>advance the purpose</Ins> of the other entity for which the individual acted as <Ins>a</Ins> director or officer or in a similar <Ins>such</Ins> capacity at the corporation’s request; and</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText><ExplanatoryNote><Label><Emphasis style="italic">Clause 6</Emphasis>:</Label><ExplanatoryText>Text of relevant portions of subsection 124(3):</ExplanatoryText><ExistingText><Subsection><Label>(3)</Label><Text>A corporation may not indemnify an individual under subsection (1) unless the individual</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>acted honestly and in good faith with a view to the best interests of the corporation, or, as the case may be, to the best interests of the other entity for which the individual acted as director or <Keep>officer</Keep> or in a similar capacity at the corporation’s request; and</Text></Paragraph></Subsection></ExistingText></ExplanatoryNote></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>7</Label><Text>The Act is amended by adding the following <Keep>after</Keep> section 172.1:</Text><AmendedText change="ins"><Heading level="1"><Label>PART XIV.2</Label><TitleText>Disclosure Relating to Impacts on the Wider Society and the Environment</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Annual report</MarginalNote><Label>172.2</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>At every annual meeting of its shareholders, the corporation shall report in the prescribed manner on its impacts on the wider society and the environment, <Keep>including</Keep> on the measures it has taken to minimize any harm it causes to the wider society and the environment.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Single or joint report</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>A corporation may comply with subsection (1) either by providing a report in respect of the corporation or by being party to a joint report in respect of affiliated corporations.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Prescribed standards</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>Regulations prescribing how the report referred to in subsection (1) shall be made may require the corporation or affiliated corporations to</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>select a prescribed third-party standard for assessing the corporation’s or affiliated corporations’ impacts on the wider society and the environment; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>assess the corporation’s or affiliated corporations’ impacts on the wider society and the environment against that standard for the most recently completed financial year.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Prescribed standards</MarginalNote><Label>(4)</Label><Text>Regulations prescribing how the report referred to in subsection (1) shall be made may prescribe different manners that are based on the corporation’s size.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Information to shareholders</MarginalNote><Label>(5)</Label><Text>The corporation shall provide the report referred to in subsection (1) to each shareholder — except to a shareholder who has informed the corporation in writing that they do not want to receive that information — by sending the information with the notice referred to in subsection 135(1) or by making the information available along with a proxy circular referred to in subsection 150(1).</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Information to Director</MarginalNote><Label>(6)</Label><Text>The corporation shall concurrently send the report referred to in subsection (1) to the Director and make it available to the public, including by publishing the report in a prominent place on the corporation’s website.</Text></Subsection></Section></AmendedText><ExplanatoryNote><Label><Emphasis style="italic">Clause 7</Emphasis>:</Label><ExplanatoryText>New.</ExplanatoryText></ExplanatoryNote></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>8</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Paragraph 239(2)(c) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(c)</Label><Text>it appears to be <Ins>consistent with the purpose</Ins> of the corporation or its subsidiary that the action be brought, prosecuted, defended or discontinued.</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText><ExplanatoryNote><Label><Emphasis style="italic">Clause 8</Emphasis>: (1)</Label><ExplanatoryText>Text of relevant portions of subsection 239(2):</ExplanatoryText><ExistingText><Subsection><Label>(2)</Label><Text>No action may be brought and no intervention in an action may be made under subsection (1) unless the court is satisfied that</Text><Paragraph><Label>. . .</Label><Text /></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(c)</Label><Text>it appears to be in the interests of the corporation or its <Keep>subsidiary</Keep> that the action be brought, prosecuted, defended or discontinued.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection></ExistingText></ExplanatoryNote></Subsection><Subsection><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Section 239 of the Act is amended by adding the following after subsection (2):</Text><AmendedText change="ins"><Subsection><MarginalNote>Presumption — proper person</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>A person who makes an application under subsection (1) in relation to the duties of a director or officer under paragraph 122(1)(b) is deemed to be a proper person <Keep>under</Keep> paragraph (d) of the definition of <DefinitionRef>complainant</DefinitionRef> in section 238 if the court is satisfied that the person is acting in pursuit of the interests of the wider society or the environment.</Text></Subsection></AmendedText><ExplanatoryNote><Label>(2)</Label><ExplanatoryText>New.</ExplanatoryText></ExplanatoryNote></Subsection></Section><Heading level="1"><TitleText>Coming into Force</TitleText></Heading><Section type="CIF"><MarginalNote>First anniversary</MarginalNote><Label>9</Label><Text>This Act comes into force on the first anniversary of the day on which it receives royal assent.</Text></Section></Body></Bill>