<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!--Arbortext, Inc., 1988-2010, v.4002--><Bill bill-origin="senate" bill-type="govt-public" xml:lang="en"><!--Authoring to Exchange Transform created with transform.acl--><Identification><BillNumber>S-7</BillNumber><Parliament><Session>1</Session><Number>44</Number><RegnalYear><Year-s>70-71</Year-s><Monarch>Elizabeth II</Monarch></RegnalYear><Year-s>2021-2022</Year-s></Parliament><LongTitle>An Act to amend the Customs Act and the Preclearance Act, 2016</LongTitle><ShortTitle status="unofficial">An Act to amend the Customs Act and the Preclearance Act, 2016</ShortTitle><RunningHead>An Act to amend the Customs Act and the Preclearance Act, 2016</RunningHead><BillHistory><Stages stage="first-reading-senate"><Date><YYYY>2022</YYYY><MM>3</MM><DD>31</DD></Date></Stages></BillHistory><BillSponsor>THE HONOURABLE SENATOR GOLD, P.C.</BillSponsor><BillRefNumber date-time="2022-3-28">91018</BillRefNumber></Identification><Introduction><Summary><TitleText>SUMMARY</TitleText><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>This enactment amends the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Customs Act</XRefExternal> to</Text><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>clarify the circumstances in which border service officers may examine documents stored on personal digital devices;</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>authorize the making of regulations in respect of those examinations; and</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>(c)</Label><Text>update certain provisions respecting enforcement, offences and punishment.</Text></Provision></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>The enactment also amends the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Preclearance Act, 2016</XRefExternal> to</Text><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>clarify the circumstances in which preclearance officers may examine, search and detain documents stored on personal digital devices;</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>authorize the making of regulations and the giving of ministerial directions in respect of those examinations, searches and detentions; and</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>(c)</Label><Text>update the French version of that Act in respect of a traveller’s obligation to identify themselves.</Text></Provision></Provision></Summary><Enacts><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>Her Majesty, by and with the advice and consent of the Senate and House of Commons of Canada, enacts as follows:</Text></Provision></Enacts></Introduction><Body><Heading level="1"><MarginalNote><HistoricalNote>R.S., c. 1 (2nd Supp.)</HistoricalNote></MarginalNote><TitleText>Customs Act</TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><Label>1</Label><Text>The <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Customs Act</XRefExternal> is amended by adding the following after section 99:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Section change="ins"><MarginalNote>Documents on personal digital device</MarginalNote><Label>99.01</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>At any time up to the time of release or at any time up to the time of exportation, an officer designated under subsection (2) may, in accordance with the regulations, examine documents, including emails, text messages, receipts, photographs or videos, that are stored on a personal digital device that has been imported or is about to be exported and is in the custody or possession of a person if the officer has a reasonable general concern that</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>this Act or a regulation made under it has been or might be contravened in respect of one or more of the documents;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>any other Act of Parliament that prohibits, controls or regulates the importation or exportation of goods and is administered or enforced by the officer or any regulation made under that Act has been or might be contravened in respect of one or more of the documents; or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(c)</Label><Text>one or more of the documents may afford evidence in respect of a contravention under</Text><Subparagraph><Label>(i)</Label><Text>this Act or a regulation made under it, or</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph><Label>(ii)</Label><Text>any other Act of Parliament that prohibits, controls or regulates the importation or exportation of goods and is administered or enforced by the officer or any regulation made under that Act.</Text></Subparagraph></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Designation by President</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The President may designate any officer or class of officers for the purposes of subsection (1).</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Non-application</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>This section does not apply in respect of personal digital devices that are imported or exported solely for</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>sale;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>an industrial, occupational, commercial, institutional or other similar use; or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(c)</Label><Text>any other prescribed use.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection></Section></AmendedText><ExplanatoryNote><TitleText>Customs Act</TitleText><Label><Emphasis style="italic">Clause 1</Emphasis>:</Label><ExplanatoryText>New.</ExplanatoryText></ExplanatoryNote></Section><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote><HistoricalNote>2001, c. 25, s. 60</HistoricalNote></MarginalNote><Label>2</Label><Text>Paragraph 99.4(a) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text><Ins>respecting the examination of documents under subsection 99.01(1);</Ins></Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label><Ins>(a.1)</Ins></Label><Text>prescribing persons or classes of persons who may be searched under subsection 99.2(2);</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText><ExplanatoryNote><Label><Emphasis style="italic">Clause 2</Emphasis>:</Label><ExplanatoryText>Relevant portion of section 99.4:</ExplanatoryText><ExistingText><Section><Label>99.4</Label><Text>The Governor in Council may make regulations</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>prescribing persons or classes of persons who may be searched under subsection 99.2(2);</Text></Paragraph></Section></ExistingText></ExplanatoryNote></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>3</Label><Text>Section 110 of the Act is amended by adding the following after subsection (3):</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Subsection change="ins"><MarginalNote>Electronic copy</MarginalNote><Label>(3.1)</Label><Text>An officer who exercises the power referred to in subsection (3) may make an electronic copy of a record or document if it is impossible or impractical to seize anything on which the record or document is stored or if seizing the thing is likely to degrade the record or document or make it unusable as evidence.</Text></Subsection></AmendedText><ExplanatoryNote><Label><Emphasis style="italic">Clause 3</Emphasis>:</Label><ExplanatoryText>New.</ExplanatoryText></ExplanatoryNote></Section><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote><HistoricalNote>1992, c. 1, s. 143 (Sch. VI, item 9)(E)</HistoricalNote></MarginalNote><Label>4</Label><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Subsection 111(1) of the English version of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Section><MarginalNote>Information for search warrant</MarginalNote><Label>111</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>A justice of the peace may at any time issue a warrant authorizing an officer to search a building, receptacle or place and to seize <Ins>any of the following items</Ins> if the justice of the peace is satisfied by information on oath in the form set out as Form 1 in Part XXVIII of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Criminal Code</XRefExternal>, <Ins>with any necessary modifications</Ins>, that there are reasonable grounds to believe that <Ins>any of the items</Ins> will be found in the building, receptacle or place:</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>any goods or conveyance in respect of which this Act or the regulations have been contravened or are suspected of having been contravened;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>any conveyance that has been made use of in respect of such goods, whether at or after the time of the contravention; <Ins>and</Ins></Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(c)</Label><Text>anything, <Ins>including a record or document in any form</Ins>, that there are reasonable grounds to believe will afford evidence in respect of a contravention of this Act or the regulations.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection></Section></AmendedText><ExplanatoryNote><Label><Emphasis style="italic">Clause 4</Emphasis>: (1) and (2)</Label><ExplanatoryText>Existing text of subsections 111(1) and (2):</ExplanatoryText><ExistingText><Section><Label>111</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>A justice of the peace who is satisfied by information on oath in the form set out as Form 1 in Part XXVIII of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Criminal Code</XRefExternal>, varied to suit the case, that there are reasonable grounds to believe that there will be found in a building, receptacle or place</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>any goods or conveyance in respect of which this Act or the regulations have been contravened or are suspected of having been contravened,</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>any conveyance that has been made use of in respect of such goods, whether at or after the time of the contravention, or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(c)</Label><Text>anything that there are reasonable grounds to believe will afford evidence in respect of a contravention of this Act or the regulations,</Text></Paragraph><ContinuedSectionSubsection><Text>may at any time issue a warrant under his hand authorizing an officer to search the building, receptacle or place for any such thing and to seize it.</Text></ContinuedSectionSubsection></Subsection><Subsection><Label>(2)</Label><Text>A justice of the peace may, where a building, receptacle or place referred to in subsection (1) is in a territorial division other than that in which the justice of the peace has jurisdiction, issue his warrant in a form similar to the form referred to in subsection (1), modified according to the circumstances, and the warrant may be executed in the other territorial division after it has been endorsed, in the manner set out in Form 28 of Part XXVIII of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Criminal Code</XRefExternal>, by a justice of the peace having jurisdiction in that territorial division.</Text></Subsection></Section></ExistingText></ExplanatoryNote></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Subsection 111(2) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Subsection><MarginalNote>Execution of warrant</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text><Ins>A</Ins> warrant <Ins>issued under subsection (1)</Ins> may be executed <Ins>anywhere in Canada</Ins>.</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(3)</Label><Text>Paragraph 111(3)(c) of the English version of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(c)</Label><Text>anything, <Ins>including a record or document in any form</Ins>, that the officer believes on reasonable grounds will afford evidence in respect of a contravention of this Act or the regulations.</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText><ExplanatoryNote><Label>(3)</Label><ExplanatoryText>Relevant portion of subsection 111(3):</ExplanatoryText><ExistingText><Subsection><Label>(3)</Label><Text>An officer who executes a warrant issued under subsection (1) may seize, in addition to the things mentioned in the warrant,</Text><Paragraph><Label>...</Label><Text> </Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(c)</Label><Text>anything that the officer believes on reasonable grounds will afford evidence in respect of a contravention of this Act or the regulations.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection></ExistingText></ExplanatoryNote></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(4)</Label><Text>Section 111 of the Act is amended by adding the following after subsection (3):</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Subsection change="ins"><MarginalNote>Electronic copy</MarginalNote><Label>(3.1)</Label><Text>An officer who executes a warrant issued under subsection (1) may make an electronic copy of a record or document if it is impossible or impractical to seize anything on which the record or document is stored or if seizing the thing is likely to degrade the record or document or make it unusable as evidence.</Text></Subsection></AmendedText><ExplanatoryNote><Label>(4)</Label><ExplanatoryText>New.</ExplanatoryText></ExplanatoryNote></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(5)</Label><Text>Section 111 of the Act is amended by adding the following after subsection (7):</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Subsection change="ins"><MarginalNote>Means of telecommunication</MarginalNote><Label>(8)</Label><Text>An information referred to in subsection (1) may be submitted by telephone or other means of telecommunication in accordance with section 487.1 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Criminal Code</XRefExternal>, with any necessary modifications.</Text></Subsection></AmendedText><ExplanatoryNote><Label>(5)</Label><ExplanatoryText>New.</ExplanatoryText></ExplanatoryNote></Subsection></Section><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote><HistoricalNote>2001, c. 25, s. 65</HistoricalNote></MarginalNote><Label>5</Label><Text>Subsection 115(1) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Section><MarginalNote>Copies of records</MarginalNote><Label>115</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>If any record is examined or seized under this Act, the Minister, or the officer by whom it is examined or seized, may make or cause to be made, <Ins>in any form</Ins>, one or more copies of <Ins>the record</Ins>, and a copy purporting to be certified by the Minister or a person authorized by the Minister is admissible in evidence and has the same probative force as the original would have if it had been proved in the ordinary way.</Text></Subsection></Section></AmendedText><ExplanatoryNote><Label><Emphasis style="italic">Clause 5</Emphasis>:</Label><ExplanatoryText>Existing text of subsection 115(1):</ExplanatoryText><ExistingText><Section><Label>115</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>If any record is examined or seized under this Act, the Minister, or the officer by whom it is examined or seized, may make or cause to be made one or more copies of it, and a copy purporting to be certified by the Minister or a person authorized by the Minister is admissible in evidence and has the same probative force as the original would have if it had been proved in the ordinary way.</Text></Subsection></Section></ExistingText></ExplanatoryNote></Section><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote><HistoricalNote>2001, c. 17, s. 256</HistoricalNote></MarginalNote><Label>6</Label><Text>Section 160.1 of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Section><MarginalNote>Penalty for hindering an officer</MarginalNote><Label>160.1</Label><Text>Every person who contravenes section 153.1</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>is guilty of an offence <Ins>punishable</Ins> on summary conviction and liable to a fine of not more than <Ins>$10,000</Ins> or <Ins>to</Ins> imprisonment for a term <Ins>of</Ins> not <Ins>more than six</Ins> months, or to both; or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph change="ins"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>is guilty of an indictable offence and liable to a fine of not more than $50,000 or to imprisonment for a term of not more than five years, or to both.</Text></Paragraph></Section></AmendedText><ExplanatoryNote><Label><Emphasis style="italic">Clause 6</Emphasis>:</Label><ExplanatoryText>Existing text of section 160.1:</ExplanatoryText><ExistingText><Section><Label>160.1</Label><Text>Every person who contravenes section 153.1 is guilty of an offence and, in addition to any penalty otherwise provided, is liable on summary conviction to</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>a fine of not less than $1,000 and not more than $25,000; or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>both a fine described in paragraph (a) and imprisonment for a term not exceeding twelve months.</Text></Paragraph></Section></ExistingText></ExplanatoryNote></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>7</Label><Text>Section 163 of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Section><MarginalNote>Limitation or prescription period in summary convictions</MarginalNote><Label>163</Label><Text>Proceedings may be instituted by way of summary conviction in respect of offences under this Act at any time within but not later than <Ins>eight</Ins> years after the time when the subject-matter of the proceedings arose.</Text></Section></AmendedText><ExplanatoryNote><Label><Emphasis style="italic">Clause 7</Emphasis>:</Label><ExplanatoryText>Existing text of section 163:</ExplanatoryText><ExistingText><Section><Label>163</Label><Text>Proceedings may be instituted by way of summary conviction in respect of offences under this Act at any time within but not later than three years after the time when the subject-matter of the proceedings arose.</Text></Section></ExistingText></ExplanatoryNote></Section><Heading level="1"><MarginalNote><HistoricalNote>2017, c. 27</HistoricalNote></MarginalNote><TitleText>Preclearance Act, 2016</TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><Label>8</Label><Text>Paragraph 20(1)(d) of the French version of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Preclearance Act, 2016</XRefExternal> is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no" xml:lang="fr"><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>d)</Label><Text>ordonner à toute personne de se présenter à un contrôleur, de <Ins>donner son identité</Ins> et de faire état de la raison de sa présence dans la zone de précontrôle;</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText><ExplanatoryNote><TitleText>Preclearance Act, 2016</TitleText><Label><Emphasis style="italic">Clause 8</Emphasis>:</Label><ExplanatoryText>Relevant portion of subsection 20(1):</ExplanatoryText><ExistingText><Section><Label>20</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>A preclearance officer may, for the purpose of conducting preclearance,</Text><Paragraph><Label>...</Label><Text> </Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(d)</Label><Text>direct a person to report to a preclearance officer, identify themselves, and state their reason for being in a preclearance area; and</Text></Paragraph></Subsection></Section></ExistingText></ExplanatoryNote></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>9</Label><Text>The Act is amended by adding the following after section 20:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Section change="ins"><MarginalNote>Documents on personal digital device</MarginalNote><Label>20.1</Label><Subsection change="ins"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>A preclearance officer may, for the purposes of conducting preclearance, examine, search and detain documents, including emails, text messages, receipts, photographs or videos, that are stored on a personal digital device that is in the possession or control of a traveller bound for the United States if the preclearance officer has a reasonable general concern that</Text><Paragraph change="ins"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>a law of the United States on importation of goods, immigration, agriculture or public health and safety has been or might be contravened in respect of one or more of the documents; or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph change="ins"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>one or more of the documents in question may <Keep>afford</Keep> evidence in respect of a contravention of any of those laws.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection change="ins"><MarginalNote>For greater certainty</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>For greater certainty, the power to examine, search and detain documents under subsection (1) includes the power to detain the personal digital device on which they are stored.</Text></Subsection><Subsection change="ins"><MarginalNote>Regulations and directions</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>A preclearance officer who examines, searches or <Keep>detains</Keep> documents under subsection (1) must do so in accordance with the regulations or any directions given under subsection 45.1(1).</Text></Subsection><Subsection change="ins"><MarginalNote>Non-application</MarginalNote><Label>(4)</Label><Text>This section does not apply in respect of personal digital devices that are bound for the United States solely for</Text><Paragraph change="ins"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>sale;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph change="ins"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>an industrial, occupational, commercial, institutional or other similar use; or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph change="ins"><Label>(c)</Label><Text>any other use that is prescribed by regulation.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection></Section></AmendedText><ExplanatoryNote><Label><Emphasis style="italic">Clause 9</Emphasis>:</Label><ExplanatoryText>New.</ExplanatoryText></ExplanatoryNote></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>10</Label><Text>Paragraph 27(2)(a) of the French version of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no" xml:lang="fr"><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>a)</Label><Text>sur ordre du contrôleur, de <Ins>donner son identité</Ins> et de faire état de la raison de sa présence dans le périmètre de précontrôle;</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText><ExplanatoryNote><Label><Emphasis style="italic">Clause 10</Emphasis>:</Label><ExplanatoryText>Relevant portion of subsection 27(2):</ExplanatoryText><ExistingText><Subsection><Label>(2)</Label><Text>A person, other than a traveller bound for the United States, who is in a preclearance perimeter must</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>as directed by a preclearance officer, identify themselves and state their reason for being in the preclearance perimeter; and</Text></Paragraph></Subsection></ExistingText></ExplanatoryNote></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>11</Label><Text>Paragraph 28(a) of the French version of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no" xml:lang="fr"><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>a)</Label><Text>ordonner à toute personne de <Ins>donner son identité</Ins> et de faire état de la raison de sa présence dans le périmètre de précontrôle;</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText><ExplanatoryNote><Label><Emphasis style="italic">Clause 11</Emphasis>:</Label><ExplanatoryText>Relevant portion of section 28:</ExplanatoryText><ExistingText><Section><Label>28</Label><Text>In a preclearance perimeter, a preclearance officer may, for the purpose of conducting preclearance or of maintaining the security of or control over the border between Canada and the United States,</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>direct that a person identify themselves and state their reason for being in the preclearance perimeter;</Text></Paragraph></Section></ExistingText></ExplanatoryNote></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>12</Label><Text>The Act is amended by adding the following after section 28:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Section change="ins"><MarginalNote>Documents on personal digital device</MarginalNote><Label>28.1</Label><Subsection change="ins"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>In a preclearance perimeter, a preclearance officer may, for the purpose of conducting preclearance or of maintaining the security of or control over the border between Canada and the United States, examine, search and detain documents, including emails, text messages, receipts, photographs or videos, that are stored on a personal digital device that is in the possession or control of a traveller bound for the United States and that is to be loaded onto a conveyance referred to in paragraph 6(2)(a) if the preclearance officer has a reasonable general concern that</Text><Paragraph change="ins"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>a law of the United States on importation of goods, immigration, agriculture or public health and safety has been or might be contravened in respect of one or more of the documents; or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph change="ins"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>one or more of the documents may afford evidence in respect of a contravention of any of those laws.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection change="ins"><MarginalNote>For greater certainty</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>For greater certainty, the power to examine, search and detain documents under subsection (1) includes the power to detain the personal digital device on which they are stored.</Text></Subsection><Subsection change="ins"><MarginalNote>Regulations and directions</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>A preclearance officer who examines, searches or <Keep>detains</Keep> documents under subsection (1) must do so in accordance with the regulations or any directions given under subsection 45.1(1).</Text></Subsection><Subsection change="ins"><MarginalNote>Non-application</MarginalNote><Label>(4)</Label><Text>This section does not apply in respect of personal digital devices that are bound for the United States solely for</Text><Paragraph change="ins"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>sale;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph change="ins"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>an industrial, occupational, commercial, institutional or other similar use; or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph change="ins"><Label>(c)</Label><Text>any other use that is prescribed by regulation.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection></Section></AmendedText><ExplanatoryNote><Label><Emphasis style="italic">Clause 12</Emphasis>:</Label><ExplanatoryText>New.</ExplanatoryText></ExplanatoryNote></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>13</Label><Text>Paragraph 31(2)(a) of the French version of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no" xml:lang="fr"><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>a)</Label><Text>lui ordonner de <Ins>donner son identité</Ins> et de fournir une pièce d’identité comportant sa photographie qui est délivrée par l’administration fédérale, une administration provinciale ou locale ou toute administration d’un autre pays;</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText><ExplanatoryNote><Label><Emphasis style="italic">Clause 13</Emphasis>:</Label><ExplanatoryText>Relevant portion of subsection 31(2):</ExplanatoryText><ExistingText><Subsection><Label>(2)</Label><Text>A preclearance officer may, for the purpose of maintaining the security of or control over the border between Canada and the United States, exercise the following powers in a preclearance area or preclearance perimeter with respect to a traveller who is withdrawing from preclearance:</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>direct the traveller to identify themselves and to produce identification that contains their photograph and that is issued by the federal government, a provincial or local government or a foreign government;</Text></Paragraph></Subsection></ExistingText></ExplanatoryNote></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>14</Label><Text>Paragraph 32(1)(a) of the French version of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no" xml:lang="fr"><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>a)</Label><Text>ordonner au voyageur de <Ins>donner son identité</Ins> et de fournir une pièce d’identité comportant sa photographie qui est délivrée par l’administration fédérale, une administration provinciale ou locale ou toute administration d’un autre pays;</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText><ExplanatoryNote><Label><Emphasis style="italic">Clause 14</Emphasis>:</Label><ExplanatoryText>Relevant portion of subsection 32(1):</ExplanatoryText><ExistingText><Section><Label>32</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>If a preclearance officer has reasonable grounds to suspect that a traveller who is withdrawing from preclearance has committed an offence under an Act of Parliament, the officer may, for the purpose of maintaining the security of or control over the border, exercise any of the following powers in a preclearance area or preclearance perimeter:</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>direct the traveller to identify themselves and to produce identification that contains their photograph and that is issued by the federal government, a provincial or local government or a foreign government;</Text></Paragraph></Subsection></Section></ExistingText></ExplanatoryNote></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>15</Label><Text>Subsection 34(1) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Section><MarginalNote>Preclearance officer</MarginalNote><Label>34</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Subject to subsection (2), in a preclearance area or preclearance perimeter, a preclearance officer may seize, including as forfeit, or accept if they are abandoned, goods that are detained by a preclearance officer under paragraph 20(1)(c), <Ins>subsection 20.1(1)</Ins>, <Ins>paragraph</Ins> 28(e) or <Ins>subsection 28.1(1)</Ins> to the extent, and in a manner, that is consistent with the laws of the United States on importation of goods, immigration, agriculture and public health and safety.</Text></Subsection></Section></AmendedText><ExplanatoryNote><Label><Emphasis style="italic">Clause 15</Emphasis>:</Label><ExplanatoryText>Existing text of subsection 34(1):</ExplanatoryText><ExistingText><Section><Label>34</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Subject to subsection (2), in a preclearance area or preclearance perimeter, a preclearance officer may seize, including as forfeit, or accept if they are abandoned, goods that are detained by a preclearance officer under paragraph 20(1)(c) or 28(e) to the extent, and in a manner, that is consistent with the laws of the United States on importation of goods, immigration, agriculture and public health and safety.</Text></Subsection></Section></ExistingText></ExplanatoryNote></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>16</Label><Text>Subsection 43(1) of the Act is amended by adding the following after paragraph (c):</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><SectionPiece><Paragraph change="ins"><Label>(c.1)</Label><Text>respecting examinations, searches and detentions under section 20.1 or 28.1;</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText><ExplanatoryNote><Label><Emphasis style="italic">Clause 16</Emphasis>:</Label><ExplanatoryText>Relevant portion of subsection 43(1):</ExplanatoryText><ExistingText><Section><Label>43</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The Governor in Council may make regulations for carrying out the purposes and provisions of this Part, including regulations</Text></Subsection></Section></ExistingText></ExplanatoryNote></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>17</Label><Text>The Act is amended by adding the following after section 45:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Section change="ins"><MarginalNote>Ministerial directions</MarginalNote><Label>45.1</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The Minister may give directions respecting <Keep>examinations</Keep>, searches and detentions under section 20.1 or 28.1.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Cessation of effect</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The directions have effect from the time they are given and cease to have effect on the earliest of</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>the day on which they are repealed,</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>the day on which a regulation made under this Act that has the same effect as the directions comes into force,</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(c)</Label><Text>one year after the day on which the directions are given or any shorter period that may be specified in them, unless they are extended by the Minister, and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(d)</Label><Text>the day that is specified by the Minister, if the Minister extends their effective period.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Extension</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>If the Minister amends the directions to extend their effective period, the extension must not exceed one year after the end of the applicable period referred to in paragraph (2)(c).</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote><XRefExternal reference-type="act">Statutory Instruments Act</XRefExternal></MarginalNote><Label>(4)</Label><Text>The <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Statutory Instruments Act</XRefExternal> does not apply to the directions. However, the Minister must cause the directions to be published in the <XRefExternal reference-type="other">Canada Gazette</XRefExternal> within 60 days after the day on which they are given.</Text></Subsection><Subsection change="ins"><MarginalNote>Conflict</MarginalNote><Label>(5)</Label><Text>If there is a conflict between the directions and the regulations, the regulations prevail to the extent of the conflict.</Text></Subsection></Section></AmendedText><ExplanatoryNote><Label><Emphasis style="italic">Clause 17</Emphasis>:</Label><ExplanatoryText>New.</ExplanatoryText></ExplanatoryNote></Section></Body></Bill>