<?xml version="1.0"?>
<Bill RHead_reign="57 Eliz. II" RHead_ParlYear="2008" DocumentTitle="BILL S-202" Bill_No="S-202" Document_No="39-2-0732" xml:lang="EN" Bill_Type="Non-amending" Stage_Name="First-Reading-Senate" Reprint="No" xml:space="preserve" ChapterNo_E="C. " ChapterNo_F="ch. " Bill-Origin="senate"><Bill_Part Part_Type="Cover" CountLines="No"><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="CovBillNo">S-202</Para></Block><Block><Para TopMargin="24" Size="9" Leading="10" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0" TextAlign="Center">First Session, Fortieth Parliament,</Para></Block><Block><Para Size="9" Leading="10" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0" TextAlign="Center">57 Elizabeth II, 2008</Para></Block><Block><Para TopMargin="48" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0" Bold="Yes" TextAlign="Center">SENATE OF CANADA</Para></Block><Block><Para TopMargin="42" Size="18" Leading="20" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0" Bold="Yes" TextAlign="Center">BILL S-202</Para></Block><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="CovLongTitle">An Act respecting commercial electronic messages</Para></Block><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="COV_StageLine"></Para></Block><Block><Para Size="9" AllCaps="Yes" Hyphenate="OFF">first reading, November 20, 2008</Para></Block><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="COV_StageLine"></Para></Block><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="Cover_Sponsors">THE HONOURABLE SENATOR GOLDSTEIN</Para></Block><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="Cover_DocNo">39-2-0732</Para></Block></Bill_Part><Bill_Part CountLines="No" Part_Type="InsideCover"><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="BPT_InsideCoverE">Available on the Parliament of Canada Web Site at the following address:<br/><B>http://www.parl.gc.ca</B></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><Para TopMargin="108" BottomMargin="4" Size="10" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">SUMMARY</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" Size="8" Leading="9" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">This enactment prohibits the sending of a commercial electronic message without the consent of the recipient.  Consent to receiving commercial electronic messages from certain senders is presumed.  The enactment sets out form and content requirements for commercial electronic messages, and also prohibits address harvesting, dictionary attacks and phishing. The enactment creates offences for the contravention of its provisions, as well as a civil right of action.</Para></Block></Bill_Part><Bill_Part Part_Type="MainText" CountLines="Yes" RunningHead_E="Anti-Spam"><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="MainText_DocNo">39-2-0732</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes"><Para Style="Session_Reign">1st Session, 40th Parliament,</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes"><Para Style="Session_Reign">57 Elizabeth II, 2008</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes"><Para Style="MainBillOrigin">senate of canada</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes"><Para Bold="Yes" Style="MAIN@BillNo_Title">BILL S-202</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes"><Para Style="MAIN@ti;04">An Act respecting commercial electronic messages</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">Her Majesty, by and with the advice and consent of the Senate and House of Commons of Canada, enacts as follows:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:SHORT TITLE--><Para TopMargin="10" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">SHORT TITLE</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Short title<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>1.</B> This Act may be cited as the <I>Anti-Spam Act</I>.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:INTERPRETATION--><Para TopMargin="10" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">INTERPRETATION</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Definitions<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>2.</B>  The following definitions apply in this Act.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><MarginalNote>“address-harvesting software”<br/>« <I>logiciel de collecte d’adresses</I> »<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0">“address-harvesting software” means software that searches the Internet for electronic addresses and collects, compiles, captures or otherwise harvests electronic addresses.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><MarginalNote>“commercial electronic message”<br/>« <I>message électronique commercial</I> »<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0">“commercial electronic message” means an electronic message that</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>a</I>) advertises, promotes or offers to supply goods, a service, land, an interest in land, or a business, investment or gaming opportunity,</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>b</I>) advertises or promotes a provider or prospective provider of anything referred to in paragraph (<I>a</I>), or</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>c</I>) is of a kind prescribed by regulation,</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0">but does not include an electronic message that is sent by or on behalf of a government department or agency, a court or a tribunal.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><MarginalNote>“educational institution”<br/>« <I>établissement d’enseignement</I> »<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0">“educational institution” means</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>a</I>) a non-profit institution licensed or recognized by or under an Act of Parliament or the legislature of a province to provide pre-school, elementary, secondary or post-secondary education;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>b</I>) a non-profit institution that is directed or controlled by a board of education regulated by or under an Act of the legislature of a province and that provides continuing, professional or vocational education or training; or</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>c</I>) a department or agency of any order of government, or any non-profit body, that controls or supervises education or training referred to in paragraph (<I>a</I>) or (<I>b</I>).</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><MarginalNote>“electronic address”<br/>« <I>adresse électronique</I> »<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0">“electronic address” means an address in connection with an e-mail account, instant messaging account, telephone account or similar account.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><MarginalNote>“electronic message”<br/>« <I>message électronique</I> »<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0">“electronic message” means a message that is sent through a telecommunications service provider to an electronic address, but does not include a message sent by way of a voice call made using a telephone service.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><MarginalNote>“harvested-address list”<br/>« <I>liste d’adresses colligées</I> »<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0">“harvested-address list” means a list, collection or compilation of electronic addresses where the production of the list, collection or compilation is, to any extent, directly or indirectly attributable to the use of address-harvesting software.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><MarginalNote>“message”<br/>« <I>message</I> »<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0">“message” means information in the form of text, data, images, sounds or any other form or combination of forms.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><MarginalNote>“person”<br/>« <I>personne</I> »<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0">“person” means an individual, partnership, corporation, trust, foundation, or an unincorporated organization or association of any kind.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><MarginalNote>“political party”<br/>« <I>parti politique</I> »<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0">“political party” means a political party that is registered under the <I>Canada Elections Act</I> or a comparable law of a province or foreign state.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><MarginalNote>“recipient”<br/>« <I>destinataire</I> »<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0">“recipient”, in respect of an electronic message, means the person who is responsible for the e-mail account, instant messaging account, telephone account or similar account to which the message is sent.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><MarginalNote>“send”<br/>« <I>envoyer</I> »<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0">“send” includes attempt to send.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><MarginalNote>“sender”<br/>« <I>expéditeur</I> »<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0">“sender”, in respect of an electronic message, includes a person who authorizes the sending of the message, but does not include a telecommunications service provider who provides an access service that is limited to handling, transmitting or relaying the message.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><MarginalNote>“telecommunications service provider”<br/>« <I>fournisseur de services de télécommunication</I> »<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0">“telecommunications service provider” has the same meaning as in the <I>Telecommunications Act</I>.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><MarginalNote>“unsubscribe facility”<br/>« <I>mécanisme de désinscription</I> »<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0">“unsubscribe facility” means an electronic address set out in a commercial electronic message to which the recipient can send an unsubscribe request to the person who sent or authorized the sending of the message.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><MarginalNote>“unsubscribe request”<br/>« <I>demande de désinscription</I> »<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0">“unsubscribe request” means an electronic message sent by the recipient of a commercial electronic message to the sender of that message to the effect that the recipient withdraws consent to receiving any further commercial electronic messages from or authorized by the sender.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Clarification — commercial electronic message<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(2) For the purposes of the definition “commercial electronic message” in subsection (1), it is immaterial whether it is lawful to acquire the goods, service, land or interest in land or to take up the business, investment or gaming opportunity, or whether the goods, service, land, interest in land, or business, investment or gaming opportunity exists.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Clarification — electronic message<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(3) For the purposes of the definition “electronic message” in subsection (1), it is immaterial whether the message reaches its intended destination or that the address to which the message is sent is a non-existent electronic address.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Definition of “non-existent electronic address”<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(4) In this section, “non-existent electronic address” means a destination, expressed as a combination of letters, numbers or symbols, or any combination thereof, that appears to be an electronic address but that is not connected to an account that is inscribed, registered, owned or used by any person.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Presumption of authorization<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>3.</B> (1) A person who receives an economic benefit from the sending, by another person, of a commercial electronic message that advertises or promotes the trade, business, property, goods or services of the first-mentionned person is presumed, in the absence of evidence to the contrary, to have authorized the sending of the message.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Telecommunications service providers<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(2) A telecommunications service provider does not authorize the sending of a commercial electronic message merely because it supplies a service that enables the message to be sent.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Receipt in Canada<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>4.</B> If a person sends a commercial electronic message from any place and it is received by another person in Canada, then, for the purposes of this Act, the act of sending is deemed to have taken place in Canada.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:FORM AND CONTENT REQUIREMENTS--><Para TopMargin="10" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">FORM AND CONTENT REQUIREMENTS</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Accurate sender information<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>5.</B> (1) A commercial electronic message shall</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>a</I>) clearly and accurately identify the person who is sending or authorized the sending of the message;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>b</I>) contain readily-accessible and accurate header and routing information; and</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>c</I>) include readily-accessible and accurate information as to how the recipient of the message can easily contact the person who is sending or authorized the sending of the message.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Validity<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(2) The information required under subsection (1) shall be valid for at least 30 days after the commercial electronic message is sent.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Accurate subject line<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>6.</B> A commercial electronic message shall include a subject line that is not intended or likely to mislead the recipient about a material fact regarding the contents or subject matter of the message.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Unsubscribe facility<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>7.</B> (1) A commercial electronic message shall include a functional unsubscribe facility and a clear statement to the effect that the recipient may use the unsubscribe facility to send an unsubscribe request to the person who sent or authorized the sending of the message.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Requirements<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(2) The unsubscribe facility</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>a</I>) shall be expressed and presented in a clear and conspicuous manner;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>b</I>) shall allow the recipient to respond to the sender using the same method of communication that was used to send the commercial electronic message;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>c</I>) shall be capable of receiving the unsubscribe request at all times during a period of at least 30 days after the message is sent; and</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>d</I>) shall not require the recipient to pay a fee to the sender of the message or to any other person in order to use the unsubscribe facility.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Ordinary service fee<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(3) Paragraph (2)(<I>d</I>) does not apply to any fee ordinarily charged by the recipient’s telecommunications service provider for handling, transmitting or relaying messages.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:PROHIBITIONS--><Para TopMargin="10" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">PROHIBITIONS</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Unsolicited commercial electronic messages<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>8.</B> (1) No person shall send or authorize the sending of a commercial electronic message unless the recipient has consented to receiving the message.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Presumed consent<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(2) A recipient is presumed to have consented to receiving an exempt commercial electronic message from a sender unless the recipient has withdrawn such consent prior to the message being sent.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Definition of “exempt commercial electronic message”<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(3) In this section, “exempt commercial electronic message” means a commercial electronic message that is sent or authorized to be sent by</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>a</I>) a political party or an association of members of a political party for an electoral district;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>b</I>) a nomination contestant, leadership contestant or candidate of a political party, or the official campaign of such a contestant or candidate;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>c</I>) a registered charity within the meaning of subsection 248(1) of the <I>Income Tax Act</I>;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>d</I>) a partnership, corporation, trust, foundation, organization or association no part of whose income is payable or otherwise available for the personal benefit of any of its proprietors, members or shareholders;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>e</I>) an educational institution, if</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="4" FirstLineIndent="0">(i) the recipient is, or has been, enrolled as a student at that institution, or</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="4" FirstLineIndent="0">(ii) a member or former member of the recipient’s household is, or has been, enrolled as a student at that institution;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>f</I>) a person who has an existing business relationship with the recipient;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>g</I>) a person who has sent the message to the recipient for the sole purpose of collecting information for a public opinion poll or survey; or</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>h</I>) any other person prescribed by regulation.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>No implied consent<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>9.</B> The consent of a recipient to receiving a commercial electronic message may not be inferred from the fact that the recipient’s electronic address has been published or is otherwise generally available to the public unless</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>a</I>) the recipient is one of the following individuals and the electronic address enables the general public to send a message that is relevant to the individual’s work, business, functions or duties:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="4" FirstLineIndent="0">(i) an employee, director, partner or officer of a person,</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="4" FirstLineIndent="0">(ii) a public office holder, or</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="4" FirstLineIndent="0">(iii) a self-employed individual; and</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>b</I>) it would be reasonable to assume that the electronic address was published with the knowledge of the individual or person concerned.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Withdrawal of consent<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>10.</B> (1) A recipient who has previously consented, or is presumed under subsection 8(2) to have consented, to receiving a commercial electronic message may withdraw consent to receiving any further commercial electronic messages from the sender by sending an unsubscribe request to the sender of the commercial electronic message or by any other means.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Effective date of unsubscribe request<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(2) The consent of a recipient to receiving commercial electronic messages from a sender is deemed to be withdrawn seven days after the day on which an unsubscribe request is sent by the recipient to the sender of the commercial electronic message.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Form and contents requirements<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>11.</B> No person shall send or authorize the sending of a commercial electronic message that does not meet the requirements set out in sections 5 to 7.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Address harvesting<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>12.</B> (1) Subject to subsection (2), no person shall supply, offer to supply, acquire or use address-harvesting software or a harvested-address list.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Exceptions<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(2) Subsection (1) does not apply to a law enforcement agency, national security agency or other person prescribed by regulation.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Dictionary attack<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>13.</B> No person shall send or authorize the sending of a commercial electronic message if the person knows or ought to know that the electronic address to which the message is sent was obtained</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>a</I>) using address-harvesting software;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>b</I>) from a harvested-address list; or</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>c</I>) using an automated means that generates possible electronic addresses by combining letters, numbers or symbols or a combination thereof.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Impersonation of a trusted source<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>14.</B> No person shall</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>a</I>) create a website or domain name that represents itself as being the website or domain name of another person without that other person’s authorization; and</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>b</I>) use that website or domain name to request or attempt to induce any person to send or provide any personal information or means of identification.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>False representation<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>15.</B> No person shall send or authorize the sending of a commercial electronic message that</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>a</I>) falsely represents itself as being sent by or on behalf of another person;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>b</I>) includes a hyperlink or other means of directing or linking the recipient to an online location that falsely purports to belong to or be associated with that other person; and</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>c</I>) requests or attempts to induce the recipient to directly or indirectly send or provide any personal information or means of identification.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:DUTY--><Para TopMargin="10" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">DUTY</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Promotion of business interest<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>16.</B> Every person who knows, or ought to know, that their trade, business, property, goods or services are being or will be advertised or promoted in a commercial electronic message sent contrary to section 8 or 11, and who receives or expects to receive an economic benefit from the sending of the message, shall take reasonable measures to prevent the sending of the message and to report any contravention to an appropriate law enforcement agency.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:ENFORCEMENT--><Para TopMargin="10" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">ENFORCEMENT</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:Offences--><Para TopMargin="5" SmallCaps="Yes" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">Offences</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Contravention — subsection 8(1)<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>17.</B> (1) Every person, other than an individual, who contravenes subsection 8(1) is guilty of an indictable offence and liable</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>a</I>) for a first offence, to a fine not exceeding <keep>$500,000</keep>; and</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>b</I>) for a second or subsequent offence, to a fine not exceeding <keep>$1,500,000</keep>.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Individuals<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(2) An individual who contravenes subsection 8(1) is guilty of an indictable offence and liable</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>a</I>) for a first offence, to a fine not exceeding <keep>$500,000</keep> or to imprisonment for a term not exceeding two years, or to both; and</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>b</I>) for a second or subsequent offence, to a fine not exceeding <keep>$1,500,000</keep> or to imprisonment for a term not exceeding five years, or to both.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Contravention of form and content requirements<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>18.</B> (1) Every person, other than an individual, who contravenes section 11 is guilty of</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>a</I>) an indictable offence and liable to a fine not exceeding <keep>$1,500,000;</keep> or</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>b</I>) an offence punishable on summary conviction and liable to a fine not exceeding <keep>$500,000.</keep></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Individuals<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(2) An individual who contravenes section 11 is guilty of</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>a</I>) an indictable offence and liable to a fine not exceeding <keep>$1,500,000</keep> or to imprisonment for a term not exceeding two years, or to both; or</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>b</I>) an offence punishable on summary conviction and liable to a fine not exceeding <keep>$500,000</keep> or to imprisonment for a term not exceeding six months, or to both.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Contravention of other provisions<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>19.</B> (1) Every person, other than an individual, who contravenes subsection 12(1), any of sections 13 to 16 or a provision of any regulation made under this Act is guilty of</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>a</I>) an indictable offence and liable to a fine not exceeding <keep>$1,500,000;</keep> or</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>b</I>) an offence punishable on summary conviction and liable to a fine not exceeding <keep>$500,000.</keep></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Individuals<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(2) An individual who contravenes subsection 12(1), any of sections 13 to 16 or a provision of any regulation made under this Act is guilty of</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>a</I>) an indictable offence and liable to a fine not exceeding <keep>$1,500,000</keep> or to imprisonment for a term not exceeding two years, or to both; or</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>b</I>) an offence punishable on summary conviction and liable to a fine not exceeding <keep>$500,000</keep> or to imprisonment for a term not exceeding six months, or to both.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Aiding and abetting<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>20.</B> Every person who knowingly counsels, induces, aids or abets or attempts to induce, aid or abet any person to contravene any of the provisions of this Act or the regulations commits an offence and is liable to the same penalty as that person.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Officers, etc. of corporations<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>21.</B> If a corporation commits an offence under this Act, any officer, director or agent or mandatary of the corporation who directed, authorized, assented to, acquiesced in or participated in the commission of the offence is a party to, and guilty of, the offence and liable on conviction to the punishment provided for the offence, whether or not the corporation has been prosecuted or convicted.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Defences<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>22.</B> In the prosecution of a person for a contravention of any provision of this Act, it is a defence for the person to prove that the contravention was due to inadvertence or based on an honest mistake of fact.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Determination of fine<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>23.</B> In determining the amount of a fine in respect of a conviction for an offence under this Act, the court shall have regard to all the relevant matters, including</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>a</I>) the nature and seriousness of the conduct that constituted the offence;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>b</I>) the nature and extent of any loss or damage suffered as a result of the commission of the offence;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>c</I>) the circumstances surrounding the commission of the offence;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>d</I>) whether the person has previously been found by a court in proceedings under this Act to have engaged in any similar conduct; and</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>e</I>) if the court considers that it is appropriate to do so, whether the person has previously been found by a court in a foreign state to have engaged in any similar conduct.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:Ancillary Order--><Para TopMargin="10" SmallCaps="Yes" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">Ancillary Order</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Monetary benefits<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>24.</B> Where a person has been convicted of an offence under this Act and the court is satisfied that monetary benefits accrued to the person as a result of the commission of the offence,</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>a</I>) the court may order the person to pay an additional fine in an amount equal to the court’s estimation of the amount of the monetary benefits; and</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>b</I>) the additional fine may exceed the maximum amount of any fine that may otherwise be imposed under this Act.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:Civil Action--><Para TopMargin="10" SmallCaps="Yes" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">Civil Action</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Right of civil action<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>25.</B> (1) A person who is, or is about to be, adversely affected as a result of conduct that is contrary to any provision of this Act or the regulations may bring an action in any court of competent jurisdiction against the person who engaged in or is engaging in the conduct.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Remedies<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(2) In a proceeding brought under subsection (1), the court may grant any or all of the following remedies:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>a</I>) an injunction;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>b</I>) an order, including an interlocutory order, requiring the defendant to refrain from doing anything that, in the opinion of the court, may constitute an offence under this Act;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>c</I>) an order, including an interlocutory order, requiring the defendant to do anything that, in the opinion of the court, may prevent the continuation of an offence under this Act;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>d</I>) damages to compensate the plaintiff for the monetary loss incurred by the plaintiff as a result of the defendant’s conduct;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>e</I>) punitive damages; or</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>f</I>) any other appropriate relief, including the costs of the action.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Making an order<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(3) The court may grant a remedy under subsection (2) whether or not it makes or has made any other order under this Act in relation to the same conduct.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Factors to consider in assessing damages<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(4) In determining the amount of damages to be awarded to the plaintiff under paragraph (2)(<I>d</I>), the court may have regard to the following:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>a</I>) the extent to which any expenses incurred by the plaintiff are attributable to the defendant’s conduct;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>b</I>) the effect of the defendant’s conduct on the plaintiff’s ability to carry on a business or other activity;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>c</I>) any damage to the reputation of the plaintiff’s business that is attributable to the defendant’s conduct;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>d</I>) any loss of business opportunities suffered by the plaintiff as a result of the defendant’s conduct; and</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>e</I>) any other matters that the court considers relevant.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Limitation period<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(5) Proceedings under subsection (1) must be brought within two years after the day on which the plaintiff became aware or should have become aware of the conduct on which the action is based.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:TELECOMMUNICATIONS SERVICE PROVIDERS--><Para TopMargin="10" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">TELECOMMUNICATIONS SERVICE PROVIDERS</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Refusing or cancelling service<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>26.</B> (1) A telecommunications service provider may, upon giving reasonable notice, refuse or cancel service or access to any person who has been convicted of an offence under this Act or who sends commercial electronic messages that the provider has reasonable grounds to believe are sent in contravention of this Act.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Filtering or blocking messages<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(2) A telecommunications service provider may, upon giving reasonable notice, filter or block some or all commercial electronic messages originating through another telecommunications service provider that hosts or facilitates any person who sends commercial electronic messages that the first-mentioned provider has reasonable grounds to believe are sent in contravention of this Act.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>No liability<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(3) A telecommunications service provider acting in good faith under subsection (1) or (2) is not liable to any person for any loss or damage resulting from the refusal, cancellation, filtering or blocking.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:REGULATIONS--><Para TopMargin="10" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">REGULATIONS</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Power of Governor in Council<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>27.</B> The Governor in Council may make regulations prescribing any matter or thing that by this Act is to be or may be prescribed and generally to carry out the purposes and provisions of this Act.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:COMING INTO FORCE--><Para TopMargin="10" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">COMING INTO FORCE</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Coming into force<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>28.</B> This Act comes into force 30 days after the day on which it receives royal assent.</Para></Block><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="BPT_ImprintE"><br/><br/>Published under authority of the Senate of Canada</Para></Block><Block Align="Yes" LineCnt="N"><Para NoLineBreak="Yes" NoHtml="Yes" Leading="0" Size="0" TopMargin="0" BottomMargin="0"></Para></Block></Bill_Part></Bill>
