<?xml version="1.0"?>
<Bill RHead_reign="57 Eliz. II" RHead_ParlYear="2008" DocumentTitle="BILL S-207" Bill_No="S-207" Document_No="38-1-0526" xml:lang="EN" Bill_Type="Non-amending" Stage_Name="First-Reading-Senate" Reprint="No" xml:space="preserve" ChapterNo_E="C. " ChapterNo_F="ch. " Bill-Origin="senate"><Bill_Part Part_Type="Cover" CountLines="No"><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="CovBillNo">S-207</Para></Block><Block><Para TopMargin="24" Size="9" Leading="10" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0" TextAlign="Center">First Session, Fortieth Parliament,</Para></Block><Block><Para Size="9" Leading="10" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0" TextAlign="Center">57 Elizabeth II, 2008</Para></Block><Block><Para TopMargin="48" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0" Bold="Yes" TextAlign="Center">SENATE OF CANADA</Para></Block><Block><Para TopMargin="42" Size="18" Leading="20" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0" Bold="Yes" TextAlign="Center">BILL S-207</Para></Block><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="CovLongTitle">An Act to require the Minister of the Environment to establish, in co-operation with the provinces, an agency with the power to identify and protect Canada芒聙聶s watersheds that will constitute sources of drinking water in the future</Para></Block><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="COV_StageLine"></Para></Block><Block><Para Size="9" AllCaps="Yes" Hyphenate="OFF">first reading, November 20, 2008</Para></Block><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="COV_StageLine"></Para></Block><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="Cover_Sponsors">THE HONOURABLE SENATOR GRAFSTEIN</Para></Block><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="Cover_DocNo">38-1-0526</Para></Block></Bill_Part><Bill_Part CountLines="No" Part_Type="InsideCover"><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="BPT_InsideCoverE">Available on the Parliament of Canada Web Site at the following address:<br/><B>http://www.parl.gc.ca</B></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><Para TopMargin="108" BottomMargin="4" Size="10" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">SUMMARY</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" Size="8" Leading="9" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">This enactment requires the Minister of the Environment to conclude an agreement to establish a federal-provincial agency that will have the power to administer both federal and provincial laws and the regulatory authority to identify, protect and restrict the use and development of lands that constitute watershed areas essential to Canada芒聙聶s drinking water needs in the future.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" Size="8" Leading="9" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">The enactment sets a time limit for concluding the agreement and for introducing in Parliament any legislation necessary to implement it.</Para></Block></Bill_Part><Bill_Part Part_Type="MainText" CountLines="Yes" RunningHead_E="Drinking Water Sources"><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="MainText_DocNo">38-1-0526</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes"><Para Style="Session_Reign">1st Session, 40th Parliament,</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes"><Para Style="Session_Reign">57 Elizabeth II, 2008</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes"><Para Style="MainBillOrigin">senate of canada</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes"><Para Bold="Yes" Style="MAIN@BillNo_Title">BILL S-207</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes"><Para Style="MAIN@ti;04">An Act to require the Minister of the Environment to establish, in co-operation with the provinces, an agency with the power to identify and protect Canada芒聙聶s watersheds that will constitute sources of drinking water in the future</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Preamble<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">Whereas Canada芒聙聶s drinking water sources are threatened by land use and development that may have an impact on the quality of the water and its suitability as drinking water;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">Whereas the need for clean, safe drinking water is increasing in all regions of Canada;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">Whereas the legislative powers that relate to the protection of watershed areas are under both federal and provincial jurisdiction;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">And whereas there is urgent need for federal and provincial governments to protect Canada芒聙聶s drinking water sources for the future;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">Now, therefore, Her Majesty, by and with the advice and consent of the Senate and House of Commons of Canada, enacts as follows:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Short title<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>1.</B> This Act may be cited as the <I>Drinking Water Sources Act</I>.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Definitions<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>2.</B> The following definitions apply in this Act.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><MarginalNote>芒聙聹agency芒聙聺<br/>脗芦 <I>agence</I> 脗禄<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0">芒聙聹agency芒聙聺 means the federal-provincial agency referred to in subsection 3(3).</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><MarginalNote>芒聙聹drinking water芒聙聺<br/>脗芦 <I>eau potable</I> 脗禄<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0">芒聙聹drinking water芒聙聺 means water for human consumption.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><MarginalNote>芒聙聹Minister芒聙聺<br/>脗芦 <I>ministre</I> 脗禄<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0">芒聙聹Minister芒聙聺 means the Minister of the Environment.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><MarginalNote>芒聙聹protected watershed芒聙聺<br/>脗芦 <I>bassin hydrographique prot脙漏g脙漏</I> 脗禄<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0">芒聙聹protected watershed芒聙聺 means a watershed in respect of which the Minister issues a protection order referred to in paragraph 3(<I>f</I>).</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><MarginalNote>芒聙聹provincial minister芒聙聺<br/>脗芦 <I>ministre provincial</I> 脗禄<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0">芒聙聹provincial minister芒聙聺 means a minister of the Crown of a province who is responsible for the protection of, and approval of the use of, public lands in the province and the quality of drinking water in the province.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><MarginalNote>芒聙聹watershed芒聙聺<br/>脗芦 <I>bassin hydrographique</I> 脗禄<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0">芒聙聹watershed芒聙聺 means an area in which natural precipitation collects naturally or as a result of artificial works or both, and from which it flows to a place from which drinking water is purified and distributed.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Consultation with provincial ministers<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>3.</B> (1) The Minister shall consult with every provincial minister in order to conclude a federal-provincial agreement dealing with the matters specified in subsection (3).</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Other ministers consulted<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(2) The Minister shall consult with the Minister of Health and the Minister of Natural Resources with respect to the principles that should govern the federal-provincial agreement.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Agreement<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(3) The agreement referred to in subsection (1) shall</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>a</I>) establish a process by which a protected watershed may be defined by agreement between the federal government and the government of any province in which it is situated;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>b</I>) specify the basis for establishing a federal-provincial agency to regulate the proposed or existing use of land within a protected watershed;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>c</I>) specify the means by which the agency will have the authority to regulate the existing or proposed use of land within a protected watershed;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>d</I>) specify the means by which the agency will be authorized, in conjunction with the Minister and the provincial minister for the province in which the land is situated, to issue permits governing the use of land within a protected watershed and to enforce federal and provincial laws respecting that land;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>e</I>) establish a process to be administered by the agency to define the anticipated needs of every municipality in Canada for drinking water until the year 2050 and to identify and define the watersheds from which the drinking water will be drawn in each case; and</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>f</I>) establish an outline of legislation to be introduced in Parliament and in the legislature of every province in order to enable the steps described in paragraphs (<I>a</I>) to (<I>e</I>) to be carried out and to authorize the Minister, with the agreement of the provincial minister concerned, to issue protection orders respecting watersheds identified and defined by the process described in paragraph (<I>e</I>).</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Time limit<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>4.</B> (1) The Minister shall, on or before December 31 of the year after the year in which this Act receives royal assent,</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>a</I>) conclude the agreement referred to in section 3; or</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>b</I>) present to both the Senate and the House of Commons a statement of the reasons why the agreement has not been concluded and an estimate of the time when it will be concluded.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Date for legislation to be introduced<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(2) The Minister shall introduce in a House of Parliament, within the first five days on which the House is sitting following the expiration of ninety days after the day on which the agreement referred to in section 3 is concluded, a bill to establish the agency and carry out any other provisions of the agreement that require legislative authority.</Para></Block><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="BPT_ImprintE"><br/><br/>Published under authority of the Senate of Canada</Para></Block><Block Align="Yes" LineCnt="N"><Para NoLineBreak="Yes" NoHtml="Yes" Leading="0" Size="0" TopMargin="0" BottomMargin="0">脗聞</Para></Block></Bill_Part></Bill>
