<?xml version="1.0"?>
<Bill RHead_reign="49-50 Eliz. II" RHead_ParlYear="2001" DocumentTitle="BILL S-36" Bill_No="S-36" Document_No="2534" xml:lang="EN" Bill_Type="Amending" Stage_Name="First-Reading-Senate" Reprint="No" xml:space="preserve" ChapterNo_E="C. " ChapterNo_F="ch. " Bill-Origin="senate"><Bill_Part Part_Type="Cover" CountLines="No"><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="CovBillNo">S-36</Para></Block><Block><Para TopMargin="24" Size="9" Leading="10" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0" TextAlign="Center">First Session, Thirty-seventh Parliament,</Para></Block><Block><Para Size="9" Leading="10" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0" TextAlign="Center">49-50 Elizabeth II, 2001</Para></Block><Block><Para TopMargin="48" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0" Bold="Yes" TextAlign="Center">SENATE OF CANADA</Para></Block><Block><Para TopMargin="42" Size="18" Leading="20" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0" Bold="Yes" TextAlign="Center">BILL S-36</Para></Block><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="CovLongTitle">An Act respecting Canadian citizenship</Para></Block><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="COV_StageLine"></Para></Block><Block><Para Size="9" AllCaps="Yes" Hyphenate="OFF">first reading, December 4, 2001</Para></Block><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="COV_StageLine"></Para></Block><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="Cover_Sponsors"><SC SC_PerCent="85">The Honourable Senator Kinsella</SC></Para></Block><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="Cover_DocNo">2534</Para></Block></Bill_Part><Bill_Part CountLines="No" Part_Type="InsideCover"><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="BPT_InsideCoverE">Available on the Parliament of Canada Web Site at the following address:<br/><B>http://www.parl.gc.ca</B></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><Para TopMargin="108" BottomMargin="4" Size="10" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center"><SC SC_PerCent="85">Summary</SC></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" Size="8" Leading="9" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">This enactment deals with the broad concept of citizenship as it applies to all Canadians.  It replaces the existing <I>Citizenship Act</I>, which deals principally with the naturalization process.  It states in positive terms the status, rights and obligations of Canadian citizenship, encouraging all citizens to participate fully in the life and growth of the nation.  It provides a modern form of oath of loyalty to be taken by new citizens, and allows existing citizens to take the oath to reaffirm their loyalty to Canada if they choose to do so.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" Size="8" Leading="9" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">A Canadian Citizenship Commission is established with a duty to promote an understanding of the nature of citizenship and respect for its value.  The Commission will also advise the Minister of Canadian Heritage and the Minister of Citizenship and Immigration on proposed programs and events that will promote and celebrate Canada and Canadian citizenship.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" Size="8" Leading="9" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">Citizenship Councillors will be appointed to continue the work of the former citizenship judges.  They will preside at citizenship ceremonies, promote citizenship and may advise the Minister on applications for citizenship.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" Size="8" Leading="9" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">The members of the Commission will be appointed from among those who hold the office of Citizenship Councillor.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" Size="8" Leading="9" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">The enactment confirms the principal rights of citizens and their responsibilities and sets out the manner in which citizenship is acquired.  It provides for the continued acquisition of citizenship at birth for everyone born in Canada.  The residency for immigrants and refugees to obtain citizenship will be based on actual presence in Canada.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" Size="8" Leading="9" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">The distinction made between adopted children and children born abroad of Canadian parents is lessened for the purpose of acquiring citizenship.  The right to transmit citizenship to persons born abroad of Canadian parents is limited to the first and second generations.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" Size="8" Leading="9" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">The enactment continues the authority of the Minister to annul the citizenship of persons who obtained their citizenship by using a false identity or who were subject to prohibitions.  It allows the Minister to refuse to grant citizenship on the advice of a Review Committee when national security requires it.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" Size="8" Leading="9" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">The enactment establishes a new Canadian Citizenship Tribunal that considers whether an application for citizenship should be refused on the basis of public interest.  If in such cases the Tribunal so advises, the Governor in Council may refuse to grant citizenship.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" Size="8" Leading="9" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">The process for dealing with applications for citizenship is administrative rather than judicial.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" Size="8" Leading="9" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">Prohibitions and offences related to citizenship and its acquisition are established in order to maintain the integrity of Canadian citizenship.</Para></Block></Bill_Part><Bill_Part Part_Type="MainText" CountLines="Yes" RunningHead_E="Code of Canadian Citizenship"><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="MainText_DocNo">2534</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes"><Para Style="Session_Reign">1st Session, 37th Parliament,</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes"><Para Style="Session_Reign">49-50 Elizabeth II, 2001</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes"><Para Style="MainBillOrigin">senate of canada</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes"><Para Bold="Yes" Style="MAIN@BillNo_Title">BILL S-36</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes"><Para Style="MAIN@ti;04">An Act respecting Canadian citizenship</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Preamble<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">WHEREAS Canadian citizenship is a special treasure of inestimable value to be nurtured and promoted;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">WHEREAS the heritage of Canadian citizens speaks to their ancient and beautiful land which they inhabit in peace with nature;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">WHEREAS Parliament is mindful of the dignity and worth of all Canadian citizens and the rich contribution that each can make to the growth of Canada;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">WHEREAS the <I>Constitution Act, 1867</I>, the common law, the <I>Civil Code</I>, the <I>Canadian Bill of Rights</I>, the <I>Constitution Act, 1982</I>, including the <I>Canadian Charter of Rights and Freedoms</I> and other enactments trace the relationships among Canadian citizens over the years;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">WHEREAS active citizens, through their labours, their democratic institutions and their laws, have built a peaceful nation where they may enjoy the harvest of nature and exercise their enterprises throughout Canada and the world community, while safeguarding the land, its creatures and resources;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">WHEREAS the citizens of Canada enjoy the benefits of peace and prosperity, and they should be given an opportunity to make a contribution, each according to their talents and abilities;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">AND WHEREAS it is desirable to enact a measure to celebrate, protect and codify the richness of Canadian citizenship;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">NOW, THEREFORE, Her Majesty, by and with the advice and consent of the Senate and House of Commons of Canada, enacts as follows:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:Short Title--><Para TopMargin="10" SmallCaps="Yes" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">Short Title</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Short title<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>1.</B> This Act may be cited as the <I>Code of Canadian Citizenship</I>.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Oath of Citizenship<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>2.</B> Every person, on taking Canadian citizenship, shall make and subscribe to the following oath:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">I, (here state full name), pledge my loyalty to Canada and Her Majesty Elizabeth the Second, Queen of Canada. I promise to respect our country’s rights and freedoms, to uphold our democratic values, to faithfully observe our laws and to fulfill my duties and obligations as a Canadian citizen.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:PART 1--><Para TopMargin="10" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">PART 1</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:PROMOTION OF CANADIAN CITIZENSHIP--><Para TopMargin="5" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">PROMOTION OF CANADIAN CITIZENSHIP</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Purpose of Part<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>3.</B> The purpose of this Part is to provide for the promotion of Canadian citizenship and to provide for programs of education in citizenship to achieve a common understanding of and a respect for citizenship.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Definitions<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>4.</B> The definitions in this section apply in this Act.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><MarginalNote>“citizen”<br/>« <I>citoyen</I> »<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0">“citizen” means a Canadian citizen.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><MarginalNote>“citizenship”<br/>« <I>citoyenneté</I> »<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0">“citizenship” means Canadian citizenship.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><MarginalNote>“Commission”<br/>« <I>Commission</I> »<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0">“Commission” means the Canadian Citizenship Commission established by section 5.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><MarginalNote>“Commissioner”<br/>« <I>commissaire</I> »<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0">“Commissioner” means a person who holds the office of Canadian Citizenship Commissioner pursuant to section 6.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><MarginalNote>“Ministers”<br/>« <I>ministres</I> »<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0">“Ministers” means the Minister of Canadian Heritage and the Minister of Citizenship and Immigration acting jointly.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Canadian Citizenship Commission<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>5.</B> There is hereby established the Canadian Citizenship Commission as an agency of the Government of Canada under the administration of the Ministers.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Canadian Citizenship Commissioners<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>6.</B> (1) The Commission consists of the Canadian Citizenship Commissioners appointed according to subsection (2).</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Commissioners appointed<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(2) The Governor in Council shall appoint not more than 9 Canadian Citizenship Commissioners from among those who hold the office of Citizenship Councillor pursuant to section 40.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Appointment of Chief and Deputy Chief<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>7.</B> (1) The Governor in Council shall name one of the Commissioners to be the Chief Canadian Citizenship Commissioner and one of them to be the Deputy Chief Canadian Citizenship Commissioner.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Term<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(2) An appointment under subsection (1) shall be for a term of not more than five years.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Reappointment<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(3) A person may be appointed under subsection (1) for a second or third term.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Chief presides<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(4) The Chief Canadian Citizenship Commissioner presides over the proceedings of the Commission.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Deputy Chief<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(5) In the absence of the Chief Canadian Citizenship Commissioner, the Deputy Chief Canadian Citizenship Commissioner presides over the proceedings of the Commission.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Functions of Commission<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>8.</B> (1) The functions of the Commission are</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>a</I>) to advise the Ministers on all matters relating to citizenship, including fostering the pride of Canadians in their country, their citizenship and their responsibilities to each other in the context of a peaceful and democratic country;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>b</I>) to review programs prepared by any department or agency of the government that are or are proposed to be offered in any manner, medium or sector, within or outside Canada, to citizens and to those seeking Canadian citizenship, that have the objective of</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="4" FirstLineIndent="0">(i) promoting the ideals of Canadian citizenship,</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="4" FirstLineIndent="0">(ii) defining the concept of Canadian citizenship, and</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="4" FirstLineIndent="0">(iii) explaining the rights and obligations that Canadian citizenship entails;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>c</I>) to advise the Ministers respecting the symbols of Canada and their use and display;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>d</I>) to review and advise on plans and proposals by the Government of Canada for events throughout Canada that celebrate Canada and Canadian citizenship; and</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>e</I>) to be a source of persons with experience in matters of citizenship from which the Citizenship Review Tribunal may be appointed from time to time, pursuant to Part 3.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Programs<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(2) Programs mentioned in paragraph (1)(<I>b</I>) include programs</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>a</I>) to assist Canadian citizens to enjoy the benefits and bear the responsibilities of citizenship; and</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>b</I>) to encourage and assist new arrivals in Canada to become Canadian citizens and to enjoy the benefits and bear the responsibilities of citizenship.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Advisory role<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>9.</B> The role of the Commission is advisory, and the Commission does not have the power to determine that any program, event or symbol or any information respecting citizenship must or must not be offered, held, used or disseminated.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Annual report<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>10.</B> (1) The Commission shall prepare and submit to the Ministers, no later than April 1 in every year, a report on its operations in respect of the previous fiscal year.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Laid before Parliament<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(2) On receiving the report from the Commission, the Ministers shall cause it to be laid before each House of Parliament on any of the first five days after it is received that the House sits.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:PART 2--><Para TopMargin="10" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">PART 2</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:CANADIAN CITIZENSHIP--><Para TopMargin="5" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">CANADIAN CITIZENSHIP</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Interpretation<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>11.</B> The definition in this section applies in this Part.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><MarginalNote>“Minister”<br/>« <I>ministre</I> »<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0">“Minister” means the Minister of Citizenship and Immigration.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Purpose of Part<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>12.</B> The purpose of this Part is to confirm the rights of Canadians to citizenship for themselves and their children and the responsibilities that attach to Canadian citizenship.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:Citizenship at Birth--><Para TopMargin="10" Italic="Yes" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">Citizenship at Birth</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Persons who are citizens<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>13.</B> (1) A person is a citizen if the person was a citizen immediately before the coming into force of this section or becomes a citizen in accordance with this Act.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Acquisition at birth<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(2) A person acquires citizenship at birth if, after the coming into force of this section,</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>a</I>) the person is born in Canada; or</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>b</I>) the person is born outside Canada of a parent who is a citizen at the time of the birth, unless the parent’s citizenship was acquired because the parent was born, outside Canada, of a father or mother who was a citizen at the time of the parent’s birth and whose citizenship was also acquired as a result of the father’s or mother’s birth, as the case may be, after February 14, 1977, outside Canada.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Birth in Canada — exception for children of foreign diplomats, etc.<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(3) Paragraph (2)(<I>a</I>) does not apply to a person if, at the time of the person’s birth, neither of the person’s parents is a citizen or lawfully admitted to Canada for permanent residence and one of the parents is</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>a</I>) a diplomatic or consular officer or other representative or employee in Canada of a foreign government;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>b</I>) an employee in the service of a person referred to in paragraph (<I>a</I>); or</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>c</I>) an officer or employee in Canada of a specialized agency of the United Nations or an officer or employee in Canada of any other international organization to whom there are granted, by or under any Act of Parliament, diplomatic privileges and immunities certified by the Minister of Foreign Affairs to be equivalent to those granted to persons referred to in paragraph (<I>a</I>).</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Deserted child<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(4) If a person who appears to be less than seven years of age is found in Canada as a deserted child, paragraph (2)(<I>a</I>) is deemed to apply to the person, unless, within seven years of the finding, it is proved that the person was not born in Canada.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Child born after death of parent<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(5) For the purposes of paragraph (2)(<I>b</I>) and subsection (3), if a child is born after the death of either of the child’s parents, the child is deemed to have been born before the death of that parent.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:Grant of citizenship--><Para TopMargin="10" Italic="Yes" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">Grant of citizenship</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>General principle<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>14.</B> (1) A person acquires citizenship on being granted citizenship by the Minister and taking the oath of citizenship provided in section 2. The requirement of taking the oath of citizenship does not apply to a person referred to in section 15, 16 or 28 or a person who is less than 14 years of age.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Adults<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(2) The Minister shall, on application, grant citizenship to a person who</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>a</I>) is at least 18 years of age;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>b</I>) has been lawfully admitted to Canada for permanent residence, continued to be a permanent resident and has, during the six years immediately before applying for citizenship, resided in Canada for at least 1,095 days, calculated in the following manner :</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="4" FirstLineIndent="0">(i) the person is deemed to have resided in Canada</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="6" FirstLineIndent="0">(A) if the person is determined to be a Convention refugee, one day for every day that the person has resided in Canada, during the period beginning on the day on which the person made application to be a Convention refugee and ending on the day before the person became a permanent resident, or</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="6" FirstLineIndent="0">(B) if the person is a visitor or has a permit within the meaning of the <I>Immigration Act</I>, one half of a day for every day that the person has resided in Canada, up to a maximum of 365 days of deemed residence, during the period that the person is a visitor or a permit holder, as the case may be, and</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="4" FirstLineIndent="0">(ii) for every day during which the person has resided in Canada after lawful admission to Canada for permanent residence, the person is deemed to have resided in Canada for one day;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>c</I>) has an adequate knowledge of one of the official languages of Canada; and</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>d</I>) has an adequate knowledge of Canada and of the responsibilities and privileges of citizenship.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Waiver on compassionate grounds<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(3) If the Minister believes there are compassionate grounds for doing so, the Minister may waive</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>a</I>) in the case of any person, the requirements of paragraph (2)(<I>c</I>) or (<I>d</I>);</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>b</I>) in the case of a minor, the requirement</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="4" FirstLineIndent="0">(i) respecting age, set out in paragraph (2)(<I>a</I>), and</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="4" FirstLineIndent="0">(ii) respecting length of residence in Canada, set out in paragraph (2)(<I>b</I>); or</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>c</I>) in the case of any person who is prevented from understanding the significance of taking the oath of citizenship by reason of mental disability, the requirement to take the oath.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Minors<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(4) The Minister shall, on application, grant citizenship to a permanent resident who is a minor at the time of the application and the child of a citizen.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Adoptees<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>15.</B> The Minister shall, on application, grant citizenship to a person who, after February 14, 1977, was adopted by a citizen while the person was a minor child and whose adoption</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>a</I>) was in the best interests of the child;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>b</I>) created a genuine relationship of parent and child;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>c</I>) was in accordance with the laws of the place where the adoption took place and the laws of the country of residence of the adopting citizen; and</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>d</I>) was not intended to circumvent the requirements under any enactment for admission to Canada or Canadian citizenship.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Statelessness — bloodline connection<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>16.</B> The Minister shall, on application, grant citizenship to a person who</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>a</I>) is born outside Canada after the coming into force of this section;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>b</I>) has a birth parent who is a citizen at the time of the birth;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>c</I>) has resided in Canada for at least 1,095 days during the six years immediately before applying for citizenship;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>d</I>) has always been stateless; and</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>e</I>) has not been convicted of an offence against national security.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Loss of  citizenship<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>17.</B> The right of citizenship may be revoked only by the due process of law and on the grounds prescribed by law.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Equality of all citizens<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>18.</B> (1) A citizen, whether or not born in Canada, is entitled to all the rights, powers and privileges, and is subject to all the responsibilities, duties and liabilities, to which a person who is a citizen at birth is entitled or subject and has the same status as that person.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Rights and responsibilities of citizens in law<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(2) A citizen has the rights granted and the responsibilities set out in the <I>Canadian Charter of Rights and Freedoms</I> and Canadian law, and is entitled to enjoy the peace and prosperity that prevails in Canada and to participate in its growth.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Respect for rights of others<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(3) Every citizen must recognize and respect the application of the rights and responsibilities mentioned in subsection (2) to other citizens.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:PART 3--><Para TopMargin="10" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">PART 3</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:NATURALIZATION--><Para TopMargin="5" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">NATURALIZATION</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Definitions<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>19.</B> (1) The definitions in this subsection apply in this Part.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><MarginalNote>“certificate of citizenship”<br/>« <I>certificat de citoyenneté</I> »<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0">“certificate of citizenship” means a certificate of citizenship issued under an Act of Parliament on or after January 1, 1947.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><MarginalNote>“certificate of naturalization”<br/>« <I>certificat de naturalisation</I> »<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0">“certificate of naturalization” means a certificate of naturalization issued under any Act in force in Canada at any time before January 1, 1947.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><MarginalNote>“certificate of renunciation”<br/>« <I>certificat de répudiation</I> »<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0">“certificate of renunciation” means a certificate of renunciation issued under an Act of Parliament on or after February 15, 1977.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><MarginalNote>“citizenship official”<br/>« <I>fonctionnaire de la citoyenneté</I> »<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0">“citizenship official” means a Citizenship Councillor, the Registrar of Canadian Citizenship and any other person to whom the Minister delegates powers, duties or functions under this Act.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><MarginalNote>“Minister”<br/>« <I>ministre</I> »<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0">“Minister” means the Minister of Citizenship and Immigration.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><MarginalNote>“minor”<br/>« <I>mineur</I> »<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0">“minor” means a person who is less than 18 years of age.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><MarginalNote>“permanent resident”<br/>« <I>résident permanent</I> »<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0">“permanent resident” has the meaning given to that expression by subsection 2(1) of the <I>Immigration Act</I>.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><MarginalNote>“prior legislation”<br/>« <I>législation antérieure</I> »<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0">“prior legislation” means any law about naturalization or citizenship in force in Canada at any time before the coming into force of this section.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><MarginalNote>“Tribunal”<br/>« <I>tribunal</I> »<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0">“Tribunal” means the Canadian Citizenship Tribunal established pursuant to section 29.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Interpretation<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(2) For the purposes of this Act,</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>a</I>) a person born on a Canadian ship as defined in section 2 of the <I>Canada Shipping Act</I> or on a Canadian aircraft as defined in subsection 3(1) of the <I>Aeronautics Act</I> is deemed to be born in Canada;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>b</I>) a person who is registered as an Indian under the <I>Indian Act</I> and who is not a citizen is deemed to be a permanent resident from the day the person registered; and</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>c</I>) a person resides in Canada if the person</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="4" FirstLineIndent="0">(i) is physically present in Canada, and</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="4" FirstLineIndent="0">(ii) is not, under an enactment in force in Canada, subject to a probation order, on parole or confined in a penitentiary, jail, reformatory or prison.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:DIVISION 1--><Para TopMargin="10" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">DIVISION 1</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:CONTINUATION OF CITIZENSHIP--><Para TopMargin="5" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">CONTINUATION OF CITIZENSHIP</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>General principle<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>20.</B> A citizen continues to be a citizen unless the person’s citizenship is lost in accordance with this Part.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Renunciation of citizenship<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>21.</B> The Minister shall, on application, allow a citizen to renounce their citizenship, if the citizen</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>a</I>) is a citizen of a country other than Canada or, if the application is accepted, becomes a citizen of another country;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>b</I>) is not a minor;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>c</I>) is not prevented from understanding the significance of renouncing citizenship by reason of the person having a mental disability; and</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>d</I>) resides outside Canada.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Waiver on compassionate grounds<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>22.</B> If the Minister believes that there are compassionate grounds for doing so, the Minister may waive the application of paragraph 21(<I>c</I>) or (<I>d</I>) to a person.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Revocation order<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>23.</B> (1) The Governor in Council may make an order revoking the citizenship or renunciation of citizenship of a person if the Governor in Council is, on the report of the Minister, satisfied that a person has obtained, retained, renounced or resumed citizenship by false representation or fraud or by knowingly concealing material circumstances.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Effective date<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(2) A revocation takes effect on the day that the Governor in Council specifies in the order.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Presumption<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>24.</B> For the purposes of section 23, a person is deemed to have obtained or resumed citizenship by false representation or fraud or by knowingly concealing material circumstances if the person was admitted to Canada for permanent residence by false representation or fraud or by knowingly concealing material circumstances and, because of that admission, the person subsequently obtained or resumed citizenship.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Notice of decision<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>25.</B> (1) The Minister shall not make a report mentioned in subsection 23(1) unless the Minister notifies the person who is to be the subject of the report that the report is to be made and</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>a</I>) the person does not, within 30 days after the sending of the notice, request the Minister to refer the matter to the Federal Court — Trial Division; or</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>b</I>) if the person does, within 30 days after the sending of the notice, request the Minister to refer the matter, and the Federal Court — Trial Division determines, on a balance of probabilities, that the person has obtained, retained, renounced or resumed citizenship by false representation or fraud or by knowingly concealing material circumstances.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Statement in notice<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(2) The notice must state that the person to whom it is sent may, within 30 days after the sending, request the Minister to refer the matter to the Federal Court — Trial Division.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Order by Minister<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>26.</B> (1) If the Minister is satisfied that a person has, after the coming into force of this section, obtained, retained, renounced or resumed citizenship in contravention of section 38 or by using a false identity, the Minister may, by order, declare that the obtention, retention, renunciation or resumption of citizenship is, and always has been, void.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Notice of decision<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(2) The Minister shall not make an order  under subsection (1) unless the Minister, at least 30 days before making it, notifies the person who is to be the subject of the order.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Statement in notice<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(3) The notice must state that the person may, within 30 days after the date on which it was sent, make representations to the Minister about the proposed order.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Informing person on annulment<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(4) On making an order under subsection (1), the Minister shall inform the person who is the subject of the order that the order has been made and advise them of their right to apply for judicial review under section 18.1 of the <I>Federal Court Act</I>.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Limitation period<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(5) The Minister may not make an order under subsection (1) more than five years after the day on which the citizenship was granted, retained, renounced or resumed, as the case may be.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:DIVISION 2--><Para TopMargin="10" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">DIVISION 2</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:RESTORATION OF CITIZENSHIP--><Para TopMargin="5" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">RESTORATION OF CITIZENSHIP</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Resumption of citizenship<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>27.</B> The Minister shall, on application, grant citizenship to a person who has lost their citizenship and</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>a</I>) whose citizenship was not revoked, declared void or annulled under this Act or prior legislation; and</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>b</I>) who was lawfully admitted to Canada for permanent residence after the loss of citizenship, has continued from that admission to be a permanent resident and, in the two years immediately before applying for citizenship, resided in Canada as a permanent resident for at least 365 days.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Citizenship for certain women<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>28.</B> A woman who notifies the Minister, in writing, that she elects to become a citizen shall be granted citizenship, effective from the day the Minister receives the notice, if the woman</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>a</I>) because of a law in force in Canada at any time before January 1, 1947 had, by reason only of her marriage or the acquisition by her husband of a foreign nationality, ceased to be a British subject; and</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>b</I>) would have been a citizen if the <I>Canadian Citizenship Act</I>, chapter C-19 of the Revised Statutes of Canada, 1970, had been in force immediately before her marriage or the acquisition by her husband of a foreign nationality.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:DIVISION 3--><Para TopMargin="10" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">DIVISION 3</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:PROHIBITIONS--><Para TopMargin="5" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">PROHIBITIONS</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:Public Interest--><Para TopMargin="5" Italic="Yes" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">Public Interest</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Tribunal<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>29.</B> (1) The Governor in Council shall, subject to this section, on the advice of the Minister, appoint a Canadian Citizenship Tribunal to carry out the functions assigned to it by this Part.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Chair<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(2) The Chief Canadian Citizenship Commissioner shall be appointed Chair of the Tribunal.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Members<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(3) The Governor in Council, on the advice of the Minister, shall appoint two Commissioners as members of the Tribunal.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Term and tenure<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(4) The Chair and each member of the Tribunal shall be appointed for a term of five years and shall serve at pleasure.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Rules of procedure<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(5) The Tribunal may, with the approval of the Governor in Council, make rules for its own procedures.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Report by Minister to Tribunal<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>30.</B> (1) If the Minister is satisfied that there are reasonable grounds to believe that it is not in the public interest for a person to become a citizen, the Minister shall submit a report to the Tribunal recommending that the person not be granted citizenship or be allowed to take the oath of citizenship.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Notice of intention<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(2) The Minister shall not submit a report unless the Minister, at least 30 days before submitting it, notifies the person who is to be the subject of the report.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Statement  in notice<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(3) The notice must include a summary of the grounds contained in the report and state that the person may, within 30 days after the date on which the notice was sent, make written representations to the Minister about those grounds.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Hearing by Tribunal<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>31.</B> (1) The Tribunal, on receiving a report under section 30, shall hold a hearing on the question of whether it would not be in the public interest for the person to become a citizen and shall consider the representations made to it by the Minister and by the person.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Order by Tribunal<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(2) If the Tribunal is satisfied that, on a balance of probabilities, it would not be in the public interest for the person to become a citizen, it shall make an order to that effect.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Effect of order<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(3) If the Tribunal makes an order under subsection (2), the Minister is deemed to reject any application for the grant or resumption of citizenship made by the person who is the subject of the order.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Appeal<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>32.</B> (1) An order of the Tribunal may be appealed to the Federal Court — Trial Division.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Effective period<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(2) An order of the Tribunal is effective for the period specified in it, which may not exceed five years.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:National Security--><Para TopMargin="10" Italic="Yes" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">National Security</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Definitions<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>33.</B> (1) In this section, “Review Committee” and “threats to the security of Canada” have the meanings assigned to those expressions by section 2 of the <I>Canadian Security Intelligence Service Act</I>.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Report to Review Committee<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(2) The Minister may report to the Review Committee about any person who, in the opinion of the Minister, should not be granted citizenship, take the oath of citizenship or be issued a certificate of renunciation because there are reasonable grounds to believe that the person has engaged or will engage in</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>a</I>) an activity that constitutes a threat to the security of Canada; or</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>b</I>) an activity that is part of a pattern of criminal activity planned and organized by a number of persons acting together to encourage the commission of an indictable offence under any Act of Parliament.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Notice<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(3) Within 10 days after a report is made, the Minister shall notify the person who is the subject of the report that the report has been made and that the Governor in Council may, following an investigation, make a declaration about that person under section 37.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Application of <I>Canadian Security Intelligence Service Act</I><br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(4) The Review Committee shall investigate the grounds on which the report is based and, for that purpose and with any modifications that the circumstances require, apply subsections 39(2) and (3) and sections 43, 44 and 48 to 51 of the <I>Canadian Security Intelligence Service Act</I> to the investigation, as if</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>a</I>) the investigation were conducted in relation to a complaint made under section 42 of that Act; and</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>b</I>) the references to “deputy head” were references to the Minister.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Summary statement<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(5) The Review Committee shall, as soon as practicable, send to the person who is the subject of the report a statement summarizing the information available to the Review Committee so as to enable that person to be informed as much as possible of the circumstances giving rise to the report, having regard to whether, in the opinion of the Review Committee, the summarized information may be disclosed without injury to national security or to the safety of persons.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Report<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(6) On completion of its investigation, the Review Committee shall report to the Governor in Council on the investigation. The Review Committee shall, when it is convenient to do so, provide the report’s conclusion to the person who is the subject of the report.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>End of investigation<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(7) If the Review Committee is of the opinion that it cannot perform the duties described in subsections (4), (5) and (6), it shall stop the investigation and give notice to the Minister and the person to whom the investigation relates.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Appointment of retired judge<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>34.</B> (1) The Governor in Council may appoint, for a period of three to five years, a retired judge of a superior court to perform the duties and have the powers and functions of a Review Committee referred to in subsections 33(4), (5) and (6). The Governor in Council shall, before making the appointment, consult with the Prime Minister of Canada, the Leader of the Official Opposition in the House of Commons, the Leader of the Opposition in the Senate and the leader of any other party in either House having at least 12 members sitting in that House.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Tenure and renewal<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(2) The Governor in Council may not remove a retired judge appointed under subsection (1) except for cause. The appointment may be renewed at the end of its term.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Remuneration<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(3) A retired judge appointed under subsection (1) is entitled to receive, for each day on which the judge performs duties and exercises functions or powers, the remuneration that the Governor in Council fixes.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Moving and travel expenses<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(4) The judge is entitled to be paid any moving expenses and travel expenses that the judge reasonably incurred to perform those duties and exercise those functions or powers outside their place of residence.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Reference<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>35.</B> (1) The Minister may refer a matter that a Review Committee has stopped investigating under subsection 33(7) to a retired judge appointed under subsection 34(1). The Minister shall provide the retired judge with a copy of the report referred to in subsection 33(2) and send the notice referred to in subsection 33(3) to the person who is the subject of the report.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Application of subsections 33(4), (5) and (6)<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(2) Subsections 33(4), (5) and (6) apply to the retired judge as if the judge were the Review Committee.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Annual report<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>36.</B> (1) A retired judge appointed under subsection 34(1) shall submit an annual report every year, on or before September 30, to the Solicitor General of Canada on the judge’s activities for the preceding fiscal year.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Tabling in Parliament<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(2) After receiving the report, the Solicitor General shall cause the report to be laid before each House of Parliament within the next 15 days the House is sitting.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Declaration<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>37.</B> (1) After considering the report made by the Review Committee under section 33, the Governor in Council may declare that there are reasonable grounds to believe that the person who is the subject of the report has engaged or will engage in an activity mentioned in paragraph 33(2)(<I>a</I>) or (<I>b</I>).</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Effect<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(2) The Minister is, on the making of a declaration by the Governor in Council, deemed to reject any application for the grant or resumption of citizenship or for a certificate of renunciation made by the person who is the subject of the declaration.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Informing person on making declaration<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(3) If the Governor in Council makes a declaration under subsection (1), the Minister shall inform the person who is the subject of the declaration that the declaration has been made and advise them of their right to apply for judicial review under section 18.1 of the <I>Federal Court Act</I>.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Effective period<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(4) A declaration is effective for the period specified in it, which may not exceed five years.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:Other Prohibitions--><Para TopMargin="10" Italic="Yes" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">Other Prohibitions</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Ineligibility<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>38.</B> Despite anything in this Act, other than sections 15, 16 and 23, no person shall be granted citizenship or take the oath of citizenship, if the person</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>a</I>) is, under any enactment in force in Canada, subject to a probation order, on parole, or confined in any penitentiary, jail, reformatory or prison;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>b</I>) is charged with, on trial for, or subject to or a party to an appeal or a review relating to an offence under this Act or an indictable offence under any other Act of Parliament;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>c</I>) is charged with, on trial for, or subject to or a party to an appeal or review relating to, an offence outside Canada that, if committed in Canada, would constitute an indictable offence under any Act of Parliament;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>d</I>) during the period beginning three years before the day on which the person applies for citizenship and ending on the day on which the person would otherwise be granted citizenship or take the oath of citizenship, has been convicted of an offence referred to in paragraph (<I>b</I>) or (<I>c</I>), whether or not, in the case of an offence outside Canada, the person has been pardoned or otherwise granted amnesty by a foreign authority in respect of the offence;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>e</I>) during the period beginning one year before the day on which the person applied for citizenship and ending on the day on which the person would otherwise be granted citizenship or take the oath of citizenship, has been convicted of two or more summary conviction offences under any other Act of Parliament;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>f</I>) is under investigation by the Minister of Justice, the Royal Canadian Mounted Police or the Canadian Security Intelligence Service for, or is charged with, on trial for, or subject to or a party to an appeal relating to, an act or omission referred to in subsection 7(3.71) of the <I>Criminal Code</I>;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>g</I>) has been convicted of an offence in respect of an act or omission referred to in subsection 7(3.71) of the <I>Criminal Code</I>;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>h</I>) requires the consent referred to in subsection 55(1) of the <I>Immigration Act</I> to be admitted to Canada, but has not obtained that consent;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>i</I>) has ceased to be a permanent resident or is subject to, or is a party to, an inquiry under the <I>Immigration Act</I> that may lead to their removal from Canada or to the loss of their status as a permanent resident, and any rights of appeal or review in relation to the inquiry are not exhausted;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>j</I>) during the five years before the day on which the person applies for citizenship, is the subject of an order under section 23 or 26 of this Act or under section 10 of the <I>Citizenship Act</I>, chapter C-29 of the Revised Statutes of Canada, 1985;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>k</I>) is the subject of an order under section 32 or a declaration under section 37;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>l</I>) is the subject of an investigation under section 15 of the <I>Canadian Security Intelligence Service Act</I> or of a report under section 33 of this Act, even during the time that the Governor in Council is deciding on whether or not to make a declaration about the person under section 37; or</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>m</I>) is under a removal order, other than an order that is of no effect because the person has subsequently been granted lawful permission to establish permanent residence in Canada, or is subject to or a party to an appeal or a review relating to the removal order.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:DIVISION 4--><Para TopMargin="10" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">DIVISION 4</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:ADMINISTRATION AND APPLICATION--><Para TopMargin="5" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">ADMINISTRATION AND APPLICATION</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:Ministerial Powers--><Para TopMargin="5" Italic="Yes" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">Ministerial Powers</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Examination for conformity<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>39.</B> (1) On receiving an application under this Act, the Minister shall, as soon as practicable, examine it to determine whether it complies with the provisions of this Act that apply to it.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Information on examination<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(2) If the Minister determines that an application does not comply with the provisions of this Act that apply to it, the Minister shall, without delay, inform the applicant of that determination and advise them of their right to apply for judicial review under section 18.1 of the <I>Federal Court Act</I>.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Power to reverse decision<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(3) The Minister may reverse a decision refusing citizenship or regarding the issuance of a certificate of citizenship, if there appears to have been a material defect in the decision.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:Citizenship Councillors--><Para TopMargin="10" Italic="Yes" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">Citizenship Councillors</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Appointment, tenure, removal and renewal of office<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>40.</B> (1) The Governor in Council may appoint a person as a Citizenship Councillor to hold office, during pleasure, for a term of not more than five years.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Full- or part-time<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(2) A Citizenship Councillor may be appointed to serve full-time or part-time.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Remuneration<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(3) Each Citizenship Councillor is entitled to receive the remuneration that the Governor in Council fixes.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Travel and living expenses<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(4) Each Citizenship Councillor is entitled to be paid any reasonable travel and living expenses that they incur in the course of their duties under this Act while absent from</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>a</I>) in the case of a full-time Citizenship Councillor, the Citizenship Councillor’s ordinary place of work; and</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>b</I>) in the case of a part-time Citizenship Councillor, the Citizenship Councillor’s ordinary place of residence.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Compensation<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(5) A Citizenship Councillor is deemed to be an employee for the purposes of the <I>Government Employees Compensation Act</I> and to be employed in the public service of Canada for the purposes of any regulations made under section 9 of the <I>Aeronautics Act</I>.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Qualifications for appointment<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(6) To be eligible for appointment as, and to serve as, a Citizenship Councillor, a person must be a citizen, have demonstrated an understanding of the values of good citizenship and be recognized for their valuable civic contribution.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Duties<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(7) The duties of a Citizenship Councillor are the following:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>a</I>) to preside at citizenship ceremonies;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>b</I>) to promote active citizenship in the community;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>c</I>) to provide, on the Minister’s request, advice and recommendations about</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="4" FirstLineIndent="0">(i) citizenship applications referred to the Citizenship Councillor,</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="4" FirstLineIndent="0">(ii) the exercise of the Minister’s discretion, and</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="4" FirstLineIndent="0">(iii) appropriate methods to evaluate citizenship applicants about their knowledge of an official language, of Canada and of the rights and responsibilities of citizenship; and</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>d</I>) to give effect to directions of the Minister.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Senior Citizenship Councillor<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>41.</B> The Minister may designate a retired judge of the Federal Court to serve as the Senior Citizenship Councillor responsible for the professional conduct of Citizenship Councillors and the coordination of their activities.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:Ceremony of Citizenship--><Para TopMargin="10" Italic="Yes" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">Ceremony of Citizenship</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Ceremony<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>42.</B> (1) A person who takes the oath of citizenship shall take it during a ceremony before a Citizenship Councillor.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Purpose and procedures for ceremony<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(2) In order to heighten the awareness of new citizens to the responsibilities and privileges associated with citizenship, the Citizenship Councillor presiding over a citizenship ceremony shall, subject to the Minister’s directives,</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>a</I>) underline the importance of the ceremony as a milestone in the life of new citizens;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>b</I>) ensure that the oath of citizenship is taken with dignity and solemnity;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>c</I>) personally give new citizens their certificate of citizenship; and</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>d</I>) promote a strong sense of civic pride, including respect for the law, for the exercise of the right to vote and for the participation of citizens in public affairs, and a sense of mutual respect and understanding between Canadians.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Exception — oath taken outside ceremony<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(3) The Minister may excuse a person from the requirement of taking the oath during a citizenship ceremony and designate any person to administer the oath and give certificates of citizenship to new citizens under procedures that the Minister fixes.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:Certificates--><Para TopMargin="10" Italic="Yes" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">Certificates</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Certificate of citizenship<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>43.</B> (1) The Minister shall, in accordance with the regulations, issue a certificate of citizenship to new citizens and, on application, issue a certificate of citizenship to current citizens.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Certificate of renunciation<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(2) The Minister shall issue a certificate of renunciation of citizenship to an applicant whose application is approved. The applicant loses their citizenship at the end of the day on which the certificate is issued or the later day that the Minister specifies in the certificate.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Surrender of certificate<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>44.</B> (1) The Minister may, by notice in writing, order a person in possession of a certificate issued under this Act or any prior legislation to surrender it to the Minister, if the Minister believes, on reasonable grounds, that the person is not entitled to the certificate or has obtained it in contravention of this Act or any prior legislation.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Compliance with notice<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(2) The person to whom the order relates shall, without delay after being provided with the notice, surrender the certificate to the Minister.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Cancellation of certificate<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>45.</B> (1) The Minister may cancel a certificate issued to a person under this Act or any prior legislation if the Minister determines that the person is not entitled to it or obtained it in contravention of this Act or prior legislation.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Return of certificate<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(2) The Minister shall return a certificate to a person who surrendered it to the Minister if the Minister determines that the person is entitled to it.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Evidence of declarations<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>46.</B> (1) A declaration made under this Act or any prior legislation may be proved in a legal proceeding by the production of the original declaration or of a copy of it that the Minister certifies to be a true copy. The declaration or copy so produced is conclusive evidence of the matters stated in it and of the declarant’s having made the declaration on the date mentioned in it.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Evidence of certificates<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(2) A certificate of citizenship, a certificate of naturalization, a certificate of renunciation or another document issued by the Minister that is evidence of the citizenship status of a person in Canada may be proved in a legal proceeding by the production of the original certificate or the other document or of a document that the Minister certifies as containing the same information as the original certificate or other document.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:Offences--><Para TopMargin="10" Italic="Yes" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">Offences</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Definition of “certificate”<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>47.</B> (1) For the purposes of this section, “certificate” means a certificate of citizenship, a certificate of naturalization, a certificate of renunciation or another document issued by the Minister as evidence of the person’s citizenship status.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Offences<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(2) Every person is guilty of an offence who</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>a</I>) for any of the purposes of this Act makes a false representation, commits fraud or knowingly conceals any material circumstance;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>b</I>) obtains or uses a certificate of another person in order to personate that other person;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>c</I>) knowingly permits their certificate to be used by another person to personate them; or</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>d</I>) whether or not for profit, traffics or offers to traffic in certificates or possesses any certificate for the purpose of trafficking.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Punishment<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(3) Every person who is guilty of an offence under subsection (2) is liable</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>a</I>) on conviction on indictment, to a fine of not more than $10,000 or imprisonment for a term of not more than five years, or to both; or</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>b</I>) on summary conviction, to a fine of not more than $1,000 or to imprisonment for a term of not more than six months, or to both.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Offence<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(4) A person is guilty of an indictable offence and liable to a fine of not more than $10,000 or to imprisonment for a term of not more than five years, or to both, if the person</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>a</I>) without lawful authority, issues or alters a certificate;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>b</I>) counterfeits a certificate; or</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>c</I>) uses, acts on or causes or attempts to cause any person to use or act on a certificate, knowing it to have been unlawfully issued or altered or to have been counterfeited.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>General offence<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(5) A person who contravenes a provision of this Act or the regulations for which no punishment is provided in the provision or other related provisions is guilty of an offence punishable on summary conviction and is liable to a fine of not more than $1,000 or to imprisonment for a term of not more than six months, or to both.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Offences respecting citizenship officials<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>48.</B> (1) Every person is guilty of an offence who</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>a</I>) being a citizenship official, wilfully makes or issues any false document or statement about a matter relating to their duties under this Act or accepts, agrees to accept or induces or assists any other person to accept any bribe or other benefit concerning a matter relating to their duties under this Act or wilfully fails, in any other manner, to perform their duties under this Act;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>b</I>) being a citizenship official, contravenes any provision of this Act or the regulations or knowingly induces, aids or abets or attempts to induce, aid or abet any other person to do so;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>c</I>) gives, offers or promises to give any bribe or consideration of any kind to, or makes any agreement or arrangement with, a citizenship official to induce them in any way not to perform their duties under this Act;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>d</I>) not being a citizenship official, personates or holds themselves out to be, or takes or uses any name, title or description or acts in any other manner that may reasonably lead any person to believe that the person is, a citizenship official; or</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>e</I>) obstructs or impedes a citizenship official in the performance of that official’s duties under this Act.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Punishment<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(2) Every person who is guilty of an offence under subsection (1) is liable</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>a</I>) on conviction on indictment, to a fine of not more than $10,000 or to imprisonment for a term of not more than five years, or to both; or</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>b</I>) on summary conviction, to a fine of not more than $1,000 or to imprisonment for a term of not more than six months, or to both.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Where offence is committed outside Canada<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>49.</B> (1) An act or omission committed outside Canada that would, if committed in Canada, be an offence under this Act is an offence under this Act.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Jurisdiction<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(2) Proceedings related to an offence under this Act that is committed outside Canada may be dealt with by a court having jurisdiction over similar offences in the place in Canada where the person who committed the offence is found, in the same manner as if the offence had been committed in that place, or by any other court to which jurisdiction has been lawfully transferred.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Limitation period<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>50.</B> (1) No proceedings in relation to an offence under this Act or the regulations may be instituted by way of summary conviction more than three years after the time when the Minister became aware of the subject-matter of the proceedings.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Declaration of Minister<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(2) A written declaration appearing to have been issued by the Minister that certifies the day on which the Minister became aware of the subject-matter of any proceedings is admissible, without proof of the signature or of the official character of the person appearing to have signed it, as evidence of the matters stated in it.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:Regulations--><Para TopMargin="10" Italic="Yes" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">Regulations</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Regulations<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>51.</B> The Governor in Council may make regulations</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>a</I>) respecting the evidence to be provided for applications and notices under this Act, including medical evidence to establish parentage, and the times when those applications and notices must be made;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>b</I>) specifying who may make an application under this Act on behalf of a minor;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>c</I>) fixing fees for</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="4" FirstLineIndent="0">(i) making applications or notices under this Act,</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="4" FirstLineIndent="0">(ii) issuing certificates under this Act,</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="4" FirstLineIndent="0">(iii) providing certified or uncertified copies of documents from the records kept in the course of the administration of this Act or any prior legislation,</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="4" FirstLineIndent="0">(iv) taking oaths or making solemn affirmations or declarations under this Act or the regulations,</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="4" FirstLineIndent="0">(v) searching records referred to in subparagraph (iii) and providing documents related to those searches, or</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="4" FirstLineIndent="0">(vi) making changes to the records referred to in subparagraph (iii);</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>d</I>) providing for the waiver or remission of fees referred to in paragraph (<I>c</I>);</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>e</I>) providing for criteria to determine whether a person meets the requirements of paragraphs 14(2)(<I>c</I>) and (<I>d</I>) and, for that purpose, authorizing the Minister to set questions that apply those criteria;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>f</I>) providing for the factors to be considered in determining whether the requirements of section 15 have been met;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>g</I>) respecting the abandonment and withdrawal of applications under this Act;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>h</I>) defining what constitutes a relationship of parent and child for the purposes of determining entitlement to citizenship under any provision of this Act;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>i</I>) prescribing, in the case of a person who fails to take the oath of citizenship at the date, time and place appointed for that purpose, the maximum grace period by the end of which the person must have taken the oath;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>j</I>) prescribing the manner in which a person who is already a citizen may voluntarily reaffirm their loyalty by making and subscribing to the oath in section 2;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>k</I>) prescribing, for the purposes of any application referred to in section 39, the nature of the evidence that is sufficient, the procedures to follow and the requirements of time;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>l</I>) prescribing the powers, duties and functions of the Registrar of Canadian Citizenship referred to in subsection 52(2);</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>m</I>) providing for the number of copies of a certificate or declaration or other documents made or issued under this Act or any prior legislation that a person is entitled to have;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>n</I>) respecting the sending of notices and other documents under this Act, including the requirements for the proof of their sending and the deeming of dates of their having been sent; and</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>o</I>) generally, to carry out the purposes and provisions of this Act.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:Delegation of Minister’s Powers--><Para TopMargin="10" Italic="Yes" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">Delegation of Minister’s Powers</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Delegation of authority<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>52.</B> (1) Anything that is required to be done or that may be done by the Minister under this Act or the regulations may be done on behalf of the Minister by any person that the Minister, in writing, authorizes to act on the Minister’s behalf, without proof of the authenticity of the authorization.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Registrar<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(2) The Minister may designate any officer or employee of the department over which the Minister presides to act as Registrar of Canadian Citizenship for the purposes of this Act.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Limitation<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(3) Only a citizen may act as Registrar of Canadian Citizenship or determine a person’s status as a citizen or a person’s entitlement to obtain, retain, renounce or resume citizenship under this Act.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:Disclosure--><Para TopMargin="10" Italic="Yes" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">Disclosure</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>New citizen’s name<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>53.</B> The name of a new citizen may, unless the new citizen objects, be disclosed by the Minister to the Speakers of the Senate and the House of Commons for use by a member of Parliament in whose electoral division, constituency or geographic region the new citizen resides, to congratulate the new citizen on acquiring their citizenship.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:Documentary Requirements--><Para TopMargin="10" Italic="Yes" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">Documentary Requirements</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Documents<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>54.</B> (1) The Minister may prescribe the form of applications, certificates and other documents required for the purposes of this Act.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Applications and notices<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(2) The Minister may prescribe the manner and place in which applications are to be made or notices are to be given under this Act.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:DIVISION 5--><Para TopMargin="10" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">DIVISION 5</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:STATUS OF CERTAIN PERSONS IN CANADA--><Para TopMargin="5" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">STATUS OF CERTAIN PERSONS IN CANADA</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:Citizen of the Commonwealth--><Para TopMargin="5" Italic="Yes" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">Citizen of the Commonwealth</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Citizen of the Commonwealth<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>55.</B> (1) Every person who, under an enactment of a Commonwealth country other than Canada, is a citizen or national of that country has in Canada the status of a citizen of the Commonwealth.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Citizen of Ireland<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(2) Any law or regulation of Canada, unless it provides otherwise, has the same effect in relation to a citizen of Ireland who is not a citizen of the Commonwealth as it has in relation to a citizen of the Commonwealth.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>British subject<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>56.</B> For the purposes of an enactment in force in Canada on and after the coming into force of this section that refers to the status of British subject, the reference to that status is to be regarded as a reference to the status of Canadian citizen or citizen of the Commonwealth or both, as the intent of the provision may require.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:Property and Legal Rights--><Para TopMargin="10" Italic="Yes" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">Property and Legal Rights</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Property and legal rights<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>57.</B> Subject to section 58,</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>a</I>) real or immovable property and personal or movable property of every description may be taken, acquired, held and disposed of by a person who is not a citizen in the same manner and in all of the same respects as by a citizen; and</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>b</I>) title to real or immovable property or personal or movable property of every description may be derived through, from or in succession to a person who is not a citizen in the same manner and in all of the same respects as though through, from or in succession to a citizen.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Authority to prohibit or restrict acquisitions of property in a province by non-Canadians<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>58.</B> (1) The Lieutenant Governor in Council of a province or any other person or authority in a province that the Lieutenant Governor in Council designates may prohibit, annul or in any manner restrict the taking or acquisition directly or indirectly of, or the succession to, any interest in real or immovable property located in the province by persons who are not citizens or by corporations or associations that are effectively controlled by persons who are not citizens.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Regulations<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(2) The Lieutenant Governor in Council of a province may make regulations that apply in the province for the purposes of</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>a</I>) determining transactions that constitute a direct or an indirect taking or acquisition of an interest in real or immovable property located in the province;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>b</I>) defining “corporations or associations that are effectively controlled by persons who are not citizens”; and</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>c</I>) defining “association”.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Restriction<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(3) Subsections (1) and (2) do not authorize or permit the Lieutenant Governor in Council of a province or any other person or authority in a province that the Lieutenant Governor in Council designates to make any decision or take any action that</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>a</I>) prohibits, annuls or restricts the taking or acquisition directly or indirectly of, or the succession to, any interest in real or immovable property located in the province by a permanent resident;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>b</I>) conflicts with any legal obligation of Canada under any international law, custom or agreement;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>c</I>) discriminates between persons who are not citizens on the basis of their nationalities, except insofar as more favourable treatment is required by any legal obligation of Canada under any international law, custom or agreement;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>d</I>) hinders any foreign state in taking or acquiring real or immovable property in the province for diplomatic or consular purposes; or</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>e</I>) prohibits, annuls or restricts the taking or acquisition directly or indirectly of any interest in real or immovable property located in a province by any person in the course or as a result of an investment that the Minister is satisfied or is, under the <I>Investment Canada Act</I>, deemed to be satisfied as likely to be of net benefit to Canada.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Offences and punishment<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>59.</B> (1) Every person who fails to comply with a prohibition, annulment or restriction under subsection 58(1) is guilty of an offence and liable on summary conviction to a fine of not more than $10,000 or to imprisonment for not more than one year, or to both.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Officers, directors or agents of corporations<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(2) If a corporation commits an offence under subsection (1), any officer, director or agent of the corporation who directed, authorized, assented to, acquiesced in or participated in the commission of the offence is a party to and guilty of the offence and is liable on conviction to the punishment provided for the offence, whether or not the corporation has been prosecuted or convicted.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Application of sections 58 and 59<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>60.</B> Sections 58 and 59 apply in any province on and after a day or days that the Governor in Council, by order, fixes.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Limits on effect of sections 57 and 58<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>61.</B> Sections 57 and 58 do not operate so as to</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>a</I>) qualify any person for any office or for any municipal, parliamentary or other franchise;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>b</I>) qualify any person to be the owner of a Canadian ship;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>c</I>) qualify any person to take, acquire, hold or dispose of any property that by or under any Act of Parliament may be taken, acquired, held or disposed of only by citizens;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>d</I>) entitle any person to any right or privilege as a citizen except the rights and privileges in relation to property that are under this Act expressly given to the person; or</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>e</I>) affect any estate or interest in real or immovable property or personal or movable property to which a person has or may become entitled, either mediately or immediately, in possession or expectancy, in pursuance of any disposition made before July 4, 1883 or any devolution by law on the death of a person dying before that date.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Trials of non-citizens<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>62.</B> A person who is not a citizen is triable at law in the same manner as if the person were a citizen.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:DIVISION 6--><Para TopMargin="10" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">DIVISION 6</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:TRANSITIONAL PROVISIONS, CONSEQUENTIAL AMENDMENTS, COORDINATING AMENDMENTS, REPEAL AND COMING INTO FORCE--><Para TopMargin="5" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">TRANSITIONAL PROVISIONS, CONSEQUENTIAL AMENDMENTS, COORDINATING AMENDMENTS, REPEAL AND COMING INTO FORCE</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:Transitional Provisions--><Para TopMargin="5" Italic="Yes" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">Transitional Provisions</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Pending applications<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>63.</B> (1) Proceedings in relation to an application made under the <I>Citizenship Act</I>, chapter C-29 of the Revised Statutes of Canada, 1985, pending on the day on which section 77 of this Act comes into force must be dealt with under this Act.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Exception<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes">(2) Despite subsection (1), if a citizenship judge under the Act referred to in that subsection is seized of the application, it is continued under that Act, with the modification that sections 29 to 37 of this Act and the provisions relating to the oath of citizenship apply to it.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Continuing jurisdiction<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes">(3) A citizenship judge referred to in subsection (2) continues to hold office as a citizenship councillor in relation to an application referred to in that subsection and has, in relation to the application, all the powers that the judge had before the day on which section 77 comes into force, with the modifications referred to in that subsection.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Examination by Minister<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes">(4) The Minister shall examine any application made under the Act referred to in subsection (1) before the day on which section 77 of this Act comes into force that had not been referred to a citizenship judge before that day.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Citizenship judge deemed Citizenship Councillor<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>64.</B> A citizenship judge under the Act referred to in section 77, immediately before the day on which that section comes into force, is deemed, on that day, to become a Citizenship Councillor appointed under this Act for a term that ends on the day that the judge’s term under that Act would have ended had section 77 not come into force.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Grant of citizenship in certain cases<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>65.</B> (1) On application, the Minister shall grant citizenship to a person who has never acquired citizenship and who was</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0" Bold="Yes">(<I>a</I>) born outside Canada, in the period beginning on January 1, 1947 and ending on February 14, 1977, of a parent having citizenship; or</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0" Bold="Yes">(<I>b</I>) adopted, in the period beginning on January 1, 1947 and ending on February 14, 1977, by a citizen as a minor child and whose adoption satisfied the conditions mentioned in paragraphs 15(<I>a</I>) to (<I>d</I>).</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Grant of citizenship in certain cases<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes">(2) On application, the Minister may grant citizenship to a person born outside Canada of a parent who has been granted citizenship under subsection (1) or under paragraph 5(2)(<I>b</I>) of the <I>Citizenship Act</I>, chapter C-29 of the Revised Statutes of Canada, 1985, if that person establishes a substantial connection with Canada.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Grant of citizenship in certain cases<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes">(3) On application, the Minister may grant citizenship to a person born outside Canada of a parent who has been granted citizenship under subsection (2) if that person establishes a substantial connection with Canada.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Form of application<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes">(4) An application must be made in the form prescribed under subsection 54(1).</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Repeal<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes">(5) This section is repealed three years after the day on which it comes into force and, for greater certainty, a person who fails to make an application prior to that repeal is not entitled, after the repeal, to assert any right or privilege that could have been asserted under this section prior to the repeal.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:Consequential Amendments--><Para TopMargin="10" Italic="Yes" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">Consequential Amendments</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:Canadian Security Intelligence Service Act--><MarginalNote>R.S., c. C-23<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">Canadian Security Intelligence Service Act</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>66.</B> Subparagraph 38(<I>c</I>)(ii) of the <I>Canadian Security Intelligence Service Act</I> is replaced by the following:</Para><ExplNote><Para Align="Yes" TopMargin="10" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0" Italic="Yes" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">Canadian Security Intelligence Service Act</Para><Para Align="Yes" TopMargin="10" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><I>Clause 66</I>: The reference to the “<I>Citizenship Act</I>” is changed to the “<I>Code of Canadian Citizenship</I>” and a cross-reference is  amended.</Para></ExplNote></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="4" FirstLineIndent="0">(ii) reports made to the Committee pursuant to <change>subsection 33(2)</change> of the <change><I>Code of Canadian Citizenship</I></change> or sections 39 and 81 of the <I>Immigration Act</I>, and</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>67.</B> Paragraphs 55(<I>a</I>) and (<I>b</I>) of the Act are replaced by the following:</Para><ExplNote><Para Align="Yes" TopMargin="10" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><I>Clause 67</I>: The reference to the “<I>Citizenship Act</I>” is changed to the “<I>Code of Canadian Citizenship</I>” and cross-references are amended.</Para></ExplNote></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>a</I>) a statement under section 46 of this Act, subsection 45(6) of the <I>Canadian Human Rights Act</I>, subsection <change>33(5)</change> of the <change><I>Code of Canadian Citizenship</I></change> or subsection 39(6) or 81(5) of the <I>Immigration Act</I>; or</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>b</I>) a report under paragraph 52(1)(<I>b</I>), subsection 52(2) or section 53 of this Act, subsection 46(1) of the <I>Canadian Human Rights Act</I>. subsection <change>33(6)</change> of the <change><I>Code of Canadian Citizenship</I></change> or subsection 39(10) or 81(8) of the <I>Immigration Act</I>.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:Criminal Code--><MarginalNote>R.S., c. C-46<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="10" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">Criminal Code</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Definitions<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>68.</B> Subsection 58(2) of the <I>Criminal Code</I> is replaced by the following:</Para><ExplNote><Para Align="Yes" TopMargin="10" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0" Italic="Yes" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">Criminal Code</Para><Para Align="Yes" TopMargin="10" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><I>Clause 68</I>: The reference to the “<I>Citizenship Act</I>” is changed to the “<I>Code of Canadian Citizenship</I>” and a cross-reference to subsection 19(1) is added.</Para></ExplNote></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(2) In this section, “certificate of citizenship” and “certificate of naturalization” have the meaning assigned to those expressions by <change>subsection 19(1)</change> of the <change><I>Code of Canadian Citizenship</I></change>.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:Canada Elections Act--><MarginalNote>2000, c. 9<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="10" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">Canada Elections Act</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>69.</B> Paragraph 65(<I>f</I>) of the <I>Canada Elections Act</I> is replaced by the following:</Para><ExplNote><Para Align="Yes" TopMargin="10" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0" Italic="Yes" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">Canada Elections Act</Para><Para Align="Yes" TopMargin="10" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><I>Clause 69</I>: The relevant portion of section 65 reads as follows:</Para><Para Align="Yes" TopMargin="5" Size="8" Leading="9" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>65.</B> The following persons are not eligible to be a candidate:</Para><Para Align="No" TopMargin="5" Size="8" Leading="9" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">. . . </Para><Para Align="No" TopMargin="5" Size="8" Leading="9" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>f</I>) a judge appointed by the Governor in Council, other than a citizenship judge appointed under the <I>Citizenship Act</I>;</Para></ExplNote></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>f</I>) a judge appointed by the Governor in Council;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:Federal Court Act--><MarginalNote>R.S., c. F-7<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="10" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">Federal Court Act</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>70.</B> Section 21 of the <I>Federal Court Act</I> is repealed.</Para><ExplNote><Para Align="Yes" TopMargin="10" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0" Italic="Yes" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">Federal Court Act</Para><Para Align="Yes" TopMargin="10" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><I>Clause 70</I>: Section 21 reads as follows:</Para><Para Align="Yes" TopMargin="5" Size="8" Leading="9" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>21.</B> The Trial Division has exclusive jurisdiction to hear and determine all appeals that may be brought pursuant to subsection 14(5) of the <I>Citizenship Act</I>.</Para></ExplNote></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:Immigration Act--><MarginalNote>R.S., c. I-2<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="10" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">Immigration Act</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>71.</B> (1) The definition “Canadian citizen” in subsection 2(1) of the <I>Immigration Act</I> is replaced by the following:</Para><ExplNote><Para Align="Yes" TopMargin="10" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0" Italic="Yes" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">Immigration Act</Para><Para Align="Yes" TopMargin="10" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><I>Clause 71</I>: The definitions “Canadian citizen” and “permanent resident” in subsection 2(1) read as follows:</Para><Para Align="Yes" TopMargin="5" Size="8" Leading="9" LeftMargin="0">“Canadian citizen” means a person who is a citizen within the meaning of the <I>Citizenship Act</I>;</Para><Para Align="No" TopMargin="5" Size="8" Leading="9" LeftMargin="0">“permanent resident” means a person who</Para><Para Align="No" TopMargin="5" Size="8" Leading="9" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>a</I>) has been granted landing,</Para><Para Align="No" TopMargin="5" Size="8" Leading="9" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>b</I>) has not become a Canadian citizen, and</Para><Para Align="No" TopMargin="5" Size="8" Leading="9" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>c</I>) has not ceased to be a permanent resident pursuant to section 24 or 25.1,</Para><Para Align="No" TopMargin="5" Size="8" Leading="9" LeftMargin="0">and includes a person who has become a Canadian citizen but who has subsequently ceased to be a Canadian citizen under subsection 10(1) of the <I>Citizenship Act</I>, without reference to subsection 10(2) of that Act;</Para></ExplNote></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>“Canadian citizen”<br/>« <I>citoyen canadien</I> »<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0">“Canadian citizen” means a person who is a citizen within the meaning of the <change><I>Code of Canadian Citizenship</I></change>;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>1992, c. 49, s. 1(6)<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes">(2) The portion of the definition “permanent resident” in subsection 2(1) of the Act after paragraph (<I>c</I>) is replaced by the following:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0">and includes a person who has become a Canadian citizen but who has subsequently <change>lost their</change> Canadian <change>citizenship</change> under <change>section 33</change> of the <change>Code of Canadian Citizenship, and a person who, having been a permanent resident, is the subject of an order under subsection 23(1) of that Act;</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>1992, c. 49, s. 16(8)<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>72.</B> Paragraph 27(2)(<I>i</I>) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Para><ExplNote><Para Align="Yes" TopMargin="10" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><I>Clause 72</I>: The relevant portion of subsection 27(2) reads as follows:</Para><Para Align="Yes" TopMargin="5" Size="8" Leading="9" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(2) An immigration officer or a peace officer shall, unless the person has been arrested pursuant to subsection 103(2), forward a written report to the Deputy Minister setting out the details of any information in the possession of the immigration officer or peace officer indicating that a person in Canada, other than a Canadian citizen or permanent resident, is a person who</Para><Para Align="No" TopMargin="5" Size="8" Leading="9" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">. . . </Para><Para Align="No" TopMargin="5" Size="8" Leading="9" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>i</I>) ceased to be a Canadian citizen pursuant to subsection 10(1) of the <I>Citizenship Act</I> in the circumstances described in subsection 10(2) of that Act;</Para></ExplNote></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0"><change>(<I>i</I>) loses their Canadian citizenship under section 33 of the <I>Code of Canadian Citizenship</I>;</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>73.</B> Subsection 41(2) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Para><ExplNote><Para Align="Yes" TopMargin="10" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><I>Clause 73</I>: Subsection 41(2) reads as follows:</Para><Para Align="Yes" TopMargin="5" Size="8" Leading="9" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(2) Where an inquiry in respect of a person is adjourned pursuant to subsection (1), that person’s claim that he is a Canadian citizen shall be referred to such member of the Queen’s Privy Council for Canada as is designated by the Governnor in Council as the Minister for the purposes of the <I>Citizenship Act</I> and that person shall forthwith make an application for a certificate of citizenship pursuant to subsection 12(1) of that Act.</Para></ExplNote></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Application for certificate of citizenship<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(2) <change>If</change> an inquiry in respect of a person is adjourned <change>under</change> subsection (1), that person’s claim <change>to be</change> a Canadian citizen shall be referred to <change>the <I>Minister of Citizenship and Immigration</I></change> and that person shall, <change>without delay</change>, make an application for a certificate of citizenship <change>under</change> subsection <change>43(1)</change> of the <change><I>Code of Canadian Citizenship</I></change>.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>74.</B> (1) Subsection 42(1) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Para><ExplNote><Para Align="Yes" TopMargin="10" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><I>Clause 74</I>: (1) Subsection 42(1) reads as follows:</Para><Para Align="Yes" TopMargin="5" Size="8" Leading="9" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>42.</B> (1) Where a certificate of citizenship is issued under section 12 of the <I>Citizenship Act</I> to a person who is the subject of an inquiry, the adjudicator who was presiding at the inquiry or any other adjudicator shall terminate the inquiry and let that person come into or remain in Canada, as the case may be.</Para></ExplNote></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>If certificate of citizenship issued<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>42.</B> (1) <change>If</change> a certificate of citizenship is issued under <change>subsection 43(1)</change> of the <change><I>Code of Canadian Citizenship</I> to a person</change> who is the subject of an inquiry, the adjudicator who was presiding at the inquiry or any other adjudicator shall terminate the inquiry and let that person come into or remain in Canada, as the case may be.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes">(2) Paragraphs 42(2)(<I>a</I>) and (<I>b</I>) of the English version of the Act are replaced by the following:</Para><ExplNote><Para Align="Yes" TopMargin="10" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(2) The relevant portion of subsection 42(2) reads as follows:</Para><Para Align="Yes" TopMargin="5" Size="8" Leading="9" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(2) An inquiry that was adjourned pursuant to subsection 41(1) shall be resumed as soon as reasonably practicable, by the adjudicator who was presiding at the inquiry or by any other adjudicator, where</Para><Para Align="No" TopMargin="5" Size="8" Leading="9" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>a</I>) the person who was the subject of the inquiry does not forthwith make an application for a certificate of citizenship pursuant to subsection 12(1) of the <I>Citizenship Act</I>;</Para><Para Align="No" TopMargin="5" Size="8" Leading="9" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>b</I>) a certificate of citizenship is not issued under section 12 of the <I>Citizenship Act</I> to that person within six months from the day on which the inquiry was adjourned or within such greater period of time as the adjudicator considers appropriate in the circumstances; or</Para></ExplNote></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>a</I>) the person who was the subject of the inquiry does not, <change>without delay,</change> make an application for a certificate of citizenship <change>under</change> the <change><I>Code of Canadian Citizenship</I></change>;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>b</I>) a certificate of citizenship is not issued under the <change><I>Code of Canadian Citizenship</I></change> to that person within six months from the day on which the inquiry was adjourned or within <change>any</change> greater period <change>that</change> the adjudicator considers appropriate in the circumstances; or</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:Public Service Superannuation Act--><MarginalNote>R.S., c. P-36<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="10" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">Public Service Superannuation Act</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>75.</B> (1) Part II of Schedule I to the <I>Public Service Superannuation Act</I> is amended by striking out the following:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="-2" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">A citizenship judge appointed by the Governor in Council pursuant to the <I>Citizenship Act</I></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="-1" LeftMargin="4" FirstLineIndent="-2" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify"><AltLang xml:lang="fr"><I>Juge de la citoyenneté nommé par le gouverneur en conseil en application de la Loi sur la citoyenneté</I></AltLang></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes">(2) Part II of Schedule I to the Act is amended by adding, in alphabetical order, the following:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="-2" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify"><change>A Citizenship Councillor appointed by the Governor in Council under the <I>Code of Canadian Citizenship</I></change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="-1" LeftMargin="4" FirstLineIndent="-2" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify"><change><AltLang xml:lang="fr"><I>Conseiller de la citoyenneté nommé par le gouverneur en conseil en application du Code de la citoyenneté canadienne</I></AltLang></change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes">(3) Part III of Schedule I to the Act is amended by adding, in alphabetical order, the following:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="-2" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify"><change>A Citizenship Councillor appointed by the Governor in Council pursuant to the <I>Code of Canadian Citizenship</I></change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="-1" LeftMargin="4" FirstLineIndent="-2" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify"><change><AltLang xml:lang="fr"><I>Conseiller de la citoyenneté nommé par le gouverneur en conseil en application du Code de la citoyenneté canadienne</I></AltLang></change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:References--><Para TopMargin="10" Italic="Yes" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">References</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Replacement of “<I>Citizenship Act</I>” with “<I>Code of Canadian Citizenship</I>”<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>76.</B> The expression “<I>Citizenship Act</I>” is replaced by the expression “<I>Code of Canadian Citizenship</I>” in the following provisions:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0" Bold="Yes">(<I>a</I>) the fifth paragraph of the preamble of the <I>Canadian Multiculturalism Act</I>;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0" Bold="Yes">(<I>b</I>) the portion of section 14 of the <I>Canadian Security Intelligence Service Act</I> after paragraph (<I>b</I>);</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0" Bold="Yes">(<I>c</I>) section 122 of the <I>Immigration Act</I>;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0" Bold="Yes">(<I>d</I>) subsection 2(1) of the <I>Oaths of Allegiance Act</I>;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0" Bold="Yes">(<I>e</I>) paragraph 13(<I>a</I>) of the <I>Official Secrets Act</I>;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0" Bold="Yes">(<I>f</I>) the definition “Canadian” in section 2 of the <I>Special Economic Measures Act</I>; and</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0" Bold="Yes">(<I>g</I>) the definition “Canadian offender” in section 2 of the <I>Transfer of Offenders Act</I>.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:Repeal--><Para TopMargin="10" Italic="Yes" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">Repeal</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Repeal of R.S., c. C-29<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>77.</B> The <I>Citizenship Act</I> is repealed.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:Coordinating Amendments--><Para TopMargin="10" Italic="Yes" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">Coordinating Amendments</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>2001, c. 27<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>78.</B> If the <I>Immigration and Refugee Protection Act</I> being c. 27 of 2001, (“the other Act”) comes into force, then, on the later of the coming into force of this Act and the other Act,</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0" Bold="Yes">(<I>a</I>) clause 14(2(<I>b</I>)(i)(B) of this Act is replaced by the following:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="6" FirstLineIndent="0">(B) if the person is a visitor or has a <change>temporary residence permit within the meaning of the <I>Immigration and Refugee Protection Act</I>, one half of a day</change> for every day that the person has resided in Canada, up to a maximum of 365 days of deemed residence, during the period that the person is a visitor or a permit holder, as the case may be, and</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0" Bold="Yes">(<I>b</I>) the definition of “permanent resident” in subsection 19(1) of this Act is replaced by the following:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>“permanent resident”<br/>« <I>résident permanent</I> »<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0">“permanent resident” has the meaning given to that expression by subsection 2(1) of the <change><I>Immigration and Refugee Protection Act</I></change>.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0" Bold="Yes">(<I>c</I>) paragraph 38(<I>h</I>) of this Act is replaced by the following:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0"><change>(<I>h</I>) requires a prescribed authorization under section 52 of the <I>Immigration and Refugee Protection Act</I> to return to Canada, but has not obtained it;</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0" Bold="Yes">(<I>d</I>) section 66 of this Act is replaced by the following:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>66.</B> Subparagraph 38(<I>c</I>)(ii) of the <I>Canadian Security Intelligence Service Act</I> is replaced by the following:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="4" FirstLineIndent="0">(ii) reports made to the Committee <change>pursuant to subsection 33(2) of the <I>Code of Canadian Citizenship</I> or section 44 of the <I>Immigration and Refugee Protection Act</I>, and</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0" Bold="Yes">(<I>e</I>) section 67 of this Act is replaced by the following:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>67.</B> Paragraphs 55(<I>a</I>) and (<I>b</I>) of the Act are replaced by the following:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>a</I>) a statement under section 46 of this Act, subsection 45(6) of the <I>Canadian Human Rights Act</I> or subsection <change>33(5)</change> of the <change><I>Code of Canadian Citizenship</I></change>; or</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>b</I>) a report under paragraph 52(1)(<I>b</I>), subsection 52(2) or section 53 of this Act, <change>subsection 46(1) of the <I>Canadian Human Rights Act</I>, subsection 33(6) of the <I>Code of Canadian Citizenship</I> or section 44 of the <I>Immigration and Refugee Protection Act</I></change>.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0" Bold="Yes">(<I>f</I>) sections 71 and 72 of this Act are repealed;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0" Bold="Yes">(<I>g</I>) paragraph 76(<I>c</I>) of this Act is repealed; and</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0" Bold="Yes">(<I>h</I>) sections 228 to 232 of the <I>Immigration and Refugee Protection Act</I> are repealed.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:Coming into Force--><Para TopMargin="10" Italic="Yes" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">Coming into Force</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Coming into force<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>79.</B> The provisions of this Act come into force on a day or days to be fixed by order of the Governor in Council.</Para></Block><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="BPT_ImprintE"><br/><br/>Published under authority of the Senate of Canada</Para></Block><Block Align="Yes" LineCnt="N"><Para NoLineBreak="Yes" NoHtml="Yes" Leading="0" Size="0" TopMargin="0" BottomMargin="0"></Para></Block></Bill_Part></Bill>
