<?xml version="1.0"?>
<Bill RHead_reign="48-49 Eliz. II" RHead_ParlYear="1999-2000" DocumentTitle="BILL S-28" Bill_No="S-28" Document_No="2503" xml:lang="EN" Bill_Type="Non-amending" Stage_Name="First-Reading-Senate" Reprint="No" xml:space="preserve" ChapterNo_E="C. " ChapterNo_F="ch. " Bill-Origin="senate"><Bill_Part Part_Type="Cover" CountLines="No"><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="CovBillNo">S-28</Para></Block><Block><Para TopMargin="24" Size="9" Leading="10" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0" TextAlign="Center">Second Session, Thirty-sixth Parliament,</Para></Block><Block><Para Size="9" Leading="10" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0" TextAlign="Center">48-49 Elizabeth II, 1999-2000</Para></Block><Block><Para TopMargin="48" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0" Bold="Yes" TextAlign="Center">SENATE OF CANADA</Para></Block><Block><Para TopMargin="42" Size="18" Leading="20" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0" Bold="Yes" TextAlign="Center">BILL S-28</Para></Block><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="CovLongTitle">An Act to amend the Act of incorporation of the Conference of Mennonites in Canada</Para></Block><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="COV_StageLine"></Para></Block><Block><Para Size="9" AllCaps="Yes" Hyphenate="OFF">first reading, June 22, 2000</Para></Block><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="COV_StageLine"></Para></Block><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="Cover_Sponsors"><SC SC_PerCent="85">The Honourable Senator Carstairs</SC></Para></Block><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="Cover_DocNo">2503</Para></Block></Bill_Part><Bill_Part CountLines="No" Part_Type="InsideCover"><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="BPT_InsideCoverE">Available on the Parliament of Canada Web Site at the following address:<br/><B>http://www.parl.gc.ca</B></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><Para TopMargin="108" BottomMargin="4" Size="10" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center"><SC SC_PerCent="85">Summary</SC></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" Size="8" Leading="9" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">This enactment changes the name of the Corporation to “Mennonite Church Canada”; revises the constitution of the Corporation, including its objects and powers; makes other changes to the Act in order to more accurately reflect the nature and scope of the Corporation’s current activities and to adapt the Act to modern conditions and circumstances; and makes technical and incidental changes to the Act.</Para></Block></Bill_Part><Bill_Part Part_Type="MainText" CountLines="Yes" RunningHead_E="Mennonite Church Canada"><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="MainText_DocNo">2503</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes"><Para Style="Session_Reign">2nd Session, 36th Parliament,</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes"><Para Style="Session_Reign">48-49 Elizabeth II, 1999-2000</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes"><Para Style="MainBillOrigin">senate of canada</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes"><Para Bold="Yes" Style="MAIN@BillNo_Title">BILL S-28</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes"><Para Style="MAIN@ti;04">An Act to amend the Act of incorporation of the Conference of Mennonites in Canada</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Preamble<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">WHEREAS the Conference of Mennonites in Canada (hereinafter referred to as “the Corporation”) was incorporated by an Act of the Parliament of Canada, being chapter 91 of the Statutes of Canada, 1947;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">AND WHEREAS the Corporation has by its petition prayed that its Act of incorporation be amended as hereinafter provided, and it is expedient to grant the prayer of the petition;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">NOW, THEREFORE, Her Majesty, by and with the advice and consent of the Senate and the House of Commons of Canada, enacts as follows:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Change of corporate name<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>1.</B> (1) The name of the Corporation incorporated by chapter 91 of the Statutes of Canada, 1947 is changed to “Mennonite Church Canada”.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Existing rights preserved<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes">(2) The change of name of the Corporation does not in any way impair, alter or affect the rights or liabilities of the Corporation, or any suit, proceeding or judgment, either by, in favour of or against the Corporation, which may be prosecuted, continued, completed or enforced as if this Act had not been enacted.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>2.</B> Section 3 of the Act is replaced by the following:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Head office<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><change><B>3.</B> (1) The head office of the Corporation shall be at Winnipeg, in the province of Manitoba, or at such other place in Canada as may be decided by the Corporation.</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Notice of change<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><change>(2) Notice in writing shall be given to the Minister of Industry by the Corporation concerning any change of the head office and a copy of such notice shall be published in the <I>Canada Gazette</I>.</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>3.</B> The Act is amended by adding the following after section 3:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Legal capacity<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><change><B>3.1</B> (1) Subject to this Act, the Corporation has all the powers, rights and privileges of a natural person.</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Capacity in Canada<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><change>(2) The Corporation may carry on business throughout Canada.</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Extraterritorial capacity<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><change>(3) The Corporation has the capacity to carry on its business, conduct its affairs and exercise its powers in any jurisdiction outside Canada, to the extent that the laws of such jurisdiction permit.</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Objects<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><change>(4) The objects of the Corporation are to</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0"><change>(<I>a</I>) promote the spiritual welfare and the unity of spirit of the members of the Corporation and, by mutual assistance, to foster, diffuse, encourage, advance and strengthen the work of the kingdom of God;</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0"><change>(<I>b</I>) build Christian communities in the Mennonite tradition;</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0"><change>(<I>c</I>) nurture the well-being of members of the Corporation, promote a spirit of unity and foster cooperation among them; and</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0"><change>(<I>d</I>) associate and work with selected organizations having one or more objects identical or similar to those of the Corporation.</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>4.</B> (1) The portion of section 4 of the Act before paragraph (<I>a</I>) and paragraph (<I>a</I>) are replaced by the following:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Powers<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><change><B>4.</B> The Corporation has, in carrying out its objects, all the powers necessary to</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0"><change>(<I>a</I>) admit, as a corporate member of the Corporation, any congregation of Mennonites, conference of Mennonites, or other entity that complies with, and qualifies under, the by-laws of the Corporation;</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes">(2) Paragraph 4(<I>d</I>) of the Act is repealed.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes">(3) Paragraph 4(<I>e</I>) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0"><change>(<I>e</I>) organize, maintain, carry on and assist, for or on behalf of any corporate member of the Corporation, churches, missions, schools, colleges, hospitals, orphanages, homes for the elderly, and any other institutions for religious, educational or congregational purposes;</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes">(4) Paragraph 4(<I>g</I>) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0"><change>(<I>g</I>) administer the property, business and other temporal affairs of the Corporation;</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0"><change>(<I>h</I>) receive and accept for its own use monies or other personal property subject to, and in consideration of, payment of interest thereon or of an annuity in respect thereof; and</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0"><change>(<I>i</I>) generally, to do all such things as are likely to promote the objects of the Corporation.</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>5.</B> Section 5 of the Act is replaced by the following:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Management<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><change><B>5.</B> The affairs of the Corporation shall be managed by a board of directors consisting of not less than three directors and not more than twenty directors, who shall be assisted by such other officers and agents as the Corporation may appoint.</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>6.</B> Paragraph 6(<I>a</I>) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0"><change>(<I>a</I>) the prerequisites of admission and the qualifications respecting any congregation of Mennonites, conference of Mennonites, or other entity, desiring to become a corporate member of the Corporation, and the release or expulsion of any corporate member from the Corporation;</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>7.</B> Section 9 of the Act is repealed. </Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>8.</B> Section 12 of the Act is replaced by the following:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Execution of documents<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><change><B>12.</B> Any deed or instrument relating to real property, or any interest therein, shall be deemed to be executed if there is affixed thereto the seal of the Corporation and the signature of any officer of the Corporation duly authorized for such purpose.</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>9.</B> Section 13 of the Act is replaced by the following:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Disposition of property by gift or loan<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><change><B>13.</B> The Corporation may make a gift of or lend any of its property, whether real or personal, for or to assist in the purchase, erection, leasing or maintenance of any building or buildings considered necessary for any church, college, school, hospital, orphanage or home for the elderly, or for any other religious, charitable, educational or congregational purpose, upon such terms and conditions as it considers expedient.</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>10.</B> Section 15 of the Act is replaced by the following:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Investment of funds<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><change><B>15.</B> The Corporation may invest its funds, or any portion thereof, either directly in the name of the Corporation or indirectly in the name of trustees, in the purchase of securities as it considers advisable and may also lend its funds or any portion thereof on any such securities.</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>11.</B> Section 16 of the Act is replaced by the following:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Meetings<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><change><B>16.</B> (1) The Corporation shall meet at such times and places as the board of directors considers necessary, but it shall meet at least once every two years, and such meetings may be held in Canada or abroad.</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Meetings in Canada<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><change>(2) Notwithstanding subsection (1), at least three out of every four meetings held by the Corporation shall be held in Canada.</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Application of <I>Canada Corporations Act</I><br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><change>(3) For greater certainty and notwithstanding section 158 of the <I>Canada Corporations Act</I>, section 102 of that Act does not apply to the Corporation.</change></Para></Block><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="BPT_ImprintE"><br/><br/>Published under authority of the Senate of Canada</Para></Block><Block Align="Yes" LineCnt="N"><Para NoLineBreak="Yes" NoHtml="Yes" Leading="0" Size="0" TopMargin="0" BottomMargin="0"></Para></Block></Bill_Part></Bill>
