﻿<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><Bill RHead_reign="62-63 Eliz. II" RHead_ParlYear="2013-2014" DocumentTitle="BILL C-14" Bill_No="C-14" Document_No="90680" xml:lang="EN" Bill_Type="Non-amending" Stage_Name="Assented-to" Reprint="No" xml:space="preserve" ChapterNo_E="C. 6" ChapterNo_F="ch. 6" Bill-Origin="commons"><Bill_Part Part_Type="Cover" CountLines="No"><Block><Para TopMargin="24" Size="9" Leading="10" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0" TextAlign="Center">Second Session, Forty-first Parliament,</Para></Block><Block><Para Size="9" Leading="10" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0" TextAlign="Center">62-63 Elizabeth II, 2013-2014</Para></Block><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="COV@StatutesTitle">STATUTES OF CANADA 2014<br />CHAPTER 6</Para></Block><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="CovLongTitle">An Act to amend the Criminal Code and the National Defence Act (mental disorder)</Para></Block><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="COV_StageLine"></Para></Block><Block><Para BottomMargin="14" Size="11" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0" Bold="Yes" TextAlign="Center">ASSENTED TO</Para></Block><Block><Para Size="8" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0" TextAlign="Center">11th APRIL, 2014</Para></Block><Block><Para TopMargin="4" Size="8" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0" TextAlign="Center">BILL C-14</Para></Block><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="COV_StageLine"></Para></Block></Bill_Part><Bill_Part CountLines="No" Part_Type="InsideCover"><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="BPT_InsideCoverE">Available on the Parliament of Canada Web Site at the following address:<br /><B>http://www.parl.gc.ca</B></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><Para TopMargin="108" BottomMargin="4" Size="10" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">SUMMARY</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" Size="8" Leading="9" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">This enactment amends the mental disorder regime in the <I>Criminal Code</I> and the <I>National Defence Act</I> to specify that the paramount consideration in the decision-making process is the safety of the public and to create a scheme for finding that certain persons who have been found not criminally responsible on account of mental disorder are high-risk accused. It also enhances the involvement of victims in the regime and makes procedural and technical amendments.</Para></Block></Bill_Part><Bill_Part Part_Type="MainText" CountLines="No" RunningHead_E="Criminal Code and National Defence (mental disorder)"><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="MAIN@RoyalAssentTitle">62-63 ELIZABETH II</Para></Block><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="MAIN@RoyalAssentTitle">——————</Para></Block><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="MAIN@RoyalAssentTitle">CHAPTER 6</Para></Block><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="LongTitleAssent">An Act to amend the Criminal Code and the National Defence Act (mental disorder)</Para></Block><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="MAIN@RoyalAssentDate">[<I>Assented to 11th April, 2014</I>]</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">Her Majesty, by and with the advice and consent of the Senate and House of Commons of Canada, enacts as follows:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:SHORT TITLE--><Para TopMargin="10" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">SHORT TITLE</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Short title<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>1.</B> This Act may be cited as the <I>Not Criminally Responsible Reform Act</I>.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:CRIMINAL CODE--><MarginalNote>R.S., c. C-46<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="10" Bold="Yes" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">CRIMINAL CODE</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>1991, c. 43, s. 4<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>2.</B> (1) The definition “disposition” in subsection 672.1(1) of the <I>Criminal Code</I> is replaced by the following:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>“disposition”<br />« <I>décision</I> »<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0">“disposition” means an order made by a court or Review Board under section 672.54, an order made by a court under section 672.58 or a finding made by a court under subsection 672.64(1);</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes">(2) Subsection 672.1(1) of the Act is amended by adding the following in alphabetical order:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>“high-risk accused”<br />« <I>accusé à haut risque</I> »<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0">“high-risk accused” means an accused who is found to be a high-risk accused by a court under subsection 672.64(1);</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>3.</B> Section 672.11 of the Act is amended by striking out “or” at the end of paragraph (<I>d</I>) and by adding the following after paragraph (<I>d</I>):</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>d.1</I>) whether a finding that the accused is a high-risk accused should be revoked under subsection 672.84(3); or</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>4.</B> Section 672.121 of the Act is amended by striking out “or” at the end of paragraph (<I>a</I>), by adding “or” at the end of paragraph (<I>b</I>) and by adding the following after paragraph (<I>b</I>):</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>c</I>) determine whether to refer to the court for review under subsection 672.84(1) a finding that an accused is a high-risk accused.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>5.</B> Subsection 672.21(3) of the Act is amended by adding the following after paragraph (<I>b</I>):</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>c</I>) determining, under section 672.84, whether to refer to the court for review a finding that an accused is a high-risk accused or whether to revoke such a finding;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>1991, c. 43, s. 4; 2005, c. 22, par. 42(<I>e</I>)(F)<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>6.</B> (1) Subsection 672.47(2) of the French version of the Act is replaced by the following:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Prolongation<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><AltLang xml:lang="fr">(2) Le tribunal, s’il est convaincu qu’il existe des circonstances exceptionnelles le justifiant, peut prolonger le délai préalable à la tenue d’une audience visée au paragraphe (1) jusqu’à un maximum de quatre-vingt-dix jours après le prononcé du verdict.</AltLang></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes">(2) Section 672.47 of the Act is amended by adding the following after subsection (3):</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Exception — high-risk accused<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(4) Despite subsections (1) to (3), if the court makes a disposition under subsection 672.64(3), the Review Board shall, not later than 45 days after the day on which the disposition is made, hold a hearing and make a disposition under paragraph 672.54(<I>c</I>), subject to the restrictions set out in that subsection.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Extension of time for hearing<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(5) If the court is satisfied that there are exceptional circumstances that warrant it, the court may extend the time for holding a hearing under subsection (4) to a maximum of 90 days after the day on which the disposition is made.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>1991, c. 43, s. 4; 2005, c. 22, par. 42(<I>g</I>)(F)<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>7.</B> (1) Subsection 672.5(1) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Procedure at disposition hearing<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>672.5</B> (1) A hearing held by a court or Review Board to make or review a disposition in respect of an accused, including a hearing referred to in subsection 672.84(1) or (3), shall be held in accordance with this section.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes">(2) Section 672.5 of the Act is amended by adding the following after subsection (5.1):</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Notice of discharge and intended place of residence<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(5.2) If the accused is discharged absolutely under paragraph 672.54(<I>a</I>) or conditionally under paragraph 672.54(<I>b</I>), a notice of the discharge and accused's intended place of residence shall, at the victim's request, be given to the victim within the time and in the manner fixed by the rules of the court or Review Board.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes">(3) Section 672.5 of the Act is amended by adding the following after subsection (13.2):</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Notice to victims — referral of finding to court<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(13.3) If the Review Board refers to the court for review under subsection 672.84(1) a finding that an accused is a high-risk accused, it shall notify every victim of the offence that they are entitled to file a statement with the court in accordance with subsection (14).</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>1999, c. 25, s. 11<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes">(4) Subsection 672.5(14) of the French version of the Act is replaced by the following:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Déclaration de la victime<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><AltLang xml:lang="fr">(14) La victime peut rédiger et déposer auprès du tribunal ou de la commission d’examen une déclaration écrite qui décrit les dommages — corporels ou autres — ou les pertes qui lui ont été causés par la perpétration de l’infraction.</AltLang></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>2005, c. 22, s. 16(3)<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes">(5) Subsections 672.5(15.2) to (16) of the Act are replaced by the following:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Inquiry by court or Review Board<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(15.2) The court or Review Board shall, as soon as practicable after a verdict of not criminally responsible on account of mental disorder is rendered in respect of an offence and before making a disposition under section 672.45, 672.47 or 672.64, inquire of the prosecutor or a victim of the offence, or any person representing a victim of the offence, whether the victim has been advised of the opportunity to prepare a statement referred to in subsection (14).</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Adjournment<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(15.3) On application of the prosecutor or a victim or of its own motion, the court or Review Board may adjourn the hearing held under section 672.45, 672.47 or 672.64 to permit the victim to prepare a statement referred to in subsection (14) if the court or Review Board is satisfied that the adjournment would not interfere with the proper administration of justice.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Definition of “victim”<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(16) In subsections (5.1), (5.2), (13.2), (13.3), (14) and (15.1) to (15.3), “victim” has the same meaning as in subsection 722(4).</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>1991, c. 43, s. 4<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>8.</B> Subsection 672.51(1) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Definition of “disposition information”<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>672.51</B> (1) In this section, “disposition information” means all or part of an assessment report submitted to the court or Review Board and any other written information before the court or Review Board about the accused that is relevant to making or reviewing a disposition.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>2005, c. 22, s. 20<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>9.</B> The portion of section 672.54 of the Act before paragraph (<I>a</I>) is replaced by the following:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Dispositions that may be made<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>672.54</B> When a court or Review Board makes a disposition under subsection 672.45(2), section 672.47, subsection 672.64(3) or section 672.83 or 672.84, it shall, taking into account the safety of the public, which is the paramount consideration, the mental condition of the accused, the reintegration of the accused into society and the other needs of the accused, make one of the following dispositions that is necessary and appropriate in the circumstances:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>2005, c. 22, s. 21<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>10.</B> Section 672.541 of the Act is replaced by the following:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Significant threat to safety of public<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>672.5401</B> For the purposes of section 672.54, a significant threat to the safety of the public means a risk of serious physical or psychological harm to members of the public — including any victim of or witness to the offence, or any person under the age of 18 years — resulting from conduct that is criminal in nature but not necessarily violent.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Victim impact statement<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>672.541</B> If a verdict of not criminally responsible on account of mental disorder has been rendered in respect of an accused, the court or Review Board shall</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>a</I>) at a hearing held under section 672.45, 672.47, 672.64, 672.81 or 672.82 or subsection 672.84(5), take into consideration any statement filed by a victim in accordance with subsection 672.5(14) in determining the appropriate disposition or conditions under section 672.54, to the extent that the statement is relevant to its consideration of the criteria set out in section 672.54;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>b</I>) at a hearing held under section 672.64 or subsection 672.84(3), take into consideration any statement filed by a victim in accordance with subsection 672.5(14), to the extent that the statement is relevant to its consideration of the criteria set out in subsection 672.64(1) or 672.84(3), as the case may be, in deciding whether to find that the accused is a high-risk accused, or to revoke such a finding; and</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>c</I>) at a hearing held under section 672.81 or 672.82 in respect of a high-risk accused, take into consideration any statement filed by a victim in accordance with subsection 672.5(14) in determining whether to refer to the court for review the finding that the accused is a high-risk accused, to the extent that the statement is relevant to its consideration of the criteria set out in subsection 672.84(1).</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Additional conditions — safety and security<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>672.542</B> When a court or Review Board holds a hearing referred to in section 672.5, the court or Review Board shall consider whether it is desirable, in the interests of the safety and security of any person, particularly a victim of or witness to the offence or a justice system participant, to include as a condition of the disposition that the accused</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>a</I>) abstain from communicating, directly or indirectly, with any victim, witness or other person identified in the disposition, or refrain from going to any place specified in the disposition; or</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>b</I>) comply with any other condition specified in the disposition that the court or Review Board considers necessary to ensure the safety and security of those persons.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>1991, c. 43, s. 4<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>11.</B> (1) Subsection 672.56(1) of the French version of the Act is replaced by the following:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Délégation<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><AltLang xml:lang="fr"><B>672.56</B> (1) La commission d’examen qui rend une décision à l’égard d’un accusé en vertu des alinéas 672.54<I>b</I>) ou <I>c</I>) peut déléguer au responsable de l’hôpital le pouvoir d’assouplir ou de resserrer les privations de liberté de l’accusé à l’intérieur des limites prévues par la décision et sous réserve des modalités de celle-ci; toute modification qu’ordonne ainsi cette personne est, pour l’application de la présente loi, réputée être une décision de la commission d’examen.</AltLang></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes">(2) Section 672.56 of the Act is amended by adding the following after subsection (1):</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Exception — high-risk accused<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(1.1) If the accused is a high-risk accused, any direction is subject to the restrictions set out in subsection 672.64(3).</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>12.</B> The Act is amended by adding the following after section 672.63:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:High-Risk Accused--><Para TopMargin="10" Italic="Yes" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">High-Risk Accused</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Finding<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>672.64</B> (1) On application made by the prosecutor before any disposition to discharge an accused absolutely, the court may, at the conclusion of a hearing, find the accused to be a high-risk accused if the accused has been found not criminally responsible on account of mental disorder for a serious personal injury offence, as defined in subsection 672.81(1.3), the accused was 18 years of age or more at the time of the commission of the offence and</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>a</I>) the court is satisfied that there is a substantial likelihood that the accused will use violence that could endanger the life or safety of another person; or</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>b</I>) the court is of the opinion that the acts that constitute the offence were of such a brutal nature as to indicate a risk of grave physical or psychological harm to another person.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Factors to consider<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(2) In deciding whether to find that the accused is a high-risk accused, the court shall consider all relevant evidence, including</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>a</I>) the nature and circumstances of the offence;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>b</I>) any pattern of repetitive behaviour of which the offence forms a part;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>c</I>) the accused’s current mental condition;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>d</I>) the past and expected course of the accused’s treatment, including the accused’s willingness to follow treatment; and</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>e</I>) the opinions of experts who have examined the accused.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Detention of high-risk accused<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(3) If the court finds the accused to be a high-risk accused, the court shall make a disposition under paragraph 672.54(<I>c</I>), but the accused’s detention must not be subject to any condition that would permit the accused to be absent from the hospital unless</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>a</I>) it is appropriate, in the opinion of the person in charge of the hospital, for the accused to be absent from the hospital for medical reasons or for any purpose that is necessary for the accused’s treatment, if the accused is escorted by a person who is authorized by the person in charge of the hospital; and</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>b</I>) a structured plan has been prepared to address any risk related to the accused’s absence and, as a result, that absence will not present an undue risk to the public.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Appeal<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(4) A decision not to find an accused to be a high-risk accused is deemed to be a disposition for the purpose of sections 672.72 to 672.78.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>For greater certainty<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(5) For greater certainty, a finding that an accused is a high-risk accused is a disposition and sections 672.72 to 672.78 apply to it.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>1991, c. 43, s. 4<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>13.</B> Section 672.75 of the Act is replaced by the following:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Automatic suspension of certain dispositions<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>672.75</B> The filing of a notice of appeal against a disposition made under section 672.58 suspends the application of the disposition pending the determination of the appeal.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>1991, c. 43, s. 4<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>14.</B> Paragraph 672.76(2)(<I>a</I>) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>a</I>) by order, direct that a disposition made under section 672.58 be carried out pending the determination of the appeal, despite section 672.75;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>a.1</I>) by order, direct that a disposition made under paragraph 672.54(<I>a</I>) be suspended pending the determination of the appeal;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>2005, c. 22, s. 27(2)<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>15.</B> Subsections 672.81(1.4) and (1.5) of the Act are replaced by the following:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Extension on consent — high-risk accused<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(1.31) Despite subsections (1) to (1.2), the Review Board may extend the time for holding a hearing in respect of a high-risk accused to a maximum of 36 months after making or reviewing a disposition if the accused is represented by counsel and the accused and the Attorney General consent to the extension.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Extension — no likely improvement<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(1.32) Despite subsections (1) to (1.2), at the conclusion of a hearing under subsection 672.47(4) or this section in respect of a high-risk accused, the Review Board may, after making a disposition, extend the time for holding a subsequent hearing under this section to a maximum of 36 months if the Review Board is satisfied on the basis of any relevant information, including disposition information as defined in subsection 672.51(1) and an assessment report made under an assessment ordered under paragraph 672.121(<I>c</I>), that the accused’s condition is not likely to improve and that detention remains necessary for the period of the extension.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Notice<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(1.4) If the Review Board extends the time for holding a hearing under subsection (1.2) or (1.32), it shall provide notice of the extension to the accused, the prosecutor and the person in charge of the hospital where the accused is detained.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Appeal<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(1.5) A decision by the Review Board to extend the time for holding a hearing under subsection (1.2) or (1.32) is deemed to be a disposition for the purpose of sections 672.72 to 672.78.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>16.</B> The Act is amended by adding the following after section 672.83:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Review of finding — high-risk accused<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>672.84</B> (1) If a Review Board holds a hearing under section 672.81 or 672.82 in respect of a high-risk accused, it shall, on the basis of any relevant information, including disposition information as defined in subsection 672.51(1) and an assessment report made under an assessment ordered under paragraph <keep>672.121(<I>c</I>),</keep> if it is satisfied that there is not a substantial likelihood that the accused — whether found to be a high-risk accused under paragraph 672.64(1)(<I>a</I>) or (<I>b</I>) — will use violence that could endanger the life or safety of another person, refer the finding for review to the superior court of criminal jurisdiction.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Review of conditions<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(2) If the Review Board is not so satisfied, it shall review the conditions of detention imposed under paragraph 672.54(<I>c</I>), subject to the restrictions set out in subsection 672.64(3).</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Review of finding by court<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(3) If the Review Board refers the finding to the superior court of criminal jurisdiction for review, the court shall, at the conclusion of a hearing, revoke the finding if the court is satisfied that there is not a substantial likelihood that the accused will use violence that could endanger the life or safety of another person, in which case the court or the Review Board shall make a disposition under any of paragraphs 672.54(<I>a</I>) to (<I>c</I>).</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Hearing and disposition<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(4) Any disposition referred to in subsection (3) is subject to sections 672.45 to 672.47 as if the revocation is a verdict.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Review of conditions<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(5) If the court does not revoke the finding, it shall immediately send to the Review Board, in original or copied form, a transcript of the hearing, any other document or information related to the hearing, and all exhibits filed with it, if the transcript, document, information or exhibits are in its possession. The Review Board shall, as soon as practicable but not later than 45 days after the day on which the court decides not to revoke the finding, hold a hearing and review the conditions of detention imposed under paragraph 672.54(<I>c</I>), subject to the restrictions set out in subsection 672.64(3).</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Appeal<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(6) A decision under subsection (1) about referring the finding to the court for review and a decision under subsection (3) about revoking the finding are deemed to be dispositions for the purpose of sections 672.72 to 672.78.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>1991, c. 43, s. 4<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>17.</B> Subsection 672.88(1) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Review Board of receiving province<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>672.88</B> (1) The Review Board of the prov-ince to which an accused is transferred under section 672.86 has exclusive jurisdiction over the accused, and may exercise the powers and shall perform the duties mentioned in sections 672.5 and 672.81 to 672.84 as if that Review Board had made the disposition in respect of the accused.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>1991, c. 43, s. 4<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>18.</B> Subsection 672.89(1) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Other interprovincial transfers<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>672.89</B> (1) If an accused who is detained in custody under a disposition made by a Review Board is transferred to another province otherwise than under section 672.86, the Review Board of the province from which the accused is transferred has exclusive jurisdiction over the accused and may continue to exercise the powers and shall continue to perform the duties mentioned in sections 672.5 and 672.81 to 672.84.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>2005, c. 22, s. 40<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>19.</B> Form 48 in Part XXVIII of the Act is amended by replacing “pursuant to section 672.54 or 672.58 of the <I>Criminal Code</I>” with “under section 672.54, 672.58 or 672.64 of the <I>Criminal Code</I> or whether the court should, under subsection 672.84(3) of that Act, revoke a finding that the accused is a high-risk accused”.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>2005, c. 22, s. 40<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>20.</B> Form 48.1 in Part XXVIII of the Act is amended by replacing “section 672.54 of the <I>Criminal Code</I>” with “section 672.54 of the <I>Criminal Code</I> or determine whether the Review Board should, under subsection 672.84(1) of that Act, refer to the superior court of criminal jurisdiction for review a finding that the accused is a high-risk accused”.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:REVIEW--><Para TopMargin="10" Bold="Yes" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">REVIEW</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Review<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>20.1</B> (1) Within five years after sections 2 to 20 come into force, a comprehensive review of the operation of sections 672.1 to 672.89 of the <I>Criminal Code</I> is to be undertaken by a committee of the Senate, of the House of Commons or of both Houses of Parliament that may be designated or established by the Senate, the House of Commons or both Houses of Parliament, as the case may be, for that purpose.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Report<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes">(2) Within a year, or such further time as authorized by the Senate, the House of Commons or both Houses of Parliament, as the case may be, after the review is undertaken, the Committee referred to in subsection (1) must submit a report on that review to the Senate, the House of Commons or both Houses of Parliament, as the case may be, including a statement of any changes recommended by the Committee.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:NATIONAL DEFENCE ACT--><MarginalNote>R.S., c. N-5<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="10" Bold="Yes" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">NATIONAL DEFENCE ACT</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>21.</B> Section 197 of the <I>National Defence Act</I> is amended by adding the following in alphabetical order:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>“disposition”<br />« <I>décision</I> »<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0">“disposition” means an order made by a court martial under section 201, 202 or 202.16 or a finding made by a court martial under subsection 202.161(4);</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><MarginalNote>“significant threat to the safety of the public”<br />« <I>risque important pour la sécurité du public</I> »<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0">“significant threat to the safety of the public” means a risk of serious physical or psychological harm to members of the public — including any victim of or witness to the offence, or any person under the age of 18 years — resulting from conduct that is criminal in nature but not necessarily violent.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>1991, c. 43, s. 18<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>22.</B> The portion of subsection 201(1) of the Act before paragraph (<I>a</I>) is replaced by the following:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Disposition<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>201.</B> (1) When a court martial makes a disposition by virtue of subsection 200(2), it shall, taking into account the safety of the public, which is the paramount consideration, the mental condition of the accused person, the reintegration of the accused person into society and the other needs of the accused person, make one of the following dispositions that is necessary and appropriate in the circumstances:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>2005, c. 22, s. 49<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>23.</B> (1) Subparagraph 202.121(1)(<I>b</I>)(ii) of the French version of the Act is replaced by the following:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="4" FirstLineIndent="0"><AltLang xml:lang="fr">(ii) d’autre part, il ne présente aucun risque important pour la sécurité du public.</AltLang></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>2005, c. 22, s. 49<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes">(2) Paragraph 202.121(4)(<I>b</I>) of the French version of the Act is replaced by the following:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0"><AltLang xml:lang="fr"><I>b</I>) d’autre part, il ne présente aucun risque important pour la sécurité du public.</AltLang></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>2005, c. 22, s. 49<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes">(3) Paragraph 202.121(7)(<I>b</I>) of the French version of the Act is replaced by the following:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0"><AltLang xml:lang="fr"><I>b</I>) qu’il ne présente aucun risque important pour la sécurité du public;</AltLang></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>1991, c. 43, s. 18<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>24.</B> (1) The portion of subsection 202.16(1) of the Act before paragraph (<I>b</I>) is replaced by the following:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Disposition<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>202.16</B> (1) When a court martial makes a disposition by virtue of subsection 202.15(1), it shall, taking into account the safety of the public, which is the paramount consideration, the mental condition of the accused person, the reintegration of the accused person into society and the other needs of the accused person, make one of the following dispositions that is necessary and appropriate in the circumstances:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>a</I>) by order, direct that the accused person be released from custody without conditions if, in the opinion of the court martial, the accused person is not a significant threat to the safety of the public;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>1991, c. 43, s. 18<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes">(2) Paragraph 202.16(1)(<I>c</I>) of the French version of the Act is replaced by the following:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0"><AltLang xml:lang="fr"><I>c</I>) la détention de l’accusé dans un hôpital ou un autre lieu approprié choisi par elle, sous réserve des modalités qu’elle estime indiquées.</AltLang></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>25.</B> The Act is amended by adding the following after section 202.16:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:High-Risk Accused--><Para TopMargin="10" Italic="Yes" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">High-Risk Accused</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Application to court martial<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>202.161</B> (1) If a court martial makes a finding under subsection 202.14(1) that an accused person is not responsible on account of mental disorder and it has not terminated its proceedings in respect of the accused person, the Director of Military Prosecutions may make an application to the court martial for a finding that the accused person is a high-risk accused.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Application to Chief Military Judge<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(2) If the court martial has terminated its proceedings in respect of the accused person, the Director of Military Prosecutions may make the application to the Chief Military Judge. On receipt of the application, the Chief Military Judge shall cause the Court Martial Administrator to convene a Standing Court Martial.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Restriction<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(3) No application shall be made under subsection (1) or (2) if a disposition has been made to release the accused person from custody without conditions or to discharge the accused person absolutely.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Finding<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(4) The court martial referred to in subsection (1) or (2) may, at the conclusion of a hearing, find the accused person to be a high-risk accused if the accused person has been found not responsible on account of mental disorder for a serious personal injury offence, the accused person was 18 years of age or more at the time of the commission of the offence and</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>a</I>) the court martial is satisfied that there is a substantial likelihood that the accused person will use violence that could endanger the life or safety of another person; or</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>b</I>) the court martial is of the opinion that the acts that constitute the offence were of such a brutal nature as to indicate a risk of grave physical or psychological harm to another person.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Definition of “serious personal injury offence”<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(5) For the purposes of subsection (4), “serious personal injury offence” means</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>a</I>) a serious offence, or an offence referred to in section 77, 86, 87, 92, 95, 113, 120, 124 or 127, involving</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="4" FirstLineIndent="0">(i) the use or attempted use of violence against another person, or</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="4" FirstLineIndent="0">(ii) conduct endangering or likely to endanger the life or safety of another person or inflicting or likely to inflict severe psychological damage upon another person; or</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>b</I>) an offence referred to in section 151, 152, 153, 153.1, 155, 160, 170, 171, 172, 271, 272 or 273 of the <I>Criminal Code</I> that is punishable under section 130 or an attempt to commit such an offence.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Factors to consider<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(6) In deciding whether to find that the accused person is a high-risk accused, the court martial shall consider all relevant evidence, including</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>a</I>) the nature and circumstances of the offence;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>b</I>) any pattern of repetitive behaviour of which the offence forms a part;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>c</I>) the accused person’s current mental condition;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>d</I>) the past and expected course of the accused person’s treatment, including the accused person’s willingness to follow treatment; and</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>e</I>) the opinions of experts who have examined the accused person.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Detention of high-risk accused person<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(7) If the court martial finds the accused person to be a high-risk accused, the court martial shall make a disposition under paragraph 202.16(1)(<I>c</I>), but the accused person’s detention must not be subject to any condition that would permit the accused person to be absent from the hospital or other appropriate place unless</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>a</I>) it is appropriate, in the opinion of the person in charge of the hospital or other appropriate place, for the accused person to be absent from the hospital or place for medical reasons or for any purpose that is necessary for the accused person’s treatment, if the accused person is escorted by a person who is authorized by the person in charge of the hospital or place; and</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>b</I>) a structured plan has been prepared to address any risk related to the accused person’s absence and, as a result, that absence will not present an undue risk to the public.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Assessment order<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(8) Subject to regulations, if the court martial has reasonable grounds to believe that evidence of the mental condition of an accused person is necessary for the purpose of determining the appropriate disposition to be made under this section, the court martial may make an order for an assessment of the accused person.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Referral to court martial for review<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>202.162</B> (1) If a Review Board, in exercising a power under section 202.25, decides to refer to a court martial for review under subsection 672.84(1) of the <I>Criminal Code</I> a finding that an accused person is a high-risk accused, the Review Board shall, immediately after making the decision, cause a copy of it to be sent to the Chief Military Judge.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Convening court martial<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(2) On receipt of a copy of the decision, the Chief Military Judge shall cause the Court Martial Administrator to convene a Standing Court Martial to review the finding.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Review of finding by court martial<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(3) The court martial shall, at the conclusion of a hearing, revoke the finding if the court martial is satisfied that there is not a substantial likelihood that the accused person will use violence that could endanger the life or safety of another person, in which case sections 202.15 and 202.21 apply as if the court martial has made a finding of not responsible on account of mental disorder.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Finding not revoked<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(4) If the court martial does not revoke the finding, it shall immediately send to the Review Board, in original or copied form, a transcript of the hearing, any other document or information related to the hearing, and all exhibits filed with it, if the transcript, document, information or exhibits are in its possession.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Assessment order<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(5) Subject to regulations, if the court martial has reasonable grounds to believe that evidence of the mental condition of the accused person is necessary for the purpose of determining whether to revoke the finding, the court martial may make an order for an assessment of the accused person.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>26.</B> The Act is amended by adding the following after section 202.2:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Procedure at disposition hearing<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>202.201</B> (1) A hearing by a court martial to make or review a disposition in respect of an accused person shall be held in accordance with this section and the regulations.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Hearing to be informal<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(2) The hearing may be conducted in as informal a manner as is appropriate in the circumstances.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Interested person may be party<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(3) The court martial may designate as a party any person who has a substantial interest in protecting the accused person’s interests, if the court martial is of the opinion that it is just to do so.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Notice of hearing — parties<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(4) The court martial shall give notice of the hearing to the parties.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Notice of hearing — victim<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(5) The court martial shall, at the request of a victim of the offence, give the victim notice of the hearing and of the relevant provisions of this Act.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Notice of release from custody and intended place of residence<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(6) If the accused person is released from custody without conditions under paragraph 202.16(1)(<I>a</I>) or with conditions under paragraph 201(1)(<I>a</I>) or 202.16(1)(<I>b</I>), a notice of the release and the accused person's intended place of residence shall, at the victim's request, be given to the victim within the time and in the manner fixed by regulations.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Order excluding public<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(7) If the court martial considers it to be in the accused person’s best interests and not contrary to the public interest, it may order the public or any members of the public to be excluded from the hearing or any part of it.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Right to counsel<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(8) The accused person or any other party has the right to be represented by counsel.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Assigning counsel<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(9) A court martial shall, either before or at the time of the hearing of an accused person who is not represented by counsel, direct that counsel be provided by the Director of Defence Counsel Services if the accused person has been found unfit to stand trial or the interests of military justice require that counsel be provided.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Right of accused person to be present<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(10) Subject to subsection (11), the accused person has the right to be present during the entire hearing.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Removal or absence of accused person<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(11) The court martial may permit the accused person to be absent during the entire hearing or any part of it on any conditions that the court martial considers appropriate. The court martial may also cause the accused person to be removed and barred from re-entry for the entire hearing or any part of it for any of the following reasons:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>a</I>) the accused person is interrupting the hearing and it is not feasible to continue it in the accused person’s presence;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>b</I>) the court martial is satisfied that the accused person’s presence would likely endanger the life or safety of another person or would seriously impair the treatment or recovery of the accused person; or</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>c</I>) the court martial is satisfied that the accused person should not be present for the hearing of evidence, oral or written submissions, or the cross-examination of any witness respecting the existence of grounds for removing the accused person under paragraph (<I>b</I>).</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Rights of parties at hearing<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(12) Any party may adduce evidence, make oral or written submissions, call witnesses and cross-examine any witness called by any other party and, on application, cross-examine any person who made an assessment report that was submitted in writing to the court martial.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Witnesses<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(13) A party may not compel the attendance of witnesses, but may request the court martial to do so.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Video links<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(14) If the accused person agrees, the court martial may permit them to appear by closed-circuit television or any other means that allows the court martial and the accused person to engage in simultaneous visual and oral communication, for any part of the hearing, so long as the accused person is given the opportunity to communicate privately with counsel if they are represented by counsel.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Determination of mental condition of accused person<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(15) A court martial that reviews a disposition shall, on receipt of an assessment report, determine if there has been any change in the accused person’s mental condition since the disposition was made or last reviewed that may provide grounds for the accused person’s release from custody under section 202.16. If the court martial determines that there has been such a change, it shall notify every victim of the offence that they may prepare a statement.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Victim impact statement<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(16) For the purpose of making or reviewing a disposition in respect of an accused person, a court martial shall consider the statement of any victim of the offence describing the harm done to, or loss suffered by, the victim arising from the commission of the offence.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Procedure<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(17) A victim’s statement must be prepared in the form, and filed in accordance with the procedures, provided for by regulations made by the Governor in Council.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Presentation of victim statement<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(18) Unless the court martial considers that it would not be in the best interests of the administration of military justice, the court martial shall, at the victim’s request, permit the victim to read their statement or to present the statement in any other manner that the court martial considers appropriate.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Consideration by court martial<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(19) Whether or not a statement has been prepared and filed, the court martial may consider any other evidence concerning any victim of the offence for the purpose of making or reviewing the disposition.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Copy of statement<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(20) The Court Martial Administrator shall, as soon as feasible after receiving a victim’s statement, ensure that a copy is provided to the prosecutor and to the accused person or their counsel.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Inquiry by court martial<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(21) As soon as feasible after a finding of not responsible on account of mental disorder is made and before making a disposition, the court martial shall inquire of the prosecutor or a victim of the offence, or any person representing a victim of the offence, whether the victim has been advised that they may prepare a statement.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Adjournment<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(22) On application of the prosecutor or a victim or on its own motion, the court martial may adjourn the hearing to permit a victim to prepare a statement or to present evidence referred to in subsection (19) if it is satisfied that the adjournment would not interfere with the proper administration of military justice.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Definitions<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(23) The following definitions apply in this section.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><MarginalNote>“common-law partner”<br />« <I>conjoint de fait</I> »<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0">“common-law partner” means, in relation to an individual, a person who is cohabiting with the individual in a conjugal relationship, having so cohabited for a period of at least one year.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><MarginalNote>“victim”<br />« <I>victime</I> »<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0">“victim”, in relation to an offence, means</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>a</I>) a person to whom harm was done or who suffered loss as a direct result of the commission of the offence; and</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>b</I>) if the person described in paragraph (<I>a</I>) is dead, ill or otherwise incapable of making a statement describing the harm done to, or loss suffered by, the person arising from the commission of the offence, the spouse or common-law partner or any relative of that person, anyone who has in law or fact the custody of that person or is responsible for the care or support of that person or any of their dependants.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Additional conditions — safety and security<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>202.202</B> If a court martial holds a hearing referred to in section 202.201, the court martial shall consider whether it is desirable, in the interests of the safety and security of any person, particularly a victim of or witness to the offence or a justice system participant, to include as a condition of the disposition that the accused</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>a</I>) abstain from communicating, directly or indirectly, with any victim, witness or other person identified in the disposition, or refrain from going to any place specified in the disposition; or</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>b</I>) comply with any other condition specified in the disposition that the court martial considers necessary to ensure the safety and security of those persons.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>27.</B> Subsection 202.24(3) of the Act is amended by adding the following after paragraph (<I>b</I>):</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>c</I>) determining under subsection 202.162(3) whether to revoke a finding that an accused person is a high-risk accused;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>2005, c. 22, s. 58<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>28.</B> Subsection 202.25(1) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Powers of Review Board<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>202.25</B> (1) Review Boards and their chairpersons may exercise the powers and shall perform the duties assigned to them under the <I>Criminal Code</I>, with any modifications that the circumstances require and unless the context otherwise requires, in relation to findings made by courts martial of unfit to stand trial or not responsible on account of mental disorder, and in relation to dispositions made under section 201 or 202.16 or subsection 202.161(4), except for the powers and duties referred to in sections 672.851 and 672.86 to 672.89 of the <I>Criminal Code</I>.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>References to Attorney General<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(1.1) For the purpose of subsection (1), a reference to the Attorney General in subsections 672.81(1.1) and (1.31) of the <I>Criminal Code</I> shall be read as a reference to the Director of Military Prosecutions.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>29.</B> Section 230 of the Act is amended by adding the following after paragraph (<I>e</I>):</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>e.1</I>) the legality of a finding made under subsection 202.161(4) or a decision made under subsection 202.162(3) about revoking such a finding;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>30.</B> Section 230.1 of the Act is amended by adding the following after paragraph (<I>f</I>):</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>f.01</I>) the legality of a decision not to make a finding under subsection 202.161(4) or a decision made under subsection 202.162(3) about revoking such a finding;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>1991, c. 43, s. 22<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>31.</B> (1) Subsection 233(1) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Automatic suspension of certain dispositions<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>233.</B> (1) Subject to subsection (2), if the disposition appealed from is a disposition made under section 202, the filing of a Notice of Appeal in accordance with section 232 suspends the application of the disposition pending the determination of the appeal.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>1991, c. 43, s. 22<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes">(2) Paragraph 233(2)(<I>a</I>) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>a</I>) by order, direct that the application of a disposition made under section 202 not be suspended pending the determination of the appeal;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>a.1</I>) by order, direct that the application <keep>of a disposition</keep> made under paragraph 202.16(1)(<I>a</I>) be suspended pending the determination of the appeal;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:REVIEW--><Para TopMargin="10" Bold="Yes" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center"><B>REVIEW</B></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Review<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>31.1</B> (1) Within five years after sections 21 to 31 come into force, a comprehensive review of the operation of sections 197 to 233 of the <I>National Defence Act</I> is to be undertaken by a committee of the Senate, of the House of Commons or of both Houses of Parliament that may be designated or established by the Senate, the House of Commons or both Houses of Parliament, as the case may be, for that purpose.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Report<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes">(2) Within a year, or such further time as authorized by the Senate, the House of Commons or both Houses of Parliament, as the case may be, after the review is undertaken, the Committee referred to in subsection (1) must submit a report on that review to the Senate, the House of Commons or both Houses of Parliament, as the case may be, including a statement of any changes recommended by the Committee.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:COORDINATING AMENDMENTS--><Para TopMargin="10" Bold="Yes" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">COORDINATING AMENDMENTS</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Bill C-15<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>32.</B> (1) Subsections (2) to (5) apply if Bill C-15, introduced in the 1st session of the 41st Parliament and entitled the <I>Strengthening Military Justice in the Defence of Canada Act</I> (in this section referred to as the “other Act”), receives royal assent.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes">(2) If section 59 of the other Act comes into force before section 26 of this Act, then, on the day on which that section 59 comes into force, that section 26 is replaced by the following:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>26.</B> Section 202.201 of the Act is replaced by the following:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Procedure at disposition hearing<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>202.201</B> (1) A hearing by a court martial to make or review a disposition in respect of an accused person shall be held in accordance with this section and the regulations.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Hearing to be informal<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(2) The hearing may be conducted in as informal a manner as is appropriate in the circumstances.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Interested person may be party<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(3) The court martial may designate as a party any person who has a substantial interest in protecting the accused person’s interests, if the court martial is of the opinion that it is just to do so.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Notice of hearing — parties<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(4) The court martial shall give notice of the hearing to the parties.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Notice of hearing — victim<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(5) The court martial shall, at the request of a victim of the offence, give the victim notice of the hearing and of the relevant provisions of this Act.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Notice of release from custody and intended place of residence<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(6) If the accused person is released from custody without conditions under paragraph 202.16(1)(<I>a</I>) or with conditions under paragraph 201(1)(<I>a</I>) or 202.16(1)(<I>b</I>), a notice of the release and the accused person's intended place of residence shall, at the victim's request, be given to the victim within the time and in the manner fixed by regulations.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Order excluding public<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(7) If the court martial considers it to be in the accused person’s best interests and not contrary to the public interest, it may order the public or any members of the public to be excluded from the hearing or any part of it.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Right to counsel<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(8) The accused person or any other party has the right to be represented by counsel.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Assigning counsel<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(9) A court martial shall, either before or at the time of the hearing of an accused person who is not represented by counsel, direct that counsel be provided by the Director of Defence Counsel Services if the accused person has been found unfit to stand trial or the interests of military justice require that counsel be provided.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Right of accused person to be present<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(10) Subject to subsection (11), the accused person has the right to be present during the entire hearing.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Removal or absence of accused person<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(11) The court martial may permit the accused person to be absent during the entire hearing or any part of it on any conditions that the court martial considers appropriate. The court martial may also cause the accused person to be removed and barred from re-entry for the entire hearing or any part of it for any of the following reasons:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>a</I>) the accused person is interrupting the hearing and it is not feasible to continue it in the accused person’s presence;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>b</I>) the court martial is satisfied that the accused person’s presence would likely endanger the life or safety of another person or would seriously impair the treatment or recovery of the accused person; or</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>c</I>) the court martial is satisfied that the accused person should not be present for the hearing of evidence, oral or written submissions, or the cross-examination of any witness respecting the existence of grounds for removing the accused person under paragraph (<I>b</I>).</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Rights of parties at hearing<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(12) Any party may adduce evidence, make oral or written submissions, call witnesses and cross-examine any witness called by any other party and, on application, cross-examine any person who made an assessment report that was submitted in writing to the court martial.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Witnesses<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(13) A party may not compel the attendance of witnesses, but may request the court martial to do so.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Video links<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(14) If the accused person agrees, the court martial may permit them to appear by closed-circuit television or any other means that allows the court martial and the accused person to engage in simultaneous visual and oral communication, for any part of the hearing, so long as the accused person is given the opportunity to communicate privately with counsel if they are represented by counsel.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Determination of mental condition of accused person<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(15) A court martial that reviews a disposition shall, on receipt of an assessment report, determine if there has been any change in the accused person’s mental condition since the disposition was made or last reviewed that may provide grounds for the accused person’s release from custody under section 202.16. If the court martial determines that there has been such a change, it shall notify every victim of the offence that they may prepare a statement.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Victim impact statement<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(16) For the purpose of making or reviewing a disposition in respect of an accused person, a court martial shall consider the statement of any victim of the offence describing the harm done to, or loss suffered by, the victim arising from the commission of the offence.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Procedure<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(17) A victim’s statement must be prepared in the form, and filed in accordance with the procedures, provided for by regulations made by the Governor in Council.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Presentation of victim statement<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(18) Unless the court martial considers that it would not be in the best interests of the administration of military justice, the court martial shall, at the victim’s request, permit the victim to read their statement or to present the statement in any other manner that the court martial considers appropriate.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Consideration by court martial<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(19) Whether or not a statement has been prepared and filed, the court martial may consider any other evidence concerning any victim of the offence for the purpose of making or reviewing the disposition.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Copy of statement<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(20) The Court Martial Administrator shall, as soon as feasible after receiving a victim’s statement, ensure that a copy is provided to the prosecutor and to the accused person or their counsel.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Inquiry by court martial<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(21) As soon as feasible after a finding of not responsible on account of mental disorder is made and before making a disposition, the court martial shall inquire of the prosecutor or a victim of the offence, or any person representing a victim of the offence, whether the victim has been advised that they may prepare a statement.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Adjournment<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(22) On application of the prosecutor or a victim or on its own motion, the court martial may adjourn the hearing to permit a victim to prepare a statement or to present evidence referred to in subsection (19) if it is satisfied that the adjournment would not interfere with the proper administration of military justice.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Definition of “victim”<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(23) In this section, “victim” has the same meaning as in section 203.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Additional conditions — safety and security<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>202.202</B> If a court martial holds a hearing referred to in section 202.201, the court martial shall consider whether it is desirable, in the interests of the safety and security of any person, particularly a victim of or witness to the offence or a justice system participant, to include as a condition of the disposition that the accused</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>a</I>) abstain from communicating, directly or indirectly, with any victim, witness or other person identified in the disposition, or refrain from going to any place specified in the disposition; or</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>b</I>) comply with any other condition specified in the disposition that the court martial considers necessary to ensure the safety and security of those persons.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes">(3) If section 26 of this Act comes into force before section 59 of the other Act, then, on the day on which that section 26 comes into force, that section 59 is replaced by the following:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>59.</B> Subsection 202.201(23) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Definition of “victim”<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(23) In this section, “victim” has the same meaning as in section 203.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes">(4) If section 59 of the other Act comes into force on the same day as section 26 of this Act, then that section 26 is deemed to have come into force before that section 59 and subsection (3) applies as a consequence.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes">(5) On the first day on which both section 61 of the other Act and section 28 of this Act are in force, subsection 202.25(1) of the <I>National Defence Act</I> is replaced by the following:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Powers of Review Board<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>202.25</B> (1) Review Boards and their chairpersons may exercise the powers and shall perform the duties assigned to them under the <I>Criminal Code</I>, with any modifications that the circumstances require and unless the context otherwise requires, in relation to findings made by courts martial of unfit to stand trial or not responsible on account of mental disorder, and in relation to dispositions made under section 201 or 202.16 or subsection 202.161(4), except for the powers and duties referred to in subsections 672.5(8.1) and (8.2) and sections 672.851 and 672.86 to 672.89 of the <I>Criminal Code</I>.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>References to Attorney General<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(1.1) For the purpose of subsection (1), a reference to the Attorney General of a province in which a hearing is held under subsection 672.5(3) of the <I>Criminal Code</I> and a reference to the Attorney General in subsections 672.81(1.1) and (1.31) of that Act shall be read as a reference to the Director of Military Prosecutions.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:COMING INTO FORCE--><Para TopMargin="10" Bold="Yes" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">COMING INTO FORCE</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Three months after royal assent<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>33.</B> (1) Sections 1 to 20 come into force three months after the day on which this Act receives royal assent.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Order in council<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes">(2) Sections 21 to 31 come into force on a day or days to be fixed by order of the Governor in Council.</Para></Block><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="BPT_ImprintE"><br /><br />Published under authority of the Speaker of the House of Commons</Para></Block><Block Align="Yes" LineCnt="N"><Para NoLineBreak="Yes" NoHtml="Yes" Leading="0" Size="0" TopMargin="0" BottomMargin="0"></Para></Block></Bill_Part></Bill>