﻿<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><Bill RHead_reign="62-63 Eliz. II" RHead_ParlYear="2013-2014" DocumentTitle="BILL C-16" Bill_No="C-16" Document_No="90712" xml:lang="EN" Bill_Type="Non-amending" Stage_Name="Assented-to" Reprint="No" xml:space="preserve" ChapterNo_E="C. 1" ChapterNo_F="ch. 1" Bill-Origin="commons"><Bill_Part Part_Type="Cover" CountLines="No"><Block><Para TopMargin="24" Size="9" Leading="10" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0" TextAlign="Center">Second Session, Forty-first Parliament,</Para></Block><Block><Para Size="9" Leading="10" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0" TextAlign="Center">62-63 Elizabeth II, 2013-2014</Para></Block><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="COV@StatutesTitle">STATUTES OF CANADA 2014<br />CHAPTER 1</Para></Block><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="CovLongTitle">An Act to give effect to the Governance Agreement with Sioux Valley Dakota Nation and to make consequential amendments to other Acts</Para></Block><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="COV_StageLine"></Para></Block><Block><Para BottomMargin="14" Size="11" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0" Bold="Yes" TextAlign="Center">ASSENTED TO</Para></Block><Block><Para Size="8" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0" TextAlign="Center">4th MARCH, 2014</Para></Block><Block><Para TopMargin="4" Size="8" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0" TextAlign="Center">BILL C-16</Para></Block><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="COV_StageLine"></Para></Block></Bill_Part><Bill_Part CountLines="No" Part_Type="InsideCover"><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="BPT_InsideCoverE">Available on the Parliament of Canada Web Site at the following address:<br /><B>http://www.parl.gc.ca</B></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><Para TopMargin="108" BottomMargin="4" Size="10" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">SUMMARY</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" Size="8" Leading="9" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">This enactment gives effect to the Governance Agreement with Sioux Valley Dakota Nation. It also makes consequential amendments to other Acts.</Para></Block></Bill_Part><Bill_Part Part_Type="MainText" CountLines="No" RunningHead_E="Sioux Valley Dakota Nation Governance"><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="MAIN@RoyalAssentTitle">62-63 ELIZABETH II</Para></Block><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="MAIN@RoyalAssentTitle">——————</Para></Block><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="MAIN@RoyalAssentTitle">CHAPTER 1</Para></Block><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="LongTitleAssent">An Act to give effect to the Governance Agreement with Sioux Valley Dakota Nation and to make consequential amendments to other Acts</Para></Block><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="MAIN@RoyalAssentDate">[<I>Assented to 4th March, 2014</I>]</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Preamble<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="20" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">Whereas Sioux Valley Dakota Nation and the Government of Canada have negotiated the Governance Agreement, and by the Agreement intend to provide for a government-to-government relationship within the framework of the Constitution of Canada;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">Whereas Sioux Valley Dakota Nation, the Government of Canada and the Government of Manitoba have negotiated the Tripartite Governance Agreement, and in that agreement Her Majesty in right of Manitoba recognizes and concurs with the Agreement;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">Whereas, on August 30, 2013, the Agreement was signed on behalf of Sioux Valley Dakota Nation and Her Majesty in right of Canada and the Tripartite Governance Agreement was signed on behalf of Sioux Valley Dakota Nation, Her Majesty in right of Canada and Her Majesty in right of Manitoba;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">And whereas, under the Agreement, the Government of Canada is to recommend to Parliament the legislation necessary to give effect to the Agreement;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">Now, therefore, Her Majesty, by and with the advice and consent of the Senate and House of Commons of Canada, enacts as follows:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:SHORT TITLE--><Para TopMargin="10" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">SHORT TITLE</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Short title<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>1.</B> This Act may be cited as the <I>Sioux Valley Dakota Nation Governance Act</I>.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:INTERPRETATION--><Para TopMargin="10" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">INTERPRETATION</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Definition of “Agreement”<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>2.</B> (1) In this Act, “Agreement” means the Governance Agreement signed on behalf of Sioux Valley Dakota Nation and Her Majesty in right of Canada on August 30, 2013 and includes any amendments made to it from time to time in accordance with its provisions.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Definitions in Agreement<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(2) In this Act, “Initial Sioux Valley Dakota Nation Land Law”, “Sioux Valley Dakota Nation Lands”, “Sioux Valley Dakota Nation Law”, “Sioux Valley Dakota Oyate Government” and “Tripartite Governance Agreement” have the same meaning as in the Agreement.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:AGREEMENT--><Para TopMargin="10" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">AGREEMENT</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Agreement given effect<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>3.</B> (1) The Agreement is approved, given effect and declared valid and has the force of law.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Third parties<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(2) For greater certainty, the Agreement is binding on, and may be relied on by, all persons and bodies.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Inconsistency with Agreement<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>4.</B> (1) The Agreement prevails over this Act and any other federal law to the extent of any inconsistency between them.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Conflict with Act<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(2) This Act prevails over any other federal law to the extent of any conflict between them.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:SIOUX VALLEY DAKOTA NATION--><Para TopMargin="10" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">SIOUX VALLEY DAKOTA NATION</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Capacity<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>5.</B> (1) Sioux Valley Dakota Nation is a legal entity and, without restricting the generality of the foregoing, has the capacity, rights, powers and privileges of a natural person and the capacity to have standing in any legal proceeding involving</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>a</I>) any aboriginal or treaty rights of Sioux Valley Dakota Nation, including those rights that may be exercised by individuals;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>b</I>) other rights of Sioux Valley Dakota Nation; or</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>c</I>) the rights of Sioux Valley Dakota Nation citizens.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Power and authority<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(2) Sioux Valley Dakota Nation exercises the power and authority to make laws, carries out other government functions and otherwise exercises power or authority through Sioux Valley Dakota Oyate Government.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Rights, interests, assets and obligations<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(3) On the coming into effect of the Agreement, all rights, interests, assets and obligations of Sioux Valley Dakota Nation as a “band”, as defined in the <I>Indian Act</I>, vest in Sioux Valley Dakota Nation.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Force of law<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>6.</B> (1) Sioux Valley Dakota Nation Laws that are made in accordance with the Agreement have the force of law.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Inconsistency<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(2) In the event of any inconsistency between a Sioux Valley Dakota Nation Law and a federal law, the provisions of the Agreement relating to that inconsistency apply.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Rights and obligations<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(3) For greater certainty, any person or body has the powers, rights, privileges and benefits that are conferred on that person or body by a Sioux Valley Dakota Nation Law and must perform the duties, and is subject to the liabilities, that are imposed on the person or body by that law.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:APPLICATION OF OTHER ACTS--><Para TopMargin="10" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">APPLICATION OF OTHER ACTS</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote><I>Indian Act</I><br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>7.</B> (1) The <I>Indian Act</I> ceases to apply to Sioux Valley Dakota Nation, to Sioux Valley Dakota Nation Lands and to persons found on those lands to the extent, in the manner and in the circumstances provided for in the Agreement.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>By-laws<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(2) Sioux Valley Dakota Nation Laws are not by-laws for the purposes of the <I>Indian Act</I>.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote><I>Indian Oil and Gas Act</I><br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>8.</B> On the coming into effect of a Sioux Valley Dakota Nation Law that deals with subject matters that are the same as, or similar to, those dealt with by the <I>Indian Oil and Gas Act</I>, that Act ceases to apply to Sioux Valley Dakota Nation, to Sioux Valley Dakota Nation Lands and to royalties from oil and gas taken from those lands.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote><I>Statutory Instruments Act</I><br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>9.</B> Sioux Valley Dakota Nation Laws are not statutory instruments for the purposes of the <I>Statutory Instruments Act</I>.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote><I>Official Languages Act</I><br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>10.</B> Sioux Valley Dakota Oyate Government and any entity, including a board, commission, tribunal, council or other body or office, established under a Sioux Valley Dakota Nation Law are not federal institutions as defined in subsection 3(1) of the <I>Official Languages Act</I>.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:GENERAL--><Para TopMargin="10" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">GENERAL</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Judicial notice of agreements<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>11.</B> (1) Judicial notice must be taken of the Agreement and the Tripartite Governance Agreement.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Publication of agreements<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(2) The Agreement and the Tripartite Governance Agreement must be published by the Queen’s Printer.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Evidence<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(3) A copy of the Agreement or the Tripartite Governance Agreement published by the Queen’s Printer is evidence of that agreement and of its contents and a copy purporting to be published by the Queen’s Printer is, unless the contrary is shown, proof that it was so published.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Judicial notice of laws<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>12.</B> (1) Judicial notice must be taken of a Sioux Valley Dakota Nation Law that is registered in the public registry of laws maintained by Sioux Valley Dakota Nation in accordance with the Agreement.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Evidence<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(2) A copy of a Sioux Valley Dakota Nation Law purporting to be registered in the public registry of laws maintained by Sioux Valley Dakota Nation in accordance with the Agreement is evidence of that law and of its contents, unless the contrary is shown.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote><I>Federal Courts Act</I><br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>13.</B> (1) A decision-making body established under a Sioux Valley Dakota Nation Law is not a federal board, commission or other tribunal as defined in subsection 2(1) of the <I>Federal Courts Act</I>.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Jurisdiction — Manitoba Court of Queen’s Bench<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(2) The Manitoba Court of Queen’s Bench has jurisdiction to</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>a</I>) make orders or issue injunctions or grant declaratory relief against a decision-making body referred to in subsection (1); and</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>b</I>) undertake judicial review of the decisions of a decision-making body referred to in subsection (1).</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Notice of issue arising<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>14.</B> (1) If an issue arises in any judicial or administrative proceeding in respect of the interpretation or validity of the Agreement or the Tripartite Governance Agreement or in respect of the validity or applicability of this Act, the Manitoba legislation that gives effect to the Agreement or any Sioux Valley Dakota Nation Law, then the issue must not be decided unless the party raising the issue has served on the Attorney General of Canada, the Attorney General of Manitoba and Sioux Valley Dakota Nation notice that is in accordance with subsection (2).</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Content and timing of notice<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(2) The notice must be served at least 14 days before the day of argument of the issue, unless the court or tribunal authorizes a shorter period, and must identify</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>a</I>) the proceeding in which the issue arises;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>b</I>) the issue;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>c</I>) the material facts giving rise to the issue;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>d</I>) the legal basis of the issue; and</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>e</I>) the date on which the issue is to be argued.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Participation in proceedings<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(3) In any proceeding in respect of which subsection (1) applies, the Attorney General of Canada, the Attorney General of Manitoba and Sioux Valley Dakota Nation may appear and participate in the proceeding as parties with the same rights as any other party.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Clarification<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(4) For greater certainty, subsections (2) and (3) do not require that an oral hearing be held if one is not otherwise required.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>No liability<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>15.</B> On the coming into effect of the Initial Sioux Valley Dakota Nation Land Law, Her Majesty in right of Canada is not liable for damages under subparagraph 3(<I>b</I>)(ii) of the <I>Crown Liability and Proceedings Act</I> in respect of a breach of duty attaching to the ownership, occupation, possession or control of Sioux Valley Dakota Nation Lands.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Part 16 of Agreement<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>16.</B> Despite subsection 3(1), Part 16 of the Agreement is deemed to have effect as of August 30, 2013.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:REGULATIONS--><Para TopMargin="10" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">REGULATIONS</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Regulations and orders<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>17.</B> (1) The Governor in Council may make any regulations or orders that the Governor in Council considers necessary for the purpose of carrying out the provisions of the Agreement or other agreements related to the implementation of the Agreement.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote><I>First Nations Fiscal Management Act</I><br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(2) For the purpose of enabling Sioux Valley Dakota Nation to benefit from the provisions of the <I>First Nations Fiscal Management Act</I> or obtain the services of any body established under that Act, the Governor in Council may make any regulations that the Governor in Council considers necessary, including regulations</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>a</I>) adapting any provision of that Act or of any regulation made under that Act; and</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>b</I>) restricting the application of any provision of that Act or of any regulation made under that Act.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:CONSEQUENTIAL AMENDMENTS--><Para TopMargin="10" Bold="Yes" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">CONSEQUENTIAL AMENDMENTS</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:Access to Information Act--><MarginalNote>R.S., c. A-1<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" Bold="Yes" SmallCaps="Yes" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">Access to Information Act</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>18.</B> Subsection 13(3) of the <I>Access to Information Act</I> is amended by striking out “or” at the end of paragraph (<I>f</I>), by adding “or’’ at the end of paragraph (<I>g</I>) and by adding the following after paragraph (<I>g</I>):</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>h</I>) Sioux Valley Dakota Oyate Government, within the meaning of subsection 2(2) of the <I>Sioux Valley Dakota Nation Governance Act</I>.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:Privacy Act--><MarginalNote>R.S., c. P-21<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="10" Bold="Yes" SmallCaps="Yes" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">Privacy Act</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>19.</B> Subsection 8(7) of the <I>Privacy Act</I> is amended by striking out “or” at the end of paragraph (<I>f</I>), by adding “or’’ at the end of paragraph (<I>g</I>) and by adding the following after paragraph (<I>g</I>):</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>h</I>) Sioux Valley Dakota Oyate Government, within the meaning of subsection 2(2) of the <I><I>Sioux Valley Dakota Nation Governance Act</I></I>.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:COORDINATING AMENDMENTS--><Para TopMargin="10" Bold="Yes" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">COORDINATING AMENDMENTS</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>2013, c. 25<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>20.</B> (1) In this section, “other Act” means the <I>Yale First Nation Final Agreement Act</I>.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes">(2) If section 20 of the other Act comes into force before section 18 of this Act, then that section 18 is replaced by the following:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>18.</B> Subsection 13(3) of the <I>Access to Information Act</I> is amended by striking out “or” at the end of paragraph (<I>g</I>), by adding “or” at the end of paragraph (<I>h</I>) and by adding the following after paragraph (<I>h</I>):</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>i</I>) Sioux Valley Dakota Oyate Government, within the meaning of subsection 2(2) of the <I><I>Sioux Valley Dakota Nation Governance Act</I></I>.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes">(3) If section 18 of this Act comes into force before section 20 of the other Act, then that section 20 is replaced by the following:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>20.</B> Subsection 13(3) of the <I>Access to Information Act</I> is amended by striking out “or” at the end of paragraph (<I>g</I>), by adding “or’’ at the end of paragraph (<I>h</I>) and by adding the following after paragraph (<I>h</I>):</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>i</I>) the Yale First Nation Government, within the meaning of subsection 2(2) of the <I>Yale First Nation Final Agreement Act</I>.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes">(4) If section 20 of the other Act comes into force on the same day as section 18 of this Act, then that section 20 is deemed to have come into force before that section 18 and subsection (2) applies as a consequence.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes">(5) If section 23 of the other Act comes into force before section 19 of this Act, then that section 19 is replaced by the following:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>19.</B> Subsection 8(7) of the <I>Privacy Act</I> is amended by striking out “or” at the end of paragraph (<I>g</I>), by adding “or” at the end of paragraph (<I>h</I>) and by adding the following after paragraph (<I>h</I>):</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>i</I>) Sioux Valley Dakota Oyate Government, within the meaning of subsection 2(2) of the <I><I>Sioux Valley Dakota Nation Governance Act</I></I>.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes">(6) If section 19 of this Act comes into force before section 23 of the other Act, then that section 23 is replaced by the following:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>23.</B> Subsection 8(7) of the <I>Privacy Act</I> is amended by striking out “or” at the end of paragraph (<I>g</I>), by adding “or’’ at the end of paragraph (<I>h</I>) and by adding the following after paragraph (<I>h</I>):</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>i</I>) the Yale First Nation Government, within the meaning of subsection 2(2) of the <I>Yale First Nation Final Agreement Act</I>.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes">(7) If section 23 of the other Act comes into force on the same day as section 19 of this Act, then that section 23 is deemed to have come into force before that section 19 and subsection (5) applies as a consequence.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:COMING INTO FORCE--><Para TopMargin="10" Bold="Yes" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">COMING INTO FORCE</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Order in council<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>21.</B> This Act, except for section 20, comes into force on a day to be fixed by order of the Governor in Council.</Para></Block><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="BPT_ImprintE"><br /><br />Published under authority of the Speaker of the House of Commons</Para></Block><Block Align="Yes" LineCnt="N"><Para NoLineBreak="Yes" NoHtml="Yes" Leading="0" Size="0" TopMargin="0" BottomMargin="0"></Para></Block></Bill_Part></Bill>