﻿<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><Bill RHead_reign="62-63 Eliz. II" RHead_ParlYear="2013-2014" DocumentTitle="BILL C-17" Bill_No="C-17" Document_No="90716" xml:lang="EN" Bill_Type="Non-amending" Stage_Name="Assented-to" Reprint="No" xml:space="preserve" ChapterNo_E="C. 24" ChapterNo_F="ch. 24" Bill-Origin="commons"><Bill_Part Part_Type="Cover" CountLines="No"><Block><Para TopMargin="24" Size="9" Leading="10" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0" TextAlign="Center">Second Session, Forty-first Parliament,</Para></Block><Block><Para Size="9" Leading="10" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0" TextAlign="Center">62-63 Elizabeth II, 2013-2014</Para></Block><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="COV@StatutesTitle">STATUTES OF CANADA 2014<br />CHAPTER 24</Para></Block><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="CovLongTitle">An Act to amend the Food and Drugs Act</Para></Block><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="COV_StageLine"></Para></Block><Block><Para BottomMargin="14" Size="11" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0" Bold="Yes" TextAlign="Center">ASSENTED TO</Para></Block><Block><Para Size="8" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0" TextAlign="Center">6th NOVEMBER, 2014</Para></Block><Block><Para TopMargin="4" Size="8" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0" TextAlign="Center">BILL C-17</Para></Block><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="COV_StageLine"></Para></Block></Bill_Part><Bill_Part CountLines="No" Part_Type="InsideCover"><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="BPT_InsideCoverE">Available on the Parliament of Canada Web Site at the following address:<br /><B>http://www.parl.gc.ca</B></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><Para TopMargin="108" BottomMargin="4" Size="10" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">SUMMARY</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" Size="8" Leading="9" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">This enactment amends the <I>Food and Drugs Act</I> regarding therapeutic products in order to improve safety by introducing measures to, among other things,</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" Size="8" Leading="9" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">(<I>a</I>) strengthen safety oversight of therapeutic products throughout their life cycle;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" Size="8" Leading="9" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">(<I>b</I>) improve reporting by certain health care institutions of serious adverse drug reactions and medical device incidents that involve therapeutic products; and</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" Size="8" Leading="9" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">(<I>c</I>) promote greater confidence in the oversight of therapeutic products by increasing transparency.</Para></Block></Bill_Part><Bill_Part Part_Type="MainText" CountLines="No" RunningHead_E="Food and Drugs"><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="MAIN@RoyalAssentTitle">62-63 ELIZABETH II</Para></Block><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="MAIN@RoyalAssentTitle">——————</Para></Block><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="MAIN@RoyalAssentTitle">CHAPTER 24</Para></Block><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="LongTitleAssent">An Act to amend the Food and Drugs Act</Para></Block><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="MAIN@RoyalAssentDate">[<I>Assented to 6th November, 2014</I>]</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><MarginalNote>Preamble<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">Whereas the safety of drugs and medical devices is a key concern for Canadians;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">And whereas new measures are required to further protect Canadians from the risks related to drugs and medical devices, other than natural health products;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">Now, therefore, Her Majesty, by and with the advice and consent of the Senate and House of Commons of Canada, enacts as follows:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:ALTERNATIVE TITLE--><Para TopMargin="10" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">ALTERNATIVE TITLE</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Alternative title<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>1.</B> This Act may be cited as the <I>Protecting Canadians from Unsafe Drugs Act (Vanessa’s Law)</I>.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:FOOD AND DRUGS ACT--><MarginalNote>R.S., c. F-27<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="10" Bold="Yes" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">FOOD AND DRUGS ACT</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>1993, c. 34, s. 71(3)<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>2.</B> (1) The definition “device” in section 2 of the <I>Food and Drugs Act</I> is replaced by the following:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>“device”<br />« <I>instrument</I> »<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0">“device” means an instrument, apparatus, contrivance or other similar article, or an <I>in vitro</I> reagent, including a component, part or accessory of any of them, that is manufactured, sold or represented for use in</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>a</I>) diagnosing, treating, mitigating or preventing a disease, disorder or abnormal physical state, or any of their symptoms, in human beings or animals,</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>b</I>) restoring, modifying or correcting the body structure of human beings or animals or the functioning of any part of the bodies of human beings or animals,</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>c</I>) diagnosing pregnancy in human beings or animals,</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>d</I>) caring for human beings or animals during pregnancy or at or after the birth of the offspring, including caring for the offspring, or</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>e</I>) preventing conception in human beings or animals;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0">however, it does not include such an instrument, apparatus, contrivance or article, or a component, part or accessory of any of them, that does any of the actions referred to in paragraphs (<I>a</I>) to (<I>e</I>) solely by pharmacological, immunological or metabolic means or solely by chemical means in or on the body of a human being or animal;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes">(2) The definition “<AltLang xml:lang="fr">étiquette</AltLang>” in section 2 of the French version of the Act is replaced by the following:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>« étiquette »<br />“<I>label</I>”<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0"><AltLang xml:lang="fr">« étiquette » Sont assimilés aux étiquettes les inscriptions, mots ou marques accompagnant les aliments, drogues, cosmétiques, instruments ou emballages ou s’y rapportant.</AltLang></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes">(3) Section 2 of the Act is amended by adding the following in alphabetical order:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>“confidential business information”<br />« <I>renseignements commerciaux confidentiels</I> »<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0">“confidential business information”, in respect of a person to whose business or affairs the information relates, means — subject to the regulations — business information</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>a</I>) that is not publicly available,</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>b</I>) in respect of which the person has taken measures that are reasonable in the circumstances to ensure that it remains not publicly available, and</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>c</I>) that has actual or potential economic value to the person or their competitors because it is not publicly available and its disclosure would result in a material financial loss to the person or a material financial gain to their competitors;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><MarginalNote>“therapeutic product”<br />« <I>produit thérapeutique</I> »<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0">“therapeutic product” means a drug or device or any combination of drugs and devices, but does not include a natural health product within the meaning of the <I>Natural Health Products Regulations</I>;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><MarginalNote>“therapeutic product authorization”<br />« <I>autorisation relative à un produit thérapeutique</I> »<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0">“therapeutic product authorization” means an authorization — including a licence and a suspended authorization or licence — that is issued under the regulations and that authorizes, as the case may be, the import, sale, advertisement, manufacture, preparation, preservation, packaging, labelling, storage or testing of a therapeutic product;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>3.</B> The Act is amended by adding the following after section 21:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:Therapeutic Products--><Para TopMargin="10" SmallCaps="Yes" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">Therapeutic Products</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Power to require information — serious risk<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>21.1</B> (1) If the Minister believes that a therapeutic product may present a serious risk of injury to human health, the Minister may order a person to provide the Minister with information that is in the person’s control and that the Minister believes is necessary to determine whether the product presents such a risk.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Disclosure — serious risk<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(2) The Minister may disclose confidential business information about a therapeutic prod­uct without notifying the person to whose business or affairs the information relates or obtaining their consent, if the Minister believes that the product may present a serious risk of injury to human health.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Disclosure — health or safety<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(3) The Minister may disclose confidential business information about a therapeutic prod­uct without notifying the person to whose business or affairs the information relates or obtaining their consent, if the purpose of the disclosure is related to the protection or promotion of human health or the safety of the public and the disclosure is to</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>a</I>) a government;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>b</I>) a person from whom the Minister seeks advice; or</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>c</I>) a person who carries out functions relating to the protection or promotion of human health or the safety of the public.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Definition of “government”<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(4) In this section, “government” means any of the following or their institutions:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>a</I>) the federal government;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>b</I>) a corporation named in Schedule III to the <I>Financial Administration Act</I>;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>c</I>) a provincial government or a public body established under an Act of the legislature of a province;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>d</I>) an aboriginal government as defined in subsection 13(3) of the <I>Access to Information Act</I>;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>e</I>) a government of a foreign state or of a subdivision of a foreign state; or</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>f</I>) an international organization of states.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Modification or replacement — labelling or packaging<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>21.2</B> The Minister may, if he or she believes that doing so is necessary to prevent injury to health, order the holder of a therapeutic product authorization that authorizes the import or sale of a therapeutic product to modify the product’s label or to modify or replace its package.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Minister’s powers — risk of injury to health<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>21.3</B> (1) If the Minister believes that a therapeutic product presents a serious or imminent risk of injury to health, he or she may order a person who sells the product to</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>a</I>) recall the product; or</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>b</I>) send the product, or cause it to be sent, to a place specified in the order.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Recall order — corrective action<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(2) For greater certainty, if the Minister makes an order under paragraph (1)(<I>a</I>) and believes that corrective action is an effective means of dealing with the risk, the order may require the person who sells the product to, instead of requesting the product’s return, request the product’s owner or user to allow corrective action to be taken in respect of the product and then take that corrective action, or cause it to be taken, if the request is accepted.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Prohibition — selling<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(3) Subject to subsection (5), no person shall sell a therapeutic product that the Minister orders them, or another person, to recall.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Power to authorize sale<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(4) The Minister may authorize a person to sell a therapeutic product, with or without conditions, even if the Minister has ordered them, or another person, to recall it.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Exception<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(5) A person does not contravene subsection (3) if they sell a therapeutic product that they have been authorized under subsection (4) to sell, provided that they sell it in accordance with any conditions that the Minister establishes.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Contravention of unpublished order<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(6) No person shall be convicted of an offence for the contravention of subsection (3) unless it is proved that, at the time of the alleged contravention, the person had been notified of the recall order or reasonable steps had been taken to bring the purport of the recall order to the notice of those persons likely to be affected by it.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote><I>Statutory Instruments Act</I><br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>21.4</B> (1) For greater certainty, orders made under any of sections 21.1 to 21.3 are not statutory instruments within the meaning of the <I>Statutory Instruments Act</I>.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Availability <keep>of orders</keep><br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(2) The Minister shall ensure that any order made under any of sections 21.1 to 21.3 is publicly available.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Injunction<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>21.5</B> (1) If, on the application of the Minister, it appears to a court of competent jurisdiction that a person has done, is about to do or is likely to do anything that constitutes or is directed toward the commission of an offence under this Act in respect of a therapeutic product, the court may issue an injunction ordering the person, who is to be named in the application, to</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>a</I>) refrain from doing anything that it appears to the court may constitute or be directed toward the commission of the offence; or</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>b</I>) do anything that it appears to the court may prevent the commission of the offence.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Notice<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(2) No injunction is to be issued under subsection (1) unless 48 hours’ notice is served on the party or parties who are named in the application or unless the urgency of the situation is such that service of notice would not be in the public interest.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>False or misleading information <keep>— therapeutic</keep> products<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>21.6</B> No person shall knowingly make a false or misleading statement to the Minister — or knowingly provide him or her with false or misleading information — in connection with any matter under this Act concerning a therapeutic product.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Terms and conditions of authorizations<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>21.7</B> The holder of a therapeutic product authorization shall comply with the terms and conditions of the authorization that are imposed under regulations made under paragraph 30(1.2)(<I>b</I>).</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Clinical trials and investigational tests<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>21.71</B> The holder of a therapeutic product authorization referred to in paragraph 30(1.2)(<I>c</I>) shall ensure that prescribed information concerning the clinical trial or investigational test is made public within the prescribed time and in the prescribed manner.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>4.</B> Section 21.4 of the Act is replaced by the following:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Power to require assessment<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>21.31</B> Subject to the regulations, the Minister may order the holder of a therapeutic product authorization to conduct an assessment of the therapeutic product to which the authorization relates and provide the Minister with the results of the assessment.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Power to require tests, studies, etc.<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>21.32</B> Subject to the regulations, the Minister may, for the purpose of obtaining additional information about a therapeutic product’s effects on health or safety, order the holder of a therapeutic product authorization to</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>a</I>) compile information, conduct tests or studies or monitor experience in respect of the therapeutic product; and</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>b</I>) provide the Minister with the information or the results of the tests, studies or monitoring.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote><I>Statutory Instruments Act</I><br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>21.4</B> (1) For greater certainty, orders made under any of sections 21.1 to 21.32 are not statutory instruments within the meaning of the <I>Statutory Instruments Act</I>.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Availability of orders<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(2) The Minister shall ensure that any order made under any of sections 21.1 to 21.32 is publicly available.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>5.</B> The Act is amended by adding the following after section 21.71:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Health care institutions to provide information<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>21.8</B> A prescribed health care institution shall provide the Minister, within the prescribed time and in the prescribed manner, with prescribed information that is in its control about a serious adverse drug reaction that involves a therapeutic product or a medical device incident that involves a therapeutic product.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>6.</B> (1) Section 30 of the Act is amended by adding the following after subsection (1.1):</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Regulations — therapeutic products<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(1.2) Without limiting the power conferred by any other subsection of this section, the Governor in Council may make regulations</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>a</I>) respecting the issuance of authorizations — including licences — that authorize, as the case may be, the import, sale, advertisement, manufacture, preparation, preservation, packaging, labelling, storage or testing of a therapeutic product, and the amendment, suspension and revocation of such authorizations;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>b</I>) authorizing the Minister to impose terms and conditions on authorizations referred to in paragraph (<I>a</I>), including existing authorizations, and to amend those terms and conditions;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>b.1</I>) requiring the Minister to ensure that decisions with regard to the issuance, amendment, suspension and revocation of authorizations referred to in paragraph (<I>a</I>), and to the imposition and amendment of terms and conditions referred to in paragraph (<I>b</I>), along with the reasons for those decisions, are publicly available;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>c</I>) requiring holders of a therapeutic product authorization that authorizes the import or sale of a therapeutic product for a clinical trial or investigational test involving human subjects, or former holders of such an authorization, to provide the Minister, after the trial or test is completed or discontinued, or, if the authorization is suspended or revoked, after the suspension or revocation, with safety information that the holders or former holders receive or become aware of about the therapeutic product;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>c.1</I>) defining “clinical trial” and “investigational test” for the purposes of this Act;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>d</I>) requiring holders of a therapeutic product authorization to provide the Minister with information, in respect of any serious risk of injury to human health, that the holders receive or become aware of and that is relevant to the safety of the therapeutic product to which the authorization relates, regarding</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="4" FirstLineIndent="0">(i) risks that have been communicated outside Canada, and the manner of the communication,</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="4" FirstLineIndent="0">(ii) changes that have taken place to labelling outside Canada, and</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="4" FirstLineIndent="0">(iii) recalls, reassessments and suspensions or revocations of authorizations, including licences, in respect of a therapeutic product, that have taken place outside Canada;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>d.1</I>) specifying the business information obtained under this Act in relation to an authorization under paragraph (<I>a</I>) that is not confidential business information, or the circumstances in which business information obtained under this Act in relation to such an authorization ceases to be confidential business information;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>d.2</I>) authorizing the Minister to disclose, without notifying the person to whose business or affairs the information relates or obtaining their consent, business information that, under regulations made under paragraph (<I>d.1</I>),</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="4" FirstLineIndent="0">(i) is not confidential business information, or</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="4" FirstLineIndent="0">(ii) has ceased to be confidential business information;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>e</I>) respecting modifications of labels and modifications and replacements of packages referred to in section 21.2;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>f</I>) respecting the recall of a therapeutic product or the sale of a therapeutic product that is the subject of a recall; and</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>g</I>) prescribing anything that is to be prescribed under section 21.71.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes">(2) Subsection 30(1.2) of the Act is amended by striking out “and” at the end of paragraph (<I>f</I>) and by adding the following after paragraph (<I>f</I>):</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>f.1</I>) respecting assessments referred to in section 21.31, and the provision of the results of the assessments to the Minister;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>f.2</I>) requiring the Minister to ensure that decisions with regard to the making of orders under section 21.31, along with the reasons for those decisions, are publicly available;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>f.3</I>) respecting the compilation of information, the conducting of tests and studies and the monitoring of experience that are referred to in paragraph 21.32(<I>a</I>), and the provision to the Minister of the information or results referred to in paragraph 21.32(<I>b</I>); and</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes">(3) Subsection 30(1.2) of the Act is amended by striking out “and” at the end of paragraph (<I>f</I>) and by adding the following after paragraph (<I>g</I>):</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>h</I>) defining “serious adverse drug reaction” and “medical device incident” for the purposes of this Act;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>i</I>) respecting the provision by health care institutions referred to in section 21.8 to the Minister of information referred to in that section; and</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>j</I>) prescribing anything that is to be prescribed under section 21.8.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes">(4) Section 30 of the Act is amended by adding the following after subsection (1.2):</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Consideration of existing information management systems<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(1.3) Before recommending to the Governor in Council that a regulation be made under paragraph (1.2)(<I>i</I>) or (<I>j</I>), the Minister shall take into account existing information management systems, with a view to not recommending the making of regulations that would impose unnecessary administrative burdens.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes">(5) The portion of subsection 30(2) of the Act before paragraph (<I>a</I>) is replaced by the following:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Regulations respecting drugs manufactured outside Canada<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(2) Without limiting the power conferred by any other subsection of this section, the Governor in Council may make such regulations governing, regulating or prohibiting</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>1994, c. 47, s. 117<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes">(6) Subsection 30(3) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Regulations — North American Free Trade Agreement and WTO Agreement<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(3) Without limiting the power conferred by any other subsection of this section, the Governor in Council may make any regulations that the Governor in Council considers necessary for the purpose of implementing, in relation to drugs, Article 1711 of the North American Free Trade Agreement or paragraph 3 of Article 39 of the Agreement on Trade-related Aspects of Intellectual Property Rights set out in Annex 1C to the WTO Agreement.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>2004, c. 23, s. 2<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes">(7) Subsection 30(5) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Regulations to implement General Council Decision<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(5) Without limiting the power conferred by any other subsection of this section, the Governor in Council may make any regulations that the Governor in Council considers necessary for the purpose of implementing the General Council Decision.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>2012, c. 19, s. 416<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>7.</B> Subsection 30.5(1) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Incorporation by reference<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>30.5</B> (1) A regulation made under this Act with respect to a food or therapeutic product and a marketing authorization may incorporate by reference any document, regardless of its source, either as it exists on a particular date or as it is amended from time to time.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>1997, c. 6, s. 91<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>8.</B> The portion of section 31 of the Act before paragraph (<I>a</I>) is replaced by the following:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Contravention of Act or regulations<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>31.</B> Subject to sections 31.1, 31.2 and 31.4, every person who contravenes any of the provisions of this Act or of the regulations is guilty of an offence and liable</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>9.</B> The Act is amended by adding the following after section 31.1:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Offences relating to therapeutic products<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>31.2</B> Subject to section 31.4, every person who contravenes any provision of this Act or the regulations, as it relates to a therapeutic product, or an order made under any of sections 21.1 to 21.3 is guilty of an offence and liable</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>a</I>) on conviction by indictment, to a fine not exceeding $5,000,000 or to imprisonment for a term not exceeding two years or to both; and</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>b</I>) on summary conviction, for a first offence, to a fine not exceeding $250,000 or to imprisonment for a term not exceeding six months or to both and, for a subsequent offence, to a fine not exceeding $500,000 or to imprisonment for a term not exceeding 18 months or to both.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Due diligence<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>31.3</B> Due diligence is a defence in a prosecution for an offence under this Act, other than an offence under section 31.4.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Offences — section 21.6 and serious risk<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>31.4</B> A person who contravenes section 21.6, or who knowingly or recklessly causes a serious risk of injury to human health in contravening another provision of this Act or the regulations, as it relates to a therapeutic product, or an order made under any of sections 21.1 to 21.3 is guilty of an offence and liable</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>a</I>) on conviction on indictment, to a fine the amount of which is at the discretion of the court or to imprisonment for a term not exceeding five years or to both; and</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>b</I>) on summary conviction, for a first offence, to a fine not exceeding $500,000 or to imprisonment for a term not exceeding 18 months or to both and, for a subsequent offence, to a fine not exceeding $1,000,000 or to imprisonment for a term not exceeding two years or to both.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Sentencing considerations<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>31.5</B> A court that imposes a sentence for an offence under section 31.2 or 31.4 shall take into account, in addition to any other principles that it is required to consider, the following factors:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>a</I>) the harm or risk of harm caused by the commission of the offence; and</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>b</I>) the vulnerability of consumers of the therapeutic product.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Parties to offence<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>31.6</B> If a person other than an individual commits an offence under section 31.2, or commits an offence under section 31.4 by reason of contravening section 21.6, then any of the person’s directors, officers or agents or mandataries who directs, authorizes, assents to or acquiesces or participates in the commission of the offence is a party to the offence and is liable on conviction to the punishment provided for by this Act, even if the person is not prosecuted for the offence.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Continuing offence<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>31.7</B> If an offence under section 31.2 or 31.4 is committed or continued on more than one day, it constitutes a separate offence for each day on which it is committed or continued.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>10.</B> The portion of section 31.2 of the Act before paragraph (<I>a</I>) is replaced by the following:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Offences relating to therapeutic products<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>31.2</B> Subject to section 31.4, every person who contravenes any provision of this Act or the regulations, as it relates to a therapeutic product, or an order made under any of sections 21.1 to 21.32 is guilty of an offence and liable</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>11.</B> The portion of section 31.4 of the Act before paragraph (<I>a</I>) is replaced by the following:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Offences — section 21.6 and serious risk<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>31.4</B> A person who contravenes section 21.6, or who knowingly or recklessly causes a serious risk of injury to human health in contravening another provision of this Act or the regulations, as it relates to a therapeutic product, or an order made under any of sections 21.1 to 21.32 is guilty of an offence and liable</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>1996, c. 19, s. 78<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>12.</B> Subsection 35(1) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Certificate of analyst<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>35.</B> (1) Subject to this section, in any prosecution for an offence under any of sections 31 to 31.2 and 31.4, a certificate purporting to be signed by an analyst and stating that an article, sample or substance has been submitted to, and analysed or examined by, the analyst and stating the results of the analysis or examination is admissible in evidence and, in the absence of evidence to the contrary, is proof of the statements contained in the certificate without proof of the signature or official character of the person appearing to have signed it.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:TRANSITIONAL PROVISION--><Para TopMargin="10" Bold="Yes" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">TRANSITIONAL PROVISION</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Therapeutic product authorizations<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>13.</B> The definition “therapeutic product authorization”, as enacted by subsection 2(3), applies to authorizations — including licences and suspended authorizations or licences — that were issued before the day on which this section comes into force and that authorize, as the case may be, the import, sale, advertisement, manufacture, preparation, preservation, packaging, labelling, storage or testing of a therapeutic product.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:COORDINATING AMENDMENTS--><Para TopMargin="10" Bold="Yes" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">COORDINATING AMENDMENTS</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Subsections 6(2) and (3)<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>14.</B> (1) If subsection 6(2) comes into force before subsection 6(3), then the English version of subsection 6(3) is amended by replacing “paragraph (<I>f</I>)” with “paragraph (<I>f.3</I>)”.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes">(2) If subsection 6(3) comes into force before subsection 6(2), then the English version of subsection 6(2) is amended by</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0" Bold="Yes">(<I>a</I>) striking out “striking out “and” at the end of paragraph (<I>f</I>) and by”; and</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0" Bold="Yes">(<I>b</I>) striking out “and” at the end of the paragraph (<I>f.3</I>) of the <I>Food and Drugs Act</I> that it enacts.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes">(3) If subsections 6(2) and (3) come into force on the same day, then subsection 6(2) is deemed to have come into force before subsection 6(3) and subsection (1) applies as a consequence.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:COMING INTO FORCE--><Para TopMargin="10" Bold="Yes" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">COMING INTO FORCE</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Order in council<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>15.</B> (1) Section 4, subsection 6(2) and sections 10 and 11 come into force on a day to be fixed by order of the Governor in Council.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Order in council<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes">(2) Section 5 and subsections 6(3) and (4) come into force on a day to be fixed by order of the Governor in Council.</Para></Block><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="BPT_ImprintE"><br /><br />Published under authority of the Speaker of the House of Commons</Para></Block><Block Align="Yes" LineCnt="N"><Para NoLineBreak="Yes" NoHtml="Yes" Leading="0" Size="0" TopMargin="0" BottomMargin="0"></Para></Block></Bill_Part></Bill>