茂禄驴<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><Bill RHead_reign="62-63-64 Eliz. II" RHead_ParlYear="2013-2014-2015" DocumentTitle="BILL C-2" Bill_No="C-2" Document_No="90699" xml:lang="EN" Bill_Type="Non-amending" Stage_Name="Assented-to" Reprint="No" xml:space="preserve" ChapterNo_E="C. 22" ChapterNo_F="ch. 22" Bill-Origin="commons"><Bill_Part Part_Type="Cover" CountLines="No"><Block><Para TopMargin="24" Size="9" Leading="10" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0" TextAlign="Center">Second Session, Forty-first Parliament,</Para></Block><Block><Para Size="9" Leading="10" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0" TextAlign="Center">62-63-64 Elizabeth II, 2013-2014-2015</Para></Block><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="COV@StatutesTitle">STATUTES OF CANADA 2015<br />CHAPTER 22</Para></Block><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="CovLongTitle">An Act to amend the Controlled Drugs and Substances Act</Para></Block><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="COV_StageLine"></Para></Block><Block><Para BottomMargin="14" Size="11" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0" Bold="Yes" TextAlign="Center">ASSENTED TO</Para></Block><Block><Para Size="8" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0" TextAlign="Center">18th JUNE, 2015</Para></Block><Block><Para TopMargin="4" Size="8" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0" TextAlign="Center">BILL C-2</Para></Block><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="COV_StageLine"></Para></Block></Bill_Part><Bill_Part CountLines="No" Part_Type="InsideCover"><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="BPT_InsideCoverE">Available on the Parliament of Canada Web Site at the following address:<br /><B>http://www.parl.gc.ca</B></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><Para TopMargin="108" BottomMargin="4" Size="10" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">SUMMARY</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" Size="8" Leading="9" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">This enactment amends the <I>Controlled Drugs and Substances Act</I> to, among other things,</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" Size="8" Leading="9" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">(<I>a</I>) create a separate exemption regime for activities involving the use of a controlled substance or precursor that is obtained in a manner not authorized under this Act;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" Size="8" Leading="9" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">(<I>b</I>) specify the purposes for which an exemption may be granted for those activities; and</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" Size="8" Leading="9" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">(<I>c</I>) set out the information that must be submitted to the Minister of Health before the Minister may consider an application for an exemption in relation to a supervised consumption site.</Para></Block></Bill_Part><Bill_Part Part_Type="MainText" CountLines="No" RunningHead_E="Controlled Drugs and Substances"><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="MAIN@RoyalAssentTitle">62-63-64 ELIZABETH II</Para></Block><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="MAIN@RoyalAssentTitle">芒聙聰芒聙聰芒聙聰芒聙聰芒聙聰芒聙聰</Para></Block><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="MAIN@RoyalAssentTitle">CHAPTER 22</Para></Block><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="LongTitleAssent">An Act to amend the Controlled Drugs and Substances Act</Para></Block><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="MAIN@RoyalAssentDate">[<I>Assented to 18th June, 2015</I>]</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><MarginalNote>Preamble<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">Whereas Parliament recognizes that the objectives of the <I>Controlled Drugs and Substances Act</I> (芒聙聹the Act芒聙聺) are the protection of public health and the protection of public safety;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">Whereas the Act and its regulations have a dual role of prohibiting certain activities associated with harmful substances and allowing access to those substances for legitimate medical, scientific and industrial purposes;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">Whereas the diversion of controlled substances and precursors, as those terms are defined in the Act, which are frequently used in the production of illicit drugs, is a worldwide problem with significant impacts on Canada;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">Whereas the money that is used to purchase controlled substances that are obtained from illicit sources often originates from criminal activity such as theft, and that money, in turn, often funds organized crime in our communities;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">Whereas the substances that are subject to the Act may pose serious risks to the health of individuals and those risks are exacerbated when those substances are unregulated, untested and obtained from illicit sources;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">Whereas the negative consequences associated with the use of illicit substances can have significant impacts on vulnerable subsets of the Canadian population;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">And whereas an exemption from the application of the Act and its regulations for certain activities in relation to controlled substances that are obtained from illicit sources should only be granted in exceptional circumstances and after the applicant has addressed rigorous criteria;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">Now, therefore, Her Majesty, by and with the advice and consent of the Senate and House of Commons of Canada, enacts as follows:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:SHORT TITLE--><Para TopMargin="10" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">SHORT TITLE</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Short title<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>1.</B> This Act may be cited as the <I>Respect for Communities Act</I>.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:CONTROLLED DRUGS AND SUBSTANCES ACT--><MarginalNote>1996, c. 19<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="10" Bold="Yes" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">CONTROLLED DRUGS AND SUBSTANCES ACT</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>2.</B> Subsection 30(2) of the <I>Controlled Drugs and Substances Act</I> is replaced by the following:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Certificate of designation<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(2) An inspector shall be provided with a prescribed certificate of designation and, on entering any place under subsection 31(1) or a supervised consumption site under subsection 31(1.1) or (1.2), shall, on request, produce the certificate to the person in charge of the place.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>3.</B> (1) Section 31 of the Act is amended by adding the following after subsection (1):</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Powers of inspectors 芒聙聰 inspection of supervised consumption sites<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(1.1) In order to confirm any information in relation to an application submitted to the Minister for an exemption for a medical purpose under subsection 56.1(2) to allow certain activities to take place at a supervised consumption site, as defined in subsection 56.1(1), an inspector may, at any reasonable time, enter the site and may for that purpose exercise any of the powers set out in paragraphs (1)(<I>a</I>) to (<I>i</I>).</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Powers of inspectors 芒聙聰 inspection of supervised consumption sites<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(1.2) In order to verify compliance or to prevent non-compliance with the provisions of this Act or the regulations, or with any terms and conditions specified by the Minister in an exemption granted under subsection 56.1(2), an inspector may, at any reasonable time, enter any supervised consumption site, as defined in subsection 56.1(1), and may for those purposes exercise any of the powers set out in paragraphs (1)(<I>a</I>) to (<I>i</I>).</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes">(2) Subsection 31(2) of the English version of the Act is replaced by the following:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Warrant required to enter dwelling-place<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(2) In the case of a dwelling-place, an inspector may enter it only with the consent of an occupant or under the authority of a warrant issued under subsection (3).</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes">(3) Paragraph 31(3)(<I>a</I>) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>a</I>) a place referred to in subsection (1) or (1.2) is a dwelling-place but otherwise meets the conditions for entry described in that subsection,</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes">(4) Subsection 31(5) of the English version of the Act is replaced by the following:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Assistance to inspector<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(5) The owner or other person in charge of a place entered by an inspector under subsection (1), (1.1) or (1.2) and every person found there shall give the inspector all reasonable assistance in that person芒聙聶s power and provide the inspector with any information that the inspector may reasonably require.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes">(5) Subsection 31(8) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Return by inspector<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(8) If an inspector determines that to ensure compliance with the regulations or with any terms and conditions specified by the Minister in an exemption granted under subsection 56.1(2) it is no longer necessary to detain a controlled substance or a precursor seized by the inspector under paragraph (1)(<I>i</I>), the inspector shall notify in writing the owner or other person in charge of the place where the seizure occurred of that determination and, on being issued a receipt for it, shall return the controlled substance or precursor to that person.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>4.</B> (1) Paragraph 55(1)(<I>n</I>) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>n</I>) respecting the qualifications for inspectors and their powers and duties in relation to the enforcement of, and compliance with, the regulations or any terms and conditions specified by the Minister in an exemption granted under subsection 56.1(2);</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes">(2) Section 55 of the Act is amended by adding the following after subsection (1):</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Exception related to paragraph (1)(<I>z</I>)<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(1.1) A regulation made under paragraph <keep>(1)(<I>z</I>)</keep> shall not exempt from the application of all or any of the provisions of this Act or the regulations</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>a</I>) any person or class of persons in relation to a controlled substance or precursor that is obtained in a manner not authorized under this Act; or</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>b</I>) any controlled substance or precursor or any class of either of them that is obtained in a manner not authorized under this Act.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Regulations<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(1.2) The Governor in Council may make regulations for carrying out the purposes of section 56.1, including</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>a</I>) defining terms for the purposes of that section;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>b</I>) amending the definitions that are set out in subsection 56.1(1);</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>c</I>) respecting any information to be submitted to the Minister under paragraph 56.1(3)(<I>z.1</I>) and the manner in which it is to be submitted;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>d</I>) respecting the circumstances in which an exemption may be granted for a medical or law enforcement purpose;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>e</I>) respecting requirements in relation to an application for an exemption made under subsection 56.1(2), including the information to be submitted with the application; and</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>f</I>) respecting terms and conditions in relation to an exemption granted under subsection 56.1(2).</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>5.</B> Section 56 of the Act is replaced by the following:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Exemption by Minister<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>56.</B> (1) The Minister may, on any terms and conditions that the Minister considers necessary, exempt from the application of all or any of the provisions of this Act or the regulations any person or class of persons or any controlled substance or precursor or any class of either of them if, in the opinion of the Minister, the exemption is necessary for a medical or scientific purpose or is otherwise in the public interest.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Exception<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(2) The Minister is not authorized under subsection (1) to exempt from the application of all or any of the provisions of this Act or the regulations</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>a</I>) any person or class of persons in relation to a controlled substance or precursor that is obtained in a manner not authorized under this Act; or</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>b</I>) any controlled substance or precursor or any class of either of them that is obtained in a manner not authorized under this Act.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Interpretation<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>56.1</B> (1) The following definitions apply in this section.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><MarginalNote>芒聙聹alternate person in charge芒聙聺<br />脗芦 <I>personne responsable suppl脙漏ante</I> 脗禄<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0">芒聙聹alternate person in charge芒聙聺 means any person designated by the applicant who is responsible, when the responsible person in charge is absent from the supervised consumption site, for ensuring that every person or class of persons who is exempted for a medical purpose under subsection (2) from the application of all or any of the provisions of this Act or the regulations complies with any terms and conditions specified by the Minister in the exemption when they are at the site.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><MarginalNote>芒聙聹designated criminal offence芒聙聺<br />脗芦 <I>infraction d脙漏sign脙漏e en mati脙篓re criminelle</I> 脗禄<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0">芒聙聹designated criminal offence芒聙聺 means</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>a</I>) an offence involving the financing of terrorism against any of sections 83.02 to 83.04 of the <I>Criminal Code</I>;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>b</I>) an offence involving fraud against any of sections 380 to 382 of the <I>Criminal Code</I>;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>c</I>) the offence of laundering proceeds of crime against section 462.31 of the <I>Criminal Code</I>;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>d</I>) an offence involving a criminal organization against any of sections 467.11 to 467.13 of the <I>Criminal Code</I>; or</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>e</I>) a conspiracy or an attempt to commit, being an accessory after the fact in relation to, or any counselling in relation to, an offence referred to in any of paragraphs (<I>a</I>) to (<I>d</I>).</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><MarginalNote>芒聙聹designated drug offence芒聙聺<br />脗芦 <I>infraction d脙漏sign脙漏e en mati脙篓re de drogue</I> 脗禄<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0">芒聙聹designated drug offence芒聙聺 means</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>a</I>) an offence against section 39, 44.2, 44.3, 48, 50.2 or 50.3 of the <I>Food and Drugs Act</I>, as those provisions read immediately before May 14, 1997;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>b</I>) an offence against section 4, 5, 6, 19.1 or 19.2 of the <I>Narcotic Control Act</I>, as those provisions read immediately before May 14, 1997;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>c</I>) an offence under Part I of this Act, except subsection 4(1); or</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>d</I>) a conspiracy or an attempt to commit, being an accessory after the fact in relation to, or any counselling in relation to, an offence referred to in any of paragraphs (<I>a</I>) to (<I>c</I>).</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><MarginalNote>芒聙聹illicit substance芒聙聺<br />脗芦 <I>substance illicite</I> 脗禄<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0">芒聙聹illicit substance芒聙聺 means a controlled substance that is obtained in a manner not authorized under this Act.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><MarginalNote>芒聙聹key staff members芒聙聺<br />脗芦 <I>principaux membres du personnel</I> 脗禄<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0">芒聙聹key staff members芒聙聺 means the persons designated by the applicant who are responsible for the direct supervision, at the supervised consumption site, of the consumption of an illicit substance by every person or class of persons who is exempted for a medical purpose under subsection (2) from the application of all or any of the provisions of this Act or the regulations.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><MarginalNote>芒聙聹local government芒聙聺<br />脗芦 <I>administration locale</I> 脗禄<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0">芒聙聹local government芒聙聺 includes</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>a</I>) a council of an incorporated city, metropolitan area, town, village or other municipality;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>b</I>) an authority responsible for delivering municipal services to an unincorporated city, metropolitan area, town, village or other municipality;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>c</I>) a council of the band, as that term is defined in subsection 2(1) of the <I>Indian Act</I>; and</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>d</I>) a government of a band that is a party to a comprehensive self-government agreement that is given effect by an Act of Parliament.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><MarginalNote>芒聙聹municipality芒聙聺<br />脗芦 <I>municipalit脙漏</I> 脗禄<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0">芒聙聹municipality芒聙聺 includes</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>a</I>) the geographical area of an incorporated or unincorporated city, metropolitan area, town, village or other municipality;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>b</I>) a reserve and designated lands, as those terms are defined in subsection 2(1) of the <I>Indian Act</I>; and</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>c</I>) lands that are subject to a comprehensive self-government agreement that is given effect by an Act of Parliament.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><MarginalNote>芒聙聹responsible person in charge芒聙聺<br />脗芦 <I>personne responsable</I> 脗禄<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0">芒聙聹responsible person in charge芒聙聺 means the person, designated by the applicant, who is responsible, when the person is at the supervised consumption site, for ensuring that every person or class of persons who is exempted for a medical purpose under subsection (2) from the application of all or any of the provisions of this Act or the regulations complies with the terms and conditions specified by the Minister in the exemption when they are at the site.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><MarginalNote>芒聙聹supervised consumption site芒聙聺<br />脗芦 <I>site de consommation supervis脙漏e</I> 脗禄<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0">芒聙聹supervised consumption site芒聙聺 means a location specified in the terms and conditions of an exemption, granted by the Minister under subsection (2) for a medical purpose, that allows any person or class of persons described in the exemption to engage in certain activities in relation to an illicit substance within a supervised and controlled environment.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Exemption by Minister<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(2) The Minister may, on any terms and conditions that the Minister considers necessary, exempt from the application of all or any of the provisions of this Act or the regulations, other than this section, if, in the opinion of the Minister, the exemption is necessary for a medical, law enforcement or prescribed purpose</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>a</I>) any person or class of persons in relation to a controlled substance or precursor that is obtained in a manner not authorized under this Act; or</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>b</I>) any controlled substance or precursor or any class of either of them that is obtained in a manner not authorized under this Act.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Information to accompany application<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(3) The Minister may consider an application for an exemption for a medical purpose under subsection (2) that would allow certain activities to take place at a supervised consumption site only after the following have been submitted:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>a</I>) scientific evidence demonstrating that there is a medical benefit to individual or public health associated with access to activities undertaken at supervised consumption sites;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>b</I>) a letter from the provincial minister who is responsible for health in the province in which the site would be located that</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="4" FirstLineIndent="0">(i) outlines his or her opinion on the proposed activities at the site,</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="4" FirstLineIndent="0">(ii) describes how those activities are integrated within the provincial health care system, and</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="4" FirstLineIndent="0">(iii) provides information about access to drug treatment services, if any, that are available in the province for persons who would use the site;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>c</I>) a letter from the local government of the municipality in which the site would be located that outlines its opinion on the proposed activities at the site, including any concerns with respect to public health or safety;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>d</I>) a description by the applicant of the measures that have been taken or will be taken to address any relevant concerns outlined in the letter referred to in paragraph (<I>c</I>);</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>e</I>) a letter from the head of the police force that is responsible for providing policing services to the municipality in which the site would be located that outlines his or her opinion on the proposed activities at the site, including any concerns with respect to public safety and security;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>f</I>) a description by the applicant of the proposed measures, if any, to address any relevant concerns outlined in the letter referred to in paragraph (<I>e</I>);</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>g</I>) a letter from the lead health professional, in relation to public health, of the government of the province in which the site would be located that outlines their opinion on the proposed activities at the site;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>h</I>) a letter from the provincial minister responsible for public safety in the province in which the site would be located that outlines his or her opinion on the proposed activities at the site;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>i</I>) a description of the potential impacts of the proposed activities at the site on public safety, including the following:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="4" FirstLineIndent="0">(i) information, if any, on crime and public nuisance in the vicinity of the site and information on crime and public nuisance in the municipalities in which supervised consumption sites are located,</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="4" FirstLineIndent="0">(ii) information, if any, on the public consumption of illicit substances in the vicinity of the site and information on the public consumption of illicit substances in the municipalities in which supervised consumption sites are located, and</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="4" FirstLineIndent="0">(iii) information, if any, on the presence of inappropriately discarded drug-related litter in the vicinity of the site and information on the presence of inappropriately discarded drug-related litter in the municipalities in which supervised consumption sites are located;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>j</I>) law enforcement research or statistics, if any, in relation to the information required under subparagraphs (<I>i</I>)(i) to (iii);</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>k</I>) relevant information, including trends, if any, on the number of persons who consume illicit substances in the vicinity of the site and in the municipality in which the site would be located;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>l</I>) relevant information, including trends, if any, on the number of persons with infectious diseases that may be in relation to the consumption of illicit substances in the vicinity of the site and in the municipality in which the site would be located;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>m</I>) relevant information, including trends, if any, on the number of deaths, if any, due to overdose 芒聙聰 in relation to activities that would take place at the site 芒聙聰 that have occurred in the vicinity of the site and in the municipality in which the site would be located;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>n</I>) official reports, if any, relevant to the establishment of a supervised consumption site, including any coroner芒聙聶s reports;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>o</I>) a report of the consultations held with the professional licensing authorities for physicians and for nurses for the province in which the site would be located that contains each authority芒聙聶s opinion on the proposed activities at the site;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>p</I>) a report of the consultations held with a broad range of community groups from the municipality in which the site would be located that includes</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="4" FirstLineIndent="0">(i) a summary of the opinions of those groups on the proposed activities at the site,</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="4" FirstLineIndent="0">(ii) copies of all written submissions received, and</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="4" FirstLineIndent="0">(iii) a description of the steps that will be taken to address any relevant concerns that were raised during the consultations;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>q</I>) a financing plan that demonstrates the feasibility and sustainability of operating the site;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>r</I>) a description of the drug treatment services available at the site, if any, for persons who would use the site and the information that would be made available to those persons in relation to drug treatment services available elsewhere;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>s</I>) relevant information, including trends, on loitering in a public place that may be related to certain activities involving illicit substances, on trafficking of controlled substances and on minor offence rates in the vicinity of the site, if any;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>t</I>) information on any public health emergency in the vicinity of the site or in the municipality in which the site would be located that may be in relation to activities involving illicit substances as declared by a competent authority with respect to public health, if any;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>u</I>) a description of the measures that will be taken to minimize the diversion of controlled substances or precursors and the risks to the health and the safety and security of persons at the site, or in the vicinity of the site, including staff members, which measures must include the establishment of procedures</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="4" FirstLineIndent="0">(i) to dispose of controlled substances, precursors, and any thing that facilitates their consumption, including how to transfer them to a police officer,</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="4" FirstLineIndent="0">(ii) to control access to the site, and</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="4" FirstLineIndent="0">(iii) to prevent the loss or theft of controlled substances and precursors;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>v</I>) a description of record keeping procedures for the disposal, loss, theft and transfer of controlled substances and <keep>precursors</keep> 芒聙聰 and any thing that facilitates their consumption 芒聙聰 left at the site;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>w</I>) the name, title and resum脙漏, including relevant education and training, of the proposed responsible person in charge, of each of their proposed alternate responsible persons, and of each of the other proposed key staff members;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>x</I>) a document issued by a Canadian police force in relation to each person referred to in paragraph (<I>w</I>), stating whether, in the 10 years before the day on which the application is made, in respect of a designated drug offence or a designated criminal offence, the person was</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="4" FirstLineIndent="0">(i) convicted as an adult,</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="4" FirstLineIndent="0">(ii) convicted as a young person in ordinary court, as those terms were defined in subsection 2(1) of the <I>Young Offenders Act</I>, chapter Y-1 of the Revised Statutes of Canada, 1985, immediately before that Act was repealed, or</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="4" FirstLineIndent="0">(iii) a young person who received an adult sentence, as those terms are defined in subsection 2(1) of the <I>Youth Criminal Justice Act</I>;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>y</I>) if any of the persons referred to in paragraph (<I>w</I>) has ordinarily resided in a country other than Canada in the 10 years before the day on which the application is made, a document issued by a police force of that country stating whether in that period that person</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="4" FirstLineIndent="0">(i) was convicted as an adult for an offence committed in that country that, if committed in Canada, would have constituted a designated drug offence or a designated criminal offence, or</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="4" FirstLineIndent="0">(ii) received a sentence 芒聙聰 for an offence they committed in that country when they were at least 14 years old but less than 18 years old that, if committed in Canada, would have constituted a designated drug offence or a designated criminal offence 芒聙聰 that was longer than the maximum youth sentence that could have been imposed under the <I>Youth Criminal Justice Act</I> for such an offence;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>z</I>) any other information that the Minister considers relevant to the consideration of the application; and</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>z.1</I>) any prescribed information that is submitted in the prescribed manner.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Information to accompany subsequent application<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(4) The Minister may consider an application for an exemption for a medical purpose under subsection (2) that would allow certain activities to continue to take place at an existing supervised consumption site only after, in addition to the information referred to in paragraphs (3)(<I>a</I>) to (<I>z.1</I>), the following have been submitted:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>a</I>) evidence, if any, of any variation in crime rates in the vicinity of the site during the period beginning on the day on which the first exemption was granted under subsection (2) in relation to the site and ending on the day on which the application is submitted; and</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>b</I>) evidence, if any, of any impacts of the activities at the site on individual or public health during that period.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Principles<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(5) The Minister may only grant an exemption for a medical purpose under subsection (2) to allow certain activities to take place at a supervised consumption site in exceptional circumstances and after having considered the following principles:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>a</I>) illicit substances may have serious health effects;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>b</I>) adulterated controlled substances may pose health risks;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>c</I>) the risks of overdose are inherent to the use of certain illicit substances;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>d</I>) strict controls are required, given the inherent health risks associated with controlled substances that may alter mental processes;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>e</I>) organized crime profits from the use of illicit substances; and</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>f</I>) criminal activity often results from the use of illicit substances.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Notice<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(6) The Minister may give notice of any application, in the form and manner determined by the Minister, for an exemption for a medical purpose under subsection (2) to allow certain activities to take place at a supervised consumption site. Members of the public have 90 days after the day on which the notice is given to provide the Minister with comments.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:COMING INTO FORCE--><Para TopMargin="10" Bold="Yes" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">COMING INTO FORCE</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Order in council<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>6.</B> The provisions of this Act come into force on a day or days to be fixed by order of the Governor in Council.</Para></Block><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="BPT_ImprintE"><br /><br />Published under authority of the Speaker of the House of Commons</Para></Block><Block Align="Yes" LineCnt="N"><Para NoLineBreak="Yes" NoHtml="Yes" Leading="0" Size="0" TopMargin="0" BottomMargin="0">脗聞</Para></Block></Bill_Part></Bill>