﻿<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><Bill RHead_reign="62-63-64 Eliz. II" RHead_ParlYear="2013-2014-2015" DocumentTitle="BILL C-247" Bill_No="C-247" Document_No="411294" xml:lang="EN" Bill_Type="Non-amending" Stage_Name="Assented-to" Reprint="No" xml:space="preserve" ChapterNo_E="C. 15" ChapterNo_F="ch. 15" Bill-Origin="commons"><Bill_Part Part_Type="Cover" CountLines="No"><Block><Para TopMargin="24" Size="9" Leading="10" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0" TextAlign="Center">Second Session, Forty-first Parliament,</Para></Block><Block><Para Size="9" Leading="10" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0" TextAlign="Center">62-63-64 Elizabeth II, 2013-2014-2015</Para></Block><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="COV@StatutesTitle">STATUTES OF CANADA 2015<br />CHAPTER 15</Para></Block><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="CovLongTitle">An Act to provide that the Department of Employment and Social Development is the main point of contact with the Government of Canada in respect of the death of a Canadian citizen or resident</Para></Block><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="COV_StageLine"></Para></Block><Block><Para BottomMargin="14" Size="11" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0" Bold="Yes" TextAlign="Center">ASSENTED TO</Para></Block><Block><Para Size="8" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0" TextAlign="Center">18th JUNE, 2015</Para></Block><Block><Para TopMargin="4" Size="8" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0" TextAlign="Center">BILL C-247</Para></Block><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="COV_StageLine"></Para></Block></Bill_Part><Bill_Part CountLines="No" Part_Type="InsideCover"><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="BPT_InsideCoverE">Available on the Parliament of Canada Web Site at the following address:<br /><B>http://www.parl.gc.ca</B></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><Para TopMargin="108" BottomMargin="4" Size="10" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">SUMMARY</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" Size="8" Leading="9" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">This enactment requires the Minister of Employment and Social Development to implement measures necessary to establish the Department of Employment and Social Development as the main point of contact with the Government of Canada in respect of matters relating to the death of a Canadian citizen or resident that pertain to the use of that person's social insurance number.</Para></Block></Bill_Part><Bill_Part Part_Type="MainText" CountLines="No" RunningHead_E="Main Point of Contact with the Government of Canada in case of Death"><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="MAIN@RoyalAssentTitle">62-63-64 ELIZABETH II</Para></Block><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="MAIN@RoyalAssentTitle">——————</Para></Block><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="MAIN@RoyalAssentTitle">CHAPTER 15</Para></Block><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="LongTitleAssent">An Act to provide that the Department of Employment and Social Development is the main point of contact with the Government of Canada in respect of the death of a Canadian citizen or resident</Para></Block><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="MAIN@RoyalAssentDate">[<I>Assented to 18th June, 2015</I>]</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><MarginalNote>Preamble<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">Whereas the Department of Employment and Social Development offers Canadians a point of access to a wide range of government services and programs either in person, by phone, by Internet or by mail;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">And whereas it is desirable to improve services to Canadians by providing those Canadians who have recently lost a loved one with a point of contact for the Government of Canada in respect of matters relating to the death of that person that pertain to the use of that person’s social insurance number;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">Now, therefore, Her Majesty, by and with the advice and consent of the Senate and House of Commons of Canada, enacts as follows:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:SHORT TITLE--><Para TopMargin="10" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">SHORT TITLE</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Short title<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>1.</B> This Act may be cited as the <I>Main Point of Contact with the Government of Canada in case of Death Act</I>.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:MANDATE--><Para TopMargin="10" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">MANDATE</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Main point of contact<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>2.</B> (1) The Minister of Employment and Social Development must implement measures necessary to establish the Department of Employment and Social Development as the main point of contact with the Government of Canada in respect of matters relating to the death of a Canadian citizen or resident that pertain to the use of that person’s social insurance number, so that no person is required to communicate directly with all persons to whom information about that deceased citizen or resident may be made available under subsection 28.2(5) or subsection 35(1) of the <I>Department of Employment and Social Development Act</I>.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Information about deceased citizen or resident — Commission<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(2) On receiving notification of the death of a Canadian citizen or resident, the Canada Employment Insurance Commission must, if it may make information relating to that deceased citizen or resident available to any persons under subsection 28.2(5) of the <I>Department of Employment and Social Development Act</I>, do so, subject to the conditions that would apply if the Commission were to make that information available under that subsection. </Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Information about deceased citizen or resident — Minister<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(3) On receiving notification of the death of a Canadian citizen or resident, the Minister of Employment and Social Development must, if the Minister may make information relating to the deceased citizen or resident that pertains to the use of their social insurance number available to a minister or public officer of a prescribed federal institution, under subsection 35(1) of the <I>Department of Employment and Social Development Act</I>, do so, subject to the conditions referred to in that subsection.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Deeming provision<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(4) For the purpose of subsections 28.2(6) or 35(2) of the <I>Department of Employment and Social Development Act</I>, the information made available to any person under subsection (2) or (3), is deemed to have been obtained, respectively, under subsection 28.2(5) or 35(1) of that Act.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:REGULATIONS--><Para TopMargin="10" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">REGULATIONS</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Regulations<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>3.</B> The Governor in Council may make regulations for carrying out the purposes and provisions of this Act.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:ANNUAL REPORT--><Para TopMargin="10" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">ANNUAL REPORT</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Annual report<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>4.</B> (1) The Minister of Employment and Social Development must, after the end of every fiscal year, report on the implementation of the measures referred to in section 2 during that fiscal year. </Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Tabling in Parliament<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(2) The Minister must cause the information relating to the implementation of the measures to be laid before each House of Parliament during the fiscal year after the fiscal year to which the information relates.</Para></Block><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="BPT_ImprintE"><br /><br />Published under authority of the Speaker of the House of Commons</Para></Block><Block Align="Yes" LineCnt="N"><Para NoLineBreak="Yes" NoHtml="Yes" Leading="0" Size="0" TopMargin="0" BottomMargin="0"></Para></Block></Bill_Part></Bill>