茂禄驴<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><Bill RHead_reign="62-63 Eliz. II" RHead_ParlYear="2013-2014" DocumentTitle="BILL C-25" Bill_No="C-25" Document_No="90713" xml:lang="EN" Bill_Type="Non-amending" Stage_Name="Assented-to" Reprint="No" xml:space="preserve" ChapterNo_E="C. 18" ChapterNo_F="ch. 18" Bill-Origin="commons"><Bill_Part Part_Type="Cover" CountLines="No"><Block><Para TopMargin="24" Size="9" Leading="10" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0" TextAlign="Center">Second Session, Forty-first Parliament,</Para></Block><Block><Para Size="9" Leading="10" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0" TextAlign="Center">62-63 Elizabeth II, 2013-2014</Para></Block><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="COV@StatutesTitle">STATUTES OF CANADA 2014<br />CHAPTER 18</Para></Block><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="CovLongTitle">An Act respecting the Qalipu Mi芒聙聶kmaq First Nation Band Order</Para></Block><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="COV_StageLine"></Para></Block><Block><Para BottomMargin="14" Size="11" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0" Bold="Yes" TextAlign="Center">ASSENTED TO</Para></Block><Block><Para Size="8" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0" TextAlign="Center">19th JUNE, 2014</Para></Block><Block><Para TopMargin="4" Size="8" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0" TextAlign="Center">BILL C-25</Para></Block><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="COV_StageLine"></Para></Block></Bill_Part><Bill_Part CountLines="No" Part_Type="InsideCover"><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="BPT_InsideCoverE">Available on the Parliament of Canada Web Site at the following address:<br /><B>http://www.parl.gc.ca</B></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><Para TopMargin="108" BottomMargin="4" Size="10" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">SUMMARY</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" Size="8" Leading="9" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">This enactment grants to the Governor in Council the power to amend the <I>Qalipu Mi芒聙聶kmaq First Nation Band Order</I>.</Para></Block></Bill_Part><Bill_Part Part_Type="MainText" CountLines="No" RunningHead_E="Qalipu Mi芒聙聶kmaq First Nation"><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="MAIN@RoyalAssentTitle">62-63 ELIZABETH II</Para></Block><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="MAIN@RoyalAssentTitle">芒聙聰芒聙聰芒聙聰芒聙聰芒聙聰芒聙聰</Para></Block><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="MAIN@RoyalAssentTitle">CHAPTER 18</Para></Block><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="LongTitleAssent">An Act respecting the Qalipu Mi芒聙聶kmaq First Nation Band Order</Para></Block><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="MAIN@RoyalAssentDate">[<I>Assented to 19th June, 2014</I>]</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Preamble<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">Whereas on June 23, 2008, the Government of Canada and the Federation of Newfoundland Indians entered into the Agreement for the Recognition of the Qalipu Mi芒聙聶kmaq Band;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">Whereas that Agreement provides for a process of enrolment for the Mi芒聙聶kmaq Group of Indians of Newfoundland, which consists of the Mi芒聙聶kmaq groups of Indians situated at various locations on the island of Newfoundland, and for that Group to be declared to be a band for the purposes of the <I>Indian Act</I>;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">Whereas the intention of the parties to the Agreement was to enable the enrolment of individuals who, on that date, self-identified as members of the Group, were recognized as such and had a current and substantial connection with one or more of the Mi芒聙聶kmaq communities identified in the Agreement;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">Whereas on September 22, 2011, the Governor in Council made the <I>Qalipu Mi芒聙聶kmaq First Nation Band Order</I>;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">Whereas on June 30, 2013, the parties to the Agreement entered into a Supplemental Agreement to clarify how to apply certain clauses of the June 23, 2008 Agreement and to ensure the fair and equal application of the enrolment criteria to all applicants;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">Whereas the Supplemental Agreement provides that the Enrolment Committee, consisting of representatives of both parties and an independent chair jointly selected by both parties, will assess enrolment applications in accordance with the Agreement and the Supplemental Agreement and will provide the parties with a new and final Founding Members List, which will form the basis for a recommendation to the Governor in Council to amend the schedule to the <I>Qalipu Mi芒聙聶kmaq First Nation Band Order</I>;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">And whereas it is desirable to grant to the Governor in Council the power to amend the <I>Qalipu Mi芒聙聶kmaq First Nation Band Order</I> so that it reflects the intention of the parties to the Agreement and the Supplemental Agreement;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">Now therefore, Her Majesty, by and with the advice and consent of the Senate and House of Commons of Canada, enacts as follows:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Short title<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>1.</B> This Act may be cited as the <I>Qalipu Mi芒聙聶kmaq First Nation Act</I>.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Definitions<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>2.</B> In this Act, 芒聙聹band芒聙聺 has the same meaning as in subsection 2(1) of the <I>Indian Act</I>, and 芒聙聹council of a band芒聙聺 has the same meaning as 芒聙聹council of the band芒聙聺 in that subsection.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Order in council<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>3.</B> The Governor in Council may, by order, amend the <I>Qalipu Mi芒聙聶kmaq First Nation Band Order</I>, in particular to add the name of a person to, or remove the name of a person from, the schedule to that Order, along with the person芒聙聶s date of birth.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>No liability<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>4.</B> (1) No person or entity has a right to claim or receive any compensation, damages or indemnity from Her Majesty in right of Canada, any employee or agent of Her Majesty, a band, a council of a band or any other person or entity only because any person芒聙聶s name, or any person芒聙聶s date of birth, was omitted or removed from the schedule to the <I>Qalipu Mi芒聙聶kmaq First Nation Band Order</I>.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Exception<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(2) Nothing in subsection (1) abrogates, or derogates from, any agreement in force entered into among Her Majesty in right of Canada, the Qalipu Mi芒聙聶kmaq First Nation and the Federation of Newfoundland Indians.</Para></Block><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="BPT_ImprintE"><br /><br />Published under authority of the Speaker of the House of Commons</Para></Block><Block Align="Yes" LineCnt="N"><Para NoLineBreak="Yes" NoHtml="Yes" Leading="0" Size="0" TopMargin="0" BottomMargin="0">脗聞</Para></Block></Bill_Part></Bill>