﻿<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><Bill RHead_reign="60 Eliz. II" RHead_ParlYear="2011" DocumentTitle="BILL C-265" Bill_No="C-265" Document_No="411274" xml:lang="EN" Bill_Type="Non-amending" Stage_Name="First-Reading-House" Reprint="No" xml:space="preserve" ChapterNo_E="C. " ChapterNo_F="ch. " Bill-Origin="commons"><Bill_Part Part_Type="Cover" CountLines="No"><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="CovBillNo">C-265</Para></Block><Block><Para TopMargin="24" Size="9" Leading="10" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0" TextAlign="Center">First Session, Forty-first Parliament,</Para></Block><Block><Para Size="9" Leading="10" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0" TextAlign="Center">60 Elizabeth II, 2011</Para></Block><Block><Para TopMargin="48" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0" Bold="Yes" TextAlign="Center">HOUSE OF COMMONS OF CANADA</Para></Block><Block><Para TopMargin="42" Size="18" Leading="20" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0" Bold="Yes" TextAlign="Center">BILL C-265</Para></Block><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="CovLongTitle">An Act to establish criteria and conditions in respect of funding for post-secondary education programs  in order to ensure the quality, accessibility, public administration and accountability of those programs</Para></Block><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="COV_StageLine"></Para></Block><Block><Para Size="9" AllCaps="Yes" Hyphenate="OFF">first reading, June 23, 2011</Para></Block><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="COV_StageLine"></Para></Block><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="Cov_StartBox"></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes"><Para Style="Cov_Box_Heading">NOTE</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes"><Para Style="Cov_Box_Para" TextAlign="Justify">2nd Session, 41st Parliament</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes"><Para Style="Cov_Box_Para" TextAlign="Justify">This bill was introduced during the First Session of the 41st Parliament. Pursuant to the Standing Orders of the House of Commons, it is deemed to have been considered and approved at all stages completed at the time of prorogation of the First Session. The number of the bill remains unchanged.</Para></Block><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="Cov_EndBox"></Para></Block><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="Cover_Sponsors"><SC SC_PerCent="85">Ms. Sitsabaiesan</SC></Para></Block><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="Cover_DocNo">411274</Para></Block></Bill_Part><Bill_Part CountLines="No" Part_Type="InsideCover"><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="BPT_InsideCoverE">Available on the Parliament of Canada Web Site at the following address:<br /><B>http://www.parl.gc.ca</B></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><Para TopMargin="108" BottomMargin="4" Size="10" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">SUMMARY</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" Size="8" Leading="9" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">This enactment establishes criteria and conditions in respect of funding for post-secondary education programs to ensure the quality, accessibility, public administration and accountability of such programs before payments are made to a province by the Government of Canada in support of those programs. It also requires the Minister of Human Resources and Skills Development to establish a framework for the division of the total Canada Social Transfer entitlement into two distinct components, the first to be provided to the provinces for the purpose of funding programs targeting social assistance and social services, and the second to be provided to the provinces solely for the purposes of post-secondary education.</Para></Block></Bill_Part><Bill_Part Part_Type="MainText" CountLines="Yes" RunningHead_E="Canada Post-Secondary Education"><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="MainText_DocNo">411274</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes"><Para Style="Session_Reign">1st Session, 41st Parliament,</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes"><Para Style="Session_Reign">60 Elizabeth II, 2011</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes"><Para Style="MainBillOrigin">house of commons of canada</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes"><Para Bold="Yes" Style="MAIN@BillNo_Title">BILL C-265</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes"><Para Style="MAIN@ti;04">An Act to establish criteria and conditions in respect of funding for post-secondary education programs  in order to ensure the quality, accessibility, public administration and accountability of those programs</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Preamble<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">Whereas the Parliament of Canada recognizes that post-secondary education has an important role in the economic, social, cultural and political development of Canada and in the learning and development opportunities of individual Canadians;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">Whereas the Parliament of Canada wishes to ensure access by all academically  capable applicants to a public post-secondary educational  institution that has been sufficiently resourced to accommodate those applicants;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">Whereas the Parliament of Canada is committed to protecting the quality of post-<keep>secondary</keep> education throughout Canada and to facilitating access to post-secondary education for all academically capable applicants</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">(<I>a</I>) by protecting the principles of free and independent academic inquiry, academic freedom, and the academic and intellectual autonomy of post-secondary educational institutions;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">(<I>b</I>) by promoting quality in teaching and research;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">(<I>c</I>) by encouraging and strengthening the present teaching and research capacities of post-secondary educational institutions and by ensuring the integrity and independence of that work;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">(<I>d</I>) by protecting the right of all academically capable applicants to open and equal access to post-secondary education;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">(<I>e</I>) by encouraging measures that remove barriers to post-secondary education due to socio-economic status or membership in a group or class of persons not fully served by existing post-secondary education programs; and</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">(<I>f</I>) by developing and maintaining financial assistance programs for students;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">And whereas the Parliament of Canada wishes to encourage the development of post-secondary education by assisting the provinces in meeting the costs of that education;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">Now, therefore, Her Majesty, by and with the advice and consent of the Senate and House of Commons of Canada, enacts as follows:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:SHORT TITLE--><Para TopMargin="10" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">SHORT TITLE</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Short Title<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>1.</B> This Act may be cited as the <I>Canada Post-Secondary Education Act</I>.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:INTERPRETATION--><Para TopMargin="10" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">INTERPRETATION</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Definitions<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>2.</B> The following definitions apply in this Act.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><MarginalNote>“cash contribution”<br />« <I>contribution pécuniaire</I> »<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0">“cash contribution” means the cash contribution in respect of post-secondary education that may be made to a province under section 6.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><MarginalNote>“Minister”<br />« <I>ministre</I> »<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0">“Minister” means the Minister of Human Resources and Skills Development.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><MarginalNote>“post-secondary education”<br />« <I>enseignement postsecondaire</I> »<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0">“post-secondary education” means,  in relation to a province,  every course of study in the province that requires for admission a secondary school diploma or equivalent, is of not less than 24 weeks’ duration, and has been certified as a course of study at a post-secondary level by such person or persons as may be designated by the provincial minister.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><MarginalNote>“post-secondary education services”<br />« <I>services d'enseignement postsecondaire</I> »<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0">“post-secondary education services” means the post-secondary educational services provided within a province.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><MarginalNote>“provincial minister”<br />« <I>ministre provincial</I> »<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0">“provincial minister” means the minister responsible for post-secondary education in a province.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><MarginalNote>“Standing Committee”<br />« <I>comité permanent</I> »<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0">“Standing Committee” means the standing committee of the House of Commons that normally considers matters related to human resources and skills development.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:ANNUAL CONTRIBUTION--><Para TopMargin="10" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">ANNUAL CONTRIBUTION</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Cash contribution payable<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>3.</B> (1) Subject to this Act, a full cash contribution is payable by Canada to each province for each fiscal year.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Non-derogation<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(2) For greater certainty, this Act does not abrogate, derogate from or otherwise impair any of the powers, rights, privileges or authorities vested in Canada or the provinces under the <I>Constitution Act, 1867</I>.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:PURPOSE--><Para TopMargin="10" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">PURPOSE</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Purpose<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>4.</B> The purpose of this Act is to establish criteria and conditions that must be satisfied  before a full cash contribution may be made to a province in respect of post-secondary education programs.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:EXEMPTION--><Para TopMargin="10" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">EXEMPTION</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Exemption<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>5.</B> Recognizing the unique nature of the jurisdiction of the Government of Quebec with regard to education, and despite any other provision of this Act, the Government of Quebec may choose to be exempted from the application of this Act and must, if it chooses to do so, receive an unconditional payment of the full cash contribution that would otherwise be paid under section 6.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:CASH CONTRIBUTION--><Para TopMargin="10" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">CASH CONTRIBUTION</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Cash contribution<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>6.</B> (1) The Minister of Finance may make a cash contribution directly to a province in each fiscal year to support the post-secondary education services of the province if  the following criteria are satisfied:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>a</I>) the operators of the post-secondary educational institutions in the province are accountable to the government of the prov- <keep>ince for</keep> the administration and operation of the post-secondary education services; and</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>b</I>) the post-secondary education services provided in the province are of a high quality, publicly administered and accessible.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Accountability<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(2) In order to satisfy the criterion relating to accountability, the post-secondary education services of a province must be directly administered by the provincial  government or by an institution that is operated on a not-for-profit basis and that</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>a</I>) is accredited, authorized or designated by the government of the province; </Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>b</I>) reports to that government in respect of the administration and operation of the   services; and</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>c</I>) is subject to a public audit of its accounts and financial transactions by the authority that is responsible under provincial law for auditing the accounts of that government.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Quality<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(3) In order to satisfy the criterion relating to quality, the post-secondary education services of a province must meet the following standards:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>a</I>) those that relate to the environment in which post-secondary education services are provided, including standards that target faculty-to-student ratios; and</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>b</I>) those that target programs and curric- <keep>ula, including</keep> standards designed to protect the principles of  academic freedom and independent academic inquiry.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Public administration<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(4) In order to satisfy the criterion relating to public administration, the post-secondary education services of a province must be provided on a public and not-for-profit basis.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Accessibility<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(5) In order to satisfy the criterion relating to accessibility, the post-secondary education serv- <keep>ices of</keep> a province must be provided on terms and conditions that</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>a</I>) ensure reasonable access to all qualified persons in the province, regardless of socio-economic status or membership in a group or class; and</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>b</I>) ensure that all persons in the province are equally entitled to post-secondary education services appropriate to their needs.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Cash contribution reduced or withheld<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>7.</B> (1) When advised by the Minister that the post-secondary education services of a province do not satisfy a criterion or condition described in section 6 in a fiscal year, the Governor in Council may, by order, if the Governor in Council considers it appropriate</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>a</I>) direct that any cash contribution to that province for a fiscal year be reduced,  with respect to each default, by an amount that the Governor in Council considers to be appropriate having regard to the gravity of the default; or</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>b</I>) direct that the whole of any cash contribution to that province for a fiscal year be withheld.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Order may be repealed<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(2) The Governor in Council may repeal or amend any order made under subsection (1) if the Governor in Council is of the opinion that the repeal or amendment is warranted in the circumstances.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Statement to be laid before Parliament<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(3) A copy of each order made under this section, together with a statement of any findings on which the order was based, must be sent to the government of the province concerned, and the Minister must cause the order and statement to be laid before each House of Parliament on any of the first 15 days on which that House is sitting after the order is made.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Order not to come into force before 30 days<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(4) An order made under subsection (1) must not come into force earlier than 30 days after a copy of the order has been sent to the government of the province concerned under subsection (3).</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Cash contribution reduced or withheld<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(5) In the case of a continuing failure to satisfy a criterion or condition described in subsection 6(1) or (2),  any reduction or withholding of a cash contribution to a province for a fiscal year must be reimposed for the following fiscal year.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Timing<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(6) Any reduction or withholding of a cash contribution under subsection (1) may be imposed in the fiscal year in which the default that gave rise to the reduction or withholding occurred or in the following fiscal year.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:REPORT TO PARLIAMENT--><Para TopMargin="10" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">REPORT TO PARLIAMENT</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Report by Minister<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>8.</B> (1) Within two months after the end of a fiscal year, the Minister must report to the Standing Committee on the administration and operation of this Act during that fiscal year, including</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>a</I>) any initiatives and developments relating to post-secondary education;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>b</I>) the extent to which the post-secondary education objectives of this Act have been satisfied;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>c</I>) the amount of the cash contribution provided to each province under this Act; and</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>d</I>) any recommendations respecting supplementary cash contributions to a province.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Contents of report<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(2) The report must also contain a summary of all information in the possession of the Minister that relates to the extent to which the post-secondary education services of each province satisfied the criteria and conditions described in section 6 during the fiscal year, including but not limited to</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>a</I>) a description of the post-secondary education services provided in each province during that fiscal year; </Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>b</I>) the amount expended by the government of each province during that fiscal year for the <keep>post-secondary</keep> education services;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>c</I>) indicators of availability, such as an analysis of the number of spaces available to groups or classes of persons who, traditionally, have not been served by post-secondary education services;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>d</I>) indicators of affordability, such as average tuition fees charged  in each province;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>e</I>) indicators of quality, such as training requirements, average class size and supplies and facilities; and</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>f</I>) indicators of accessibility, such as eligi- <keep>bility criteria</keep> and the number of students receiving financial aid.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Report to Parliament<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(3) The Standing Committee must review the annual report of the Minister under this Act and shall cause its review and recommendations to be laid before each House of Parliament on any of the first 15 days on which that House is sitting after the review is completed.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Committee may seek advice<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(4) In conducting its review under subsection (3), the Standing Committee may seek the advice and assistance of any department, agency or association.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:DIVISION OF CANADA SOCIAL TRANSFER--><Para TopMargin="10" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">DIVISION OF CANADA SOCIAL TRANSFER</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Division of Canada Social Transfer<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>9.</B> (1) Within six months after the day on which this Act comes into force, the Minister must, after consultation with the provinces and with the intention of developing a long-term and predictable funding formula for federal contributions, establish a framework for the division of the total Canada Social Transfer entitlement into two distinct components, the first to be provided to the provinces for the purpose of funding programs in respect of social assistance and social services, including early childhood development and early learning and child care services, and the second to be provided to the provinces solely for the purposes of post-secondary education.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Implementation<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(2) Within 60 days after this Act comes into force, the Minister must implement any remaining measures that must be taken in order to implement the division of the Canada Social Transfer, including amendments to the  <I>Federal-Provincial Fiscal Arrangements Act</I>.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:REGULATIONS--><Para TopMargin="10" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">REGULATIONS</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Regulations<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>10.</B> The Governor in Council may make regulations for the purpose of carrying the purposes and provisions of this Act into effect, including regulations respecting the information the Minister may require for the purpose of reporting to Parliament under section 8 and for the purpose of implementing section 9.</Para></Block><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="BPT_ImprintE"><br /><br />Published under authority of the Speaker of the House of Commons</Para></Block><Block Align="Yes" LineCnt="N"><Para NoLineBreak="Yes" NoHtml="Yes" Leading="0" Size="0" TopMargin="0" BottomMargin="0"></Para></Block></Bill_Part></Bill>