茂禄驴<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><Bill RHead_reign="60-61 Eliz. II" RHead_ParlYear="2011-2012" DocumentTitle="BILL C-439" Bill_No="C-439" Document_No="411508" xml:lang="EN" Bill_Type="Non-amending" Stage_Name="First-Reading-House" Reprint="No" xml:space="preserve" ChapterNo_E="C. " ChapterNo_F="ch. " Bill-Origin="commons"><Bill_Part Part_Type="Cover" CountLines="No"><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="CovBillNo">C-439</Para></Block><Block><Para TopMargin="24" Size="9" Leading="10" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0" TextAlign="Center">First Session, Forty-first Parliament,</Para></Block><Block><Para Size="9" Leading="10" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0" TextAlign="Center">60-61 Elizabeth II, 2011-2012</Para></Block><Block><Para TopMargin="48" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0" Bold="Yes" TextAlign="Center">HOUSE OF COMMONS OF CANADA</Para></Block><Block><Para TopMargin="42" Size="18" Leading="20" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0" Bold="Yes" TextAlign="Center">BILL C-439</Para></Block><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="CovLongTitle">An Act respecting the rights of air passengers</Para></Block><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="COV_StageLine"></Para></Block><Block><Para Size="9" AllCaps="Yes" Hyphenate="OFF">first reading, June 20, 2012</Para></Block><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="COV_StageLine"></Para></Block><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="Cov_StartBox"></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes"><Para Style="Cov_Box_Heading">NOTE</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes"><Para Style="Cov_Box_Para" TextAlign="Justify">2nd Session, 41st Parliament</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes"><Para Style="Cov_Box_Para" TextAlign="Justify">This bill was introduced during the First Session of the 41st Parliament. Pursuant to the Standing Orders of the House of Commons, it is deemed to have been considered and approved at all stages completed at the time of prorogation of the First Session. The number of the bill remains unchanged.</Para></Block><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="Cov_EndBox"></Para></Block><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="Cover_Sponsors"><SC SC_PerCent="85">Mr. Hyer</SC></Para></Block><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="Cover_DocNo">411508</Para></Block></Bill_Part><Bill_Part CountLines="No" Part_Type="InsideCover"><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="BPT_InsideCoverE">Available on the Parliament of Canada Web Site at the following address:<br /><B>http://www.parl.gc.ca</B></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><Para TopMargin="108" BottomMargin="4" Size="10" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">SUMMARY</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" Size="8" Leading="9" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">This enactment places obligations on Canadian air carriers to provide compensation and other assistance to passengers in certain cases when a flight has been cancelled or delayed, when boarding has been denied, and when an aircraft has remained on the ground for a period of more than an hour at an airport. It also requires those air carriers to disclose all relevant information to the public regarding the pricing of flights and to keep passengers informed regarding any misplaced baggage and any developments in respect of their flights that could have a significant impact on their travel plans.</Para></Block></Bill_Part><Bill_Part Part_Type="MainText" CountLines="Yes" RunningHead_E="Air Passengers' Bill of Rights"><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="MainText_DocNo">411508</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes"><Para Style="Session_Reign">1st Session, 41st Parliament,</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes"><Para Style="Session_Reign">60-61 Elizabeth II, 2011-2012</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes"><Para Style="MainBillOrigin">house of commons of canada</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes"><Para Bold="Yes" Style="MAIN@BillNo_Title">BILL C-439</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes"><Para Style="MAIN@ti;04">An Act respecting the rights of air passengers</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">Her Majesty, by and with the advice and consent of the Senate and House of Commons of Canada, enacts as follows:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:SHORT TITLE--><Para TopMargin="10" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">SHORT TITLE</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Short title<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>1.</B> This Act may be cited as the <I>Air Passengers' Bill of Rights</I>.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:INTERPRETATION--><Para TopMargin="10" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">INTERPRETATION</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Definitions<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>2.</B> The following definitions apply in this Act.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><MarginalNote>芒聙聹aerodrome芒聙聺<br />脗芦 <I>a脙漏rodrome</I> 脗禄<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0">芒聙聹aerodrome芒聙聺 has the same meaning as in subsection 3(1) of the <I>Aeronautics Act</I>.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><MarginalNote>芒聙聹air carrier芒聙聺<br />脗芦 <I>transporteur a脙漏rien</I> 脗禄<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0">芒聙聹air carrier芒聙聺 means any person who operates a domestic service or an international service.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><MarginalNote>芒聙聹air crew芒聙聺<br />脗芦 <I>personnel d'a脙漏ronef</I> 脗禄<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0">芒聙聹air crew芒聙聺 means the flight crew and one or more persons who, under the authority of an air carrier, perform in-flight duties in the passenger cabin of an aircraft of the air carrier.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><MarginalNote>芒聙聹airport芒聙聺<br />脗芦 <I>a脙漏roport</I> 脗禄<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0">芒聙聹airport芒聙聺 means an aerodrome in respect of which a Canadian aviation document is in force.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><MarginalNote>芒聙聹Canadian芒聙聺<br />脗芦 <I>canadien</I> 脗禄<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0">芒聙聹Canadian芒聙聺 has the same meaning as in subsection 55(1) of the <I>Canada Transportation Act</I>.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><MarginalNote>芒聙聹cancellation芒聙聺<br />脗芦 <I>annulation</I> 脗禄<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0">芒聙聹cancellation芒聙聺 means the non-operation of a flight on which at least one seat was reserved for a passenger.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><MarginalNote>芒聙聹denied boarding芒聙聺<br />脗芦 <I>refus d'embarquement</I> 脗禄<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0">芒聙聹denied boarding芒聙聺 means a refusal to allow a passenger to board  a flight, despite the fact that they have a ticket for that flight, except if there are reasonable grounds to deny boarding, such as reasons of health, safety or security or inadequate travel documents.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><MarginalNote>芒聙聹domestic service芒聙聺<br />脗芦 <I>service int脙漏rieur</I> 脗禄<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0">芒聙聹domestic service芒聙聺 means an air service between points in Canada, from and to the same point in Canada or between Canada and a point outside Canada that is not in the territory of another country. </Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><MarginalNote>芒聙聹final destination芒聙聺<br />脗芦 <I>destination finale</I> 脗禄<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0">芒聙聹final destination芒聙聺 means the destination on the ticket presented at the check-in counter or, in the case of directly connecting flights, the destination of the last flight. </Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><MarginalNote>芒聙聹international service芒聙聺<br />脗芦 <I>service international</I> 脗禄<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0">芒聙聹international service芒聙聺 means a scheduled or non-scheduled  air service between Canada and a point in the territory of another country or between a point in the territory of another country and Canada, including international and transborder charters. </Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><MarginalNote>芒聙聹passenger芒聙聺<br />脗芦 <I>passager</I> 脗禄<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0">芒聙聹passenger芒聙聺 means a person, other than a member of the air crew, who uses, or intends to use, an air carrier's domestic service or international service by boarding the air carrier's aircraft pursuant to a valid contract or arrangement.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><MarginalNote>芒聙聹passenger with reduced mobility芒聙聺<br />脗芦 <I>passager 脙聽 mobilit脙漏 r脙漏duite</I> 脗禄<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0">芒聙聹passenger with reduced mobility芒聙聺 means a passenger whose mobility is reduced when using transport because of a physical disability (sensory or locomotory, permanent or tempo- <keep>rary), intellectual</keep> impairment, age or any other cause, and whose situation needs special attention and adaptation to the person's needs of the services made available to all passengers.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><MarginalNote>芒聙聹reservation芒聙聺<br />脗芦 <I>r脙漏servation</I> 脗禄<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0">芒聙聹reservation芒聙聺 means a ticket or other proof that indicates that a seat on a flight has been reserved for a particular passenger by the air carrier.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><MarginalNote>芒聙聹ticket芒聙聺<br />脗芦 <I>billet</I> 脗禄<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0">芒聙聹ticket芒聙聺 means a valid document giving entitlement to transport, or something equivalent in paperless form, including electronic form, issued or authorized by the air carrier or its authorized agent.
</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:APPLICATION--><Para TopMargin="10" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">APPLICATION</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Application<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>3.</B> (1) This Act applies to all operations of Canadian air carriers and to operations of all air carriers that take place in Canada.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Exception<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(2) Despite subsection (1), this Act does not apply in respect of any flight that originates north of sixty degrees north latitude.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Inconsistency or conflict<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(3) Where there is any inconsistency or conflict between the provisions of this Act and any other Act of Parliament or regulations made under that Act, this Act is to prevail to the extent of the inconsistency or conflict.
</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:CANCELLATION--><Para TopMargin="10" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">CANCELLATION</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Rights of passengers<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>4.</B> (1) In case of cancellation of a flight, the air carrier must offer to every affected passenger</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>a</I>) reimbursement or re-routing in accord- ance with section 10;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>b</I>) meals and refreshments in accordance with paragraph 12(1)(<I>a</I>) and means of communication in accordance with paragraph 12(1)(<I>d</I>), as well as, in the event of re-routing in the case where the air carrier reasonably expects that the delay in the departure of a flight will require the passengers to stay overnight at the point of departure, accommodation in accordance with paragraph 12(1)(<I>b</I>) and transportation in accordance with paragraph 12(1)(<I>c</I>); and

</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>c</I>) compensation in accordance with section 9 unless</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="4" FirstLineIndent="0">(i) the passenger was informed of the cancellation at least two weeks before the scheduled time of departure,</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="4" FirstLineIndent="0">(ii) the passenger has accepted in writing the re-routing offered by the air carrier, or</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="4" FirstLineIndent="0">(iii) the air carrier can prove that the cancellation was caused by extraordinary circumstances which could not have been avoided even if all reasonable measures had been taken.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Extraordinary circumstances<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(2) For greater certainty, the extraordinary circumstances referred to in subparagraph <keep>(1)(<I>c</I>)(iii)</keep> include the closing of an airport to aircraft traffic due to weather conditions.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Explanation<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(3) When a passenger is informed of a cancellation, an explanation in writing must be provided to the passenger, including information about other possible transportation. If the air carrier contends that the cancellation was caused by extraordinary circumstances, the explanation must include detailed information about the exact nature of those circumstances.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Burden of proof<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(4) The burden of proof concerning whether and when a passenger has been informed of the cancellation of a flight must rest with the air carrier.
</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Air carrier not responsible<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(5) If the air carrier required to provide services or compensation under subsection (1) is of the opinion that the cancellation of a flight results from a measure or decision taken by an airport authority, the Canadian Air Transport Security Authority, NAV CANADA or the Canada Border Services Agency, it may submit the matter to the Canadian Transportation Agency, which must determine the responsibility of the organization in question and its obligation to refund the air carrier the amounts it had to pay out under that subsection.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:DELAY--><Para TopMargin="10" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">DELAY</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Reasonable expectation of delay<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>5.</B> (1) The air carrier must offer to every affected passenger meals and refreshments in accordance with paragraph 12(1)(<I>a</I>) and means of communication in accordance with paragraph 12(1)(<I>d</I>) if it reasonably expects a flight to be delayed two hours or more beyond its scheduled time of departure.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Overnight stay<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(2) If the air carrier reasonably expects that the delay in the departure of a flight will require the passengers to stay overnight at the point of departure, it must also offer to every affected passenger accommodation in accordance with paragraph 12(1)(<I>b</I>) and transportation  in accord- ance with paragraph 12(1)(<I>c</I>).

</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Air carrier not responsible<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(3) If the air carrier required to provide services or compensation under subsection (1) or (2) is of the opinion that the delay results from a measure or decision taken by an airport authority , the Canadian Air Transport Security Authority, NAV CANADA or the Canada Border Services Agency, it may submit the matter to the Canadian Transportation Agency, which must determine the responsibility of the organization in question and its obligation to refund the air carrier the amounts it had to pay out under subsection (1) or (2).</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Delay of five hours or more<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(4) If the delay in the departure of a flight is five hours or more, the air carrier must also offer to every affected passenger reimbursement in accordance with paragraph 10(1)(<I>a</I>).
</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:TARMAC RIGHTS--><Para TopMargin="10" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">TARMAC RIGHTS</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Aircraft on ground for extended period<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>6.</B> (1) If one or more passengers are on board an aircraft operated by an air carrier for a period of more than one hour while the aircraft is on the ground at an aerodrome, the air carrier must provide passengers with</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>a</I>) electric generation service to provide temporary power for fresh air and lights;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>b</I>) waste removal service in order to service the holding tanks for on-board restrooms;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>c</I>) adequate food and drinking water and other refreshments; and</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>d</I>) an opportunity to disembark from the aircraft if it is possible to do so without causing any undue risk to the health or safety of the passengers or any other person and  to the safe operation of the aircraft or any other aircraft.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Compensation<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(2) The air carrier must pay compensation to every affected passenger in the amount of 100 Canadian dollars for each hour in which one or more of the obligations set out in paragraphs <keep>(1)(<I>a</I>)</keep> to (<I>d</I>) are not met.
</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Amount of compensation<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(3) Despite subsection (2), the amount of compensation provided under this section to a passenger must not exceed the total amount paid by the passenger in respect of the flight for which the passenger boarded the aircraft.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Air carrier not responsible<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(4) If the air carrier required to provide services or compensation under this section is of the opinion that the presence of passengers for more than an hour aboard an aircraft on the ground results from a measure or decision taken by an airport authority, the Canadian Air Transport Security Authority, NAV CANADA or the Canada Border Services Agency, it may submit the matter to the Canadian Transportation Agency, which must determine the responsibility of the organization in question and its obligation to refund the air carrier the amounts it had to pay out under this section.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:DENIAL OF BOARDING--><Para TopMargin="10" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">DENIAL OF BOARDING</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Voluntary surrender of reservations<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>7.</B> If an air carrier finds that it will be necessary to deny boarding on an aircraft as a result of a flight being overbooked, it must immediately determine whether there are any passengers who are willing to voluntarily surrender their reservations in exchange for benefits agreed to by the passenger and the air carrier. Any benefits so provided are in addition to the compensation provided under section 9.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>When boarding may be denied<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>8.</B> (1) If the air carrier determines that there are not enough passengers willing to voluntarily surrender their reservations under section 7 to allow the remaining passengers with reservations to board the flight, the air carrier may deny boarding to certain passengers.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Compensation<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(2) The air carrier must provide compensation in accordance with section 9 to every passenger who is denied boarding.
</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:RIGHT TO COMPENSATION 芒聙聰 CANCELLATION OR DENIED BOARDING--><Para TopMargin="10" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">RIGHT TO COMPENSATION 芒聙聰 CANCELLATION OR DENIED BOARDING</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Amount of compensation<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>9.</B> (1) Every passenger to whom this section applies is to receive compensation in the amount of

</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>a</I>) 250 Canadian dollars for all flights of 1500 kilometres or less;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>b</I>) 400 Canadian dollars for all flights between 1500 and 3500 kilometres; and

</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>c</I>) 600 Canadian dollars for all flights of 3500 kilometres or more.


</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Amount of compensation<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(2) Despite subsection (1), the amount of compensation provided under this section to a passenger in respect of a flight that has been cancelled or a flight in respect of which the passenger has been denied boarding must not exceed the total amount paid by the passenger in respect of the flight.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:RIGHT TO REIMBURSEMENT OR RE-ROUTING 芒聙聰 CANCELLATION OR DELAY--><Para TopMargin="10" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">RIGHT TO REIMBURSEMENT OR RE-ROUTING 芒聙聰 CANCELLATION OR DELAY</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Choice between reimbursement or re-routing<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>10.</B> (1) The air carrier must offer without charge to every passenger to whom this section applies the choice between</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>a</I>) reimbursement of the full cost of the ticket at the price at which it was bought, for the part or parts of the journey not made 芒聙聰 and for the part or parts already made if the flight is no longer serving any purpose in relation to the passenger's original travel plan 芒聙聰 together with, when relevant, a return flight to the first point of departure at the earliest opportunity;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>b</I>) re-routing, under comparable transport conditions, to their final destination at the earliest opportunity; and</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>c</I>) re-routing, under comparable transport conditions, to their final destination at a later date at the passenger's convenience, subject to availability of seats.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Compensation<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(2) If an air carrier fails to comply with subsection (1), it must pay compensation to every affected passenger in the amount of 1000 Canadian dollars. The payment of compensation is in addition to the reimbursement that is paid to the passenger in accordance with paragraph (1)(<I>a</I>).</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Where re-routing is to another airport<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>11.</B> If, in the case where a town, city or region is served by several airports, an air carrier offers a passenger a flight to an airport other than the airport in respect of which the booking was made, the air carrier must also offer to bear the cost of transporting the passenger from that other airport either to the airport for which the booking was made, or to another nearby destination agreed to by the passenger.
</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:RIGHT TO CARE 芒聙聰 CANCELLATION OR DELAY--><Para TopMargin="10" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">RIGHT TO CARE 芒聙聰 CANCELLATION OR DELAY</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Meals, accommodation, etc.<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>12.</B> (1) The air carrier must offer without charge to every passenger to whom this section applies</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>a</I>) meals and refreshments in a reasonable relation to the waiting time;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>b</I>) hotel accommodation in cases where a stay of one or more nights is required;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>c</I>) transportation between the airport and place of accommodation;  and</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>d</I>) a total of two telephone calls, telex or fax messages, or e-mails.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Compensation<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(2) If an air carrier fails to comply with subsection (1), it must pay compensation to every affected passenger in the amount of 250 Canadian dollars.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Particular attention to certain passengers<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>13.</B> (1) In carrying out its obligations under this Act, every air carrier must pay particular attention to</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>a</I>) the needs of unaccompanied children;  and</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>b</I>) the needs of any passenger with reduced mobility and of any person accompanying such a passenger.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Compensation<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(2) If an air carrier fails to comply with subsection (1), it must pay compensation to every affected person in the amount of 250 Canadian dollars.
</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:RIGHT TO BE INFORMED--><Para TopMargin="10" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">RIGHT TO BE INFORMED</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Duty to disclose pricing<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>14.</B> (1) In order to enable a purchaser of an air service to readily determine the total amount to be paid for the service, every air carrier who advertises a price for an air service must</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>a</I>) include in the advertised price all costs to the carrier of providing the service; and</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>b</I>) specify in the advertisement all fees, charges and taxes that are collected by the carrier on behalf of another person in respect of the service.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Penalty<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(2) If an air carrier fails to comply with subsection (1), it must pay an administrative monetary penalty in the amount of 5 000 Canadian dollars for every day the non-compliant advertisement is published or broadcast.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Duty to provide flight information<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>15.</B> (1) If an air carrier acquires any information in respect of the flight of a passenger that could have a significant impact on the travel plans of that passenger, it must make every reasonable effort to provide the passenger with that information within one hour of acquiring it.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Compensation<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(2) If an air carrier fails to comply with subsection (1), it must pay compensation to every affected passenger in the amount of 250 Canadian dollars.

</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Baggage<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>16.</B> (1) If the baggage of a passenger has been misplaced and an air carrier acquires any information in respect of the location of the baggage, the air carrier must, within one hour of acquiring that information, make every reasonable effort to inform the passenger of the location of the baggage and the measures that are being taken to return the baggage to the passenger.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Compensation<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(2) If an air carrier fails to comply with subsection (1), it must pay compensation to every affected passenger in the amount of 50 Canadian dollars.

</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Announcements at airport<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>17.</B> (1) Every air carrier operating at an airport must make announcements at the airport respecting cancellations, delays and diversions of its flights to and from that airport within 10 minutes of becoming aware of these events by means of public audio announcements and posting on airport television monitors.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Penalty<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(2) If an air carrier fails to comply with subsection (1), it must pay an administrative monetary penalty in the amount of 500 Canadian dollars.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Obligation to inform passengers of their rights<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>18.</B> (1) Every air carrier must ensure that at check-in a clearly legible notice containing the following text is displayed in both official languages in a manner clearly visible to passengers:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify"> 

芒聙聹If you are denied boarding, your flight is cancelled or delayed for at least two hours or your baggage has been misplaced, ask at the check-in counter or boarding gate for a written notice setting out the rules for compensation and assistance under the <I>Airline Passengers' Bill of Rights</I>.芒聙聺.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Penalty<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(2) If an air carrier fails to comply with subsection (1), it must pay an administrative monetary penalty in the amount of 500 Canadian dollars.
</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Written notice<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>19.</B> (1) Every air carrier must immediately provide every passenger who has been affected by a denial of boarding, a cancellation, a flight delay of two hours or more or misplaced baggage with a written notice that contains</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>a</I>) the rules for compensation and other assistance that are available to passengers under this Act;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>b</I>) the contact details of the Canadian Transportation Agency; and</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>c</I>) a form on which the passenger may make a claim for compensation and other assistance under this Act.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Compensation<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(2) If an air carrier fails to comply with subsection (1), it must pay compensation to every affected passenger in the amount of 100 Canadian dollars.

</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Visually impaired<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>20.</B> The notices referred to in subsections 18(1) and 19(1) must be provided to blind and visually impaired persons in an appropriate alternative medium.
</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:APPLICATION OF CANADA TRANSPORTATION ACT--><Para TopMargin="10" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">APPLICATION OF <I>CANADA TRANSPORTATION ACT</I></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote><I>Canada Transportation Act</I><br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>21.</B> (1) Sections 178 to 181 of the <I>Canada Transportation Act</I> apply to sections 14, 17 and 18 as if they were provisions designated by the Canadian Transportation Agency under paragraph 177(1)(<I>a</I>) of that Act.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Role of Agency<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(2) 

The Canadian Transportation Agency is responsible for the enforcement of sections 14, 17 and 18, including the collection of the administrative monetary penalties prescribed by those sections.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:MISCELLANEOUS--><Para TopMargin="10" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">MISCELLANEOUS</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Compensation and reimbursement<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>22.</B> Any compensation or reimbursement that is required to be paid under this Act must be paid within seven days in cash, by electronic bank transfer, bank order or bank cheque or, with the signed agreement of the passenger, in travel vouchers or other services.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Measurement of distances<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>23.</B> The distances referred to in this Act must be measured by the great circle route method, which involves measuring the shortest course between two points on the earth芒聙聶s surface.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Annual adjustment<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>24.</B> (1) Every dollar amount specified in this Act with respect to compensation or an administrative monetary penalty is to be adjusted on the first day of every calendar year so that the amount payable is equal to the product obtained by multiplying</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>a</I>) the amount that would have been payable in the previous year</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0">by</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>b</I>) the ratio that the Consumer Price Index for the 12-month period ending on December 31 of the previous year bears to the Consumer Price Index for the 12-month period next before that 12-month period.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Consumer Price Index<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(2) For the purposes of subsection (1), the Consumer Price Index, for any 12-month period, means the average of the Consumer Price Index for Canada as published by Statistics Canada under the authority of the <I>Statistics Act</I>, for each month in that 12-month period.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:OTHER SOURCES OF COMPENSATION--><Para TopMargin="10" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">OTHER SOURCES OF COMPENSATION</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Compensation for passengers<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>25.</B> (1) For greater certainty, nothing in this Act limits the right of a passenger to seek compensation for any financial or other loss that the passenger has incurred in connection with air transportation from any person that the passenger considers to be responsible for that loss.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Compensation for air carriers<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(2) For greater certainty, nothing in this Act limits the right of an air carrier to seek compensation for any liability incurred by the air carrier as a result of the failure to meet obligations imposed by this Act from any person that the air carrier considers to be responsible for that failure.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:REGULATIONS--><Para TopMargin="10" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">REGULATIONS</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Regulations<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>26.</B> (1) The Governor in Council may make regulations in respect of any matter referred to in this Act.

</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>For greater certainty<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(2) For greater certainty, no provision of any regulations made under subsection (1) may negate or diminish the effect of any of the provisions of this Act.
</Para></Block><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="BPT_ImprintE"><br /><br />Published under authority of the Speaker of the House of Commons</Para></Block><Block Align="Yes" LineCnt="N"><Para NoLineBreak="Yes" NoHtml="Yes" Leading="0" Size="0" TopMargin="0" BottomMargin="0">脗聞</Para></Block></Bill_Part></Bill>