﻿<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><Bill RHead_reign="60-61 Eliz. II" RHead_ParlYear="2011-2012" DocumentTitle="BILL C-446" Bill_No="C-446" Document_No="411637" xml:lang="EN" Bill_Type="Non-amending" Stage_Name="First-Reading-House" Reprint="No" xml:space="preserve" ChapterNo_E="C. " ChapterNo_F="ch. " Bill-Origin="commons"><Bill_Part Part_Type="Cover" CountLines="No"><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="CovBillNo">C-446</Para></Block><Block><Para TopMargin="24" Size="9" Leading="10" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0" TextAlign="Center">First Session, Forty-first Parliament,</Para></Block><Block><Para Size="9" Leading="10" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0" TextAlign="Center">60-61 Elizabeth II, 2011-2012</Para></Block><Block><Para TopMargin="48" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0" Bold="Yes" TextAlign="Center">HOUSE OF COMMONS OF CANADA</Para></Block><Block><Para TopMargin="42" Size="18" Leading="20" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0" Bold="Yes" TextAlign="Center">BILL C-446</Para></Block><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="CovLongTitle">An Act to amend the Corrections and Conditional Release Act (blood samples)</Para></Block><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="COV_StageLine"></Para></Block><Block><Para Size="9" AllCaps="Yes" Hyphenate="OFF">first reading, October 2, 2012</Para></Block><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="COV_StageLine"></Para></Block><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="Cov_StartBox"></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes"><Para Style="Cov_Box_Heading">NOTE</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes"><Para Style="Cov_Box_Para" TextAlign="Justify">2nd Session, 41st Parliament</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes"><Para Style="Cov_Box_Para" TextAlign="Justify">This bill was introduced during the First Session of the 41st Parliament. Pursuant to the Standing Orders of the House of Commons, it is deemed to have been considered and approved at all stages completed at the time of prorogation of the First Session. The number of the bill remains unchanged.</Para></Block><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="Cov_EndBox"></Para></Block><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="Cover_Sponsors"><SC SC_PerCent="85">Mr. Leef</SC></Para></Block><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="Cover_DocNo">411637</Para></Block></Bill_Part><Bill_Part CountLines="No" Part_Type="InsideCover"><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="BPT_InsideCoverE">Available on the Parliament of Canada Web Site at the following address:<br /><B>http://www.parl.gc.ca</B></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><Para TopMargin="108" BottomMargin="4" Size="10" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">SUMMARY</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" Size="8" Leading="9" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">This enactment amends the <I>Corrections and Conditional Release Act</I> to establish a procedure by which an employee of the Correctional Service of Canada may apply to a court to have blood samples taken from an inmate of a penitentiary and analyzed when the employee has come in contact with a bodily substance of the inmate.</Para></Block></Bill_Part><Bill_Part Part_Type="MainText" CountLines="Yes" RunningHead_E="Corrections and Conditional Release (blood samples)"><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="MainText_DocNo">411637</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes"><Para Style="Session_Reign">1st Session, 41st Parliament,</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes"><Para Style="Session_Reign">60-61 Elizabeth II, 2011-2012</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes"><Para Style="MainBillOrigin">house of commons of canada</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes"><Para Bold="Yes" Style="MAIN@BillNo_Title">BILL C-446</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes"><Para Style="MAIN@ti;04">An Act to amend the Corrections and Conditional Release Act (blood samples)</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>1992, c. 20<br /></MarginalNote><Para LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">Her Majesty, by and with the advice and consent of the Senate and House of Commons of Canada, enacts as follows:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><change><B>1.</B> The <I>Corrections and Conditional Release Act</I> is amended by adding the following after section 57.1:</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:Taking of blood samples from inmates--><Para TopMargin="10" Italic="Yes" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center"><change>Taking of blood samples from inmates</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><change><B>57.11</B> The following definitions apply in this section and in sections 57.12 to 57.194.</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><MarginalNote>“analyst”<br />« <I>analyste</I> »<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0"><change>“analyst” means any person or person of a class of persons designated by the Attorney General as being qualified to analyze blood samples for the purposes of this section and sections 57.12 to 57.194.</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><MarginalNote>“designated virus”<br />« <I>virus désigné</I> »<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0"><change>“designated virus” means the hepatitis B virus, the hepatitis C virus or a human immunodeficiency virus.</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><MarginalNote>“justice”<br />« <I>juge de paix</I> »<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0"><change>“justice” means a justice of the peace or a provincial court judge.</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><MarginalNote>“peace officer”<br />« <I>agent de la paix</I> »<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0"><change>“peace officer” has the same meaning as in section 2 of the <I>Criminal Code</I>.</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><MarginalNote>“physician’s report”<br />« <I>rapport de médecin</I> »<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0"><change>“physician’s report” means a report that</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0"><change>(<I>a</I>) is made by a qualified medical practitioner who has expertise in occupational and environmental health matters and in protocols and standards of practice in respect of blood-borne pathogens; and</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0"><change>(<I>b</I>) provides an assessment of the risk to the health of a staff member described in section 57.12 as a result of coming into contact with a bodily substance of an inmate.</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><MarginalNote>“provincial court judge”<br />« <I>juge de la cour provinciale</I> »<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0"><change>“provincial court judge”  has the same meaning as in section 2 of the <I>Criminal Code</I>.</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><MarginalNote>“qualified medical practitioner”<br />« <I>médecin qualifié</I> »<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0"><change>“qualified medical practitioner” has the same meaning as in subsection 254(1) of the <I>Criminal Code</I>.</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><MarginalNote>“qualified technician”<br />« <I>technicien qualifié</I> »<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0"><change>“qualified technician” means any person or person of a class of persons designated by the Attorney General as being qualified to take samples of blood for the purposes of this section and sections 57.12 to 57.194.</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Application for warrant<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><change><B>57.12</B> A staff member may apply to a justice for a warrant authorizing the taking of  blood samples from an inmate, in order to determine whether the inmate carries a designated virus, if the staff member believes on reasonable grounds that</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0"><change>(<I>a</I>) the staff member came into contact with a bodily substance of the inmate while in the execution of his or her duties;</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0"><change>(<I>b</I>) the staff member may have become infected with a designated virus as a result of coming into contact with the bodily substance; and</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0"><change>(<I>c</I>) by reason of the lengthy incubation periods for diseases caused by the designated viruses and the methods available for ascertaining the presence of such viruses in the human body, an analysis of the staff member's blood would not accurately determine, in a timely manner, whether he or she had become infected with a designated virus as a result of coming into contact with the bodily substance.</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Appearance<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><change><B>57.13</B> A justice who receives an application under section 57.12 shall cause the staff member and the inmate in question to appear before the justice.</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Issuance of warrant by justice<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><change><B>57.14</B> (1) A justice before whom a staff member and an inmate have appeared in accordance with section 57.13 may issue a warrant authorizing a peace officer to require a qualified medical practitioner to take, or to cause to be taken by a qualified technician acting under the direction of the qualified medical practitioner, such samples of the inmate’s blood as, in the opinion of the person taking the samples, are necessary to enable a proper analysis to be made in order to determine whether the inmate carries a designated virus, if </change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0"><change>(<I>a</I>) the justice is satisfied that there are reasonable grounds to believe that</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="4" FirstLineIndent="0"><change>(i) the staff member came  into contact with a bodily substance of the inmate while in the execution of his or her duties,</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="4" FirstLineIndent="0"><change>(ii) the staff member may have become infected with a designated virus as a result of coming into contact with the bodily substance, and</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="4" FirstLineIndent="0"><change>(iii) by reason of the lengthy incubation periods for diseases caused by the designated viruses and the methods available for ascertaining the presence of such viruses in the human body, an analysis of the staff member's blood would not accurately determine, in a timely manner, whether he or she had become infected with a designated virus as a result of coming into contact with the bodily substance;</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0"><change>(<I>b</I>) a qualified medical practitioner is of the opinion that the taking of the blood samples will not endanger the inmate’s life or health;</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0"><change>(<I>c</I>) the staff member has submitted to the justice a physician’s report made within seven days after he or she came into contact with the bodily substance; and</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0"><change>(<I>d</I>) the physician’s report referred to in paragraph (<I>c</I>) states that the analysis of the samples of the inmate’s blood is necessary to determine whether there is any risk to the staff member's health as a result of coming into contact with the bodily substance.</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Examination of staff member<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><change>(2) A qualified medical practitioner who makes a physician’s report referred to in paragraph (1)(<I>c</I>) may require the staff member to submit to an examination or treatment for the purpose of making the report.</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Issuance of warrant by provincial court judge<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><change>(3) The warrant referred to in subsection (1) may also be issued by a provincial court judge if the staff member and the inmate in question appear before the judge and the staff member establishes that</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0"><change>(<I>a</I>) he or she believes on reasonable grounds that the inmate is infected with a designated virus;</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0"><change>(<I>b</I>) there is a significant risk that staff members could come into contact with a bodily substance of the inmate and as a result become infected with such a virus;</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0"><change>(<I>c</I>) this risk prevents staff members from properly and safely exercising their duties; and</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0"><change>(<I>d</I>) a qualified medical practitioner is of the opinion that the taking of blood samples will not endanger the inmate’s life or health.</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>For greater certainty<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><change><B>57.15</B> No person shall take a blood sample from an inmate without his or her consent unless</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0"><change>(<I>a</I>) a warrant has been issued under section 57.14 authorizing the taking of the blood sample;</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0"><change>(<I>b</I>) the blood sample is taken by a qualified medical practitioner or by a qualified technician acting under the direction of a qualified medical practitioner; and</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0"><change>(<I>c</I>) the qualified medical practitioner is of the opinion that the taking of the blood sample will not endanger the inmate’s life or health.</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>No offence committed<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><change><B>57.16</B> (1) No qualified medical practitioner or qualified technician is guilty of an offence only by reason of his or her refusal to take blood samples from an inmate for the purposes of this Act.</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>No offence committed<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><change>(2) No qualified medical practitioner is guilty of an offence only by reason of his or her refusal to cause a qualified technician to take blood samples from an inmate for the purposes of this Act.</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>No criminal or civil liability<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><change><B>57.17</B> No qualified medical practitioner by whom or under whose direction blood samples are taken from an inmate pursuant to a warrant issued under section 57.14 and no qualified technician acting under the direction of a qualified medical practitioner incurs any criminal or civil liability for anything that they have done in accordance with sections 57.12  to 57.194 with reasonable care and skill.</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Certificate of qualified medical practitioner<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><change><B>57.18</B> (1) On completion of the taking of blood samples from an inmate by a qualified medical practitioner or a qualified technician pursuant to a warrant issued under section 57.14, the qualified medical practitioner shall give to the peace officer responsible for executing the warrant, or to another peace officer acting on his or her behalf, a copy of a certificate</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0"><change>(<I>a</I>) stating</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="4" FirstLineIndent="0"><change>(i) that the qualified medical practitioner took the blood samples from the inmate mentioned in the warrant,</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="4" FirstLineIndent="0"><change>(ii) that, before the blood samples were taken, the qualified medical practitioner was of the opinion that the taking of the samples would not endanger the inmate’s life or health, and</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="4" FirstLineIndent="0"><change>(iii) the time and place where the blood samples were taken; or</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0"><change>(<I>b</I>) stating</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="4" FirstLineIndent="0"><change>(i) that the qualified medical practitioner caused the blood samples to be taken by a qualified technician under his or her direction from the inmate referred to in the warrant, and</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="4" FirstLineIndent="0"><change>(ii) that, before the blood samples were taken, the qualified medical practitioner was of the opinion that the taking of the samples would not endanger the inmate’s life or health.</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Certificate of qualified technician<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><change>(2) On completion of the taking of blood samples from the inmate pursuant to a warrant issued under section 57.14, the qualified technician shall give to the qualified medical practitioner who caused him to take the samples and to the peace officer responsible for executing the warrant, or to another peace officer acting on his or her behalf, a copy of a certificate stating</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0"><change>(<I>a</I>) that the qualified technician took the blood samples;</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0"><change>(<I>b</I>) the time and place where the blood samples were taken; and</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0"><change>(<I>c</I>) that the blood samples were taken directly from the inmate referred to in the warrant.</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Report of analyst<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><change><B>57.19</B> (1) On completion of the analysis of a blood sample taken from an inmate pursuant to a warrant issued under section 57.14, the analyst shall</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0"><change>(<I>a</I>) take all reasonable measures to provide a report on the results of the analysis to the inmate's physician;</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0"><change>(<I>b</I>) if the analyst succeeds in providing the report to the inmate’s physician pursuant to paragraph (<I>a</I>), take all reasonable measures to notify the inmate in writing that his or her physician received the report;</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0"><change>(<I>c</I>) take all reasonable measures to provide a report on the results of the analysis to the staff member's physician; and</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0"><change>(<I>d</I>) take all reasonable measures to provide to the staff member</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="4" FirstLineIndent="0"><change>(i) a notice in writing  that the analyst has taken all reasonable measures to provide a report on the results of the analysis to the staff member's physician, and</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="4" FirstLineIndent="0"><change>(ii) a recommendation in writing that the staff member consult his or her physician for a proper interpretation of the results of the analysis.</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Certificate of analyst<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><change>(2) On completion of an analysis of a blood sample taken from an inmate pursuant to a warrant issued under section 57.14, the analyst shall give to the peace officer responsible for executing the warrant, or to another peace officer acting on his or her behalf, a copy of a certificate stating</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0"><change>(<I>a</I>) that the analyst completed the analysis of the blood sample; and</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0"><change>(<I>b</I>) that the analyst took all reasonable measures to provide the reports and notices referred to in subsection (1).</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Protection of blood sample<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><change>(3) Every analyst who receives a blood sample for analysis pursuant to a warrant issued under section 57.14</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0"><change>(<I>a</I>) shall ensure that the sample is not used for any purpose other than the analysis and the reporting of results described in this section;</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0"><change>(<I>b</I>) shall not disclose the results of the analysis to any person, except in accordance with this section; and</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0"><change>(<I>c</I>) shall not release the blood sample to any person unless the release is</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="4" FirstLineIndent="0"><change>(i) for a purpose described in this section, or</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="4" FirstLineIndent="0"><change>(ii) for the purpose of the retention of the blood sample by a person authorized by the analyst to retain the sample, to which only that person and the analyst have access.</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Prohibition regarding blood sample<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><change><B>57.191</B> No person shall use or analyze a blood sample taken from an inmate pursuant to a warrant issued under section 57.14 for any purpose other than that specified in the warrant.</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Disclosure of identity<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><change><B>57.192</B> Except as expressly authorized by this Act, no person shall provide another person with any information that could disclose the identity of a staff member who has made an application under section 57.11 or an inmate in respect of whom a warrant has been issued under section 57.14.</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Offences<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><change><B>57.193</B> Every person who contravenes subsection 57.19(3) or section 57.191 or 57.192 is guilty of an offence punishable on summary conviction.</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Evidence<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><change><B>57.194</B> The results of the analysis of a blood sample obtained pursuant to a warrant issued under section 57.14 and a certificate, report or notice provided for in sections 57.18 and 57.19 may not be received in evidence in a civil proceeding or in a criminal prosecution, except in a prosecution under section 57.193.</change></Para></Block><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="BPT_ImprintE"><br /><br />Published under authority of the Speaker of the House of Commons</Para></Block><Block Align="Yes" LineCnt="N"><Para NoLineBreak="Yes" NoHtml="Yes" Leading="0" Size="0" TopMargin="0" BottomMargin="0"></Para></Block></Bill_Part></Bill>