ГЇВ»Вї<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><Bill RHead_reign="62-63 Eliz. II" RHead_ParlYear="2013-2014" DocumentTitle="BILL C-442" Bill_No="C-442" Document_No="411619" xml:lang="EN" Bill_Type="Non-amending" Stage_Name="Assented-to" Reprint="No" xml:space="preserve" ChapterNo_E="C. 37" ChapterNo_F="ch. 37" Bill-Origin="commons"><Bill_Part Part_Type="Cover" CountLines="No"><Block><Para TopMargin="24" Size="9" Leading="10" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0" TextAlign="Center">Second Session, Forty-first Parliament,</Para></Block><Block><Para Size="9" Leading="10" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0" TextAlign="Center">62-63 Elizabeth II, 2013-2014</Para></Block><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="COV@StatutesTitle">STATUTES OF CANADA 2014<br />CHAPTER 37</Para></Block><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="CovLongTitle">An Act respecting a Federal Framework on Lyme Disease</Para></Block><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="COV_StageLine"></Para></Block><Block><Para BottomMargin="14" Size="11" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0" Bold="Yes" TextAlign="Center">ASSENTED TO</Para></Block><Block><Para Size="8" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0" TextAlign="Center">16th DECEMBER, 2014</Para></Block><Block><Para TopMargin="4" Size="8" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0" TextAlign="Center">BILL C-442</Para></Block><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="COV_StageLine"></Para></Block></Bill_Part><Bill_Part CountLines="No" Part_Type="InsideCover"><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="BPT_InsideCoverE">Available on the Parliament of Canada Web Site at the following address:<br /><B>http://www.parl.gc.ca</B></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><Para TopMargin="108" BottomMargin="4" Size="10" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">SUMMARY</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" Size="8" Leading="9" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">This enactment requires the Minister of Health to convene a conference with the provincial and territorial ministers responsible for health and with representatives of the medical community and patientsГўВЂВ™ groups for the purpose of developing a comprehensive federal framework to address the challenges of the recognition and timely diagnosis and treatment of Lyme disease.</Para></Block></Bill_Part><Bill_Part Part_Type="MainText" CountLines="No" RunningHead_E="Federal Framework on Lyme Disease"><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="MAIN@RoyalAssentTitle">62-63 ELIZABETH II</Para></Block><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="MAIN@RoyalAssentTitle">ГўВЂВ”ГўВЂВ”ГўВЂВ”ГўВЂВ”ГўВЂВ”ГўВЂВ”</Para></Block><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="MAIN@RoyalAssentTitle">CHAPTER 37</Para></Block><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="LongTitleAssent">An Act respecting a Federal Framework on Lyme Disease</Para></Block><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="MAIN@RoyalAssentDate">[<I>Assented to 16th December, 2014</I>]</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><MarginalNote>Preamble<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">Whereas Lyme disease is an illness caused by the bacterium <I>Borrelia burgdorferi</I> that is spread to humans and animals through the bite of certain types of ticks and that can have serious consequences if left untreated, including recurring attacks of arthritis and neurological problems;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">Whereas the risk of exposure to Lyme disease is highest in parts of southern and southeastern Quebec, southern and eastern Ontario, southeastern Manitoba, New Brunswick, Nova Scotia and much of southern British Columbia;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">Whereas numerous peer-reviewed scientific studies have warned that a warming climate will expand the geographic range of Lyme disease-carrying ticks further into Canada, including a 2012 paper by Leighton et al., which states that over 80% of the population in Eastern and Central Canada could be living in areas at risk of Lyme disease by 2020;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">Whereas, since 2009, Lyme disease has been a nationally reportable disease in Canada and all medical professionals must report cases of Lyme disease to their provincial public health authority, which in turn provides the data to the Public Health Agency of Canada;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify"> Whereas Canadians will benefit from the establishment of guidelines regarding the prevention, identification, treatment and management of Lyme disease, a coordinated national effort to track the spread of the disease, and increased public education and awareness to better prevent and detect instances of Lyme disease in Canada;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">Whereas recent research further demonstrates the persistence of <I>Borrelia</I> spirochetes after antibiotic treatment that follows the guidelines used in Canada (Embers et al., 2012) and  indicates that current serology does not adequately describe the diversity of <I>Borrelia</I> bacteria existing in Canada and that the general understanding of, and practices for dealing with, Lyme disease are no longer sufficient or in line with emerging evidence of how the disease operates (Ogden et al., 2011);</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">Whereas the current guidelines in Canada are based on those in the United States and are so restrictive as to severely limit the diagnosis of acute Lyme disease and deny the existence of continuing infection, thus abandoning sick people with a treatable illness;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">And whereas the 2010 report prepared for the Provincial Health Services Authority of British Columbia entitled <I>Chronic Lyme Disease in British Columbia, A Review of Strategic and Policy Issues</I> concluded that current diagnostic testing for Lyme disease is inadequate and advocated placing the highest priority on the development of reliable diagnostic testing for the disease and on educating physicians so they can recognize the symptoms of Lyme disease and treat patients in a manner that is medically appropriate, including treatment with antibiotics as justified;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">Now, therefore, Her Majesty, by and with the advice and consent of the Senate and House of Commons of Canada, enacts as follows:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:SHORT TITLE--><Para TopMargin="10" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">SHORT TITLE</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Short title<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>1.</B> This Act may be cited as the <I>Federal Framework on Lyme Disease Act</I>.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:INTERPRETATION--><Para TopMargin="10" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">INTERPRETATION</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Definitions<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>2.</B> The following definitions apply in this Act.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><MarginalNote>ГўВЂВњAgencyГўВЂВќ<br />Г‚В« <I>Agence</I> Г‚В»<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0">ГўВЂВњAgencyГўВЂВќ means the Public Health Agency of Canada.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><MarginalNote>ГўВЂВњfederal frameworkГўВЂВќ<br />Г‚В« <I>cadre fГѓВ©dГѓВ©ral</I> Г‚В»<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0">ГўВЂВњfederal frameworkГўВЂВќ means a framework to address the challenges of the recognition and timely diagnosis and treatment of Lyme disease.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><MarginalNote>ГўВЂВњMinisterГўВЂВќ<br />Г‚В« <I>ministre</I> Г‚В»<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0">ГўВЂВњMinisterГўВЂВќ means the Minister of Health.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><MarginalNote>ГўВЂВњprovincial and territorial ministersГўВЂВќ<br />Г‚В« <I>ministres provinciaux et territoriaux</I> Г‚В»<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0">ГўВЂВњprovincial and territorial ministersГўВЂВќ means the provincial and territorial ministers responsible for health.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:FEDERAL FRAMEWORK ON LYME DISEASE--><Para TopMargin="10" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">FEDERAL FRAMEWORK ON LYME DISEASE</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Conference<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>3.</B> The Minister must, no later than 12 months after the day on which this Act comes into force, convene a conference with the provincial and territorial ministers and stakeholders, including representatives of the medical community and patientsГўВЂВ™ groups, for the purpose of developing a comprehensive federal framework that includes</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>a</I>) the establishment of a national medical surveillance program to use data collected by the Agency to properly track incidence rates and the associated economic costs of Lyme disease;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>b</I>) the establishment of guidelines regarding the prevention, identification, treatment and management of Lyme disease, and the sharing of best practices throughout Canada; and</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>c</I>) the creation and distribution <keep>of standard-</keep>ized educational materials related to Lyme disease, for use by any public health care provider within Canada, designed to increase national awareness about the disease and enhance its prevention, identification, treatment and management.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Preparation and publication of report<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>4.</B> The Minister must prepare a report that sets out the federal framework and publish the report on the AgencyГўВЂВ™s website within one year after the federal framework referred to in section 3 is developed.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Report to Parliament<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>5.</B> The Minister must cause a copy of the report referred to in section 4 to be laid before each House of Parliament on any of the first 90 days on which that House is sitting after the report has been published on the AgencyГўВЂВ™s website.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:REVIEW AND REPORT--><Para TopMargin="10" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">REVIEW AND REPORT</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Review<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>6.</B> The Agency must</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>a</I>) complete a review of the effectiveness of the federal framework no later than five years after the day on which the report referred to in section 4 is published on the AgencyГўВЂВ™s website; and</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>b</I>) table a report on its findings before each House of Parliament within the next ten sitting days after the review is completed.</Para></Block><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="BPT_ImprintE"><br /><br />Published under authority of the Speaker of the House of Commons</Para></Block><Block Align="Yes" LineCnt="N"><Para NoLineBreak="Yes" NoHtml="Yes" Leading="0" Size="0" TopMargin="0" BottomMargin="0">Г‚В„</Para></Block></Bill_Part></Bill>