﻿<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><Bill RHead_reign="60-61 Eliz. II" RHead_ParlYear="2011-2012" DocumentTitle="BILL C-441" Bill_No="C-441" Document_No="411532" xml:lang="EN" Bill_Type="Non-amending" Stage_Name="First-Reading-House" Reprint="No" xml:space="preserve" ChapterNo_E="C. " ChapterNo_F="ch. " Bill-Origin="commons"><Bill_Part Part_Type="Cover" CountLines="No"><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="CovBillNo">C-441</Para></Block><Block><Para TopMargin="24" Size="9" Leading="10" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0" TextAlign="Center">First Session, Forty-first Parliament,</Para></Block><Block><Para Size="9" Leading="10" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0" TextAlign="Center">60-61 Elizabeth II, 2011-2012</Para></Block><Block><Para TopMargin="48" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0" Bold="Yes" TextAlign="Center">HOUSE OF COMMONS OF CANADA</Para></Block><Block><Para TopMargin="42" Size="18" Leading="20" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0" Bold="Yes" TextAlign="Center">BILL C-441</Para></Block><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="CovLongTitle">An Act to amend the Canada Transportation Act (shippers' protection)</Para></Block><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="COV_StageLine"></Para></Block><Block><Para Size="9" AllCaps="Yes" Hyphenate="OFF">first reading, June 20, 2012</Para></Block><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="COV_StageLine"></Para></Block><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="Cov_StartBox"></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes"><Para Style="Cov_Box_Heading">NOTE</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes"><Para Style="Cov_Box_Para" TextAlign="Justify">2nd Session, 41st Parliament</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes"><Para Style="Cov_Box_Para" TextAlign="Justify">This bill was introduced during the First Session of the 41st Parliament. Pursuant to the Standing Orders of the House of Commons, it is deemed to have been considered and approved at all stages completed at the time of prorogation of the First Session. The number of the bill remains unchanged.</Para></Block><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="Cov_EndBox"></Para></Block><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="Cover_Sponsors"><SC SC_PerCent="85">Ms. Chow</SC></Para></Block><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="Cover_DocNo">411532</Para></Block></Bill_Part><Bill_Part CountLines="No" Part_Type="InsideCover"><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="BPT_InsideCoverE">Available on the Parliament of Canada Web Site at the following address:<br /><B>http://www.parl.gc.ca</B></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><Para TopMargin="108" BottomMargin="4" Size="10" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">SUMMARY</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" Size="8" Leading="9" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">This enactment amends the <I>Canada Transportation Act</I> to add a requirement that notice be provided to stakeholders who would be directly affected by any proposed local rail service changes and to provide access to a dispute resolution process for disputes related to such a change. It also adds a provision to require railway companies to negotiate level of service agreements with stakeholders regarding the provision of services under section 113 of the Act and to give the railway company or stakeholder access to the dispute resolution process if no agreement is reached within the specified time. In addition, the enactment requires railway companies to report to their stakeholders and to the public on matters related to the level of service.</Para></Block></Bill_Part><Bill_Part Part_Type="MainText" CountLines="Yes" RunningHead_E="Canada Transportation (shippers' protection)"><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="MainText_DocNo">411532</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes"><Para Style="Session_Reign">1st Session, 41st Parliament,</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes"><Para Style="Session_Reign">60-61 Elizabeth II, 2011-2012</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes"><Para Style="MainBillOrigin">house of commons of canada</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes"><Para Bold="Yes" Style="MAIN@BillNo_Title">BILL C-441</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes"><Para Style="MAIN@ti;04">An Act to amend the Canada Transportation Act (shippers' protection)</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">Her Majesty, by and with the advice and consent of the Senate and House of Commons of Canada, enacts as follows:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:SHORT TITLE--><Para TopMargin="10" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">SHORT TITLE</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Short title<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>1.</B> This Act may be cited as the <I>Rail Customer Protection Act</I>.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:CANADA TRANSPORTATION ACT--><MarginalNote>1996, c. 10<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="10" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center"><B>CANADA TRANSPORTATION ACT</B></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>2.</B> Section 53 of the <I>Canada Transportation Act</I> is amended by adding the following after subsection (2):</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Rail service framework<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify"><change>(2.1) In addition to the matters assessed under subsection (2), the review shall include an assessment of the provisions and operation of Division IV.</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>3.</B> The Act is amended by adding the following after section 113:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Definitions<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><change><B>113.1</B> (1) The following definitions apply in this section and in sections 113.2 and 113.3.</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><MarginalNote>“operational relationship”<br />« <I>relation opérationnelle</I> »<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0"><change>“operational relationship” includes a relationship between a railway company and a person or entity that  receives, loads, carries, unloads, delivers or interswitches traffic for the railway company.</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><MarginalNote>“stakeholder”<br />« <I>intervenant</I> »<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0"><change>“stakeholder” means, in relation to a railway company, a person or an entity that has an operational relationship with, or is a shipper with, the railway company or that represents the interests of persons or entities that have an operational relationship with, or are shippers with, the railway company.</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Notice of change<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><change>(2) Subject to subsection (6), if a railway company plans any change to its local rail service from the established practice, the company shall provide written notice of the planned change to the stakeholders that will be directly affected by the proposed change at least 10 working days before the change is made. For the purposes of this section, a change in local rail service includes a reduction <keep>in or discontin-</keep>uation of service.</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>No earlier change<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><change>(3) No change in local rail service shall be made by the railway company before the expiration of the notice period described in subsection (2) unless all stakeholders that will be directly affected by the proposed change agree to the proposed change.</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Tariff commitment<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><change>(4) Every railway company shall include, in a tariff issued under section 118, a commitment to meet the requirements set out in subsection (2).</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Dispute resolution process<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><change>(5) A railway company or a stakeholder that will be directly affected by the proposed change may refer any dispute relating to that change to the dispute resolution process established under paragraph 113.3(<I>a</I>).</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Exception<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><change>(6) A railway company is not required to meet the notice requirement set out in subsection (2) if it is prevented from doing so by conditions that are outside its control and that could not be avoided by the exercise of due care, such as extreme weather events, terrorist activities or accidents.</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Service level agreements<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><change><B>113.2</B> (1) At the request of a stakeholder, a railway company shall negotiate with the stakeholder in good faith for the purpose of establishing or renewing a level of service agreement that addresses the manner in which the service obligations under section 113 shall be fulfilled by the railway company and that includes the following elements:</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0"><change>(<I>a</I>) the obligations of the railway company and the obligations of the stakeholder;</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0"><change>(<I>b</I>) the communication protocol to be followed by both parties and the procedure that applies in the event of a disagreement; </change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0"><change>(<I>c</I>) the traffic volume limits; </change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0"><change>(<I>d</I>) the key indicators to be used for performance measurement; </change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0"><change>(<I>e</I>) the performance standards to be met;</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0"><change>(<I>f</I>) the consequences of the non-performance of the obligations, including penalties; </change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0"><change>(<I>g</I>) the requirement, in the event of a dispute, to use the resolution process established under paragraph 113.3(<I>a</I>); and </change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0"><change>(<I>h</I>) the circumstances in which the railway company's obligations cannot be met because of conditions that are outside its control and that could not be avoided by the exercise of due care, such as extreme weather events, terrorist activities or accidents.</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Dispute resolution process<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><change>(2) If the railway company and the stakeholder fail to reach agreement on the establishment or renewal of the level of service agreement within 6 months after the stakeholder has requested negotiations under subsection (1), the railway company or the stakeholder may refer the matter for determination using the dispute resolution process established under paragraph 113.3(<I>a</I>).</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Regulations<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><change><B>113.3</B> The Governor in Council shall, within one year after the coming into force of this Act, make regulations respecting </change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0"><change>(<I>a</I>) the establishment of a dispute resolution process for any matters in dispute under sections 113.1 and 113.2; and</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0"><change>(<I>b</I>) the provision, by each railway company, of </change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="4" FirstLineIndent="0"><change>(i) a confidential annual report that shall be issued to stakeholders with whom it has a level of service agreement and that contains information on the level of service provided, factors that influenced that level and any issues related to the level of service provided, and </change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="4" FirstLineIndent="0"><change>(ii) a quarterly public report that shall be posted on its website and that addresses service in each shipping sector on a general basis, including sector-specific information on its rolling stock, fulfilment of car orders and car movements, as well as service data.</change></Para></Block><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="BPT_ImprintE"><br /><br />Published under authority of the Speaker of the House of Commons</Para></Block><Block Align="Yes" LineCnt="N"><Para NoLineBreak="Yes" NoHtml="Yes" Leading="0" Size="0" TopMargin="0" BottomMargin="0"></Para></Block></Bill_Part></Bill>