﻿<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><Bill RHead_reign="60-61-62 Eliz. II" RHead_ParlYear="2011-2012-2013" DocumentTitle="BILL C-474" Bill_No="C-474" Document_No="411393" xml:lang="EN" Bill_Type="Non-amending" Stage_Name="First-Reading-House" Reprint="No" xml:space="preserve" ChapterNo_E="C. " ChapterNo_F="ch. " Bill-Origin="commons"><Bill_Part Part_Type="Cover" CountLines="No"><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="CovBillNo">C-474</Para></Block><Block><Para TopMargin="24" Size="9" Leading="10" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0" TextAlign="Center">First Session, Forty-first Parliament,</Para></Block><Block><Para Size="9" Leading="10" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0" TextAlign="Center">60-61-62 Elizabeth II, 2011-2012-2013</Para></Block><Block><Para TopMargin="48" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0" Bold="Yes" TextAlign="Center">HOUSE OF COMMONS OF CANADA</Para></Block><Block><Para TopMargin="42" Size="18" Leading="20" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0" Bold="Yes" TextAlign="Center">BILL C-474</Para></Block><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="CovLongTitle">An Act respecting the promotion of financial transparency, improved accountability and long-term economic sustainability through the public reporting of payments made by mining, oil and gas corporations to foreign governments</Para></Block><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="COV_StageLine"></Para></Block><Block><Para Size="9" AllCaps="Yes" Hyphenate="OFF">first reading, February 26, 2013</Para></Block><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="COV_StageLine"></Para></Block><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="Cov_StartBox"></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes"><Para Style="Cov_Box_Heading">NOTE</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes"><Para Style="Cov_Box_Para" TextAlign="Justify">2nd Session, 41st Parliament</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes"><Para Style="Cov_Box_Para" TextAlign="Justify">This bill was introduced during the First Session of the 41st Parliament. Pursuant to the Standing Orders of the House of Commons, it is deemed to have been considered and approved at all stages completed at the time of prorogation of the First Session. The number of the bill remains unchanged.</Para></Block><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="Cov_EndBox"></Para></Block><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="Cover_Sponsors"><SC SC_PerCent="85">Mr. McKay</SC></Para></Block><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="Cover_DocNo">411393</Para></Block></Bill_Part><Bill_Part CountLines="No" Part_Type="InsideCover"><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="BPT_InsideCoverE">Available on the Parliament of Canada Web Site at the following address:<br /><B>http://www.parl.gc.ca</B></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><Para TopMargin="108" BottomMargin="4" Size="10" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">SUMMARY</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" Size="8" Leading="9" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">This enactment requires mining, oil and gas corporations to submit annual transparency reports that disclose all payments provided by them or their subsidiaries to a foreign government for the purpose of furthering mining, oil or gas industry activities. It also makes it an offence to fail to comply with this requirement and establishes a penalty for such contravention.</Para></Block></Bill_Part><Bill_Part Part_Type="MainText" CountLines="Yes" RunningHead_E="Transparency of Payments Made by Mining, Oil and Gas Corporations to Foreign Governments"><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="MainText_DocNo">411393</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes"><Para Style="Session_Reign">1st Session, 41st Parliament,</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes"><Para Style="Session_Reign">60-61-62 Elizabeth II, 2011-2012-2013</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes"><Para Style="MainBillOrigin">house of commons of canada</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes"><Para Bold="Yes" Style="MAIN@BillNo_Title">BILL C-474</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes"><Para Style="MAIN@ti;04">An Act respecting the promotion of financial transparency, improved accountability and long-term economic sustainability through the public reporting of payments made by mining, oil and gas corporations to foreign governments</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Preamble<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">Whereas Canada strongly supports international efforts to fight corruption, encourage transparency and promote increased accountability;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">Whereas Canada officially supports the Extractive Industries Transparency Initiative (EITI), an international coalition of governments, industries, investors and international and non-governmental organizations that advocates for improved governance through the full publication and verification of payments made to governments by mining, oil and gas corporations and government revenues from those corporations;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">Whereas Canadians recognize that proper natural resource management is enabled by transparency and the regular publication of information on public resources and reve-<keep>nues, which</keep> allows investors to properly assess risk, governments to monitor company compliance and citizens to see the value placed on their natural resource assets;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">Whereas Canada and Canadians accept the EITI principle that the prudent use of natural resource wealth should be an important en- <keep>gine for sustainable</keep> economic growth that <keep>contributes to sustainable</keep> development and poverty reduction, but that, if not managed properly, it can have negative economic and social impacts;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">Whereas Canada’s Sustainable Economic Growth Strategy advocates increased transparency to aid in promoting international development by fostering a stable foundation for viable business and industries to thrive and in helping to maximize the contribution of growth to the public resources available for investment in the welfare of the population by promoting sound fiscal, financial and economic management;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">Whereas Canada has ratified the United Nations Convention against Corruption, which requires States Parties to take measures to promote the transparency of private entities and to ensure the public has effective access to information;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">Whereas Canada is a signatory to the OECD Convention on Combating Bribery of Foreign Public Officials in International Business Transactions, which came into force in Canada with the adoption of the <I>Corruption of Foreign Public Officials Act</I>;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">Whereas Canada is a signatory to the G8 Declaration: Renewed Commitment for Freedom and Democracy and a party to the G8/Africa Joint Declaration: Shared Values, Shared Responsibilities, both issued at the G8 Summit of Deauville in 2011, and thus welcomes efforts to increase revenue transparency and is committed to setting in place transparency legislation that requires mining, oil and gas corporations to disclose the payments they make to foreign governments;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">Whereas Canada recognizes that extractive revenue transparency will improve the business climate in which the Canadian extractive industry operates by helping Canadian investors to manage the risks of investing in the extractive industry abroad;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">And whereas Canada recognizes that promoting transparency will improve the competitive advantage of Canadian companies operating abroad by further enhancing the reputation of Canada’s extractive sector;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">Now, therefore, Her Majesty, by and with the advice and consent of the Senate and House of Commons of Canada, enacts as follows:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:SHORT TITLE--><Para TopMargin="10" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">SHORT TITLE</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Short title<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>1.</B> This Act may be cited as the <I>Transparency of Payments Made by Mining, Oil and Gas Corporations to Foreign Governments Act</I>.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:PURPOSE--><Para TopMargin="10" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">PURPOSE</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Purpose<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>2.</B> The purpose of this Act is to promote financial transparency, improved accountability and long-term economic sustainability by publishing payments made to foreign governments by mining, oil and gas corporations.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:INTERPRETATION--><Para TopMargin="10" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">INTERPRETATION</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Definitions<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>3.</B> The following definitions apply in this Act.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><MarginalNote>“Canadian corporation”<br />« <I>société canadienne</I> »<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0">“Canadian corporation” means, for the purposes of this Act, an entity that has been incorporated under the laws of Canada or a province or that is considered to be resident in Canada under the <I>Income Tax Act</I> or any applicable tax treaty.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><MarginalNote>“EITI”<br />« <I>ITIE</I> »<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0">“EITI” means the coalition of governments, industries, investors and international and non-governmental organizations that constitutes the Extractive Industries Transparency Initiative and that advocates for improved governance through the full publication and verification of payments made to governments by mining, oil and gas corporations and government revenues from those corporations.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><MarginalNote>“EITI Rules”<br />« <I>Règles de l’ITIE</I> »<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0">“EITI Rules” means the rules established by the EITI Board for the purpose of implementing the EITI and published on the EITI website as the <I>EITI Rules, 2011 Edition</I>.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><MarginalNote>“extractive corporation”<br />« <I>société extractive</I> »<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0">“extractive corporation” means any Canadian corporation that engages in international mining, oil or gas industry activities, either directly or through a subsidiary.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><MarginalNote>“extractive project”<br />« <I>projet d’extraction</I> »<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0">“extractive project” refers to any oil, natural gas or mineral exploration, development, production, transport, refining or marketing activity from which payments above the not-negligible threshold originate, that is governed by a lease, concession or similar legal agreement.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><MarginalNote>“foreign government”<br />« <I>gouvernement étranger</I> »<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0">“foreign government” means the government of a foreign state or the government of a political subdivision of a foreign state and includes</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>a</I>) any department or branch of a foreign government;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>b</I>) any agency of a foreign government;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>c</I>) any corporation that is at least majority-owned, directly or indirectly, by a foreign government; and</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>d</I>) any foreign public official acting in their official capacity.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><MarginalNote>“foreign public official”<br />« <I>agent public étranger</I> »<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0">“foreign public official” means</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>a</I>) a person who holds a legislative, administrative or judicial position of a foreign state;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>b</I>) a person who performs public duties or functions for a foreign state, including a person employed by a board, commission, corporation or other body or authority that is established to perform a duty or function on behalf of the foreign state, or is performing such a duty or function; and</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>c</I>) an official or agent of a public international organization that is formed by two or more states or governments or by two or more such public international organizations.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><MarginalNote>“gas”<br />« <I>gaz</I> »<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0">“gas” has the same meaning as in section 2 of the <I>Canada Oil and Gas Operations Act</I>.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><MarginalNote>“mineral resources”<br />« <I>ressources minérales</I> »<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0">“mineral resources” means all naturally occurring minerals, but does not include peat, petroleum, natural gas, bitumen, oil shales, limestone, marble, clay, gypsum, earth, ash, marl, gravel, sand or any element that forms part of the agricultural surface of the land.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><MarginalNote>“mining, oil or gas industry activities”<br />« <I>activités minières, pétrolières ou gazières</I> »<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0">“mining, oil or gas industry activities” includes the exploration, extraction, production, conservation, processing, transportation and other significant actions relating to mineral resources, oil or gas.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><MarginalNote>“oil”<br />« <I>pétrole</I> »<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0">“oil” has the same meaning as in section 2 of the <I>Canada Oil and Gas Operations Act</I>.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><MarginalNote>“operator”<br />« <I>exploitant</I> »<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0">“operator” means the party in a joint venture who is designated as the operator of an extractive project by agreement between  or among the parties or who actually conducts the operations of the extractive project.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><MarginalNote>“payment”<br />« <I>paiement</I> »<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0">“payment” means a payment that is given for the purposes of furthering the mining, oil or gas industry and that is not negligible and, without limiting the generality of the foregoing, includes</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>a</I>) taxes, including but not limited to, corporate taxes, remittance taxes, mining taxes, value-added taxes, import taxes and export taxes;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>b</I>) royalties;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>c</I>) dividends and profit shares;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>d</I>) licence fees, rental fees, entry fees and other consideration paid for licences or concessions;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>e</I>) production entitlements and in-kind payment volumes; </Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>f</I>) bonuses, including but not limited to, signature, discovery and production bonuses;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>g</I>) provision of infrastructure and other in-kind payments;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>h</I>) social payments and transfers; </Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>i</I>) fees paid for services rendered in the context of a contractual or employment agreement, including consulting fees; and</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>j</I>) other prescribed material benefits that are not negligible.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><MarginalNote>“prescribed”<br /><I>Version anglaise seulement</I><br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0">“prescribed” means prescribed by regulations made under section 7.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><MarginalNote>“subsidiary”<br />« <I>filiale</I> »<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0">“subsidiary”, in the context of a particular extractive project, means a corporation in which a Canadian corporation</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>a</I>) holds, directly or indirectly, a voting interest greater than 50%;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>b</I>) holds a voting interest of 50% and is the operator of the extractive project; or</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>c</I>) holds a voting interest of less than 50%, is the largest single holder of voting shares and is the operator of the extractive project.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:ANNUAL TRANSPARENCY REPORTS--><Para TopMargin="10" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">ANNUAL TRANSPARENCY REPORTS</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Submission of annual transparency reports<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>4.</B> (1) Every extractive corporation must submit an annual transparency report, along with proof that the report was independently audited in accordance with subsection (7), to the Minister of Foreign Affairs and the Minister of Natural Resources on or before the 180th day after the end of its fiscal year.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Available to public<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(2) Every extractive corporation must post the annual transparency report submitted under subsection (1) on its website on or before the 180th day after the end of its fiscal year and leave it up until the posting of the annual transparency report for the following fiscal year.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Information disclosed<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(3) The annual transparency report submitted under subsection (1) must disclose all payments provided by an extractive corporation or its subsidiaries to a foreign government for the purposes of furthering mining, oil or gas industry activities, and must include the following information:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>a</I>) a statement of total payments made by the extractive corporation or its subsidiaries to foreign governments, categorized by foreign government to which the payments were made;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>b</I>) subject to subsection (4), a statement of total payments made by the extractive corporation or its subsidiaries to foreign governments, categorized by <keep>extractive proj-</keep>ect; and</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>c</I>) subject to subsection (4), a statement of total payments made by the extractive corporation or its subsidiaries to foreign governments related to each <keep>extractive proj-</keep>ect, categorized as follows:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="4" FirstLineIndent="0">(i) taxes, including but not limited to, corporate taxes, remittance taxes, mining taxes, value-added taxes, import taxes and export taxes,</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="4" FirstLineIndent="0">(ii) royalties,</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="4" FirstLineIndent="0">(iii) dividends and profit shares,</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="4" FirstLineIndent="0">(iv) licence fees, rental fees, entry fees and other consideration paid for licences or concessions,</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="4" FirstLineIndent="0">(v) production entitlements and in-kind payment volumes,</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="4" FirstLineIndent="0">(vi) bonuses, including but not limited to signature, discovery and production bonuses,</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="4" FirstLineIndent="0">(vii) provision of infrastructure and other in-kind payments,</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="4" FirstLineIndent="0">(viii) social payments and transfers,</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="4" FirstLineIndent="0">(ix) fees paid for services rendered, in the context of a contractual or employment agreement, including consulting fees, and</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="4" FirstLineIndent="0">(x) any other payments not included under subparagraphs (i) to (ix).</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Specialized disclosure<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(4) If any payments made by the extractive corporation or its subsidiaries to foreign governments are not attributed to individual extractive projects, the report referred to in subsection (3) must include a statement of those payments and their recipients, indicating the payments made in each of the categories referred to in subparagraphs (3)(<I>c</I>)(i) to (x).</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Investigation by Minister<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(5) If the Minister of Natural Resources has reasonable grounds to believe that any payments disclosed in accordance with subsection (4) can in fact be attributed to individual extractive projects, the Minister may conduct an investigation into the circumstances relating to the payments.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Contextual details<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(6) The information disclosed in respect of the categories referred to in paragraph (3)(<I>c</I>) must include</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>a</I>) the currency used to make the payment;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>b</I>) the financial period in which the payment was made;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>c</I>) the business segment of the extractive corporation or its subsidiary that made the payment;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>d</I>) the foreign government that received the payment, and the country in which the foreign government is located;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>e</I>) the extractive project to which the payment relates; and</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>f</I>) any other prescribed information relating to the context of the payment or extractive project.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Independent audit<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(7) Before an annual transparency report is submitted under subsection (1), it must be audited by a qualified independent auditor, unless the information contained in the report has already been audited by a qualified independent auditor in accordance with international auditing standards.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Annual compilation<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>5.</B> The Minister of Natural Resources must post an annual compilation of the information received in accordance with subsections 4(3) and (4), and organized in accordance with that subsection, on the departmental website. The compilation must be in the form of a publicly accessible and searchable database.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:OFFENCES AND PUNISHMENTS--><Para TopMargin="10" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">OFFENCES AND PUNISHMENTS</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Strict liability offence — summary conviction<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>6.</B> (1) Every extractive corporation that contravenes section 4 is guilty of an offence and is liable on summary conviction to a fine of not less than $20,000 and not more than $5,000,000.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Venue<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(2) Any complaint or information in respect of an offence under this Act may be heard, tried or determined by any Canadian court with jurisdiction over the extractive corporation.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:REGULATIONS--><Para TopMargin="10" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">REGULATIONS</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Regulations<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>7.</B> The Governor in Council may make regulations</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>a</I>) amending, in order to be consistent with the EITI Rules and other internationally accepted revenue disclosure standards, the information required to be submitted under subsections 4(3),  (4) and (6) to add, modify or remove any information that must be submitted;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>b</I>) amending, in order to be consistent with the principles of the EITI, the definition of the term “payment” to include commonly recognized revenue streams for the commercial development of minerals, oil or gas; and</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>c</I>) generally, for carrying into effect the purposes and provisions of this Act.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:COMING INTO FORCE--><Para TopMargin="10" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">COMING INTO FORCE</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Coming into force<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>8.</B> This Act comes into force 30 days after the day on which it receives royal assent.</Para></Block><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="BPT_ImprintE"><br /><br />Published under authority of the Speaker of the House of Commons</Para></Block><Block Align="Yes" LineCnt="N"><Para NoLineBreak="Yes" NoHtml="Yes" Leading="0" Size="0" TopMargin="0" BottomMargin="0"></Para></Block></Bill_Part></Bill>