茂禄驴<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><Bill RHead_reign="60-61-62 Eliz. II" RHead_ParlYear="2011-2012-2013" DocumentTitle="BILL C-486" Bill_No="C-486" Document_No="411687" xml:lang="EN" Bill_Type="Non-amending" Stage_Name="First-Reading-House" Reprint="No" xml:space="preserve" ChapterNo_E="C. " ChapterNo_F="ch. " Bill-Origin="commons"><Bill_Part Part_Type="Cover" CountLines="No"><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="CovBillNo">C-486</Para></Block><Block><Para TopMargin="24" Size="9" Leading="10" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0" TextAlign="Center">First Session, Forty-first Parliament,</Para></Block><Block><Para Size="9" Leading="10" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0" TextAlign="Center">60-61-62 Elizabeth II, 2011-2012-2013</Para></Block><Block><Para TopMargin="48" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0" Bold="Yes" TextAlign="Center">HOUSE OF COMMONS OF CANADA</Para></Block><Block><Para TopMargin="42" Size="18" Leading="20" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0" Bold="Yes" TextAlign="Center">BILL C-486</Para></Block><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="CovLongTitle">An Act respecting corporate practices relating to the extraction, processing, purchase, trade and use of conflict minerals from the Great Lakes Region of Africa</Para></Block><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="COV_StageLine"></Para></Block><Block><Para Size="9" AllCaps="Yes" Hyphenate="OFF">first reading, March 26, 2013</Para></Block><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="COV_StageLine"></Para></Block><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="Cov_StartBox"></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes"><Para Style="Cov_Box_Heading">NOTE</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes"><Para Style="Cov_Box_Para" TextAlign="Justify">2nd Session, 41st Parliament</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes"><Para Style="Cov_Box_Para" TextAlign="Justify">This bill was introduced during the First Session of the 41st Parliament. Pursuant to the Standing Orders of the House of Commons, it is deemed to have been considered and approved at all stages completed at the time of prorogation of the First Session. The number of the bill remains unchanged.</Para></Block><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="Cov_EndBox"></Para></Block><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="Cover_Sponsors"><SC SC_PerCent="85">Mr. Dewar</SC></Para></Block><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="Cover_DocNo">411687</Para></Block></Bill_Part><Bill_Part CountLines="No" Part_Type="InsideCover"><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="BPT_InsideCoverE">Available on the Parliament of Canada Web Site at the following address:<br /><B>http://www.parl.gc.ca</B></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><Para TopMargin="108" BottomMargin="4" Size="10" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">SUMMARY</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" Size="8" Leading="9" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">This enactment requires Canadian companies to exercise due diligence in respect of the exploitation and trading of designated minerals originating in the Great Lakes Region of Africa in seeking to ensure that no armed rebel organization or criminal entity or public or private security force that is engaged in illegal activities or serious human rights abuses has benefited from any transaction involving such minerals.</Para></Block></Bill_Part><Bill_Part Part_Type="MainText" CountLines="Yes" RunningHead_E="Conflict Minerals"><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="MainText_DocNo">411687</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes"><Para Style="Session_Reign">1st Session, 41st Parliament,</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes"><Para Style="Session_Reign">60-61-62 Elizabeth II, 2011-2012-2013</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes"><Para Style="MainBillOrigin">house of commons of canada</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes"><Para Bold="Yes" Style="MAIN@BillNo_Title">BILL C-486</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes"><Para Style="MAIN@ti;04">An Act respecting corporate practices relating to the extraction, processing, purchase, trade and use of conflict minerals from the Great Lakes Region of Africa</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Preamble<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">Whereas Canada recognizes that the illegal exploitation and trading of gold, cassiterite, wolframite and coltan and their derivatives, such as tin, tungsten and tantalum, can be directly linked to the fuelling of armed conflict and to the funding of armed groups engaged in illegal activities or serious human rights abuses in the Great Lakes Region of Africa;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">Whereas Canada recognizes that these conflicts have devastating impacts on the peace, safety and security of people in the countries of the Great Lakes Region of Africa;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">Whereas Canada strongly supports international efforts to fight the illegal exploitation and trading of natural resources, encourages transparency in relation to activities involving conflict minerals and is committed to preventing the extraction and trading of minerals from protracting or becoming a direct or indirect source of conflict, human rights abuses and insecurity;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">Whereas Canada believes that the responsible management of natural resources should enable countries to derive and sustain social and economic benefits from their natural resources;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">Whereas Canada officially supports the Extractive Industries Transparency Initiative, an international coalition of governments, <keep>companies, civil</keep> society groups, investors and international organizations that advocates for revenue transparency at the local level for mining, oil and gas industries;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">Whereas Canada is a signatory to the Organisation for Economic Co-operation and Development (OECD) <I>Declaration on International Investment and Multinational Enterprises</I> 芒聙聰which is implemented nationally by Canada芒聙聶s National Contact Point for the <I>OECD Guidelines for Multinational Enterprises</I> 芒聙聰 and, by extension, supports the <I>OECD Due Diligence Guidance for Responsible Supply Chains of Minerals from Conflict-Affected and High-Risk Areas</I>, which provides management recommendations for responsible global supply chains of minerals to help companies to respect human rights and avoid contributing to conflict through their mineral or metal purchasing decisions and practices;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">Whereas Canada has shown international leadership in promoting responsible supply chain management through its roles in developing the <I>OECD Due Diligence Guidance for Responsible Supply Chains of Minerals from Conflict-Affected and High-Risk Areas</I> and the Kimberley Process regulating the international trade in diamonds;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">Whereas Canada has been instrumental in the establishment of the  International Conference on the Great Lakes Region and supports its Regional Initiative on Natural Resources which aims to break the links between armed conflict and  the illegal exploitation of natural resources;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">Whereas Canada has adopted <I>Building the Canadian Advantage: a Corporate Social Responsibility (CSR) Strategy for the Canadian International Extractive Sector</I> through which it commits to the promotion and support of corporate social responsibility for the Canadian extractive sector operating abroad, and encourages socially responsible corporate practices in all sectors and industries;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">Whereas the responsible management of natural resources may contribute to international development as defined by CIDA's Sustainable Economic Growth Strategy by contributing to a stable investment environment and by maximizing the availability of public resources to be reinvested in the welfare of local communities;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">Whereas promoting responsible management of natural resources can improve the competitive advantage of Canadian companies using minerals from the Great Lakes Region of Africa by further enhancing the reputation of Canadian industries, reducing supply chain risk and increasing transparency and accountability in the corporate operating environment;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">And whereas Canada is committed to encouraging the responsible exploitation of natural resources and strongly supports continued responsible investment in the mining economies of the Great Lakes Region and the responsible sourcing of the region芒聙聶s minerals as a critical potential contributor to stability and development;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">Now, therefore, Her Majesty, by and with the advice and consent of the Senate and House of Commons of Canada, enacts as follow:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:SHORT TITLE--><Para TopMargin="10" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">SHORT TITLE</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Short title<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>1.</B> This Act may be cited as the <I>Conflict Minerals Act</I>.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:INTERPRETATION--><Para TopMargin="10" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">INTERPRETATION</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Interpretation<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>2.</B> The following definitions apply in this Act.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><MarginalNote>芒聙聹company芒聙聺<br />脗芦 <I>entreprise</I> 脗禄<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0">芒聙聹company芒聙聺 means any corporation or legal person incorporated by or under an Act of Parliament or the legislature of a province, or a subsidiary of such an entity.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><MarginalNote>芒聙聹Department芒聙聺<br />脗芦 <I>minist脙篓re</I> 脗禄<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0">芒聙聹Department芒聙聺 means the Department of Foreign Affairs and International Trade.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><MarginalNote>芒聙聹designated mineral芒聙聺<br />脗芦 <I>min脙漏ral d脙漏sign脙漏</I> 脗禄<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0">芒聙聹designated mineral芒聙聺 means a mineral originating in the Great Lakes Region of Africa that is</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>a</I>) gold, cassiterite, wolframite, coltan or any of their derivatives, such as tin, tungsten and tantalum; or</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>b</I>) any other mineral or derivative specified by order of the Minister.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><MarginalNote>芒聙聹Great Lakes Region of Africa芒聙聺<br />脗芦 <I>r脙漏gion des Grands Lacs africains</I> 脗禄<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0">芒聙聹Great Lakes Region of Africa芒聙聺 means the region of Africa that consists of Angola, Burundi, the Central African Republic, the Democratic Republic of the Congo, Kenya, Rwanda, Sudan, Tanzania, Uganda and Zambia, and any additional country specified by the International Conference on the Great Lakes Region.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><MarginalNote>芒聙聹illegal activity芒聙聺<br />脗芦 <I>activit脙漏 ill脙漏gale</I> 脗禄<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0">芒聙聹illegal activity芒聙聺 means</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>a</I>) any illegal activity that is intended to undermine or overthrow a legitimate government by violent means; and</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>b</I>) the illegal engagement in or profiting from the extraction, trade or transport of a designated mineral.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><MarginalNote>芒聙聹International Conference on the Great Lakes Region芒聙聺<br />脗芦 <I>Conf脙漏rence internationale sur la r脙漏gion des Grands Lacs</I> 脗禄<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0">芒聙聹International Conference on the Great Lakes Region芒聙聺 means the intergovernmental organization of countries in the Great Lakes Region of Africa, the members of which are Angola, Burundi, the Central African Republic, the Republic of Congo, the Democratic Republic of Congo, Kenya, Uganda, Rwanda, Sudan, Tanzania and Zambia.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><MarginalNote>芒聙聹Minister芒聙聺<br />脗芦 <I>ministre</I> 脗禄<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0">芒聙聹Minister芒聙聺 means the Minister of Foreign Affairs.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><MarginalNote>芒聙聹non-state armed group芒聙聺<br />脗芦 <I>groupe arm脙漏 non 脙漏tatique</I> 脗禄<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0">芒聙聹non-state armed group芒聙聺 means an armed rebel organization or other armed criminal entity.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><MarginalNote>芒聙聹OECD芒聙聺<br />脗芦 <I>OCDE</I> 脗禄<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0">芒聙聹OECD芒聙聺 means the Organisation for Economic Co-operation and Development.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><MarginalNote>芒聙聹public security force芒聙聺<br />脗芦 <I>force de s脙漏curit脙漏 publique</I> 脗禄<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0">芒聙聹public security force芒聙聺 means a lawful armed unit that is part of an army or a police force or other national force.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><MarginalNote>芒聙聹private security force芒聙聺<br />脗芦 <I>force de s脙漏curit脙漏 priv脙漏e</I> 脗禄<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0">芒聙聹private security force芒聙聺 means an armed individual or group of individuals employed or hired to provide private security services.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><MarginalNote>芒聙聹serious human rights abuse芒聙聺<br />脗芦 <I>graves violations des droits de la personne</I> 脗禄<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0">芒聙聹serious human rights abuse芒聙聺 includes</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>a</I>) any form of torture or other cruel, inhuman or degrading treatment;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>b</I>) any form of forced or compulsory labour;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>c</I>) child labour;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>d</I>) sexual violence and any other gross human rights violation; and</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>e</I>) war crimes, crimes against humanity, genocide and other serious violations of international humanitarian law.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><MarginalNote>芒聙聹supply chain芒聙聺<br />脗芦 <I>cha脙庐ne d芒聙聶approvisionnement</I> 脗禄<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0">芒聙聹supply chain芒聙聺 means the system that includes all of the activities, organizations, actors, technology, information, resources and services involved in moving a designated mineral from the extraction site to its incorporation in the final product for end consumers.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><MarginalNote>芒聙聹supply chain policy芒聙聺<br />脗芦 <I>politique relative 脙聽 la cha脙庐ne d芒聙聶approvisionnement</I> 脗禄<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0">芒聙聹supply chain policy芒聙聺 means the policy described in the document entitled <I>Model Supply Chain Policy for a Responsible Global Supply Chain of Minerals from Conflict-Affected and High-Risk Areas</I>, as set out in Annex II of the OECD document entitled <I>Due <keep>Diligence Guid-</keep>ance for Responsible Supply Chains of Minerals from Conflict-Affected and High-Risk Areas</I>, as amended from time to time.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:DUE DILIGENCE--><Para TopMargin="10" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">DUE DILIGENCE</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Requirement of due diligence<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>3.</B> (1) A company must exercise due diligence in respect of any extraction, processing, purchasing, trading in or use of designated minerals that it carries out in the course of its activities, or that it contracts to have carried out.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>For greater certainty<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(2) For greater certainty, the requirement to exercise due diligence applies as soon as a company commences any of the activities referred to in subsection (1) and continues until those activities have been completed.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Exercise of due diligence<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(3) For the purposes of this Act, the exercise of due diligence means conforming to the supply chain policy and includes, but is not limited to,</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>a</I>) the establishment of strong company management systems by, for example, adopting and committing to the supply chain policy for designated minerals and strengthening the company engagement with suppliers;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>b</I>) the identification of any risk that the supplier is sourcing from, or is directly or indirectly linked to, any non-state armed group or any public or private security force that is engaged in illegal activity or serious human rights abuse, and an assessment of the level of the risk;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>c</I>) the design and implementation of strategies to respond to any identified risk by, for example, immediately suspending or discontinuing engagement with a supplier; and</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>d</I>) carrying out an independent third-party audit of the company芒聙聶s due diligence practices.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:ANNUAL REPORT--><Para TopMargin="10" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">ANNUAL REPORT</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Report to Minister<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>4.</B> If a company has, during a fiscal year that commences after the date on which this Act comes into force, processed, purchased, traded in, used or extracted a designated mineral, or contracted to do so, the company must, within 60 days after the end of that fiscal year, submit to the Minister and publish on its website</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>a</I>) a report that specifies the measures taken by the company to exercise due diligence in respect of the source and supply chain of designated minerals; </Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>b</I>) an independent third party audit of the report that has been conducted in accordance with the supply chain policy and the particulars of the entity that conducted the audit;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>c</I>) a description of any use by the company of the designated mineral and of any products containing the designated mineral that were manufactured, or contracted to be manufactured, by the company;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>d</I>) a description of any commercial and financial transactions that have occurred in relation to the designated mineral to which the company was a party;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>e</I>) if applicable, a description of the facilities used by the company to process the designated mineral;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>f</I>) the country of origin of any such designated mineral; and</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>g</I>) a detailed description of the efforts made to determine the mine or location of origin of the designated mineral and the results of those efforts.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Publication by Minister<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>5.</B> Upon receiving a report referred to in section 4, the Minister must</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>a</I>) publish it on the departmental website and cause it to be laid before both Houses of Parliament; and</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>b</I>) share the report with the government of every country from which the reporting company obtained designated minerals during the fiscal year to which the report relates.</Para></Block><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="BPT_ImprintE"><br /><br />Published under authority of the Speaker of the House of Commons</Para></Block><Block Align="Yes" LineCnt="N"><Para NoLineBreak="Yes" NoHtml="Yes" Leading="0" Size="0" TopMargin="0" BottomMargin="0">脗聞</Para></Block></Bill_Part></Bill>