﻿<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><Bill RHead_reign="62-63 Eliz. II" RHead_ParlYear="2013-2014" DocumentTitle="BILL C-49" Bill_No="C-49" Document_No="90754" xml:lang="EN" Bill_Type="Amending" Stage_Name="First-Reading-House" Reprint="No" xml:space="preserve" ChapterNo_E="C. " ChapterNo_F="ch. " Bill-Origin="commons"><Bill_Part Part_Type="Cover" CountLines="No"><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="CovBillNo">C-49</Para></Block><Block><Para TopMargin="24" Size="9" Leading="10" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0" TextAlign="Center">Second Session, Forty-first Parliament,</Para></Block><Block><Para Size="9" Leading="10" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0" TextAlign="Center">62-63 Elizabeth II, 2013-2014</Para></Block><Block><Para TopMargin="48" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0" Bold="Yes" TextAlign="Center">HOUSE OF COMMONS OF CANADA</Para></Block><Block><Para TopMargin="42" Size="18" Leading="20" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0" Bold="Yes" TextAlign="Center">BILL C-49</Para></Block><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="CovLongTitle">An Act to amend the Competition Act</Para></Block><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="COV_StageLine"></Para></Block><Block><Para Size="9" AllCaps="Yes" Hyphenate="OFF">first reading, December 9, 2014</Para></Block><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="COV_StageLine"></Para></Block><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="Cover_Sponsors">MINISTER OF INDUSTRY</Para></Block><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="Cover_DocNo">90754</Para></Block></Bill_Part><Bill_Part CountLines="No" Part_Type="InsideCover"><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="BPT_InsideCoverE">Available on the Parliament of Canada Web Site at the following address:<br /><B>http://www.parl.gc.ca</B></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><Para TopMargin="108" BottomMargin="4" Size="10" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">SUMMARY</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" Size="8" Leading="9" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">This enactment amends the <I>Competition Act</I> to authorize the Commissioner of Competition to conduct inquiries to determine the reasons why a product or class of products has a higher selling price in Canada than in the United States and to require the Commissioner to make public reports on completed inquiries. It also requires that those amendments be reviewed within five years after the day on which they come into force.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" Size="8" Leading="9" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">The enactment also amends that Act to expressly authorize the issuance of court orders requiring a person who is located outside Canada to attend an examination, to produce documents or to make a written return in order to provide the Commissioner with information. It also amends that Act to enable the Commissioner to obtain a court order requiring a person to provide the Commissioner with information that an affiliate of the person is likely to have and that is relevant to an inquiry. Finally, the enactment amends that Act to expand the concept of affiliation to a broader range of business organizations.</Para></Block></Bill_Part><Bill_Part Part_Type="MainText" CountLines="Yes" RunningHead_E="Competition"><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="MainText_DocNo">90754</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes"><Para Style="Session_Reign">2nd Session, 41st Parliament,</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes"><Para Style="Session_Reign">62-63 Elizabeth II, 2013-2014</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes"><Para Style="MainBillOrigin">house of commons of canada</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes"><Para Bold="Yes" Style="MAIN@BillNo_Title">BILL C-49</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes"><Para Style="MAIN@ti;04">An Act to amend the Competition Act</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">Her Majesty, by and with the advice and consent of the Senate and House of Commons of Canada, enacts as follows:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:ALTERNATIVE TITLE--><Para TopMargin="10" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">ALTERNATIVE TITLE</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Alternative title<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>1.</B> This Act may be cited as the <I>Price Transparency Act</I>.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:COMPETITION ACT--><MarginalNote>R.S., c. C-34; <keep>R.S., c. 19</keep> (2nd Supp.), s. 19<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="10" Bold="Yes" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">COMPETITION ACT</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>2.</B> (1) Subsection 2(1) of the <I>Competition Act</I> is amended by adding the following in alphabetical order:</Para><ExplNote><Para Align="Yes" TopMargin="10" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0" Italic="Yes" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">Competition Act</Para><Para Align="Yes" TopMargin="10" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><I>Clause 2</I>: (1) New.</Para></ExplNote></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>“entity”<br />« <I>entité</I> »<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0"><change>“entity” means a corporation or a partnership, sole proprietorship, trust or other unincorporated organization capable of conducting business;</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>R.S., c. 19 (2nd Supp.), s. 20(4); 1999, c. 31, s. 44(F)<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes">(2) Subsections 2(2) and (3) of the Act are replaced by the following:</Para><ExplNote><Para Align="Yes" TopMargin="10" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(2) Existing text of subsections 2(2) and (3):</Para><Para Align="Yes" TopMargin="5" Size="8" Leading="9" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(2) For the purposes of this Act,</Para><Para Align="No" TopMargin="5" Size="8" Leading="9" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>a</I>) one corporation is affiliated with another corporation if one of them is the subsidiary of the other or both are subsidiaries of the same corporation or each of them is controlled by the same person;</Para><Para Align="No" TopMargin="5" Size="8" Leading="9" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>b</I>) if two corporations are affiliated with the same corporation at the same time, they are deemed to be affiliated with each other; and</Para><Para Align="No" TopMargin="5" Size="8" Leading="9" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>c</I>) a partnership or sole proprietorship is affiliated with another partnership, sole proprietorship or a company if both are controlled by the same person.</Para><Para Align="Yes" TopMargin="5" Size="8" Leading="9" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(3) For the purposes of this Act, a corporation is a subsidiary of another corporation if it is controlled by that other corporation.</Para></ExplNote></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Affiliation<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(2) For the purposes of this Act,</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>a</I>) one <change>entity</change> is affiliated with another <change>entity</change> if one of them is the subsidiary of the other or both are subsidiaries of the same <change>entity</change> or each of them is controlled by the same person;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>b</I>) if two <change>entities</change> are affiliated with the same <change>entity</change> at the same time, they are deemed to be affiliated with each other; and</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>c</I>) <change>an individual</change> is affiliated with <change>an entity</change> if <change>the individual controls the entity</change>.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Subsidiary entity<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(3) For the purposes of this Act, <change>an entity</change> is a subsidiary of another <change>entity</change> if it is controlled by that other <change>entity</change>.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>R.S., c. 19 (2nd Supp.), s. 20(4)<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes">(3) The portion of paragraph 2(4)(<I>a</I>) of the Act before subparagraph (ii) is replaced by the following:</Para><ExplNote><Para Align="Yes" TopMargin="10" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(3) and (4) Relevant portion of subsection 2(4):</Para><Para Align="Yes" TopMargin="5" Size="8" Leading="9" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(4) For the purposes of this Act,</Para><Para Align="No" TopMargin="5" Size="8" Leading="9" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>a</I>) a corporation is controlled by a person other than Her Majesty if</Para><Para Align="No" TopMargin="5" Size="8" Leading="9" LeftMargin="4" FirstLineIndent="0">(i) securities of the corporation to which are attached more than fifty per cent of the votes that may be cast to elect directors of the corporation are held, directly or indirectly, whether through one or more subsidiaries or otherwise, otherwise than by way of security only, by or for the benefit of that person, and</Para><Para Align="No" TopMargin="5" Size="8" Leading="9" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">... </Para><Para Align="No" TopMargin="5" Size="8" Leading="9" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>c</I>) a partnership is controlled by a person if the person holds an interest in the partnership that entitles the person to receive more than fifty per cent of the profits of the partnership or more than fifty per cent of its assets on dissolution.</Para></ExplNote></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>a</I>) a corporation is controlled by <change>an entity or an individual</change> other than Her Majesty if</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="4" FirstLineIndent="0">(i) securities of the corporation to which are attached more than 50% of the votes that may be cast to elect directors of the corporation are held, directly or indirectly, whether through one or more subsidiaries or otherwise, otherwise than by way of security only, by or for the benefit of that <change>entity or individual</change>, and</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>1999, c. 2, s. 1(3)<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes">(4) Paragraph 2(4)(<I>c</I>) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>c</I>) <change>an entity other than a corporation</change> is controlled by <change>an entity or individual</change> if <change>the entity or individual, directly or indirectly, whether through one or more subsidiaries or otherwise,</change> holds an interest in <change>the entity that is not a corporation</change> that entitles <change>them</change> to receive more than 50% of the profits of <change>that entity</change> or more than 50% of its assets on dissolution.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>3.</B> Section 10 of the Act is amended by adding the following after subsection (1):</Para><ExplNote><Para Align="Yes" TopMargin="10" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><I>Clause 3</I>: New.</Para></ExplNote></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Inquiry — higher price in Canada<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><change>(1.1) If the Commissioner has reason to believe that the selling price of a product or class of products is or was higher in Canada than the selling price of that product or class of products — or of a similar product or class of similar products — in the United States, the Commissioner may make an inquiry into the matter with a view to determining the facts, including the extent of the difference between the selling prices, and the reasons for that difference.</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>R.S., c. 19 (2nd Supp.), s. 24<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>4.</B> Subsections 11(2) and (3) of the Act are replaced by the following:</Para><ExplNote><Para Align="Yes" TopMargin="10" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><I>Clause 4</I>: Existing text of subsections 11(2) and (3):</Para><Para Align="Yes" TopMargin="5" Size="8" Leading="9" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(2) Where the person against whom an order is sought under paragraph <keep>(1)(<I>b</I>)</keep> in relation to an inquiry is a corporation and the judge to whom the application is made under subsection (1) is satisfied by information on oath or solemn affirmation that an affiliate of the corporation, whether the affiliate is located in Canada or outside Canada, has records that are relevant to the inquiry, the judge may order the corporation to produce the records.</Para><Para Align="Yes" TopMargin="5" Size="8" Leading="9" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(3) No person shall be excused from complying with an order under subsection (1) or (2) on the ground that the testimony, record or other thing or return required of the person may tend to criminate the person or subject him to any proceeding or penalty, but no testimony given by an individual pursuant to an order made under paragraph (1)(<I>a</I>), or return made by an individual pursuant to an order made under paragraph (1)(<I>c</I>), shall be used or received against that individual in any criminal proceedings thereafter instituted against him, other than a prosecution under section 132 or 136 of the <I>Criminal Code</I>.</Para></ExplNote></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Order —<keep>information</keep> in possession of affiliate<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><change>(2) If, on the <I>ex parte</I> application of the Commissioner or his or her authorized representative, a judge of a superior or county court is satisfied by information on oath or solemn affirmation that an inquiry is being made under section 10 and that any affiliate of a person, whether the affiliate is located in Canada or outside Canada, has or is likely to have information that is relevant to the inquiry, the judge may order the person to</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0"><change>(<I>a</I>) produce to the Commissioner or the authorized representative of the Commissioner within a period and at a place specified in the order, a record, a copy of a record certified by affidavit to be a true copy, or any other thing, specified in the order; or</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0"><change>(<I>b</I>) make and deliver to the Commissioner or the authorized representative of the Commissioner, within a period specified in the order, a written return on oath or solemn affirmation showing in detail the information that is required by the order.</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Person outside Canada<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><change>(2.1) An order under subsection (1) or (2) may be made against a person who is located outside Canada.</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>No person excused from complying with order<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(3) No person shall be excused from complying with an order <change>made</change> under subsection (1) or (2) on the ground that the testimony, record or other thing or return required of the person may tend to criminate the person or subject him <change>or her</change> to any proceeding or penalty, but no testimony given by an individual <change>under</change> an order made under paragraph (1)(<I>a</I>), or return made by an individual <change>under</change> an order made under paragraph (1)(<I>c</I>) <change>or (2)(<I>b</I>)</change>, shall be used or received against that individual in any criminal proceedings instituted against him <change>or her after the testimony is given or the return is made</change>, other than a prosecution under section 132 or 136 of the <I>Criminal Code</I>.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>5.</B> The Act is amended by adding the following after section 23:</Para><ExplNote><Para Align="Yes" TopMargin="10" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><I>Clause 5</I>: New.</Para></ExplNote></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Report —<keep>inquiry under</keep> subsection 10(1.1)<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><change><B>23.1</B> (1) Subject to subsections 22(1) and 23(1), the Commissioner shall prepare a report in writing setting out the Commissioner’s conclusions with respect to an inquiry made under subsection 10(1.1) and shall make the report accessible to the public.</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Time period<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><change>(2) The Commissioner shall take all reasonable steps to complete the report within one year after the day on which the Commissioner receives — on the Commissioner’s request or as the result of an order made under section 11 — the information that the Commissioner considers sufficient for the inquiry.</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>2009, c. 2, s. 410<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>6.</B> Paragraph 45(6)(<I>a</I>) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Para><ExplNote><Para Align="Yes" TopMargin="10" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><I>Clause 6</I>: Relevant portion of subsection 45(6):</Para><Para Align="Yes" TopMargin="5" Size="8" Leading="9" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(6) Subsection (1) does not apply if the conspiracy, agreement or arrangement</Para><Para Align="No" TopMargin="5" Size="8" Leading="9" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>a</I>) is entered into only by companies each of which is, in respect of every one of the others, an affiliate; or</Para></ExplNote></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>a</I>) is entered into only by <change>entities</change> each of which is, in respect of every one of the others, an affiliate <change>or by entities and an individual each of which is, in respect of every one of the others, an affiliate</change>; or</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>R.S., c. 19 (2nd Supp.), s. 33<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>7.</B> Subsection 47(3) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Para><ExplNote><Para Align="Yes" TopMargin="10" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><I>Clause 7</I>: Existing text of subsection 47(3):</Para><Para Align="Yes" TopMargin="5" Size="8" Leading="9" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(3) This section does not apply in respect of an agreement or arrangement that is entered into or a submission that is arrived at only by companies each of which is, in respect of every one of the others, an affiliate.</Para></ExplNote></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Exception<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(3) This section does not apply in respect of an agreement or arrangement that is entered into or a submission that is arrived at only by <change>entities</change> each of which is, in respect of every one of the others, an affiliate <change>or by entities and an individual each of which is, in respect of every one of the others, an affiliate</change>.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>2009, c. 2, s. 426<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>8.</B> Subsection 76(4) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Para><ExplNote><Para Align="Yes" TopMargin="10" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><I>Clause 8</I>: Existing text of subsection 76(4):</Para><Para Align="Yes" TopMargin="5" Size="8" Leading="9" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(4) No order may be made under subsection (2) if the person referred to in subsection (3) and the customer or other person referred to in subparagraph <keep>(1)(<I>a</I>)(i)</keep> or (ii) are principal and agent or mandator and mandatary, or are affiliated corporations or directors, agents, mandataries, officers or employees of</Para><Para Align="No" TopMargin="5" Size="8" Leading="9" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>a</I>) the same corporation, partnership or sole proprietorship; or</Para><Para Align="No" TopMargin="5" Size="8" Leading="9" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>b</I>) corporations, partnerships or sole proprietorships that are affiliated.</Para></ExplNote></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>When no order may be made<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(4) No order may be made under subsection (2) if the person referred to in subsection (3) and the customer or other person referred to in subparagraph (1)(<I>a</I>)(i) or (ii) are</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>a</I>) principal and agent or mandator and mandatary;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0"><change>(<I>b</I>) a corporation and an individual who controls it or affiliated corporations; or</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0"><change>(<I>c</I>)</change> directors, agents, mandataries, officers or employees of the same <change>entity</change> or of <change>entities</change> that are affiliated.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>1999, c. 31, s. 52(1)(F)<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>9.</B> (1) The portion of subsection 77(4) of the Act after paragraph (<I>c</I>) is replaced by the following:</Para><ExplNote><Para Align="Yes" TopMargin="10" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><I>Clause 9</I>: (1) Relevant portion of subsection 77(4):</Para><Para Align="Yes" TopMargin="5" Size="8" Leading="9" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(4) The Tribunal shall not make an order under this section where, in its opinion,</Para><Para Align="No" TopMargin="5" Size="8" Leading="9" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">... </Para><Para Align="No" TopMargin="5" Size="8" Leading="9" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>c</I>) tied selling that is engaged in by a person in the business of lending money is for the purpose of better securing loans made by that person and is reasonably necessary for that purpose,</Para><Para Align="No" TopMargin="5" Size="8" Leading="9" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0">and no order made under this section applies in respect of exclusive dealing, market restriction or tied selling between or among companies, partnerships and sole proprietorships that are affiliated.</Para></ExplNote></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0">No order made under this section applies in respect of exclusive dealing, market restriction or tied selling between or among <change>entities</change> that are affiliated.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>R.S., c. 19 (2nd Supp.), s. 45; 1999, c. 31, ss. 52(2) and (3)(F)<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes">(2) Subsection 77(5) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Para><ExplNote><Para Align="Yes" TopMargin="10" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(2) Existing text of subsection 77(5):</Para><Para Align="Yes" TopMargin="5" Size="8" Leading="9" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(5) For the purposes of subsection (4),</Para><Para Align="No" TopMargin="5" Size="8" Leading="9" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>a</I>) one company is affiliated with another company if one of them is the subsidiary of the other or both are the subsidiaries of the same company or each of them is controlled by the same person;</Para><Para Align="No" TopMargin="5" Size="8" Leading="9" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>b</I>) if two companies are affiliated with the same company at the same time, they are deemed to be affiliated with each other;</Para><Para Align="No" TopMargin="5" Size="8" Leading="9" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>c</I>) a partnership or sole proprietorship is affiliated with another partnership, sole proprietorship or a company if both are controlled by the same person; and</Para><Para Align="No" TopMargin="5" Size="8" Leading="9" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>d</I>) a company, partnership or sole proprietorship is affiliated with another company, partnership or sole proprietorship in respect of any agreement between them whereby one party grants to the other party the right to use a trade-mark or trade-name to identify the business of the grantee, if</Para><Para Align="No" TopMargin="5" Size="8" Leading="9" LeftMargin="4" FirstLineIndent="0">(i) the business is related to the sale or distribution, pursuant to a marketing plan or system prescribed substantially by the grantor, of a multiplicity of products obtained from competing sources of supply and a multiplicity of suppliers, and</Para><Para Align="No" TopMargin="5" Size="8" Leading="9" LeftMargin="4" FirstLineIndent="0">(ii) no one product dominates the business.</Para></ExplNote></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>If entity affiliated<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(5) For the purposes of subsection (4), <change>an entity</change> is affiliated with another <change>entity</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0"><change>(<I>a</I>) in the manner set out in paragraph 2(2)(<I>a</I>) or (<I>b</I>); and</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>b</I>) in respect of any agreement between them <change>in which</change> one <change>of them</change> grants to the other the right to use a trademark or trade name to identify the business of the grantee, if</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="4" FirstLineIndent="0">(i) the business is related to the sale or distribution, <change>in accordance with</change> a marketing plan or system prescribed substantially by the grantor, of a multiplicity of products obtained from competing sources of supply and a multiplicity of suppliers, and</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="4" FirstLineIndent="0">(ii) no one product dominates the business.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>2009, c. 2, s. 429<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>10.</B> Subsection 90.1(7) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Para><ExplNote><Para Align="Yes" TopMargin="10" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><I>Clause 10</I>: Existing text of subsection 90.1(7):</Para><Para Align="Yes" TopMargin="5" Size="8" Leading="9" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(7) Subsection (1) does not apply if the agreement or arrangement is entered into, or would be entered into, only by companies each of which is, in respect of every one of the others, an affiliate.</Para></ExplNote></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Exception<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(7) Subsection (1) does not apply if the agreement or arrangement is entered into, or would be entered into, only by <change>entities</change> each of which is, in respect of every one of the others, an affiliate <change>or by entities and an individual each of which is, in respect of every one of the others, an affiliate</change>.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>R.S., c. 19 (2nd Supp.), s. 45<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>11.</B> (1) The definition “person” in subsection 108(1) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Para><ExplNote><Para Align="Yes" TopMargin="10" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><I>Clause 11</I>: (1) Existing text of the definition:</Para><Para Align="Yes" TopMargin="5" Size="8" Leading="9" LeftMargin="0">“person” means an individual, body corporate, unincorporated syndicate, unincorporated organization, trustee, executor, administrator or other legal representative, but does not include a bare trustee;</Para></ExplNote></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>“person”<br />« <I>personne</I> »<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0">“person” means <change>an entity</change>, an individual <change>or a</change> trustee, executor, administrator or <change>liquidator of the succession, administrator of the property of others</change> or representative, but does not include a bare trustee <change>or a trustee responsible exclusively for preserving and transferring the property of a person</change>;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes">(2) Subsection 108(1) of the Act is amended by adding the following in alphabetical order:</Para><ExplNote><Para Align="Yes" TopMargin="10" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(2) New.</Para></ExplNote></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>“equity interest”<br />« <I>intérêt relatif à des capitaux propres</I> »<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0"><change>“equity interest” means</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0"><change>(<I>a</I>) in the case of a corporation, a share in the corporation; and</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0"><change>(<I>b</I>) in the case of an entity other than a corporation, an interest that entitles the holder of that interest to receive profits of that entity or assets of that entity on its dissolution.</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>R.S., c. 19 (2nd Supp.), s. 45<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes">(3) Subsection 108(2) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Para><ExplNote><Para Align="Yes" TopMargin="10" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(3) Existing text of subsection 108(2):</Para><Para Align="Yes" TopMargin="5" Size="8" Leading="9" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(2) For the purposes of this Part, except for the purposes of section 113, one corporation is not affiliated with another corporation by reason only of the fact that both corporations are controlled by Her Majesty in right of Canada or a province, as the case may be.</Para></ExplNote></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Entities controlled by Her Majesty<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(2) For the purposes of this Part, except section 113, one <change>entity</change> is not affiliated with another <change>entity</change> by reason only of the fact that both <change>entities</change> are controlled by Her Majesty in right of Canada or a province, as the case may be.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>1999, c. 2, s. 26<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>12.</B> Subsection 109(2) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Para><ExplNote><Para Align="Yes" TopMargin="10" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><I>Clause 12</I>: Existing text of subsection 109(2):</Para><Para Align="Yes" TopMargin="5" Size="8" Leading="9" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(2) For the purposes of this Part, the parties to a proposed acquisition of shares are the person or persons who propose to acquire the shares and the corporation the shares of which are to be acquired.</Para></ExplNote></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Parties to acquisition of shares or interest<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(2) For the purposes of this Part,</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0"><change>(<I>a</I>)</change> the parties to a proposed acquisition of shares are the person or persons who propose to acquire the shares and the corporation <change>whose</change> shares are to be acquired; <change>and</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0"><change>(<I>b</I>) the parties to a proposed acquisition of an interest in a combination are the person or persons who propose to acquire the interest and the combination whose interest is to be acquired.</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>2009, c. 2, s. 436<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>13.</B> (1) The portion of subsection 110(3) of the Act before subparagraph (<I>a</I>)(ii) is replaced by the following:</Para><ExplNote><Para Align="Yes" TopMargin="10" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><I>Clause 13</I>: (1) Relevant portion of subsection 110(3):</Para><Para Align="Yes" TopMargin="5" Size="8" Leading="9" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(3) Subject to sections 111 and 113, this Part applies in respect of a proposed acquisition of voting shares of a corporation that carries on an operating business or controls a corporation that carries on an operating business</Para><Para Align="No" TopMargin="5" Size="8" Leading="9" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>a</I>) if</Para><Para Align="No" TopMargin="5" Size="8" Leading="9" LeftMargin="4" FirstLineIndent="0">(i) the aggregate value of the assets in Canada, determined as of the time and in the manner that is prescribed, that are owned by the corporation or by corporations controlled by that corporation, other than assets that are shares of any of those corporations, would exceed the amount determined under subsection (7) or (8), as the case may be, or</Para></ExplNote></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Acquisition of shares<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(3) Subject to sections 111 and 113, this Part applies in respect of a proposed acquisition of voting shares of a corporation that carries on an operating business or controls <change>an entity</change> that carries on an operating business</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>a</I>) if</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="4" FirstLineIndent="0">(i) the aggregate value of the assets in Canada, determined as of the time and in the manner that is prescribed, that are owned by the corporation or by <change>entities</change> controlled by that corporation, other than assets that are <change>equity interests in those entities</change>, would exceed the amount <change>set out in</change> subsection (7) or <change>the amount</change> determined under <change>subsection</change> (8), as the case may be, or</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>2009, c. 2, s. 436<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes">(2) The portion of subsection 110(4) of the Act before paragraph (<I>b</I>) is replaced by the following:</Para><ExplNote><Para Align="Yes" TopMargin="10" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(2) Relevant portion of subsection 110(4):</Para><Para Align="Yes" TopMargin="5" Size="8" Leading="9" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(4) Subject to subsection (4.1) and section 113, this Part applies in respect of a proposed amalgamation of two or more corporations if one or more of those corporations carries on an operating business, or controls a corporation that carries on an operating business, where</Para><Para Align="No" TopMargin="5" Size="8" Leading="9" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>a</I>) the aggregate value of the assets in Canada, determined as of the time and in the manner that is prescribed, that would be owned by the continuing corporation that would result from the amalgamation or by corporations controlled by the continuing corporation, other than assets that are shares of any of those corporations, would exceed the amount determined under subsection (7) or (8), as the case may be; or</Para></ExplNote></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Amalgamation<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(4) Subject to subsection (4.1) and section 113, this Part applies in respect of a proposed amalgamation of two or more <change>entities</change> if one or more of those <change>entities</change> carries on an operating business, or controls <change>an entity</change> that carries on an operating business, <change>if</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>a</I>) the aggregate value of the assets in Canada, determined as of the time and in the manner that is prescribed, that would be owned by the continuing <change>entity</change> that would result from the amalgamation or by <change>entities</change> controlled by the continuing <change>entity</change>, other than assets that are <change>equity interests in those entities</change>, would exceed the amount <change>set out in</change> subsection (7) or <change>the amount</change> determined under <change>subsection</change> (8), as the case may be; or</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>2009, c. 2, s. 436<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes">(3) The portion of subsection 110(4.1) of the Act before paragraph (<I>a</I>) is replaced by the following:</Para><ExplNote><Para Align="Yes" TopMargin="10" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(3) Relevant portion of subsection 110(4.1):</Para><Para Align="Yes" TopMargin="5" Size="8" Leading="9" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(4.1) This Part does not apply in respect of a proposed amalgamation of two or more corporations if one or more of those corporations carries on an operating business or controls a corporation that carries on an operating business, unless each of at least two of the amalgamating corporations, together with its affiliates,</Para></ExplNote></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>General limit relating to parties to an amalgamation<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(4.1) This Part does not apply in respect of a proposed amalgamation of two or more <change>entities</change> if one or more of those <change>entities</change> carries on an operating business or controls <change>an entity</change> that carries on an operating business, unless each of at least two of the amalgamating <change>entities</change>, together with its affiliates,</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>2009, c. 2, s. 436<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes">(4) The portion of subsection 110(5) of the Act before paragraph (<I>a</I>) is replaced by the following:</Para><ExplNote><Para Align="Yes" TopMargin="10" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(4) Relevant portion of subsection 110(5):</Para><Para Align="Yes" TopMargin="5" Size="8" Leading="9" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(5) Subject to sections 112 and 113, this Part applies in respect of a proposed combination of two or more persons to carry on business otherwise than through a corporation if one or more of those persons proposes to contribute to the combination assets that form all or part of an operating business carried on by those persons, or corporations controlled by those persons, and if</Para></ExplNote></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Combination<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(5) Subject to sections 112 and 113, this Part applies in respect of a proposed combination of two or more persons to carry on business otherwise than through a corporation if one or more of those persons proposes to contribute to the combination assets that form all or part of an operating business carried on by those persons, or <change>entities</change> controlled by those persons, and if</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>1999, c. 31, s. 229<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>14.</B> Paragraph 111(<I>f</I>) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Para><ExplNote><Para Align="Yes" TopMargin="10" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><I>Clause 14</I>: Relevant portion of section 111:</Para><Para Align="Yes" TopMargin="5" Size="8" Leading="9" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>111.</B> The following classes of transactions are exempt from the application of this Part:</Para><Para Align="No" TopMargin="5" Size="8" Leading="9" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">... </Para><Para Align="No" TopMargin="5" Size="8" Leading="9" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>f</I>) an acquisition of voting shares of a corporation pursuant to an agreement in writing that provides for the issuance of those shares only if the person or persons acquiring them incur expenses to carry out exploration or development activities with respect to a Canadian resource property, as defined in subsection 66(15) of the <I>Income Tax Act</I>, in respect of which the corporation has the right to carry out those activities where the corporation does not have any significant assets other than that property.</Para></ExplNote></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>f</I>) an acquisition of <change>equity interests in an entity under</change> an agreement in writing that provides for the <change>creation</change> of those <change>equity interests</change> only if the person or persons acquiring them incur expenses to carry out exploration or development activities with respect to a Canadian resource property, as defined in subsection 66(15) of the <I>Income Tax Act</I>, in respect of which the <change>entity</change> has the right to carry out those activities <change>if</change> the <change>entity</change> does not have any significant assets other than that property.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>2009, c. 2, s. 437<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>15.</B> (1) Paragraph 114(1)(<I>b</I>) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Para><ExplNote><Para Align="Yes" TopMargin="10" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><I>Clause 15</I>: (1) Relevant portion of subsection 114(1):</Para><Para Align="Yes" TopMargin="5" Size="8" Leading="9" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>114.</B> (1) Subject to this Part, the parties to a proposed transaction shall, before the transaction is completed, notify the Commissioner that the transaction is proposed and supply the Commissioner with the prescribed information in accordance with this Part, if</Para><Para Align="No" TopMargin="5" Size="8" Leading="9" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">... </Para><Para Align="No" TopMargin="5" Size="8" Leading="9" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>b</I>) two or more corporations propose to amalgamate in the circumstances set out in subsection 110(4); or</Para></ExplNote></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>b</I>) two or more <change>entities</change> propose <keep>to amalgam-</keep>ate in the circumstances set out in subsection 110(4); or</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>2009, c. 2, s. 437<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes">(2) Subsection 114(3) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Para><ExplNote><Para Align="Yes" TopMargin="10" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(2) Existing text of subsection 114(3):</Para><Para Align="Yes" TopMargin="5" Size="8" Leading="9" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(3) If a proposed transaction is an acquisition of shares and the Commissioner receives information supplied under subsection (1) by a party to the transaction, other than the corporation whose shares are being acquired, before receiving such information from the corporation,</Para><Para Align="No" TopMargin="5" Size="8" Leading="9" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>a</I>) the Commissioner shall immediately notify the corporation that the Commissioner has received from that party the prescribed information; and</Para><Para Align="No" TopMargin="5" Size="8" Leading="9" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>b</I>) the corporation shall supply the Commissioner with the prescribed information within 10 days after being notified under paragraph (<I>a</I>).</Para></ExplNote></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Entity whose equity interests are acquired<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(3) If a proposed transaction <keep>is an acqui-</keep>sition of <change>equity interests in an entity</change> <keep>and the Commissioner</keep> receives information supplied under subsection (1) by a party to the <keep>transaction, other</keep> than the <change>entity</change> whose <change>equity interests</change> are being acquired, before receiving <change>the</change> information from the <change>entity</change>,</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>a</I>) the Commissioner shall immediately notify the <change>entity</change> that the Commissioner has received from that party the prescribed information; and</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>b</I>) the <change>entity</change> shall supply the Commissioner with the prescribed information within 10 days after being notified under paragraph (<I>a</I>).</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>R.S., c. 19 (2nd Supp.), s. 45; 1999, c. 2, s. 33 and par. <keep>37(<I>z.16</I>);</keep> 2009, c. 2, s. 438<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>16.</B> Section 116 of the Act is replaced by the following:</Para><ExplNote><Para Align="Yes" TopMargin="10" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><I>Clause 16</I>: Existing text of section 116:</Para><Para Align="Yes" TopMargin="5" Size="8" Leading="9" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>116.</B> (1) If any of the information required under section 114 is not known or reasonably obtainable, or cannot be supplied because of the privilege that exists in respect of lawyers and notaries and their clients or because of a confidentiality requirement established by law, the person who is supplying the information may, instead of supplying the information, inform the Commissioner under oath or solemn affirmation of the matters in respect of which information has not been supplied and the reason why it has not been supplied.</Para><Para Align="Yes" TopMargin="5" Size="8" Leading="9" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(2) If any of the information required under section 114 could not, on any reasonable basis, be considered to be relevant to an assessment by the Commissioner as to whether the proposed transaction would or would be likely to prevent or lessen competition substantially, the person who is supplying the information may, in lieu of supplying the information, inform the Commissioner under oath or solemn affirmation of the matters in respect of which information has not been supplied and why the information was not considered relevant.</Para><Para Align="Yes" TopMargin="5" Size="8" Leading="9" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(2.1) If any of the information required under section 114 has previously been supplied to the Commissioner, the person who is supplying the information may, in lieu of supplying it, inform the Commissioner under oath or solemn affirmation of the matters in respect of which information has previously been supplied and when it was supplied.</Para><Para Align="Yes" TopMargin="5" Size="8" Leading="9" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(3) Where a person chooses not to supply the Commissioner with information required under section 114 and so informs the Commissioner in accordance with subsection (2) or (2.1) and the Commissioner or a person authorized by the Commissioner notifies that person, within seven days after the Commissioner is so informed, that the information is required, the person shall supply the Commissioner with the information.</Para></ExplNote></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>If information cannot be supplied<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>116.</B> (1) If any of the information required under section 114 is not known or reasonably obtainable, or cannot be supplied because of the privilege that exists in respect of lawyers and notaries and their clients or because of a confidentiality requirement established by law, the <change>entity or individual</change> who is supplying the information may, instead of supplying the information, inform the Commissioner under oath or solemn affirmation of the matters in respect of which information has not been supplied and the reason why it has not been supplied.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>If information not relevant<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(2) If any of the information required under section 114 could not, on any reasonable basis, be considered to be relevant to an assessment by the Commissioner as to whether the proposed transaction would or would be likely to prevent or lessen competition substantially, the <change>entity or individual</change> who is supplying the information may, <change>instead</change> of supplying the information, inform the Commissioner under oath or solemn affirmation of the matters in respect of which information has not been supplied and why the information was not considered relevant.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>If information previously supplied<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(2.1) If any of the information required under section 114 has previously been supplied to the Commissioner, the <change>entity or individual</change> who is supplying the information may, <change>instead</change> of supplying it, inform the Commissioner under oath or solemn affirmation of the matters in respect of which information has previously been supplied and when it was supplied.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Commissioner may require information<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(3) <change>If an entity or individual</change> chooses not to supply the Commissioner with information required under section 114 and so informs the Commissioner in accordance with subsection (2) or (2.1) and the Commissioner or a person authorized by the Commissioner notifies that <change>entity or individual</change>, within seven days after the Commissioner is so informed, that the information is required, the <change>entity or individual</change> shall supply the Commissioner with the information.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>R.S., c. 19 (2nd Supp.), s. 45<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>17.</B> Subsection 117(1) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Para><ExplNote><Para Align="Yes" TopMargin="10" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><I>Clause 17</I>: Existing text of subsection 117(1):</Para><Para Align="Yes" TopMargin="5" Size="8" Leading="9" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>117.</B> (1) Nothing in section 114 requires any person who is a director of a corporation to supply information that is known to that person by virtue only of his position as a director of an affiliate of the corporation that is neither a wholly-owned affiliate nor a wholly-owning affiliate of the corporation.</Para></ExplNote></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Saving<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>117.</B> (1) Nothing in section 114 requires</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0"><change>(<I>a</I>)</change> any <change>individual</change> who is a director of a corporation to supply information that is known to that <change>individual</change> by virtue only of <change>their</change> position as a director of an affiliate of the corporation that is neither a wholly-owned affiliate nor a wholly-owning affiliate of the corporation; or</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0"><change>(<I>b</I>) any individual who, in respect of an entity other than a corporation, serves in a capacity similar to that of a director to supply information that is known to that individual by virtue only of their serving in that capacity with respect to an affiliate of the entity that is neither a wholly-owned affiliate nor a wholly-owning affiliate of the entity.</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>R.S., c. 19 (2nd Supp.), s. 45; 1999, c. 2, par. 37(<I>z.17</I>)<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>18.</B> Section 118 of the Act is replaced by the following:</Para><ExplNote><Para Align="Yes" TopMargin="10" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><I>Clause 18</I>: Existing text of section 118:</Para><Para Align="Yes" TopMargin="5" Size="8" Leading="9" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>118.</B> The information supplied to the Commissioner under section 114 shall be certified on oath or solemn affirmation</Para><Para Align="No" TopMargin="5" Size="8" Leading="9" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>a</I>) in the case of a corporation supplying the information, by an officer thereof or other person duly authorized by the board of directors or other governing body of the corporation, or</Para><Para Align="No" TopMargin="5" Size="8" Leading="9" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>b</I>) in the case of any other person supplying the information, by that person,</Para><Para Align="No" TopMargin="5" Size="8" Leading="9" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0">as having been examined by that person and as being, to the best of his knowledge and belief, correct and complete in all material respects.</Para></ExplNote></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Information to be certified<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>118.</B> The information supplied to the Commissioner under section 114 shall be certified on oath or solemn affirmation as having been examined by <change>one of the following individuals</change> and as being, to the best of <change>that individual’s</change> knowledge and belief, correct and complete in all material respects:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>a</I>) in the case of a corporation supplying the information, by an officer <change>of the corporation</change> or other person duly authorized by the board of directors or other governing body of the corporation;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0"><change>(<I>b</I>) in the case of an entity other than a corporation supplying the information, by an individual who serves in a capacity similar to that of an officer of a corporation or other individual duly authorized by the governing body of that entity;</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>c</I>) in the case of <change>an individual</change> supplying the information, by that <change>individual</change>.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>2009, c. 2, s. 439<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>19.</B> Subsections 123(2) and (3) of the Act are replaced by the following:</Para><ExplNote><Para Align="Yes" TopMargin="10" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><I>Clause 19</I>: Existing text of subsections 123(2) and (3):</Para><Para Align="Yes" TopMargin="5" Size="8" Leading="9" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(2) A proposed transaction referred to in section 114 may be completed before the end of a period referred to in subsection (1) if, before the end of that period, the Commissioner or a person authorized by the Commissioner notifies the persons who are required to give notice and supply information that the Commissioner does not, at that time, intend to make an application under section 92 in respect of the proposed transaction.</Para><Para Align="Yes" TopMargin="5" Size="8" Leading="9" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(3) In the case of an acquisition of voting shares to which subsection 114(3) applies, the periods referred to in subsection (1) shall be determined without reference to the day on which the information required under section 114 is received by the Commissioner from the corporation whose shares are being acquired.</Para></ExplNote></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Waiving of waiting period<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(2) A proposed transaction referred to in section 114 may be completed before the end of a period referred to in subsection (1) if, before the end of that period, the Commissioner or a person authorized by the Commissioner notifies <change>the parties to the transaction</change> that the Commissioner does not, at that time, intend to make an application under section 92 in respect of <change>that</change> proposed transaction.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Acquisition of equity interests<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(3) In the case of an acquisition of <change>equity interests</change> to which subsection 114(3) applies, the periods referred to in subsection (1) shall be determined without reference to the day on which the information required under section 114 is received by the Commissioner from the <change>entity</change> whose <change>equity interests</change> are being acquired.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>20.</B> The Act is amended by adding the following after section 127:</Para><ExplNote><Para Align="Yes" TopMargin="10" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><I>Clause 20</I>: New.</Para></ExplNote></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Review —subsection <keep>10(1.1)</keep> and section 23.1<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><change><B>127.1</B> (1) Within five years after the day on which this section comes into force, a review of subsection 10(1.1) and section 23.1 and their operation shall be undertaken by a committee of the Senate, of the House of Commons or of both Houses of Parliament that is designated or established for that purpose.</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Report<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><change>(2) The committee shall cause a report on the review to be laid before each House of Parliament within a reasonable time after the review has been completed.</change></Para></Block><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="BPT_ImprintE"><br /><br />Published under authority of the Speaker of the House of Commons</Para></Block><Block Align="Yes" LineCnt="N"><Para NoLineBreak="Yes" NoHtml="Yes" Leading="0" Size="0" TopMargin="0" BottomMargin="0"></Para></Block></Bill_Part></Bill>