﻿<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><Bill RHead_reign="62-63 Eliz. II" RHead_ParlYear="2013-2014" DocumentTitle="BILL C-525" Bill_No="C-525" Document_No="411746" xml:lang="EN" Bill_Type="Non-amending" Stage_Name="Assented-to" Reprint="No" xml:space="preserve" ChapterNo_E="C. 40" ChapterNo_F="ch. 40" Bill-Origin="commons"><Bill_Part Part_Type="Cover" CountLines="No"><Block><Para TopMargin="24" Size="9" Leading="10" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0" TextAlign="Center">Second Session, Forty-first Parliament,</Para></Block><Block><Para Size="9" Leading="10" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0" TextAlign="Center">62-63 Elizabeth II, 2013-2014</Para></Block><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="COV@StatutesTitle">STATUTES OF CANADA 2014<br />CHAPTER 40</Para></Block><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="CovLongTitle">An Act to amend the Canada Labour Code, the Parliamentary Employment and Staff Relations Act and the Public Service Labour Relations Act (certification and revocation — bargaining agent)</Para></Block><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="COV_StageLine"></Para></Block><Block><Para BottomMargin="14" Size="11" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0" Bold="Yes" TextAlign="Center">ASSENTED TO</Para></Block><Block><Para Size="8" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0" TextAlign="Center">16th DECEMBER, 2014</Para></Block><Block><Para TopMargin="4" Size="8" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0" TextAlign="Center">BILL C-525</Para></Block><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="COV_StageLine"></Para></Block></Bill_Part><Bill_Part CountLines="No" Part_Type="InsideCover"><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="BPT_InsideCoverE">Available on the Parliament of Canada Web Site at the following address:<br /><B>http://www.parl.gc.ca</B></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><Para TopMargin="108" BottomMargin="4" Size="10" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">SUMMARY</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" Size="8" Leading="9" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">This enactment amends the <I>Canada Labour Code</I>, the <I>Parliamentary Employment and Staff Relations Act</I> and the <I>Public Service Labour Relations Act</I> to provide that the certification and decertification of a bargaining agent under these Acts must be achieved by a secret ballot vote-based majority.</Para></Block></Bill_Part><Bill_Part Part_Type="MainText" CountLines="No" RunningHead_E="Canada Labour Code, Parliamentary Employment and Staff Relations and Public Service Labour Relations (certification and revocation — bargaining agent)"><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="MAIN@RoyalAssentTitle">62-63 ELIZABETH II</Para></Block><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="MAIN@RoyalAssentTitle">——————</Para></Block><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="MAIN@RoyalAssentTitle">CHAPTER 40</Para></Block><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="LongTitleAssent">An Act to amend the Canada Labour Code, the Parliamentary Employment and Staff Relations Act and the Public Service Labour Relations Act (certification and revocation — bargaining agent)</Para></Block><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="MAIN@RoyalAssentDate">[<I>Assented to 16th December, 2014</I>]</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">Her Majesty, by and with the advice and consent of the Senate and House of Commons of Canada enacts as follows:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:SHORT TITLE--><Para TopMargin="10" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">SHORT TITLE</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Short title<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>1.</B> This Act may be cited as the <I>Employees' Voting Rights Act</I>.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:CANADA LABOUR CODE--><MarginalNote>R.S., c. L-2<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="10" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center"><B>CANADA LABOUR CODE</B></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>2.</B> Section 28 of the <I>Canada Labour Code</I> is replaced by the following:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Duty to certify trade union<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>28.</B> (1) If the Board is satisfied on the basis of the results of a secret ballot representation vote that a majority of the employees in a unit who have cast a ballot have voted to have a trade union represent them as their bargaining agent, the Board shall, subject to this Part, certify the trade union as the bargaining agent for the unit.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Representation vote<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(2) The Board shall order that a secret ballot representation vote be taken among the employees in a unit if the Board</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>a</I>) has received from a trade union an application for certification as the bargaining agent for the unit;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>b</I>) has determined that the unit constitutes a unit appropriate for collective bargaining; and</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>c</I>) is satisfied on the basis of evidence of membership in the trade union that, as of the date of the filing of the application, at least 40% of the employees in the unit wish to have the trade union represent them as their bargaining agent.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>3.</B> (1) Subsection 29(1) of the Act is repealed.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes">(2) Subsection 29(2) of the Act is repealed.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>4.</B> (1) Subsection 38(1) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Application for revocation of certification<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>38.</B> (1) If a trade union has been certified as the bargaining agent for a bargaining unit, any employee who claims to represent at least 40% of the employees in the bargaining unit may, subject to subsection (5), apply to the Board for an order revoking the certification of that trade union.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>(2)</B> <B>Subsection 38(3) of the Act is replaced by the following:</B></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Application for order that bargaining agent not entitled to represent bargaining unit<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(3) If a collective agreement applicable to a bargaining unit is in force but the bargaining agent that is a party to the collective agreement has not been certified by the Board, any employee who claims to represent at least 40% of the employees in the bargaining unit may, subject to subsection (5), apply to the Board for an order declaring that the bargaining agent is not entitled to represent the employees in the bargaining unit.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>5.</B> Subsections 39(1) and (2) of the Act are replaced by the following:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Order revoking certification or declaring bargaining agent not entitled to represent bargaining unit<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>39.</B> If the Board has received an application for an order made under subsection 38(1) or (3) in respect of a bargaining agent for a bargaining unit, the Board shall grant the order if</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>a</I>) it is satisfied on the basis of written evidence that, as of the date of the filing of the application, at least 40% of the employees in the bargaining unit no longer wish to have the bargaining agent represent them, and</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>b</I>) it is satisfied on the basis of the results of a secret ballot representation vote that a majority of the employees in the bargaining unit who have cast a ballot no longer wish to be represented by the bargaining agent.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:PARLIAMENTARY EMPLOYMENT AND STAFF RELATIONS ACT--><MarginalNote>R.S., c.33 (2nd Supp.)<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="10" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center"><B>PARLIAMENTARY EMPLOYMENT AND STAFF RELATIONS ACT</B></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>6.</B> Section 25 of the <I>Parliamentary Employment and Staff Relations Act</I> is replaced by the following:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Duty to certify employee organization<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>25.</B> (1) If the Board is satisfied on the basis of the results of a secret ballot representation vote that a majority of the employees in a proposed bargaining unit who have cast a ballot have voted to have an employee organization represent them as their bargaining agent, the Board shall, subject to this Part, certify the employee organization as bargaining agent for the employees in the unit.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Representation vote<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(2) The Board shall direct that a secret ballot representation vote be taken among a group of employees if the Board</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>a</I>) has received from an employee organization an application for certification as bargaining agent for a bargaining unit in accordance with this Part;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>b</I>) has determined, in accordance with section 23, that the group of employees constitutes a unit appropriate for collective bargaining;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>c</I>) is satisfied on the basis of evidence of membership in the employee organization that, as of the date of the filing of the application, at least 40% of the employees in the unit wish to have the employee organization represent them as their bargaining agent; and</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>d</I>) is satisfied that the persons representing the employee organization in the making of the application have been duly authorized to make the application.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>7.</B> (1) The portion of subsection 26(1) of the Act before paragraph (<I>a</I>) is replaced by the following:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Powers of Board in relation to certification<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>26.</B> (1) For the purpose of enabling the Board to discharge any obligation imposed by section 25 to satisfy itself as to the matters described in subsection 25(1) and paragraphs 25(2)(<I>c</I>) and (<I>d</I>), the Board may</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes">(2) Subsection 26(2) of the Act is repealed.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes">(3) The portion of subsection 26(3) of the Act before paragraph (<I>a</I>) is replaced by the following:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Arrangements to be made for representation vote<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(3) If the Board directs that a representation vote be taken, the Board shall</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>8.</B> <B>(1)</B> <B>Subsection 29(1) of the Act is replaced by the following:</B></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Application for declaration that employee organization no longer represents employees<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>29.</B> (1) If a collective agreement or an arbitral award is in force in respect of a bargaining unit, any person claiming to represent at least 40% of the employees in the bargaining unit may, in accordance with subsection (2), apply to the Board for a declaration that the employee organization certified as bargaining agent for that bargaining unit no longer represents a majority of the employees therein.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>(2)</B> <B>Subsections 29(3) to (5) of the Act are replaced by the following:</B></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Where no collective agreement or award in force<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(3) If no collective agreement or arbitral award is in force in respect of a bargaining unit, any person claiming to represent at least 40% of the employees in the bargaining unit may, at any time after the expiration of twelve months from the date of certification of the bargaining agent for that bargaining unit, apply to the Board for a declaration that the employee organization certified as bargaining agent for that bargaining unit no longer represents a majority of the employees therein.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Taking of representation vote<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(4) On an application under subsection (1) or (3), if the Board is satisfied on the basis of written evidence that, as of the date of the filing of an application for a declaration made under subsection (1) or (3), as the case may be, at least 40% of the employees in the bargaining unit no longer wish to have the employee organization represent them, the Board shall order that a secret ballot representation vote be taken.  The provisions of subsection 26(3) apply in relation to the taking of the vote.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Revocation of certification of employee organization<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(5) On an application under subsection (1) or (3), if after conducting the secret ballot repre-<keep>sentation vote</keep> referred to in subsection (4), the Board is satisfied that a majority of the employees in the bargaining unit who have cast a ballot no longer wish to be represented by the employee organization, it must revoke the certification of the employee organization as the bargaining agent.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:PUBLIC SERVICE LABOUR RELATIONS ACT--><MarginalNote>2003, c. 22, s. 2<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="10" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center"><B>PUBLIC SERVICE LABOUR RELATIONS ACT</B></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>9.</B> Subsection 64(1) of the <I>Public Service Labour Relations Act</I> is replaced by the following:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Duty to certify employee organization<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>64.</B> (1) If the Board is satisfied on the basis of the results of a secret ballot representation vote that a majority of the employees in a proposed bargaining unit who have cast a ballot have voted to have the applicant employee organization represent them as their bargaining agent, the Board must, subject to this Part, certify the employee organization as the bargaining agent for the unit.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Representation vote<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(1.1) After having determined a unit appropriate for collective bargaining, the Board must order that a secret ballot representation vote be taken among the employees in the unit if it is satisfied</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>a</I>) on the basis of evidence of membership in the employee organization that, as of the date of the filing of the application, at least 40% of the employees in the unit wish to have the employee organization represent them as their bargaining agent;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>b</I>) that the persons representing the employee organization in the making of the application have been duly authorized to make the application; and</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>c</I>) if the applicant is a council of employee organizations, that each of the employee organizations forming the council has vested appropriate authority in the council to enable it to discharge the duties and responsibilities of a bargaining agent.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>10.</B> Subsection 65(1) of the Act is repealed.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>11.</B> Subsection 94(1) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>When employee organization no longer represents employees<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>94.</B> (1) Any person claiming to represent at least 40% of the employees in the bargaining unit bound by a collective agreement or an arbitral award may apply to the Board for a declaration that the employee organization that is certified as the bargaining agent for the bargaining unit no longer represents a majority of the employees in the bargaining unit.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>12.</B> Sections 95 and 96 of the Act are replaced by the following:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Taking of representation vote<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>95.</B> If the Board is satisfied on the basis of written evidence that, as of the date of the filing of an application for a declaration made under subsection 94(1), at least 40% of the employees in the bargaining unit no longer wish to have the employee organization represent them, the Board shall order that a representation vote be taken. The provisions of subsection 65(2) apply in relation to the taking of the vote.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Revocation of certification<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>96.</B> If, after conducting the representation vote referred to in section 95, the Board is satisfied that a majority of the employees in the bargaining unit who have cast a ballot no longer wish to be represented by the employee organization, it must revoke the certification of the employee organization as the bargaining agent.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:COMING INTO FORCE--><Para TopMargin="10" Bold="Yes" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">COMING INTO FORCE</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Six months after royal assent<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>13.</B> This Act comes into force six months after the day on which it receives royal assent.</Para></Block><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="BPT_ImprintE"><br /><br />Published under authority of the Speaker of the House of Commons</Para></Block><Block Align="Yes" LineCnt="N"><Para NoLineBreak="Yes" NoHtml="Yes" Leading="0" Size="0" TopMargin="0" BottomMargin="0"></Para></Block></Bill_Part></Bill>