﻿<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><Bill RHead_reign="62 Eliz. II" RHead_ParlYear="2013" DocumentTitle="BILL C-542" Bill_No="C-542" Document_No="412052" xml:lang="EN" Bill_Type="Non-amending" Stage_Name="First-Reading-House" Reprint="No" xml:space="preserve" ChapterNo_E="C. " ChapterNo_F="ch. " Bill-Origin="commons"><Bill_Part Part_Type="Cover" CountLines="No"><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="CovBillNo">C-542</Para></Block><Block><Para TopMargin="24" Size="9" Leading="10" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0" TextAlign="Center">Second Session, Forty-first Parliament,</Para></Block><Block><Para Size="9" Leading="10" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0" TextAlign="Center">62 Elizabeth II, 2013</Para></Block><Block><Para TopMargin="48" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0" Bold="Yes" TextAlign="Center">HOUSE OF COMMONS OF CANADA</Para></Block><Block><Para TopMargin="42" Size="18" Leading="20" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0" Bold="Yes" TextAlign="Center">BILL C-542</Para></Block><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="CovLongTitle">An Act to establish a National Urban Workers Strategy</Para></Block><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="COV_StageLine"></Para></Block><Block><Para Size="9" AllCaps="Yes" Hyphenate="OFF">first reading, October 21, 2013</Para></Block><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="COV_StageLine"></Para></Block><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="Cover_Sponsors"><SC SC_PerCent="85">Mr. Cash</SC></Para></Block><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="Cover_DocNo">412052</Para></Block></Bill_Part><Bill_Part CountLines="No" Part_Type="InsideCover"><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="BPT_InsideCoverE">Available on the Parliament of Canada Web Site at the following address:<br /><B>http://www.parl.gc.ca</B></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><Para TopMargin="108" BottomMargin="4" Size="10" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">SUMMARY</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" Size="8" Leading="9" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">This enactment proposes to develop a National Urban Workers Strategy to address the common challenges faced by workers in Canada and to resolve inequities in taxation and access to social support mechanisms, including employment insurance. It requires the Minister of Human Resources and Skills Development to strike a task force, the membership of which  must include the Minister of National Revenue, the Minister of Labour, the President of the Treasury Board and the Minister of Industry, to develop a National Urban Workers Strategy.  The task force must consult with provincial and territorial ministers responsible for social services, labour, pensions and others areas that relate to workers, as well as with labour organizations, representatives from industry and associations representing groups affected by this Act.</Para></Block></Bill_Part><Bill_Part Part_Type="MainText" CountLines="Yes" RunningHead_E="National Urban Workers Strategy"><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="MainText_DocNo">412052</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes"><Para Style="Session_Reign">2nd Session, 41st Parliament,</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes"><Para Style="Session_Reign">62 Elizabeth II, 2013</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes"><Para Style="MainBillOrigin">house of commons of canada</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes"><Para Bold="Yes" Style="MAIN@BillNo_Title">BILL C-542</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes"><Para Style="MAIN@ti;04">An Act to establish a National Urban Workers Strategy</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><MarginalNote>Preamble<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">Whereas recent studies indicate that a growing sector of workers in urban areas cannot find stable, permanent and full-time employment;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">Whereas workers in precarious employment enjoy relatively less access to workplace benefits and pensions and have little job security or access to income security programs; </Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">Whereas workers in Canadian towns and cities face particular challenges and inequities in taxation and access to social support mecha- nisms, including employment insurance;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">Whereas it is essential to respect, protect and better support workers and acknowledge their contribution to Canadian society and the Canadian economy;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">And whereas  these factors, while growing disproportionally in urban areas,  also exist in rural areas of Canada and addressing them thus supports workers across the country;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">Now, therefore, Her Majesty, by and with the advice and consent of the Senate and House of Commons of Canada, enacts as follows: </Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:SHORT TITLE--><Para TopMargin="10" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">SHORT TITLE</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Short title<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>1.</B> This Act may be cited as the <I>National Urban Workers Strategy Act</I>.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:INTERPRETATION--><Para TopMargin="10" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">INTERPRETATION</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Definition of “Minister”<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>2.</B> In this Act, “Minister” means the Minister of Human Resources and Skills Development.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:APPLICATION--><Para TopMargin="10" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">APPLICATION</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Application<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>3.</B> (1) This Act applies to all workers in Canada, with particular attention to urban workers as described in subsection (2).</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Urban worker<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(2) For the purposes of this Act, an <keep>individ-</keep>ual is an urban worker if his or her source of income is vulnerable or precarious because he or she works without benefits, workplace pensions or job security in the following circumstances:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>a</I>) as an employee on a short-term contractual basis, whether continuously or intermittently;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>b</I>) as a self-employed individual;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>c</I>) as an employee on a part-time basis; or</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>d</I>) as an intern.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:NATIONAL URBAN WORKERS STRATEGY--><Para TopMargin="10" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">NATIONAL URBAN WORKERS STRATEGY</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Strike task force<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>4.</B> (1) Within 60 days after the coming into force of this Act, the Minister must strike a task force, the membership of which must include the Minister of National Revenue, the Minister of Labour, the President of  the Treasury Board and the Minister of Industry, for the purpose of developing a National Urban Workers Strategy. </Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Consultations<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(2) Within 180 days after the coming into force of this Act, for the purpose of developing the Strategy, the task force must consult with</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>a</I>) provincial and territorial ministers responsible for employment, taxation, labour matters, relevant social services, pensions and other areas that relate to workers; and</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>b</I>) labour organizations, representatives from industry and associations representing groups affected by this Act.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>National Urban Workers Strategy<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>5.</B> (1) The National Urban Workers Strategy must be designed to address the common challenges faced by workers, to resolve inequities in taxation, to improve access to social support mechanisms, including employment insurance and to generally improve the conditions of  workers by addressing the elements and issues set out in subsections (2) to (5).</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Employment insurance and income security<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(2) The Strategy must identify the policy and legislative changes to the employment insurance regime that, while maintaining the integrity and financial sustainability of the regime, would improve access to employment insurance for workers and, more particularly,</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>a</I>) extend broader access to employment insurance benefits for workers by</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="4" FirstLineIndent="0">(i) reducing the waiting period that must be served before benefits may be paid,</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="4" FirstLineIndent="0">(ii) reducing the hours of employment required to qualify for benefits,</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="4" FirstLineIndent="0">(iii) raising the level of benefits, and</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="4" FirstLineIndent="0">(iv) extending the maximum benefit period;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>b</I>) improve the benefits available to  workers in cyclical or intermittent employment sectors and protect  those workers from being forced to take lower-paying jobs; and</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>c</I>) improve income security <keep>for self-</keep><keep>employed individuals.</keep></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Taxation inequities<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(3) The Strategy must identify policy and legislative changes to address the inequities of the current taxation regime that affect workers and, more particularly,</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>a</I>) study the viability and impacts of income averaging for vulnerable workers with volatile incomes, such as employees who work on a short-term contractual basis and self-employed individuals;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>b</I>) review GST collection requirements for self-employed individuals;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>c</I>) clarify and  simplify the process for filing income taxes for employees who work <keep>on a short-term</keep> contractual basis and self-<keep>employed</keep> individuals; and</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>d</I>) expand the Working Income Tax Benefit.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Pension security<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(4) The Strategy must identify policy and legislative changes to address the need for workers to have access to an adequate pension in order to maintain quality of life in retirement years and, more particularly,</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>a</I>) to increase benefits paid out by the Canada Pension Plan or Quebec Pension Plan, as the case may be;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>b</I>) to restore the age of eligibility for Old Age Security and Guaranteed Income Supplement benefits to 65 years of age;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>c</I>) to increase the Guaranteed Income Supplement while ensuring the long-term fiscal sustainability of the program;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>d</I>) to improve the availability of affordable retirement savings vehicles that provide minimum guaranteed benefits; and</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>e</I>) to protect workplace pensions more effectively under federal bankruptcy legislation.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Other factors<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(5) The Strategy must identify policy and legislative changes proposed, within the limits of their respective jurisdictions, by the task force and by the provincial and territorial ministers referred to in paragraph 4(2)(<I>a</I>), to address other factors related to the changing type of work in urban areas, including</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>a</I>) developing measures to prevent the erroneous classification of certain employees as independent contractors;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>b</I>) increasing public awareness, monitoring and enforcement of existing legislation and strengthening employment standards to prevent the misuse of paid and unpaid internships;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>c</I>) developing measures to address the lack of additional benefits, including health, dental and drug insurance, for workers who do not have access to such benefits; and</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>d</I>) increasing public awareness, monitoring and enforcement of legislation pertaining to temporary employment agencies.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:REPORT--><Para TopMargin="10" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">REPORT</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Report to Parliament<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>6.</B> The Minister must cause a report on the work of the task force, including the matters referred to in subsections 5(1) to (4), to be laid before each House of Parliament on any of the first five days on which that House is sitting following the expiration of 180 days after the formation of the task force.</Para></Block><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="BPT_ImprintE"><br /><br />Published under authority of the Speaker of the House of Commons</Para></Block><Block Align="Yes" LineCnt="N"><Para NoLineBreak="Yes" NoHtml="Yes" Leading="0" Size="0" TopMargin="0" BottomMargin="0"></Para></Block></Bill_Part></Bill>