﻿<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><Bill RHead_reign="62 Eliz. II" RHead_ParlYear="2013" DocumentTitle="BILL C-558" Bill_No="C-558" Document_No="412065" xml:lang="EN" Bill_Type="Non-amending" Stage_Name="First-Reading-House" Reprint="No" xml:space="preserve" ChapterNo_E="C. " ChapterNo_F="ch. " Bill-Origin="commons"><Bill_Part Part_Type="Cover" CountLines="No"><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="CovBillNo">C-558</Para></Block><Block><Para TopMargin="24" Size="9" Leading="10" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0" TextAlign="Center">Second Session, Forty-first Parliament,</Para></Block><Block><Para Size="9" Leading="10" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0" TextAlign="Center">62 Elizabeth II, 2013</Para></Block><Block><Para TopMargin="48" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0" Bold="Yes" TextAlign="Center">HOUSE OF COMMONS OF CANADA</Para></Block><Block><Para TopMargin="42" Size="18" Leading="20" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0" Bold="Yes" TextAlign="Center">BILL C-558</Para></Block><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="CovLongTitle">An Act to establish the position of Parliamentary Science Officer</Para></Block><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="COV_StageLine"></Para></Block><Block><Para Size="9" AllCaps="Yes" Hyphenate="OFF">first reading, December 3, 2013</Para></Block><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="COV_StageLine"></Para></Block><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="Cover_Sponsors"><SC SC_PerCent="85">Mr. Stewart</SC></Para></Block><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="Cover_DocNo">412065</Para></Block></Bill_Part><Bill_Part CountLines="No" Part_Type="InsideCover"><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="BPT_InsideCoverE">Available on the Parliament of Canada Web Site at the following address:<br /><B>http://www.parl.gc.ca</B></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><Para TopMargin="108" BottomMargin="4" Size="10" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">SUMMARY</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" Size="8" Leading="9" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">This enactment establishes the position of Parliamentary Science Officer, the holder of which is an officer of Parliament.</Para></Block></Bill_Part><Bill_Part Part_Type="MainText" CountLines="Yes" RunningHead_E="Parliamentary Science Officer"><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="MainText_DocNo">412065</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes"><Para Style="Session_Reign">2nd Session, 41st Parliament,</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes"><Para Style="Session_Reign">62 Elizabeth II, 2013</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes"><Para Style="MainBillOrigin">house of commons of canada</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes"><Para Bold="Yes" Style="MAIN@BillNo_Title">BILL C-558</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes"><Para Style="MAIN@ti;04">An Act to establish the position of Parliamentary Science Officer</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">Her Majesty, by and with the advice and consent of the Senate and House of Commons of Canada, enacts as follows:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:SHORT TITLE--><Para TopMargin="10" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">SHORT TITLE</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Short title<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>1.</B> This Act may be cited as the <I>Parliamentary Science Officer Act</I>.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:PARLIAMENTARY SCIENCE OFFICER--><Para TopMargin="10" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">PARLIAMENTARY SCIENCE OFFICER</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Parliamentary Science Officer<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>2.</B> There is  established the position of Parliamentary Science Officer, the holder of which is an officer of Parliament.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Mandate<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>3.</B> (1) The mandate of the Parliamentary Science Officer is to advise and report to Parliament on all aspects related to science and technology in Canada in order to</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>a</I>) ensure that the legislative process is informed by sound scientific and technical evidence;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>b</I>) provide Parliament with accurate and timely advice on all scientific matters of relevance and on science and technology policy;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>c</I>) promote transparency and integrity in scientific research;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>d</I>) encourage coordination between all federal departments and agencies that conduct scientific and technical research; and</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>e</I>) raise awareness of science and technology issues across government and among Canadians.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Responsibilities<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(2) The mandate of the Parliamentary Science Officer includes the following responsibilities:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>a</I>) to provide sound information and independent analysis — on his or her own initiative or when requested to do so under this section — to the Senate and to the House of Commons concerning</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="4" FirstLineIndent="0">(i) federal science and technology policy, including trends in public funding and support for scientific research,</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="4" FirstLineIndent="0">(ii) scientific integrity within federal departments and agencies, including the extent to which there is freedom from political influence in the research process and in the open communication of scientific results, and</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="4" FirstLineIndent="0">(iii) the state of current <keep>scientific evi-</keep>dence — including accepted theories, established findings and <keep>existing uncer-</keep><keep>tainties — relevant</keep> to any specific matter or proposal over which Parliament has jurisdiction;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>b</I>) when requested to do so by the Standing Committee on Industry, Science and Technology of the House of Commons or the Standing Committee on Social Affairs, Science and Technology of the Senate, to undertake research into any aspect of federal science and technology policy or to assess the state of scientific integrity within federal departments and agencies; </Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>c</I>) when requested to do so by a member of either House or by a committee of the Senate or of the House of Commons, or a committee of both Houses, to assess the state of scientific and technical evidence — including accepted theories, established findings, and existing uncertainties — relevant to any specific matter or proposal over which Parliament has jurisdiction; and</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>d</I>) to communicate all of its research, analyses and reports to parliamentarians and Canadians in a clear and accessible manner.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Complementary mandate<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(3) Without limiting the generality of subsections (1) and (2), the mandate of the Parliamentary Science Officer applies in such a way as to complement the activities and work of existing federal science and technology advisory bodies, including the Science, Technology and Innovation Council, as well as the activities of the Council of Canadian Academies.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Definition of “legislative process”<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(4) For the purposes of this section, “legislative process” means</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>a</I>) the consideration, analysis and study of bills, motions and regulations that are tabled in Parliament;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>b</I>) the work of committees of the Senate or of the House of Commons and joint committees of both Houses; and</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>c</I>) the work of individual parliamentarians in carrying out their parliamentary functions.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Appointment<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>4.</B> The Governor in Council must, by commission under the Great Seal, appoint a Parliamentary Science Officer after consultation with the leader of every recognized party in both Houses of Parliament and approval of the appointment by resolution of those Houses.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Qualifications<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>5.</B> In order to be appointed under section 4, a person must, at the time of his or her appointment, </Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>a</I>) be able to understand English and French without the aid of an interpreter and to express himself or herself clearly in both official languages; </Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>b</I>) have an appropriate educational background, including a doctoral degree in natural sciences, engineering sciences, health sciences or social sciences; </Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>c</I>) have experience conducting scientific research and a record of  peer-reviewed publications in his or her field of specialization; and </Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>d</I>) have extensive knowledge of federal science and technology policy, particularly within departments and agencies that undertake or support scientific research.  </Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Salary and travel and living expenses<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>6.</B> The Parliamentary Science Officer is to be paid a salary equal to the salary of a judge of the Federal Court, other than the Chief Justice of the Federal Court, and is entitled to be paid reasonable travel and living expenses while absent from his or her ordinary place of residence in the course of his or her duties.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Tenure<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>7.</B> The Parliamentary Science Officer holds office during good behaviour for a term of seven years, but may be removed for cause by the Governor in Council at any time on address of the Senate and House of Commons.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>One term<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>8.</B> No person may be appointed as Parliamentary Science Officer for more than one term.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>New Parliamentary Science Officer<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>9.</B> Six months prior to the expiration of the serving Parliamentary Science Officer’s term, the Governor in Council must confirm the appointment of a new Parliamentary Science Officer in accordance with section 4, to take effect upon the expiration of the serving Parliamentary Science Officer’s term.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Cessation of office<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>10.</B> (1) If the Parliamentary Science Officer ceases to hold office, the Governor in Council must appoint a new Parliamentary Science Officer, in accordance with section 4, no later than six months after the cessation of office.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Circumstances of cessation<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(2) A Parliamentary Science Officer ceases to hold office when he or she </Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>a</I>) is removed for cause by the Governor in Council on address of the Senate and House of Commons;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>b</I>) resigns;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>c</I>) dies; or</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>d</I>) is otherwise incapacitated.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>No other office or employment<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>11.</B> (1) The Parliamentary Science Officer must engage exclusively in the functions, duties and responsibilities assigned to his or her office under this Act or any other Act of Parliament and may not hold any other office under Her Majesty or engage in any other employment for reward.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Exception<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(2) Despite subsection (1), the Parliamentary Science Officer may conduct independent scientific research and participate in the peer-review process associated with being a scientist.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Deputy head<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>12.</B> The Parliamentary Science Officer has the rank of a deputy head of a department of the Government of Canada and has the control and management of the office of the Parliamentary Science Officer.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:REPORT--><Para TopMargin="10" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">REPORT</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Annual report<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>13.</B> The Parliamentary Science Officer must report annually to the Senate and the House of Commons</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>a</I>) on the discharge of his or her mandate;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>b</I>) on the state of science and technology in Canada, including the extent to which scientific work within federal departments and agencies is coordinated; and</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>c</I>) calling attention in the report to anything that he or she considers to be of significance and of a nature that should be brought to the attention of the Senate or the House of Commons.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Release of reports<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>14.</B> Any analysis, research or report that is prepared by the Parliamentary Science Officer pursuant to section 3 or 13 must immediately be made available to the public and to all members of the Senate and the House of Commons.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:ACCESS TO INFORMATION--><Para TopMargin="10" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">ACCESS TO INFORMATION</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Access to data, information, etc.<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>15.</B> Except as provided by any other Act of Parliament that expressly refers to this section, the Parliamentary Science Officer is entitled, by request made to the deputy head of a department within the meaning of any of paragraphs (<I>a</I>), (<I>a.1</I>) and (<I>d</I>) of the definition “department” in section 2 of the <I>Financial Administration Act</I>, or to his or her equivalent, or to any other person designated by that deputy head or his or her equivalent for the purpose of this section, to free and timely access to any data, information, records, explanations and assistance that the Parliamentary Science Officer considers necessary to fulfil his or her responsibilities under section 3.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Refusal to provide data, information, etc.<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>16.</B> If the deputy head of a department or his or her equivalent or designate refuses to provide the data, information, records, explanations or assistance requested under section 15, the Federal Court must, if it determines that there is no ground to refuse to provide the data, information, records, explanations or assistance, order the deputy head of the department or his or her equivalent or designate to provide the data, information, records, explanations or assistance, subject to such conditions as the Court deems appropriate.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Exception<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>17.</B> Sections 15 and 16 do not apply in respect of any data, information, records or explanations </Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>a</I>) that are information the disclosure of which is restricted under section 19 of the <I>Access to Information Act</I> or any provision set out in Schedule II to that Act; or </Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>b</I>) that are contained in a confidence of the Queen’s Privy Council for Canada described in subsection 69(1) of that Act, unless the data, information, records or explanations are also contained in any other record, within the meaning of section 3 of that Act, and are not information referred to in paragraph (<I>a</I>).</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Confidentiality<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>18.</B> The Parliamentary Science Officer, and every person acting on behalf or under the direction of the Parliamentary Science Officer, must not disclose any scientific data that come to their knowledge under section 15 or 16, unless the disclosure is essential for the performance of his or her mandate and the scientific data to which the disclosure relates are not information described in subsection 13(1), section 14, any of paragraphs 18(<I>a</I>) to (<I>d</I>), section 18.1, any of paragraphs 20(1)(<I>b</I>) to (<I>d</I>) or section 20.1 of the <I>Access to Information Act</I>.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>No other grounds<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>19.</B> No grounds other than those described in section 17 may be relied upon to authorize a refusal to provide the data, information, records, explanations or assistance requested.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:POWERS--><Para TopMargin="10" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">POWERS</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Powers to contract<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>20.</B> The Parliamentary Science Officer may, in carrying out the work of the office of the Parliamentary Science Officer, enter into contracts, memoranda of understanding or other arrangements.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:STAFF--><Para TopMargin="10" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">STAFF</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Staff<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>21.</B> (1) The Parliamentary Science Officer may employ any officers and employees and may engage the services of any agents, advisers and consultants that the Parliamentary Science Officer considers necessary for the proper conduct of the work of the office of the Parliamentary Science Officer.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Technical assistance<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(2) The Parliamentary Science Officer may engage on a temporary basis the services of persons having technical or specialized knowledge necessary for the performance of his or her mandate.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:ESTIMATES--><Para TopMargin="10" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">ESTIMATES</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Estimates to be prepared<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>22.</B> Prior to each fiscal year, the Parliamentary Science Officer must cause to be prepared an estimate of the sums that will be required to pay the charges and expenses of the office of the Parliamentary Science Officer during the fiscal year.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Inclusion in government estimates<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>23.</B> The estimate referred to in section 22 must be considered by the Speaker of the House of Commons and then transmitted to the President of the Treasury Board, who must lay it before the House of Commons with the estimates of the Government for the fiscal year.</Para></Block><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="BPT_ImprintE"><br /><br />Published under authority of the Speaker of the House of Commons</Para></Block><Block Align="Yes" LineCnt="N"><Para NoLineBreak="Yes" NoHtml="Yes" Leading="0" Size="0" TopMargin="0" BottomMargin="0"></Para></Block></Bill_Part></Bill>