茂禄驴<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><Bill RHead_reign="62-63-64 Eliz. II" RHead_ParlYear="2013-2014-2015" DocumentTitle="BILL C-63" Bill_No="C-63" Document_No="90770" xml:lang="EN" Bill_Type="Non-amending" Stage_Name="Assented-to" Reprint="No" xml:space="preserve" ChapterNo_E="C. 24" ChapterNo_F="ch. 24" Bill-Origin="commons"><Bill_Part Part_Type="Cover" CountLines="No"><Block><Para TopMargin="24" Size="9" Leading="10" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0" TextAlign="Center">Second Session, Forty-first Parliament,</Para></Block><Block><Para Size="9" Leading="10" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0" TextAlign="Center">62-63-64 Elizabeth II, 2013-2014-2015</Para></Block><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="COV@StatutesTitle">STATUTES OF CANADA 2015<br />CHAPTER 24</Para></Block><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="CovLongTitle">An Act to give effect to the D脙漏line Final Self-Government Agreement and to make consequential and related amendments to other Acts</Para></Block><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="COV_StageLine"></Para></Block><Block><Para BottomMargin="14" Size="11" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0" Bold="Yes" TextAlign="Center">ASSENTED TO</Para></Block><Block><Para Size="8" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0" TextAlign="Center">18th JUNE, 2015</Para></Block><Block><Para TopMargin="4" Size="8" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0" TextAlign="Center">BILL C-63</Para></Block><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="COV_StageLine"></Para></Block></Bill_Part><Bill_Part CountLines="No" Part_Type="InsideCover"><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="BPT_InsideCoverE">Available on the Parliament of Canada Web Site at the following address:<br /><B>http://www.parl.gc.ca</B></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><Para TopMargin="108" BottomMargin="4" Size="10" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">RECOMMENDATION</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" Size="8" Leading="9" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">His Excellency the Governor General recommends to the House of Commons the appropriation of public revenue under the circumstances, in the manner and for the purposes set out in a measure entitled 芒聙聹<I>An Act to give effect to the D脙漏line Final Self-Government Agreement and to make consequential and related amendments to other Acts</I>芒聙聺.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><Para TopMargin="60" BottomMargin="4" Size="10" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">SUMMARY</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" Size="8" Leading="9" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">This enactment gives effect to the D脙漏line Final Self-Government Agreement among the Sahtu Dene and Metis of D脙漏line, as represented by the D脙漏line First Nation Band and the D脙漏line Land Corporation, the Government of Canada and the Government of the Northwest Territories. It also makes consequential and related amendments to other Acts.</Para></Block></Bill_Part><Bill_Part Part_Type="MainText" CountLines="No" RunningHead_E="D脙漏line Final Self-Government Agreement"><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="MAIN@RoyalAssentTitle">62-63-64 ELIZABETH II</Para></Block><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="MAIN@RoyalAssentTitle">芒聙聰芒聙聰芒聙聰芒聙聰芒聙聰芒聙聰</Para></Block><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="MAIN@RoyalAssentTitle">CHAPTER 24</Para></Block><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="LongTitleAssent">An Act to give effect to the D脙漏line Final Self-Government Agreement and to make consequential and related amendments to other Acts</Para></Block><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="MAIN@RoyalAssentDate">[<I>Assented to 18th June, 2015</I>]</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Preamble<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">Whereas the <I>Constitution Act, 1982</I> recognizes and affirms the existing Aboriginal and treaty rights of the Aboriginal peoples of Canada;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">Whereas the Sahtu Dene and Metis Comprehensive Land Claim Agreement, signed on September 6, 1993, provides for the negotiation of self-government agreements among the Sahtu Dene and Metis, the Government of Canada and the Government of the Northwest Territories;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">Whereas the Sahtu Dene and Metis Comprehensive Land Claim Agreement provides that self-government negotiations will address the desire of the Sahtu Dene and Metis to have self-government exercised as close to the community level as is reasonably possible;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">Whereas the Sahtu Dene and Metis of D脙漏line, as represented by the D脙漏line First Nation Band and the D脙漏line Land Corporation, the Government of Canada and the Government of the Northwest Territories have negotiated the D脙漏line Final Self-Government Agreement in accordance with chapter 5 and Appendix B of the Sahtu Dene and Metis Comprehensive Land Claim Agreement;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">Whereas the Sahtu Dene and Metis of D脙漏line approved the D脙漏line Final Self-Government Agreement by a vote held on March 10, 11 and 12, 2014;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">And whereas the D脙漏line Final Self-Government Agreement requires that legislation be enacted by the Parliament of Canada in order for that Agreement to be ratified;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">Now, therefore, Her Majesty, by and with the advice and consent of the Senate and House of Commons of Canada, enacts as follows:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:SHORT TITLE--><Para TopMargin="10" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">SHORT TITLE</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Short title<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>1.</B> This Act may be cited as the <I>D脙漏line Final Self-Government Agreement Act</I>.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:INTERPRETATION--><Para TopMargin="10" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">INTERPRETATION</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Definitions<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>2.</B> The following definitions apply in this Act.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><MarginalNote>芒聙聹D脙漏line Agreement芒聙聺<br />脗芦 <I>accord de Deline</I> 脗禄<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0">芒聙聹D脙漏line Agreement芒聙聺 means the D脙漏line Final Self-Government Agreement among the D脙漏line First Nation Band, the D脙漏line Land Corporation, the Government of Canada and the Government of the Northwest Territories, signed on February 18, 2015, including any amendments made to it.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><MarginalNote>芒聙聹D脙漏line First Nation Band芒聙聺<br />脗芦 <I>bande de la Premi脙篓re Nation de Deline</I> 脗禄<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0">芒聙聹D脙漏line First Nation Band芒聙聺 has the same meaning as in chapter 1 of the D脙漏line Agreement.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><MarginalNote>芒聙聹D脙漏line Got芒聙聶ine Government芒聙聺<br />脗芦 <I>gouvernement Gotine de Deline</I> 脗禄<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0">芒聙聹D脙漏line Got芒聙聶ine Government芒聙聺 means the government established in accordance with chapter 3 of the D脙漏line Agreement.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><MarginalNote>芒聙聹D脙漏line Land Corporation芒聙聺<br />脗芦 <I>soci脙漏t脙漏 fonci脙篓re de Deline</I> 脗禄<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0">芒聙聹D脙漏line Land Corporation芒聙聺 has the same meaning as in chapter 1 of the D脙漏line Agreement.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><MarginalNote>芒聙聹D脙漏line law芒聙聺<br />脗芦 <I>loi de Deline</I> 脗禄<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0">芒聙聹D脙漏line law芒聙聺 has the meaning assigned by the definition 芒聙聹DGG Law芒聙聺 in chapter 1 of the D脙漏line Agreement.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><MarginalNote>芒聙聹D脙漏line Tax Treatment Agreement芒聙聺<br />脗芦 <I>accord sur le traitement fiscal de Deline</I> 脗禄<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0">芒聙聹D脙漏line Tax Treatment Agreement芒聙聺 means the tax treatment agreement referred to in 22.3.1 of the D脙漏line Agreement, including any amendments made to it.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><MarginalNote>芒聙聹Sahtu Agreement芒聙聺<br />脗芦 <I>accord du Sahtu</I> 脗禄<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0">芒聙聹Sahtu Agreement芒聙聺 means the Agreement as defined in section 2 of the <I>Sahtu Dene and Metis Land Claim Settlement Act</I>. </Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Status of D脙漏line Agreement<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>3.</B> The D脙漏line Agreement is a treaty within the meaning of sections 25 and 35 of the <I>Constitution Act, 1982</I>.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:D脙聣LINE AGREEMENT--><Para TopMargin="10" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">D脙聣LINE AGREEMENT</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>D脙漏line Agreement given effect<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>4.</B> (1) The D脙漏line Agreement is approved, given effect and declared valid and has the force of law.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Rights and obligations<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(2) For greater certainty, a person or entity has the powers, rights, privileges and benefits conferred on the person or entity by the D脙漏line Agreement and must perform the duties, and is subject to the liabilities, imposed on the person or entity by the D脙漏line Agreement.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Third parties<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(3) For greater certainty, the D脙漏line Agreement is binding on, and may be relied on by, all persons and entities.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>D脙漏line Agreement prevails<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>5.</B> (1) Subject to section 6, the D脙漏line Agreement prevails over this Act and any other federal law to the extent of any inconsistency between them.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Act prevails<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(2) Subject to section 7, this Act prevails over any other federal law to the extent of any conflict between them.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Inconsistency with D脙漏line Agreement<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>6.</B> The <I>Sahtu Dene and Metis Land Claim Settlement Act</I> and the Sahtu Agreement prevail over the D脙漏line Agreement to the extent of any inconsistency between that Act and the D脙漏line Agreement or between the Sahtu Agreement and the D脙漏line Agreement.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Inconsistency with this Act<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>7.</B> The <I>Sahtu Dene and Metis Land Claim Settlement Act</I> and the Sahtu Agreement prevail over this Act to the extent of any inconsistency between that Act and this Act or between the Sahtu Agreement and this Act.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Inconsistency with D脙漏line law<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>8.</B> The <I>Sahtu Dene and Metis Land Claim Settlement Act</I> and the Sahtu Agreement prevail over D脙漏line law to the extent of any inconsistency between that Act and D脙漏line law or between the Sahtu Agreement and D脙漏line law.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:D脙聣LINE GOT芒聙聶INE GOVERNMENT--><Para TopMargin="10" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">D脙聣LINE GOT芒聙聶INE GOVERNMENT</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Capacity of natural person<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>9.</B> The D脙漏line Got芒聙聶ine Government is a legal entity and has the capacity, rights, powers and privileges of a natural person.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Force of law<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>10.</B> D脙漏line law that is made in accordance with the D脙漏line Agreement has the force of law.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:APPLICATION OF OTHER ACTS--><Para TopMargin="10" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">APPLICATION OF OTHER ACTS</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Meaning of 芒聙聹D脙漏line First Nation Citizen芒聙聺<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>11.</B> (1) In this section, 芒聙聹D脙漏line First Nation Citizen芒聙聺 has the meaning assigned by the definition 芒聙聹DFN Citizen芒聙聺 in chapter 1 of the D脙漏line Agreement.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote><I>Indian Act</I><br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(2) Subject to 2.8 of the D脙漏line Agreement, the <I>Indian Act</I> does not apply to the D脙漏line Got芒聙聶ine Government or to D脙漏line First Nation Citizens as of the day on which section 4 comes into force.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote><I>Statutory Instruments Act</I><br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>12.</B> A D脙漏line law is not a statutory instrument for the purposes of the <I>Statutory Instruments Act</I>.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:TAXATION--><Para TopMargin="10" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">TAXATION</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>D脙漏line Tax Treatment Agreement<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>13.</B> The D脙漏line Tax Treatment Agreement is approved, given effect and declared valid and has the force of law during the period that it is in effect.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Clarification<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>14.</B> The D脙漏line Tax Treatment Agreement does not form part of the D脙漏line Agreement and it is not a treaty or a land claims agreement within the meaning of sections 25 and 35 of the <I>Constitution Act, 1982</I>.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:GENERAL--><Para TopMargin="10" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">GENERAL</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote><keep>Judicial notice</keep> <keep>芒聙聰 Agreements</keep><br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>15.</B> (1) Judicial notice must be taken of the D脙漏line Agreement and the D脙漏line Tax Treatment Agreement.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Publication<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(2) The D脙漏line Agreement and the D脙漏line Tax Treatment Agreement must be published by the Queen芒聙聶s Printer.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Evidence<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(3) A copy of the D脙漏line Agreement or the D脙漏line Tax Treatment Agreement published by the Queen芒聙聶s Printer is evidence of that agreement and of its contents, and a copy purporting to be published by the Queen芒聙聶s Printer is presumed to be so published unless the contrary is shown.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Judicial notice 芒聙聰 <keep>D脙漏line law</keep><br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>16.</B> (1) Judicial notice must be taken of any D脙漏line law that is registered in the public registry referred to in 3.7 of the D脙漏line Agreement.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Evidence<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(2) A copy of any D脙漏line law purporting to be deposited in the public registry referred to in 3.7 of the D脙漏line Agreement is evidence of that law and of its contents, unless the contrary is shown.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Meaning of 芒聙聹institutions芒聙聺<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>17.</B> (1) In this section, 芒聙聹institutions芒聙聺 has the meaning assigned by the definition 芒聙聹Institutions of the DGG芒聙聺 in chapter 1 of the D脙漏line Agreement.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote><I>Federal Courts Act</I><br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(2) The D脙漏line Got芒聙聶ine Government and its institutions are not federal boards, commissions or other tribunals as defined in subsection 2(1) of the <I>Federal Courts Act</I>.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Jurisdiction 芒聙聰 Supreme Court of Northwest Territories<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(3) The Supreme Court of the Northwest Territories has exclusive original jurisdiction to hear and determine applications for judicial review of the decisions of the D脙漏line Got芒聙聶ine Government or its institutions, except if an agreement made in accordance with 22.2.2 of the D脙漏line Agreement provides otherwise.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Notice of issues arising<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>18.</B> (1) If an issue arises in any judicial or administrative proceeding in respect of the interpretation, validity or applicability of the D脙漏line Agreement, of this Act, of the Act of the legislature of the Northwest Territories that gives effect to the D脙漏line Agreement or of any D脙漏line law, then the issue must not be decided until the party raising the issue has served notice on the Attorney General of Canada, the Attorney General of the Northwest Territories and the D脙漏line Got芒聙聶ine Government.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Content and timing<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(2) The notice must</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>a</I>) describe the proceeding;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>b</I>) state the subject matter of the issue;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>c</I>) state the day on which the issue is to be argued;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>d</I>) give the particulars that are necessary to show the point to be argued; and</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>e</I>) be served at least 14 days before the day on which the issue is to be argued, unless the court or tribunal authorizes a shorter period.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Participation in proceedings<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(3) The Attorney General of Canada, the Attorney General of the Northwest Territories and the D脙漏line Got芒聙聶ine Government may appear and participate in any proceeding in respect of which subsection (1) applies as parties with the same rights as any other party.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Clarification<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(4) For greater certainty, subsections (2) and (3) do not require that an oral hearing be held if one is not otherwise required.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Retroactive effect<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>19.</B> Despite subsection 4(1), 2.5.1 and 4.6 of the D脙漏line Agreement, chapter 31 of that Agreement and 2.1, 2.2, 3.3, 5.1 and 5.2 of schedule C to that Agreement are deemed to have effect as of October 1, 2013.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Orders and regulations<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>20.</B> The Governor in Council may make any orders and regulations that are necessary for the purpose of carrying out any of the provisions of the D脙漏line Agreement or of any other agreements that are related to the implementation of the D脙漏line Agreement.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:CONSEQUENTIAL AND RELATED AMENDMENTS--><Para TopMargin="10" Bold="Yes" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">CONSEQUENTIAL AND RELATED AMENDMENTS</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:Payments in Lieu of Taxes Act--><MarginalNote>R.S., c. M-13; 2000, c. 8, s. 2<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" Bold="Yes" SmallCaps="Yes" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">Payments in Lieu of Taxes Act</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>21.</B> The definition 芒聙聹taxing authority芒聙聺 in subsection 2(1) of the <I>Payments in Lieu of Taxes Act</I> is amended by adding the following after paragraph (<I>g</I>):</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>g.1</I>) the D脙漏line Got芒聙聶ine Government, as defined in section 2 of the <I>D脙漏line Final Self-Government Agreement Act</I>, if it levies and collects a real property tax or a frontage or area tax in respect of D脙漏line Lands, as defined in 22.1.1 of the D脙漏line Final Self-Government Agreement that is approved, given effect and declared valid by that Act;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:Mackenzie Valley Resource Management Act--><MarginalNote>1998, c. 25<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="10" Bold="Yes" SmallCaps="Yes" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">Mackenzie Valley Resource Management Act</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>2005, c. 1, s. 15(1)<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>22.</B> (1) The definitions 芒聙聹local government芒聙聺 and 芒聙聹Sahtu First Nation芒聙聺 in section 2 of the <I>Mackenzie Valley Resource Management Act</I> are replaced by the following:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>芒聙聹local government芒聙聺<br />脗芦 <I>administration locale</I> 脗禄<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0">芒聙聹local government芒聙聺 means any local government established under the laws of the Northwest Territories, including a city, town, village, hamlet, charter community, settlement or government of a Tlicho community, whether incorporated or not, and includes the territorial government in the case where it is acting in the place of that local government in accordance with those laws. It also includes the D脙漏line Got芒聙聶ine Government in the case where it is exercising the jurisdiction and authority set out in 9.1 of the D脙漏line Agreement.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><MarginalNote>芒聙聹Sahtu First Nation芒聙聺<br />脗芦 <I>premi脙篓re nation du Sahtu</I> 脗禄<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0">芒聙聹Sahtu First Nation芒聙聺 means the Sahtu Dene and Metis as represented by The Sahtu Secretariat Incorporated, a corporation without share capital under Part II of the <I>Canada Corporations Act</I>, R.S.C. 1970, c. C-32, being the successor, for the purposes of this Act, to the Sahtu Tribal Council referred to in the Sahtu Agreement, or by any successor to that corporation. It also includes the D脙漏line Got芒聙聶ine Government in the case where The Sahtu Secretariat Incorporated or its successor has made a delegation or assignment to that government of any powers and functions conferred under this Act.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes">(2) Section 2 of the Act is amended by adding the following in alphabetical order:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>芒聙聹D脙漏line Agreement芒聙聺<br />脗芦 <I>accord de Deline</I> 脗禄<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0">芒聙聹D脙漏line Agreement芒聙聺 means the D脙漏line Final Self-Government Agreement among the D脙漏line First Nation Band, the D脙漏line Land Corporation, the Government of Canada and the Government of the Northwest Territories, signed on February 18, 2015, including any amendments made to it, that is approved, given effect and declared valid by the <I>D脙漏line Final Self-Government Agreement Act</I>.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><MarginalNote>芒聙聹D脙漏line Got芒聙聶ine Government芒聙聺<br />脗芦 <I>gouvernement Gotine de Deline</I> 脗禄<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0">芒聙聹D脙漏line Got芒聙聶ine Government芒聙聺 means the government established in accordance with chapter 3 of the D脙漏line Agreement.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><MarginalNote>芒聙聹D脙漏line lands芒聙聺<br />脗芦 <I>terres de Deline</I> 脗禄<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0">芒聙聹D脙漏line lands芒聙聺 means the lands whose title is vested in the D脙漏line Got芒聙聶ine Government in accordance with 21.2.1 of the D脙漏line Agreement.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><MarginalNote>芒聙聹D脙漏line law芒聙聺<br />脗芦 <I>loi de Deline</I> 脗禄<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0">芒聙聹D脙漏line law芒聙聺 has the meaning assigned by the definition 芒聙聹DGG Law芒聙聺 in chapter 1 of the D脙漏line Agreement.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>23.</B> Section 4 of the Act is amended by adding the following after subsection (4):</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Delegation by D脙漏line Got芒聙聶ine Government<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(5) The D脙漏line Got芒聙聶ine Government may, in conformity with the D脙漏line Agreement, delegate any of its functions under this Act to</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>a</I>) a body or office established by a D脙漏line law;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>b</I>) a department, agency or office of the federal or the territorial government;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>c</I>) a board or other public body established by or under an Act of Parliament or by a territorial law; or</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>d</I>) any other entity.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>24.</B> Subsection 5(1) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Conflict<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>5.</B> (1) If there is any inconsistency or conflict between this Act and a land claim agreement, the D脙漏line Agreement, an Act giving effect to any of those agreements or the <I>Indian Act</I>, then the land claim agreement, the D脙漏line Agreement, the Act or the <I>Indian Act</I> prevails over this Act to the extent of the inconsistency or conflict.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>2005, c. 1, s. 18<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>25.</B> Subsection 8(1) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Consultation<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>8.</B> (1) The federal Minister shall consult the first nations, the Tlicho Government and the D脙漏line Got芒聙聶ine Government with respect to the amendment of this Act.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>2005, c. 1, s. 23<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>26.</B> Subsection 16(2) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Status or entitlements under agreement<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(2) A member of a board is not placed in a material conflict of interest merely because of any status or entitlement conferred on the member under the Gwich芒聙聶in Agreement, the Sahtu Agreement, the Tlicho Agreement or any other agreement between a first nation and Her Majesty in right of Canada for the settlement of a claim to lands or under the D脙漏line Agreement.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>2005, c. 1, s. 25<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>27.</B> Section 22 of the Act is replaced by the following:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Government information<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>22.</B> Subject to any other federal or territorial law and to any Tlicho law or D脙漏line law, a board may obtain from any department or agency of the federal or territorial government, the Tlicho Government or the D脙漏line Got芒聙聶ine Government any information in the possession of the department, agency, Tlicho Government or D脙漏line Got芒聙聶ine Government that the board requires for the performance of its functions.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>2014, c. 2, s. 128(1)<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>28.</B> Subsection 31(1) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote><I>Statutory Instruments Act</I><br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>31.</B> (1) Sections 3, 5 and 11 of the <I>Statutory Instruments Act</I> do not apply in respect of rules under section 30, a land use plan or amendment to a land use plan under Part 2, rules under subsection 49(2), guidelines or policies under section 65, policy directions under subsection 50.1(1) or 83(1), (2) or (2.1), directions under section 106, policy directions under section 109 or 109.1 or subsection 142.2(1) or guidelines under section 120.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>29.</B> Section 63 of the Act is amended by adding the following after subsection (4):</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Consultation with D脙漏line Got芒聙聶ine Government<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(5) The Sahtu Land and Water Board shall consult the D脙漏line Got芒聙聶ine Government before issuing, amending or renewing any licence, permit or authorization for a use of D脙漏line lands or waters on those lands or a deposit of waste on those lands or in those waters.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>30.</B> (1) Section 83 of the Act is amended by adding the following after subsection (1):</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Notice to D脙漏line Got芒聙聶ine Government<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(1.1) The federal Minister shall inform the D脙漏line Got芒聙聶ine Government, to the extent provided for in 2.7.1 of the D脙漏line Agreement, of the Minister芒聙聶s intention to give a written policy direction to the Sahtu Land and Water Board if the policy direction is in relation to the use of land or water or the deposit of waste in the area described in schedule A to the D脙漏line Agreement.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes">(2) Section 83 of the Act is amended by adding the following after subsection (2):</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Policy directions by D脙漏line Got芒聙聶ine Government<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(2.1) The D脙漏line Got芒聙聶ine Government may, after consultation with the Sahtu Land and Water Board and the federal Minister, give written policy directions to the Board with respect to the performance of any of the Board芒聙聶s functions under this Part in relation to the use of D脙漏line lands. Policy directions are binding on the Board to the extent that compliance with them does not require the Board to exceed its approved budget.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>2005, c. 1, s. 47<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes">(3) Subsection 83(5) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Conflict between policy directions<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(5) If there is a conflict between policy directions given by the federal Minister under subsection (1) and policy directions given by the Tlicho Government under subsection (2) or by the D脙漏line Got芒聙聶ine Government under subsection (2.1), the policy directions given under subsection (2) or (2.1), as the case may be, prevail to the extent of the conflict.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>2005, c. 1, s. 47<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes">(4) Subsection 83(6) of the English version of the Act is replaced by the following:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Conflict between legislation and policy directions<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(6) If there is a conflict between policy directions given by the federal Minister, the Tlicho Government or the D脙漏line Got芒聙聶ine Government under this section and the provisions of any Act of Parliament, of any regulations made under an Act of Parliament or of any territorial law, those provisions prevail to the extent of the conflict.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>31.</B> Section 85 of the Act is amended by adding the following after subsection (5):</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Notice to D脙漏line Got芒聙聶ine Government<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(6) An inspector shall, if it is reasonable to do so, give the D脙漏line Got芒聙聶ine Government prior notice of entry by the inspector on D脙漏line lands.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>32.</B> The Act is amended by adding the following after section 90.1:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Prohibition 芒聙聰 D脙漏line lands<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>90.11</B> Even if the regulations do not require a permit or other authorization under Part 3 or 4 for a particular use of land, a person shall not use D脙漏line lands without such a permit or authorization if one is required by a D脙漏line law for uses of that type.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>33.</B> The Act is amended by adding the following after section 90.2:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Exception<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>90.21</B> Despite the regulations, a permit or other authorization under Part 3 or 4 for a particular use of lands in the Community of D脙漏line, as described in schedule B to the D脙漏line Agreement, is not required if a D脙漏line law provides that one is not required for uses of that type.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>2014, c. 2, s. 192<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>34.</B> Section 95 of the Act is replaced by the following:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Fees<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>95.</B> Despite subsection 72.03(1) or any territorial law, the Gwich芒聙聶in and Sahtu First Nations, the Tlicho Government and the D脙漏line Got芒聙聶ine Government are not required to pay any fee in respect of the use of waters or the deposit of waste for non-commercial purposes on their first nation lands, Tlicho lands or D脙漏line lands as the case may be.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>35.</B> Subsection 106.1(2) of the Act is amended by striking out 芒聙聹and芒聙聺 at the end of paragraph (<I>c</I>), by adding 芒聙聹and芒聙聺 at the end of paragraph (<I>d</I>) and by adding the following after paragraph (<I>d</I>):</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>e</I>) the D脙漏line Got芒聙聶ine Government with respect to the amendment of any D脙漏line law regarding the use of D脙漏line lands or waters on those lands or regarding a deposit of waste on those lands or in those waters.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>36.</B> The Act is amended by adding the following after section 109.1:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:Powers of D脙漏line Got芒聙聶ine Government--><Para TopMargin="10" SmallCaps="Yes" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">Powers of D脙漏line Got芒聙聶ine Government</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Policy directions by D脙漏line Got芒聙聶ine Government<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>109.11</B> The D脙漏line Got芒聙聶ine Government may exercise the same powers and shall perform the same duties in relation to the Board and the regional panel of the Board referred to in subsection 99(2) as those that the D脙漏line Got芒聙聶ine Government has under section 83 in relation to the Sahtu Land and Water Board.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>37.</B> Section 109.2 of the Act is amended by adding the following after subsection (2):</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Conflict between policy directions<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(3) If there is a conflict between policy directions given by the federal Minister under section 109 and policy directions given by the D脙漏line Got芒聙聶ine Government under section 109.11, the policy directions given under section 109.11 prevail to the extent of the conflict.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Conflict between legislation and policy directions<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(4) If there is a conflict between policy directions given by the federal Minister under section 109 or by the D脙漏line Got芒聙聶ine Government under section 109.11 and the provisions of any Act of Parliament, of any regulations made under an Act of Parliament or of any territorial law, those provisions prevail to the extent of the conflict.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>2005, c. 1, s. 71<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>38.</B> Section 118 of the Act is replaced by the following:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Issuance of licence, permit or other authorization<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>118.</B> (1) A licence, permit or other authorization required for the carrying out of a development shall not be issued under any federal, territorial, Tlicho or D脙漏line law unless the requirements of this Part have been complied with in relation to the development.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Requirements<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(2) If the Gwich芒聙聶in or Sahtu First Nation, the Tlicho Government, the D脙漏line Got芒聙聶ine Government, a local government or a department or agency of the federal or territorial government proposes to carry out a development that does not require a licence, permit or other authorization under any federal, territorial, Tlicho or D脙漏line law, it shall comply with the requirements of this Part before taking any irrevocable action in relation to the development.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>2005, c. 1, s. 73<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>39.</B> Section 121 of the Act is replaced by the following:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Written reasons<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>121.</B> The Review Board, a review panel of the Review Board, a review panel or a joint panel established jointly by the Review Board and any other person or body, the federal Minister, a responsible minister, a designated regulatory agency, a regulatory authority, a department or agency of the federal or territorial government, a local government, the Gwich芒聙聶in or Sahtu First Nation, the Tlicho Government or the D脙漏line Got芒聙聶ine Government shall issue and make available to the public written reasons for any decision or recommendation made under the process established by this Part.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>2005, c. 1, s. 74<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>40.</B> Subsection 123.2(2) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Status or entitlements under agreement<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(2) A person is not placed in a material conflict of interest merely because of any status or entitlement conferred on the person under the Gwich芒聙聶in Agreement, the Sahtu Agreement, the Tlicho Agreement or any other agreement between a first nation and Her Majesty in right of Canada for the settlement of a claim to lands or under the D脙漏line Agreement.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:First Nations Goods and Services Tax Act--><MarginalNote>2003, c. 15, s. 67<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="10" Bold="Yes" SmallCaps="Yes" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">First Nations Goods and Services Tax Act</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>41.</B> Schedule 1 to the <I>First Nations Goods and Services Tax Act</I> is amended by adding the following in alphabetical order:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><TABLE space-before="12pt" frame="topbot"><tgroup cols="3"><colspec colname="1" colwidth="33*" /><colspec colname="2" colwidth="33*" /><colspec colname="3" colwidth="33*" /><thead valign="top"><row rowsep="1" topdouble="yes"><entry colname="1" colsep="0" rowsep="0"><Para TopMargin="5" BottomMargin="3pt" Size="8" Leading="9" LeftMargin="0" RightMargin="1.5pt" FirstLineIndent="0" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Left"><B>Column 1</B></Para></entry><entry colname="2" colsep="0" rowsep="0"><Para TopMargin="5" BottomMargin="3pt" Size="8" Leading="9" LeftMargin="0" RightMargin="1.5pt" FirstLineIndent="0" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Left"><B>Column 2</B></Para></entry><entry colname="3" colsep="0" rowsep="0"><Para TopMargin="5" BottomMargin="3pt" Size="8" Leading="9" LeftMargin="0" RightMargin="1.5pt" FirstLineIndent="0" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Left"><B>Column 3</B></Para></entry></row><row rowsep="0" topmarginspacing="4"><entry colname="1" colsep="0" rowsep="1"><Para TopMargin="5" BottomMargin="3pt" Size="8" Leading="9" LeftMargin="0" RightMargin="1.5pt" FirstLineIndent="0" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Left"><B>First Nation</B></Para></entry><entry colname="2" colsep="0" rowsep="1"><Para TopMargin="5" BottomMargin="3pt" Size="8" Leading="9" LeftMargin="0" RightMargin="1.5pt" FirstLineIndent="0" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Left"><B>Governing Body</B></Para></entry><entry colname="3" colsep="0" rowsep="1"><Para TopMargin="5" BottomMargin="3pt" Size="8" Leading="9" LeftMargin="0" RightMargin="1.5pt" FirstLineIndent="0" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Left"><B>Lands</B></Para></entry></row></thead><tbody valign="top"><row rowsep="0" topmarginspacing="4"><entry colname="1" colsep="0" rowsep="0"><Para TopMargin="5" BottomMargin="3pt" Size="8" Leading="9" LeftMargin="0" RightMargin="1.5pt" FirstLineIndent="0" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Left">D脙漏line First Nation</Para></entry><entry colname="2" colsep="0" rowsep="0"><Para TopMargin="5" BottomMargin="3pt" Size="8" Leading="9" LeftMargin="0" RightMargin="1.5pt" FirstLineIndent="0" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Left">D脙漏line Got芒聙聶ine Government</Para></entry><entry colname="3" colsep="0" rowsep="0"><Para TopMargin="5" BottomMargin="3pt" Size="8" Leading="9" LeftMargin="0" RightMargin="1.5pt" FirstLineIndent="0" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Left">D脙漏line Lands, as defined in 22.1.1 of the D脙漏line Final Self-Government Agreement that is approved, given effect and declared valid by the <I>D脙漏line Final Self-Government Agreement Act</I></Para></entry></row></tbody></tgroup></TABLE></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:COORDINATING AMENDMENTS--><Para TopMargin="10" Bold="Yes" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">COORDINATING AMENDMENTS</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>2014, c. 2<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>42.</B> (1) In this section, 芒聙聹other Act芒聙聺 means the <I>Northwest Territories Devolution Act</I>.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes">(2) On the first day on which both subsection 128(2) of the other Act and section 28 of this Act are in force, subsection 31(1) of the <I>Mackenzie Valley Resource Management Act</I> is replaced by the following:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote><I>Statutory Instruments Act</I><br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>31.</B> (1) Sections 3, 5 and 11 of the <I>Statutory Instruments Act</I> do not apply in respect of rules under section 30, a land use plan or amendment to a land use plan under Part 2, rules under subsection 49(2), guidelines or policies under section 65, policy directions under subsection 50.1(1), 83(1), (2) or (2.1) or 142.2(1) or guidelines under section 120.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes">(3) If section 137 of the other Act comes into force before section 29 of this Act, then, on the day on which that section 29 comes into force, subsection 63(5) of the <I>Mackenzie Valley Resource Management Act</I> is replaced by the following:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Consultation with D脙漏line Got芒聙聶ine Government<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(5) The Board shall consult the D脙漏line Got芒聙聶ine Government before issuing, amending or renewing any licence, permit or other authorization for a use of D脙漏line lands or waters on those lands or a deposit of waste on those lands or in those waters.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes">(4) If section 29 of this Act comes into force before section 137 of the other Act, then, on the day on which that section 137 comes into force, section 63 of the <I>Mackenzie Valley Resource Management Act</I> is amended by adding the following after subsection (4):</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Consultation with D脙漏line Got芒聙聶ine Government<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(5) The Board shall consult the D脙漏line Got芒聙聶ine Government before issuing, amending or renewing any licence, permit or other authorization for a use of D脙漏line lands or waters on those lands or a deposit of waste on those lands or in those waters.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes">(5) If section 29 of this Act comes into force on the same day as section 137 of the other Act, then that section 29 is deemed to have come into force before that section 137 and subsection (4) applies as a consequence.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes">(6) If subsection 175(2) of the other Act comes into force before subsection 30(1) of this Act, then, on the day on which that subsection 30(1) comes into force, subsection 83(1.1) of the <I>Mackenzie Valley Resource Management Act</I> is replaced by the following:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Notice to D脙漏line Got芒聙聶ine Government<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(1.1) The federal Minister shall inform the D脙漏line Got芒聙聶ine Government, to the extent provided for in 2.7.1 of the D脙漏line Agreement, of the Minister芒聙聶s intention to give a written policy direction to the Board if the policy direction is in relation to the use of land or water or the deposit of waste in the area described in schedule A to the D脙漏line Agreement.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes">(7) If subsection 30(1) of this Act comes into force before subsection 175(2) of the other Act, then, on the day on which that subsection 175(2) comes into force, section 83 of the <I>Mackenzie Valley Resource Management Act</I> is amended by adding the following after subsection (1):</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Notice to D脙漏line Got芒聙聶ine Government<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(1.1) The federal Minister shall inform the D脙漏line Got芒聙聶ine Government, to the extent provided for in 2.7.1 of the D脙漏line Agreement, of the Minister芒聙聶s intention to give a written policy direction to the Board if the policy direction is in relation to the use of land or water or the deposit of waste in the area described in schedule A to the D脙漏line Agreement.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes">(8) If subsection 30(1) of this Act comes into force on the same day as subsection 175(2) of the other Act, then that subsection 30(1) is deemed to have come into force before that subsection 175(2) and subsection (7) applies as a consequence.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes">(9) If subsection 175(2) of the other Act comes into force before subsection 30(2) of this Act, then, on the day on which that subsection 30(2) comes into force, subsection 83(2.1) of the <I>Mackenzie Valley Resource Management Act</I> is replaced by the following:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Policy directions by D脙漏line Got芒聙聶ine Government to Board<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(2.1) The D脙漏line Got芒聙聶ine Government may, after consultation with the Board and the federal Minister, give written policy directions to the Board with respect to the performance of any of the Board芒聙聶s functions under this Part in relation to the use of D脙漏line lands. Policy directions are binding on the Board to the extent that compliance with them does not require the Board to exceed its approved budget.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes">(10) If subsection 30(2) of this Act comes into force before subsection 175(2) of the other Act, then, on the day on which that subsection 175(2) comes into force, section 83 of the <I>Mackenzie Valley Resource Management Act</I> is amended by adding the following after subsection (2):</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Policy directions by D脙漏line Got芒聙聶ine Government to Board<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(2.1) The D脙漏line Got芒聙聶ine Government may, after consultation with the Board and the federal Minister, give written policy directions to the Board with respect to the performance of any of the Board芒聙聶s functions under this Part in relation to the use of D脙漏line lands. Policy directions are binding on the Board to the extent that compliance with them does not require the Board to exceed its approved budget.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes">(11) If subsection 30(2) of this Act comes into force on the same day as subsection 175(2) of the other Act, then that subsection 30(2) is deemed to have come into force before that subsection 175(2) and subsection (10) applies as a consequence.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes">(12) On the first day on which both section 176 of the other Act and section 2 of this Act are in force, subsection 83.1(2) of the <I>Mackenzie Valley Resource Management Act</I> is amended by striking out 芒聙聹and芒聙聺 at the end of paragraph (<I>c</I>), by adding 芒聙聹and芒聙聺 at the end of paragraph (<I>d</I>) and by adding the following after paragraph (<I>d</I>):</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>e</I>) the D脙漏line Got芒聙聶ine Government with respect to the amendment of any D脙漏line law regarding the use of D脙漏line lands or waters on those lands or a deposit of waste on those lands or in those waters.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes">(13) If section 181 of the other Act comes into force before section 32 of this Act, then, on the day on which that section 32 comes into force, section 90.11 of the <I>Mackenzie Valley Resource Management Act</I> is replaced by the following:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Prohibition 芒聙聰 D脙漏line lands<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>90.11</B> Even if the regulations do not require a permit or other authorization under this Part for a particular use of land, no person shall use D脙漏line lands without such a permit or authorization if one is required by a D脙漏line law for uses of that type.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes">(14) If section 32 of this Act comes into force before section 181 of the other Act, then that section 181 is replaced by the following:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>181.</B> Sections 90.1 to 90.2 of the Act are replaced by the following:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Regulations respecting cost recovery<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>90.01</B> The Governor in Council may, following consultation by the federal Minister with first nations, the Tlicho Government, the territorial Minister and the Board, make regulations respecting the recovery of amounts and costs for the purposes of section 68.1, including prescribing the amounts and services for the purposes of that section and exempting any class of applicants or licensees from the application of that section.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Regulations respecting consultation<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>90.02</B> The Governor in Council may, following consultation by the federal Minister with first nations, the Tlicho Government, the territorial Minister and the Board, make regulations respecting any consultation with a first nation, the Tlicho First Nation, the Tlicho Government or an aboriginal people who use an area outside the Mackenzie Valley that may occur under this Part, including the manner in which it is to be conducted, and providing for the delegation of certain procedural aspects of such a consultation.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Prohibition 芒聙聰 Tlicho lands<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>90.1</B> Even if the regulations do not require a permit or other authorization under this Part for a particular use of land, no person shall use Tlicho lands without such a permit or authorization if one is required by a Tlicho law for uses of that type.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Prohibition 芒聙聰 D脙漏line lands<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>90.11</B> Even if the regulations do not require a permit or other authorization under this Part for a particular use of land, no person shall use D脙漏line lands without such a permit or authorization if one is required by a D脙漏line law for uses of that type.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Exception<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>90.2</B> Despite the regulations, a permit or other authorization under this Part for a particular use of land in a Tlicho community is not required if the local government of that community has enacted a bylaw providing that one is not required for uses of that type.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes">(15) If section 32 of this Act comes into force on the same day as section 181 of the other Act, then that section 32 is deemed to have come into force before that section 181 and subsection (14) applies as a consequence.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes">(16) On the first day on which both section 181 of the other Act and section 33 of this Act are in force, section 90.21 of the <I>Mackenzie Valley Resource Management Act</I> is replaced by the following:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Exception<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>90.21</B> Despite the regulations, a permit or other authorization under this Part for a particular use of lands in the Community of D脙漏line, as described in schedule B to the D脙漏line Agreement, is not required if a D脙漏line law provides that one is not required for uses of that type.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes">(17) If section 193 of the other Act comes into force before section 35 of this Act, then that section 35 is repealed.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes">(18) If section 193 of the other Act comes into force on the same day as section 35 of this Act, then that section 35 is deemed never to have come into force and is repealed.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes">(19) If section 193 of the other Act comes into force before section 36 of this Act, then that section 36 is repealed.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes">(20) If section 193 of the other Act comes into force on the same day as section 36 of this Act, then that section 36 is deemed never to have come into force and is repealed.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes">(21) If section 193 of the other Act comes into force before section 37 of this Act, then that section 37 is repealed.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes">(22) If section 193 of the other Act comes into force on the same day as section 37 of this Act, then that section 37 is deemed never to have come into force and is repealed.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:COMING INTO FORCE--><Para TopMargin="10" Bold="Yes" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">COMING INTO FORCE</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Order in council<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>43.</B> The provisions of this Act, other than sections 19 and 42, come into force on a day or days to be fixed by order of the Governor in Council.</Para></Block><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="BPT_ImprintE"><br /><br />Published under authority of the Speaker of the House of Commons</Para></Block><Block Align="Yes" LineCnt="N"><Para NoLineBreak="Yes" NoHtml="Yes" Leading="0" Size="0" TopMargin="0" BottomMargin="0">脗聞</Para></Block></Bill_Part></Bill>