茂禄驴<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><Bill RHead_reign="62-63-64 Eliz. II" RHead_ParlYear="2013-2014-2015" DocumentTitle="BILL C-65" Bill_No="C-65" Document_No="90774" xml:lang="EN" Bill_Type="Amending" Stage_Name="First-Reading-House" Reprint="No" xml:space="preserve" ChapterNo_E="C. " ChapterNo_F="ch. " Bill-Origin="commons"><Bill_Part Part_Type="Cover" CountLines="No"><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="CovBillNo">C-65</Para></Block><Block><Para TopMargin="24" Size="9" Leading="10" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0" TextAlign="Center">Second Session, Forty-first Parliament,</Para></Block><Block><Para Size="9" Leading="10" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0" TextAlign="Center">62-63-64 Elizabeth II, 2013-2014-2015</Para></Block><Block><Para TopMargin="48" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0" Bold="Yes" TextAlign="Center">HOUSE OF COMMONS OF CANADA</Para></Block><Block><Para TopMargin="42" Size="18" Leading="20" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0" Bold="Yes" TextAlign="Center">BILL C-65</Para></Block><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="CovLongTitle">An Act to amend the Copyright Act (access to copyrighted works or other subject-matter for persons with perceptual disabilities)</Para></Block><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="COV_StageLine"></Para></Block><Block><Para Size="9" AllCaps="Yes" Hyphenate="OFF">first reading, June 8, 2015</Para></Block><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="COV_StageLine"></Para></Block><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="Cover_Sponsors">MINISTER OF INDUSTRY</Para></Block><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="Cover_DocNo">90774</Para></Block></Bill_Part><Bill_Part CountLines="No" Part_Type="InsideCover"><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="BPT_InsideCoverE">Available on the Parliament of Canada Web Site at the following address:<br /><B>http://www.parl.gc.ca</B></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><Para TopMargin="108" BottomMargin="4" Size="10" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">SUMMARY</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" Size="8" Leading="9" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">This enactment amends the provisions of the <I>Copyright Act</I> on access for persons with perceptual disabilities to copyrighted materials and, in doing so, implements the Marrakesh Treaty to Facilitate Access to Published Works for Persons Who Are Blind, Visually Impaired, or Otherwise Print Disabled. The amendments facilitate access for such persons to copyrighted materials while ensuring that the interests of copyright owners are safeguarded.</Para></Block></Bill_Part><Bill_Part Part_Type="MainText" CountLines="Yes" RunningHead_E="     Copyright Act (access to copyrighted works or other subject-matter      for persons with perceptual disabilities)"><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="MainText_DocNo">90774</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes"><Para Style="Session_Reign">2nd Session, 41st Parliament,</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes"><Para Style="Session_Reign">62-63-64 Elizabeth II, 2013-2014-2015</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes"><Para Style="MainBillOrigin">house of commons of canada</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes"><Para Bold="Yes" Style="MAIN@BillNo_Title">BILL C-65</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes"><Para Style="MAIN@ti;04">An Act to amend the Copyright Act (access to copyrighted works or other subject-matter for persons with perceptual disabilities)</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">Her Majesty, by and with the advice and consent of the Senate and House of Commons of Canada, enacts as follows:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:SHORT TITLE--><Para TopMargin="10" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">SHORT TITLE</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Short title<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>1.</B> This Act may be cited as the <I>Support for Canadians with Print Disabilities Act</I>.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:COPYRIGHT ACT--><MarginalNote>R.S., c. C-42<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="10" Bold="Yes" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">COPYRIGHT ACT</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>2012, c. 20, s. 36<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>2.</B> (1) The portion of subsection 32(1) of the French version of the <I>Copyright Act</I> before paragraph (<I>a</I>) is replaced by the following:</Para><ExplNote><Para Align="Yes" TopMargin="10" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0" Italic="Yes" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">Copyright Act</Para><Para Align="Yes" TopMargin="10" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><I>Clause 2</I>: (1) to (4) Relevant portion of subsection 32(1):</Para><Para Align="Yes" TopMargin="5" Size="8" Leading="9" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>32.</B> (1) It is not an infringement of copyright for a person with a perceptual disability, for a person acting at the request of such a person or for a non-profit organization acting for the benefit of such a person to</Para><Para Align="No" TopMargin="5" Size="8" Leading="9" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>a</I>) make a copy or sound recording of a literary, musical, artistic or dramatic work, other than a cinematographic work, in a format specially designed for persons with a perceptual disability;</Para><Para Align="No" TopMargin="5" Size="8" Leading="9" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">... 脗聽</Para><Para Align="No" TopMargin="5" Size="8" Leading="9" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>c</I>) perform in public a literary or dramatic work, other than a cinematographic work, in sign language, either live or in a format specially designed for persons with a perceptual disability.</Para></ExplNote></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Production d芒聙聶un exemplaire sur un autre support<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><AltLang xml:lang="fr"><B>32.</B> (1) Ne constitue pas une violation du droit d芒聙聶auteur le fait, pour une personne ayant une d脙漏ficience perceptuelle, une personne agissant 脙聽 sa demande ou un organisme sans but lucratif agissant dans son int脙漏r脙陋t, <change>d芒聙聶accomplir l芒聙聶un</change> des <change>actes suivants</change> : </AltLang></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>1997, c. 24, s. 19<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes">(2) Paragraph 32(1)(<I>a</I>) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>a</I>) <change>reproduce</change> a literary, musical, artistic or dramatic work, other than a cinematographic work, in a format specially designed for persons with a perceptual disability;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0"><change>(<I>a.1</I>) fix a performer芒聙聶s performance of a literary, musical, artistic or dramatic work, other than a cinematographic work, in a format specially designed for persons with a perceptual disability;</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0"><change>(<I>a.2</I>) reproduce a sound recording, or a fixation of a performer芒聙聶s performance referred to in paragraph (<I>a.1</I>), in a format specially designed for persons with a perceptual disability;</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes">(3) Subsection 32(1) of the Act is amended by striking out 芒聙聹or芒聙聺 at the end of paragraph (<I>b</I>) and by adding the following after that paragraph:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0"><change>(<I>b.1</I>) provide a person with a perceptual disability with, or provide such a person with access to, a work or other subject-matter to which any of paragraphs (<I>a</I>) to (<I>b</I>) applies, in a format specially designed for persons with a perceptual disability, and do any other act that is necessary for that purpose; or</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>1997, c. 24, s. 19<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes">(4) Paragraph 32(1)(<I>c</I>) of the French version of the Act is replaced by the following:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0"><AltLang xml:lang="fr"><I>c</I>) l芒聙聶ex脙漏cution en public en langage gestuel d芒聙聶une oeuvre litt脙漏raire ou dramatique 芒聙聰 sauf cin脙漏matographique 芒聙聰 <change>soit</change> en <change>direct soit</change> sur un support pouvant servir aux personnes ayant une d脙漏ficience perceptuelle.</AltLang></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>1997, c. 24, s. 19<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes">(5) Subsections 32(2) and (3) of the Act are replaced by the following:</Para><ExplNote><Para Align="Yes" TopMargin="10" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(5) Existing text of subsections 32(2) and (3):</Para><Para Align="Yes" TopMargin="5" Size="8" Leading="9" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(2) Subsection (1) does not authorize the making of a large print book.</Para><Para Align="Yes" TopMargin="5" Size="8" Leading="9" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(3) Subsection (1) does not apply where the work or sound recording is commercially available in a format specially designed to meet the needs of any person referred to in that subsection, within the meaning of paragraph (<I>a</I>) of the definition 芒聙聹commercially available芒聙聺.</Para></ExplNote></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Limitation<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(2) Subsection (1) does not apply <change>if</change> the work or <change>other subject-matter</change> is commercially available, within the meaning of paragraph (<I>a</I>) of the definition 芒聙聹commercially available芒聙聺 <change>in section 2</change>, in a format specially designed to meet the needs of <change>the</change> person <change>with a perceptual disability</change> referred to in that subsection.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>2012, c. 20, s. 37<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>3.</B> (1) Subsections 32.01(1) to (4) of the Act are replaced by the following:</Para><ExplNote><Para Align="Yes" TopMargin="10" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><I>Clause 3</I>: (1) Existing text of subsections 32.01(1) to (4):</Para><Para Align="Yes" TopMargin="5" Size="8" Leading="9" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>32.01</B> (1) Subject to this section, it is not an infringement of copyright for a non-profit organization acting for the benefit of persons with a print disability to make a copy, in a format specially designed for persons with a print disability, of a work and to send the copy to a non-profit organization in another country for use by persons with print disabilities in that country, if the author of the work that is reformatted is</Para><Para Align="No" TopMargin="5" Size="8" Leading="9" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>a</I>) a Canadian citizen or permanent resident within the meaning of subsection 2(1) of the <I>Immigration and Refugee Protection Act</I>; or</Para><Para Align="No" TopMargin="5" Size="8" Leading="9" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>b</I>) a citizen or permanent resident of the country to which the copy is sent.</Para><Para Align="Yes" TopMargin="5" Size="8" Leading="9" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(2) Subsection (1) does not authorize a large print book or a cinematographic work to be sent outside Canada.</Para><Para Align="Yes" TopMargin="5" Size="8" Leading="9" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(3) Subsection (1) does not authorize a copy to be sent to a country if the organization knows or has reason to believe that the work, in the format specially designed for persons with a print disability, is available in that country within a reasonable time and for a reasonable price, and may be located in that country with reasonable effort.</Para><Para Align="Yes" TopMargin="5" Size="8" Leading="9" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(3.1) If a non-profit organization that is relying on the exception set out in subsection (1) infringes copyright by reason only of making a mistake in good faith as to the citizenship or residency of the author of the work, an injunction is the only remedy that the owner of the copyright in the work has against the organization.</Para><Para Align="Yes" TopMargin="5" Size="8" Leading="9" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(4) The organization making and sending the copy shall pay, in accordance with the regulations, any royalty established under the regulations to the copyright owner in the work.</Para></ExplNote></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Print disability 芒聙聰 <keep>outside</keep> Canada<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>32.01</B> (1) Subject to this section, it is not an infringement of copyright for a non-profit organization acting for the benefit of persons with a print disability to <change>do any of the following</change>:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0"><change>(<I>a</I>) for the purpose of doing any of the acts set out in paragraph (<I>b</I>),</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="4" FirstLineIndent="0"><change>(i) reproduce a literary, musical, artistic or dramatic work, other than a cinematographic work, in a format specially designed for persons with a print disability,</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="4" FirstLineIndent="0"><change>(ii) fix a performer芒聙聶s performance of a literary, musical, artistic or dramatic work, other than a cinematographic work, in a format specially designed for persons with a print disability, or</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="4" FirstLineIndent="0"><change>(iii) reproduce a sound recording, or a fixation of a performer芒聙聶s performance referred to in subparagraph (ii), in a format specially designed for persons with a print disability;</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0"><change>(<I>b</I>) provide either of the following with, or provide either of the following with access to, a work or other subject-matter to which any of subparagraphs (<I>a</I>)(i) to (iii) applies, in a format specially designed for persons with a print disability, and do any other act that is necessary for that purpose:</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="4" FirstLineIndent="0"><change>(i) a non-profit organization, in a country other than Canada, acting for the benefit of persons with a print disability in that country, or</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="4" FirstLineIndent="0"><change>(ii) a person with a print disability, in a country other than Canada, who has made a request to be provided with, or provided with access to, the work or other subject-matter through a non-profit organization acting for the benefit of persons with a print disability in that country.</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Available in other country<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(2) <change>Paragraph</change> (1)<change>(<I>b</I>)</change> does not <change>apply</change> if the work <change>or other subject-matter</change>, in the format specially designed for persons with a print disability, is available in <change>the other</change> country within a reasonable time and for a reasonable price and may be located in that country with reasonable effort.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Marrakesh Treaty country<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><change>(3) An injunction is the only remedy that the owner of the copyright in the work or other subject-matter has against a non-profit organization relying on the exception set out in paragraph (1)(<I>b</I>) if</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0"><change>(<I>a</I>) the other country referred to in that paragraph is a Marrakesh Treaty country; and</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0"><change>(<I>b</I>) the non-profit organization infringes copyright by reason only that the work or other subject-matter, in the format described in subsection (2), is available, and may be located, as described in that subsection.</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0"><change>The owner of the copyright bears the burden of demonstrating that the work or other subject-matter, in the format described in subsection (2), is available, and may be located, as described in that subsection.</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Not a Marrakesh Treaty country<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(3.1) An injunction is the only remedy that the owner of the copyright in the work or <change>other subject-matter</change> has against a non-profit organization relying on the exception set out in <change>paragraph</change> (1)<change>(<I>b</I>)</change> if</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0"><change>(<I>a</I>) the other country referred to in that paragraph is not a Marrakesh Treaty country;</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0"><change>(<I>b</I>) the non-profit organization infringes copyright by reason only that the work or other subject-matter, in the format described in subsection (2), is available, and may be located, as described in that subsection; and</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0"><change>(<I>c</I>) the non-profit organization demonstrates that it had reasonable grounds to believe that the work or other subject-matter, in the format described in subsection (2), was not available, and could not be located, as described in that subsection.</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Royalty<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(4) <change>A non-profit</change> organization <change>relying on</change> the <change>exception set out</change> in <change>subsection (1)</change> shall pay, in accordance with the regulations, any royalty established under the regulations to the copyright owner.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>2012, c. 20, s. 37<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes">(2) Subsection 32.01(6) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Para><ExplNote><Para Align="Yes" TopMargin="10" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(2) Existing text of subsection 32.01(6):</Para><Para Align="Yes" TopMargin="5" Size="8" Leading="9" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(6) The organization making and sending the copy shall submit reports to an authority in accordance with the regulations on the organization芒聙聶s activities under this section.</Para></ExplNote></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Reports<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(6) <change>A non-profit</change> organization <change>relying on</change> the <change>exception set out in subsection (1)</change> shall submit reports to an authority, in accordance with the regulations, on the organization芒聙聶s activities under this section.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>2012, c. 20, s. 37<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes">(3) Paragraph 32.01(7)(<I>a</I>) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Para><ExplNote><Para Align="Yes" TopMargin="10" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(3) and (4) Relevant portion of subsection 32.01(7):</Para><Para Align="Yes" TopMargin="5" Size="8" Leading="9" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(7) The Governor in Council may make regulations</Para><Para Align="No" TopMargin="5" Size="8" Leading="9" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>a</I>) requiring a non-profit organization that seeks to send a copy outside Canada to, before doing so, enter into a contract with the recipient non-profit organization with respect to the use of the copy;</Para><Para Align="No" TopMargin="5" Size="8" Leading="9" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">... 脗聽</Para><Para Align="No" TopMargin="5" Size="8" Leading="9" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>d</I>) respecting to which collective society a royalty is payable in relation to works or classes of works for the purposes of subsection (5);</Para></ExplNote></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>a</I>) requiring that, before a non-<keep>profit organ-</keep>ization <change>provides, or provides access to</change>, a <change>work or other subject-matter under paragraph (1)(<I>b</I>), the organization</change> enter into a contract with respect to the use of the <change>work or other subject-matter</change> with, <change>as the case may be</change>, the recipient non-profit organization <change>or the non-profit organization through which the request was made</change>;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>2012, c. 20, s. 37<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes">(4) Paragraph 32.01(7)(<I>d</I>) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>d</I>) respecting to which collective society a royalty is payable in relation to works <change>or other subject-matter</change>, or classes of works <change>or other subject-matter</change>, for the purposes of subsection (5);</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>2012, c. 20, s. 37<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes">(5) Subsection 32.01(8) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Para><ExplNote><Para Align="Yes" TopMargin="10" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(5) Existing text of subsection 32.01(8):</Para><Para Align="Yes" TopMargin="5" Size="8" Leading="9" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(8) In this section, 芒聙聹print disability芒聙聺 means a disability that prevents or inhibits a person from reading a literary, musical or dramatic work in its original format, and includes such a disability resulting from</Para><Para Align="No" TopMargin="5" Size="8" Leading="9" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>a</I>) severe or total impairment of sight or the inability to focus or move one芒聙聶s eyes;</Para><Para Align="No" TopMargin="5" Size="8" Leading="9" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>b</I>) the inability to hold or manipulate a book; or</Para><Para Align="No" TopMargin="5" Size="8" Leading="9" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>c</I>) an impairment relating to comprehension.</Para></ExplNote></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Definitions<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(8) <change>The following definitions apply</change> in this section.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><MarginalNote>芒聙聹Marrakesh Treaty country芒聙聺<br />脗芦 <I>pays partie au Trait脙漏 de Marrakech</I> 脗禄<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0"><change>芒聙聹Marrakesh Treaty country芒聙聺 means a country that is a party to the Marrakesh Treaty to Facilitate Access to Published Works for Persons Who Are Blind, Visually Impaired, or Otherwise Print Disabled, done at Marrakesh on June 27, 2013.</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><MarginalNote>芒聙聹print disability芒聙聺<br />脗芦 <I>d脙漏ficience de lecture des imprim脙漏s</I> 脗禄<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0">芒聙聹print disability芒聙聺 means a disability that prevents or inhibits a person from reading a literary, musical, <change>artistic</change> or dramatic work in its original format and includes such a disability resulting from</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>a</I>) severe or total impairment of sight or the inability to focus or move one芒聙聶s eyes;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>b</I>) the inability to hold or manipulate a book; or</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>c</I>) an impairment relating to comprehension.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>4.</B> The Act is amended by adding the following after section 32.01:</Para><ExplNote><Para Align="Yes" TopMargin="10" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><I>Clause 4</I>: New.</Para></ExplNote></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Definition of 芒聙聹non-profit organization芒聙聺<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><change><B>32.02</B> In sections 32 and 32.01, 芒聙聹non-profit organization芒聙聺 includes a department, agency or other portion of any order of government, including a municipal or local government, when it is acting on a non-profit basis.</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>2012, c. 20, s. 47<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>5.</B> Section 41.16 of the Act is replaced by the following:</Para><ExplNote><Para Align="Yes" TopMargin="10" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><I>Clause 5</I>: Existing text of section 41.16:</Para><Para Align="Yes" TopMargin="5" Size="8" Leading="9" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>41.16</B> (1) Paragraph 41.1(1)(<I>a</I>) does not apply to a person with a perceptual disability, another person acting at their request or a non-profit organization acting for their benefit if that person or organization circumvents a technological protection measure for the sole purpose of making a work, a performer芒聙聶s performance fixed in a sound recording or a sound recording perceptible to the person with a perceptual disability.</Para><Para Align="Yes" TopMargin="5" Size="8" Leading="9" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(2) Paragraphs 41.1(1)(<I>b</I>) and (<I>c</I>) do not apply to a person who offers or provides services to persons or organizations referred to in subsection (1), or manufactures, imports or provides a technology, device or component, for the purposes of enabling those persons or organizations to circumvent a technological protection measure in accordance with that subsection, to the extent that the services, technology, device or component do not unduly impair the technological protection measure.</Para></ExplNote></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Persons with perceptual disabilities<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>41.16</B> (1) Paragraph 41.1(1)(<I>a</I>) does not apply to a person with a perceptual disability, <change>to</change> another person acting at their request or <change>to</change> a non-profit organization, <change>as defined in section 32.02</change>, acting for their benefit, if that person or organization circumvents a technological protection measure <change>solely</change> for <change>one or more</change> of the <change>following purposes</change>:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0"><change>(<I>a</I>)</change> <change>to make</change> a work, a performer芒聙聶s performance fixed in a sound recording or a sound recording perceptible to the person with a perceptual disability;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0"><change>(<I>b</I>) to permit a person, or a non-profit organization referred to in subsection 32(1), to benefit from the exception set out in section 32;</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0"><change>(<I>c</I>) to permit a non-profit organization referred to in subsection 32.01(1) to benefit from the exception set out in section 32.01.</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Services, technology, device or component<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(2) Paragraphs 41.1(1)(<I>b</I>) and (<I>c</I>) do not apply to a person who offers or provides services to persons or <change>non-profit</change> organizations referred to in subsection (1) or <change>who</change> manufactures, imports or provides a technology, device or component, for the <change>sole purpose</change> of enabling those persons or <change>non-profit</change> organizations to circumvent a technological protection measure in accordance with that subsection.</Para></Block><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="BPT_ImprintE"><br /><br />Published under authority of the Speaker of the House of Commons</Para></Block><Block Align="Yes" LineCnt="N"><Para NoLineBreak="Yes" NoHtml="Yes" Leading="0" Size="0" TopMargin="0" BottomMargin="0">脗聞</Para></Block></Bill_Part></Bill>