﻿<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><Bill RHead_reign="62-63-64 Eliz. II" RHead_ParlYear="2013-2014-2015" DocumentTitle="BILL C-653" Bill_No="C-653" Document_No="412005" xml:lang="EN" Bill_Type="Non-amending" Stage_Name="First-Reading-House" Reprint="No" xml:space="preserve" ChapterNo_E="C. " ChapterNo_F="ch. " Bill-Origin="commons"><Bill_Part Part_Type="Cover" CountLines="No"><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="CovBillNo">C-653</Para></Block><Block><Para TopMargin="24" Size="9" Leading="10" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0" TextAlign="Center">Second Session, Forty-first Parliament,</Para></Block><Block><Para Size="9" Leading="10" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0" TextAlign="Center">62-63-64 Elizabeth II, 2013-2014-2015</Para></Block><Block><Para TopMargin="48" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0" Bold="Yes" TextAlign="Center">HOUSE OF COMMONS OF CANADA</Para></Block><Block><Para TopMargin="42" Size="18" Leading="20" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0" Bold="Yes" TextAlign="Center">BILL C-653</Para></Block><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="CovLongTitle">An Act to amend the Canada Water Act (recycling, conservation and efficiency)</Para></Block><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="COV_StageLine"></Para></Block><Block><Para Size="9" AllCaps="Yes" Hyphenate="OFF">first reading, February 18, 2015</Para></Block><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="COV_StageLine"></Para></Block><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="Cover_Sponsors"><SC SC_PerCent="85">Mr. Scarpaleggia</SC></Para></Block><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="Cover_DocNo">412005</Para></Block></Bill_Part><Bill_Part CountLines="No" Part_Type="InsideCover"><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="BPT_InsideCoverE">Available on the Parliament of Canada Web Site at the following address:<br /><B>http://www.parl.gc.ca</B></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><Para TopMargin="108" BottomMargin="4" Size="10" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">SUMMARY</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" Size="8" Leading="9" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">This enactment amends the <I>Canada Water Act</I> to</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" Size="8" Leading="9" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">(<I>a</I>) authorize the Governor in Council to make regulations respecting water devices and standards for water recycling, water conservation and water efficiency; </Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" Size="8" Leading="9" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">(<I>b</I>) confer powers on the Minister of the Environment in respect of the development and undertaking of programs relating to the development and promotion of water devices and water-recycling, water conservation and water efficiency practices;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" Size="8" Leading="9" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">(<I>c</I>) establish requirements in respect of the importation and interprovincial sale or shipping of water devices;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" Size="8" Leading="9" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">(<I>d</I>) create offences in respect of the failure to provide required information and the failure to comply with requirements in respect of the importation and the interprovincial sale or shipping of water devices; and</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" Size="8" Leading="9" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">(<I>e</I>) require the Minister to demonstrate in a report to Parliament</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" Size="8" Leading="9" LeftMargin="4" FirstLineIndent="0" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">(i) the extent to which the water efficiency standards prescribed under this Act compare to standards established by other jurisdictions, and</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" Size="8" Leading="9" LeftMargin="4" FirstLineIndent="0" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">(ii) the extent to which water efficiency standards have been prescribed under this Act for water devices whose use has a significant impact on water consumption in Canada.</Para></Block></Bill_Part><Bill_Part Part_Type="MainText" CountLines="Yes" RunningHead_E="Canada Water (recycling, conservation and efficiency)"><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="MainText_DocNo">412005</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes"><Para Style="Session_Reign">2nd Session, 41st Parliament,</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes"><Para Style="Session_Reign">62-63-64 Elizabeth II, 2013-2014-2015</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes"><Para Style="MainBillOrigin">house of commons of canada</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes"><Para Bold="Yes" Style="MAIN@BillNo_Title">BILL C-653</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes"><Para Style="MAIN@ti;04">An Act to amend the Canada Water Act (recycling, conservation and efficiency)</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">Her Majesty, by and with the advice and consent of the Senate and House of Commons of Canada, enacts as follows:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:CANADA WATER ACT--><MarginalNote>R.S., c. C-11<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="10" Bold="Yes" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">CANADA WATER ACT</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>1.</B> (1) The preamble to the <I>Canada Water Act</I> is amended by adding the following after the first paragraph:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify"><change>AND WHEREAS those demands are increasing rapidly as a result of population and industrial growth and there is a need to sustain Canada’s agricultural, fishing, forestry and other resource-based sectors;</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify"><change>AND WHEREAS there is concern that climate change will affect the availability and quality of water resources as a result of drought cycles that are increasing in frequency, length and warmth;</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes">(2) The third paragraph of the preamble to the Act is replaced by the following:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify"><change>AND WHEREAS there is a significant and immediate opportunity to promote the recycling, conservation and efficient use of the water resources of Canada to protect the well-being and prosperity of the people of Canada and the quality of the Canadian environment in general;</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify"><change>AND WHEREAS the Government of Canada is committed to ensuring sustained improvement in the efficient use of water in all sectors of the Canadian economy;</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">AND WHEREAS Parliament desires that, in addition, comprehensive programs be undertaken by the Government of Canada and by the Government of Canada in cooperation with provincial governments <change>— each</change> in accordance with <change>its</change> responsibilities in relation to water resources <change>—</change> for research and planning with respect to those resources, for <change>the</change> conservation, <change>sustainable</change> development and utilization <change>of those resources</change> and for <change>the research, development and promotion of  water devices and water-recycling, water conservation and water efficiency practices</change> to ensure the optimum use <change>of those resources</change> for the benefit of all Canadians;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>2.</B> Subsection 2(1) of the Act is amended by adding the following in alphabetical order:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>“recycling”<br />« <I>recyclage</I> »<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0"><change>“recycling” in respect of water, means any process by which water that has been used is made available for further use or reuse with or without treatment or processing to alter its physical, chemical or aesthetic qualities.</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><MarginalNote>“water device”<br />« <I>dispositif  d’eau</I> »<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0"><change>“water device” includes a water-applying device, water-consuming device, water-recycling device, water-conserving device and water efficient device.</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>3.</B> Subsection 18(1) of the Act is amended by striking out “and” at the end of paragraph (<I>i</I>) and by adding the following after that paragraph:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0"><change>(<I>i.1</I>) prescribing classes of water devices;</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0"><change>(<I>i.2</I>) prescribing test methods or protocols for determining the water efficiency rating of water devices;</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0"><change>(<I>i.3</I>) respecting labels to be applied to water devices;</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0"><change>(<I>i.4</I>) prescribing information to be made available by manufacturers, importers and distributors of water devices; </change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0"><change>(<I>i.5</I>) establishing or recognizing standards for water recycling, water conservation and water efficiency;</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0"><change>(<I>i.6</I>) defining “water-applying device”, “water-consuming device”, “water-recycling device”, “water-conserving device” and “water efficient device”;</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0"><change>(<I>i.7</I>) prescribing anything that is required by this Act to be prescribed; and</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>4.</B> The Act is amended by adding the following after section 18:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:PART III--><Para TopMargin="10" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center"><change>PART III</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:WATER RECYCLING, WATER CONSERVATION AND WATER EFFICIENCY --><Para TopMargin="5" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center"><change>WATER RECYCLING, WATER CONSERVATION AND WATER EFFICIENCY </change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:Arrangements--><Para TopMargin="5" SmallCaps="Yes" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center"><change>Arrangements</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Establishment of intergovernmental committees or other bodies<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><change><B>19.</B> Subject to the approval of the Governor in Council and taking into consideration the distinctive geography of Canada and the character of water as a natural resource, the Minister may, in order to facilitate the formulation of policies and programs with respect to the recycling, conservation and efficient use of the water resources of Canada and to ensure the optimum use of those resources for the benefit of all Canadians, enter into arrangements with the government of the United States and with provincial governments to establish, on an international, national, provincial, regional, lake or river-basin basis, intergovernmental committees or other bodies for the purpose of</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0"><change>(<I>a</I>) allowing consultation to take place on a continuing basis in respect of  development of and research on water devices and water-recycling, water conservation and water efficiency practices;</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0"><change>(<I>b</I>) providing expertise in respect of the formulation of water-recycling, water conservation and water efficiency policies and programs; and</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0"><change>(<I>c</I>) facilitating the coordination, promotion and implementation of water-recycling, water conservation and water efficiency policies and programs.</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:Programs--><Para TopMargin="10" SmallCaps="Yes" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center"><change>Programs</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Agreements regarding programs<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><change><B>20.</B> Subject to the other provisions of this Act, the Minister may, with the approval of the Governor in Council, enter into agreements with the government of the United States, provincial governments, industrial and trade organizations and communities with an interest in the recycling, conservation and efficient use of water, to provide for programs to</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0"><change>(<I>a</I>) develop water devices; and</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0"><change>(<I>b</I>) promote the adoption of water devices and water-recycling, water conservation and water efficiency practices.</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Development, undertaking of programs under agreement<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><change><B>21.</B> (1) The Minister may, with the approval of the Governor in Council, develop and undertake a program pursuant to an agreement that has been entered into under section 20.</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Development, undertaking of programs without agreement<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><change>(2) The Minister may, with the approval of the Governor in Council, develop and undertake a program described in paragraph 20(<I>a</I>) or (<I>b</I>), despite the fact that an agreement has not been entered into under section 20 in respect of that program,  if the Governor in Council is satisfied that all reasonable efforts have been made by the Minister to enter into such an agreement and that, despite those efforts, it is not possible for an agreement to be entered into in a timely fashion.</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Ministerial agreements with other countries<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><change><B>22.</B> The Minister may, with the approval of the Governor in Council, enter into agreements with the governments of other countries to facilitate the implementation and enforcement in those countries of programs or standards applicable to water devices.</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Ministerial agreements with provinces etc.<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><change><B>23.</B> The Minister may, with the approval of the Governor in Council, enter into agreements with provincial and municipal governments and any organization or group of organizations in Canada respecting the development and <keep>operation of</keep> demonstration projects or programs involving water recycling, water conservation or water efficiency.</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Research and development<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><change><B>24.</B> The Minister may, in connection with the development and undertaking of programs, conduct research involving any aspect of water recycling, water conservation and water efficiency in cooperation with any government, organization or person.</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Contribution to funding<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><change><B>24.1</B> The Minister may, with the approval of the Governor in Council, contribute to the funding of any program undertaken under paragraph 20(<I>b</I>) or section 23.</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Conditions applicable to grants and contributions<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><change><B>24.2</B> The Minister may, with the approval of the Governor in Council, establish conditions to apply to applicants for and recipients of grants and contributions provided by the Government of Canada to implement water-recycling, water conservation and water efficiency practices.</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Annual report<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><change><B>24.3</B> (1) Within sixty days after the end of each fiscal year, the Minister shall publish on the departmental website an annual report on the activities carried out under sections 20 to 24.1.</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Reports and recommendations<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><change>(2) The Minister may, from time to time, publish on the departmental website reports and recommendations on water-recycling, water conservation and water efficiency policies and practices.</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:Importation and Interprovincial Sale or Shipping--><Para TopMargin="10" SmallCaps="Yes" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center"><change>Importation and Interprovincial Sale or Shipping</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Information to be provided by importers etc.<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><change><B>24.4</B> (1) Every person who imports a water device into Canada, or sells or ships a water device from one province to another, shall provide the Minister, in the prescribed form and manner and at the prescribed time, with the prescribed information regarding those devices, including information regarding their water efficiency, their shipment or their importation.</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Exceptions<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><change>(2) The requirement under subsection (1) to provide prescribed information in respect of the water efficiency of any particular water device does not apply if the Minister is satisfied that</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0"><change>(<I>a</I>) the information has previously been provided under that subsection; or</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0"><change>(<I>b</I>) information has previously been provided under that subsection in respect of the water efficiency of comparable water devices that differ from those devices solely in a manner that does not relate to water efficiency.</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Prohibition<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><change><B>24.5</B> (1) No person shall import a water device into Canada, or sell or ship a water device from one province to another, unless</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0"><change>(<I>a</I>) the water device has been certified by an accredited organization to conform to stand­ards established or incorporated by regulation; and</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0"><change>(<I>b</I>) the water device is labelled in accordance with the regulations and the prescribed information is included in its packaging.</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Definition of “accredited organization”<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><change>(2) In this section, “accredited organization” means an organization accredited by the Stand­ards Council of Canada as being competent to certify the conformance of water devices to standards established or incorporated by regulation.  </change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>5.</B> Subsection 25(1) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Designation<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>25.</B> (1) The Minister may designate any qualified person as an inspector or analyst for the purposes of this Act but, if a qualified officer of any other department or agency of the Government of Canada <change>or of a provincial government with which an agreement has been entered into under section 20</change> carries out similar duties for the purposes of <change>other legislation,</change> the Minister shall designate that officer whenever possible.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>6.</B> (1) Paragraph 26(1)(<I>a</I>) of the Act is amended by striking out “or” at the end of subparagraph (i) and by adding the following after subparagraph (ii):</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="4" FirstLineIndent="0"><change>(iii) there is being carried out any activity relating to the importing, manufacturing or distributing of water devices, or</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="4" FirstLineIndent="0"><change>(iv) there is being or has been carried out any testing of water devices;</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes">(2) Subsection 26(1) of the Act is amended by striking out “and” at the end of paragraph (<I>b</I>) and by adding the following after that paragraph:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0"><change>(<I>b.1</I>) examine and seize any water device found therein or open any container found therein that the inspector believes on reasonable grounds contains a water device; and</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>7.</B> The Act is amended by adding the following after section 30:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Punishment<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><change><B>30.1</B> Every person who contravenes section 24.4 is guilty of an offence and liable on summary conviction to a fine not exceeding five thousand dollars for each offence.</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Punishment<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><change><B>30.2</B> Every person who contravenes section 24.5 is guilty of an offence and liable on summary conviction to a fine not exceeding fifty thousand dollars for each offence.</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>8.</B> Section 31 of the Act is replaced by the following:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Punishment<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>31.</B> Every person who contravenes section 27 or any regulation made under paragraph 18(1)(<I>e</I>), (<I>f</I>), (<I>g</I>)<change>, (<I>i.3</I>), (<I>i.4</I>)</change> or <change>(<I>i.5</I>)</change> is guilty of an offence punishable on summary conviction.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>9.</B> Section 38 of the Act is renumbered as subsection 38(1) and is amended by adding the following:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Comparison of water efficiency standards<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><change>(2) Once every three years, the Minister shall, in the report referred to in subsection (1),  demonstrate the extent to which the water efficiency standards prescribed under this Act are as stringent as comparable standards <keep>established by</keep> a province, the United Mexican States, the United States of America or a state of the United States of America.</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Report on extent water efficiency standards established<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><change>(3) Within four years after the day on which this section comes into force, the Minister shall, in the report referred to in subsection (1), demonstrate the extent to which water efficiency standards have been prescribed under this Act for water devices whose use has a significant impact on water consumption in Canada.</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:COMING INTO FORCE--><Para TopMargin="10" Bold="Yes" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">COMING INTO FORCE</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Order in council<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>10.</B> The provisions of this Act come into force on a day or days to be fixed by the Governor in Council.</Para></Block><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="BPT_ImprintE"><br /><br />Published under authority of the Speaker of the House of Commons</Para></Block><Block Align="Yes" LineCnt="N"><Para NoLineBreak="Yes" NoHtml="Yes" Leading="0" Size="0" TopMargin="0" BottomMargin="0"></Para></Block></Bill_Part></Bill>