﻿<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><Bill RHead_reign="62-63-64 Eliz. II" RHead_ParlYear="2013-2014-2015" DocumentTitle="BILL C-689" Bill_No="C-689" Document_No="412289" xml:lang="EN" Bill_Type="Non-amending" Stage_Name="First-Reading-House" Reprint="No" xml:space="preserve" ChapterNo_E="C. " ChapterNo_F="ch. " Bill-Origin="commons"><Bill_Part Part_Type="Cover" CountLines="No"><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="CovBillNo">C-689</Para></Block><Block><Para TopMargin="24" Size="9" Leading="10" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0" TextAlign="Center">Second Session, Forty-first Parliament,</Para></Block><Block><Para Size="9" Leading="10" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0" TextAlign="Center">62-63-64 Elizabeth II, 2013-2014-2015</Para></Block><Block><Para TopMargin="48" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0" Bold="Yes" TextAlign="Center">HOUSE OF COMMONS OF CANADA</Para></Block><Block><Para TopMargin="42" Size="18" Leading="20" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0" Bold="Yes" TextAlign="Center">BILL C-689</Para></Block><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="CovLongTitle">An Act to enact the Global Human Rights Accountability Act and to make related amendments to the Special Economic Measures Act and the Immigration and Refugee Protection Act</Para></Block><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="COV_StageLine"></Para></Block><Block><Para Size="9" AllCaps="Yes" Hyphenate="OFF">first reading, June 9, 2015</Para></Block><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="COV_StageLine"></Para></Block><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="Cover_Sponsors"><SC SC_PerCent="85">Mr. Cotler</SC></Para></Block><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="Cover_DocNo">412289</Para></Block></Bill_Part><Bill_Part CountLines="No" Part_Type="InsideCover"><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="BPT_InsideCoverE">Available on the Parliament of Canada Web Site at the following address:<br /><B>http://www.parl.gc.ca</B></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><Para TopMargin="108" BottomMargin="4" Size="10" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">SUMMARY</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" Size="8" Leading="9" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">This enactment enacts the <I>Global Human Rights Accountability Act</I> to provide for the taking of restrictive measures in respect of foreign nationals responsible for gross violations of internationally recognized human rights. It also proposes related amendments to the <I>Special Economic Measures Act</I> and to the <I>Immigration and Refugee Protection Act</I>.</Para></Block></Bill_Part><Bill_Part Part_Type="MainText" CountLines="Yes" RunningHead_E="Global Magnitsky Human Rights Accountability"><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="MainText_DocNo">412289</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes"><Para Style="Session_Reign">2nd Session, 41st Parliament,</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes"><Para Style="Session_Reign">62-63-64 Elizabeth II, 2013-2014-2015</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes"><Para Style="MainBillOrigin">house of commons of canada</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes"><Para Bold="Yes" Style="MAIN@BillNo_Title">BILL C-689</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes"><Para Style="MAIN@ti;04">An Act to enact the Global Human Rights Accountability Act and to make related amendments to the Special Economic Measures Act and the Immigration and Refugee Protection Act</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Preamble<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">Whereas human rights and the rule of law are integral to international law and Canada has repeatedly asserted its commitment to promoting international justice and respect for human rights;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">Whereas signatory States to international human rights agreements have committed themselves to the obligations and responsibilities set out in those agreements;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">Whereas Sergei Magnitsky, a Moscow lawyer who uncovered the largest tax fraud in Russian history, was detained without trial, tortured and consequently died in a Moscow prison on November 16, 2009;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">Whereas no thorough, independent and objective investigation has been conducted by Russian authorities into the detention, torture and death of Sergei Magnitsky, nor have the individuals responsible been brought to justice;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">Whereas the unprecedented posthumous trial and conviction of Sergei Magnitsky in Russia for the very fraud he uncovered constitute a violation of the principles of fundamental justice and the rule of law;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">Whereas the United States of America <keep>has adopted</keep> legislation imposing sanctions <keep>against the</keep> individuals complicit in the Sergei <keep>Magnitsky case,</keep> and motions calling for similar sanctions have been adopted by the European Parliament, the Parliamentary Assembly of the Organization for Security and Cooperation in Europe, the Parliamentary Assembly of the Council of Europe, the British House of Commons, the Dutch House of Representatives and the Italian Chamber of Deputies;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">Whereas motions unanimously adopted by the House of Commons of Canada on March 25, 2015, and by the Senate of Canada on May 5, 2015, condemn the mistreatment of Sergei Magnitsky as “a violation of the principles of fundamental justice and the rule of law” and call for sanctions against individuals “who were responsible for the detention, torture or death of Sergei Magnitsky or who have been involved in covering up the crimes he exposed”;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">And whereas the motions adopted by the House of Commons and by the Senate also call for sanctions against any foreign nationals responsible for violations of internationally recognized human rights in a foreign country, when authorities in that country are unable or unwilling to conduct a thorough, independent and objective investigation of the violations;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">Now, therefore, Her Majesty, by and with the advice and consent of the Senate and House of Commons of Canada, enacts as follows:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:SHORT TITLE--><Para TopMargin="10" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">SHORT TITLE</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Short title<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>1.</B> This Act may be cited as the <I>Global Magnitsky Human Rights Accountability Act</I>.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:ENACTMENT OF THE GLOBAL HUMAN RIGHTS ACCOUNTABILITY ACT--><Para TopMargin="10" Bold="Yes" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">ENACTMENT OF THE GLOBAL HUMAN RIGHTS ACCOUNTABILITY ACT</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Enactment<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>2.</B> The <I>Global Human Rights Accountability Act</I> is enacted as follows:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="4" FirstLineIndent="-4" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">An Act to provide for the taking of restrictive measures in respect of foreign nationals responsible for gross violations of internationally recognized human rights</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:SHORT TITLE--><Para TopMargin="10" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">SHORT TITLE</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Short title<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>1.</B> This Act may be cited as the <I>Global Human Rights Accountability Act</I>.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:INTERPRETATION--><Para TopMargin="10" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">INTERPRETATION</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Definitions<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>2.</B> (1) The following definitions apply in this Act.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><MarginalNote>“Canadian”<br />« <I>Canadien</I> »<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0">“Canadian” means a person who is a citizen within the meaning of the <I>Citizenship Act</I> or a corporation incorporated or continued by or under the laws of Canada or of a province.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><MarginalNote>“entity”<br />« <I>entité</I> »<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0">“entity” means a corporation, trust, partnership, fund, an unincorporated association or organization or a foreign state.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><MarginalNote>“foreign national”<br />« <I>étranger</I> »<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0">“foreign national” means an individual who is not </Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>a</I>) a Canadian citizen; or</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>b</I>) a permanent resident under the <I>Immigration and Refugee Protection Act</I>. </Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><MarginalNote>“foreign state”<br />« <I>État étranger</I> »<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0">“foreign state” means a country other than Canada, and includes</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>a</I>) any of its political subdivisions;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>b</I>) its government and any of its departments, or the government or any department of any of its political subdivisions; and</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>c</I>) any of its agencies or any agency of any of its political subdivisions.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><MarginalNote>“Minister”<br />« <I>ministre</I> »<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0">“Minister” means the Minister of Foreign Affairs.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><MarginalNote>“person”<br />« <I>personne</I> »<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0">“person” means an individual or an entity.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><MarginalNote>“prescribed”<br /><I>Version anglaise seulement</I><br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0">“prescribed” means prescribed by regulation.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><MarginalNote>“property”<br />« <I>bien</I> »<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0">“property” means any real, personal, movable or immovable property.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Property of a person<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(2) For the purposes of this Act, the property of a person includes property controlled, directly or indirectly, by the person.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:HER MAJESTY--><Para TopMargin="10" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">HER MAJESTY</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Binding on Her Majesty<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>3.</B> This Act is binding on Her Majesty in right of Canada or a province.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:ORDERS AND REGULATIONS--><Para TopMargin="10" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">ORDERS AND REGULATIONS</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Orders and regulations<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>4.</B> (1) The Governor in Council may, if satisfied based on reliable and appropriate evidence that the circumstances described in subsection (2) have occurred,</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>a</I>) make any orders or regulations with respect to the restriction or prohibition of any of the activities referred to in subsection (4) in relation to the foreign national’s property that the Governor in Council considers necessary; and</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>b</I>) by order, cause to be seized, frozen or sequestrated in the manner set out in the order any of the foreign national’s property situated in Canada.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Circumstances<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(2) The circumstances referred to in subsection (1) are the following:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>a</I>) a foreign national is responsible for, or complicit in, extrajudicial killings, torture or other gross violations of internationally recognized human rights committed against individuals in any foreign country who seek</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="4" FirstLineIndent="0">(i) to expose illegal activity carried out by government officials, or</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="4" FirstLineIndent="0">(ii) to obtain, exercise, defend or promote internationally recognized human rights and freedoms, such as the freedoms of religion, expression, association and assembly, and the rights to a fair trial and democratic elections;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>b</I>) a foreign national acts as an agent or on behalf of a foreign state in a matter relating to an activity described in paragraph (<I>a</I>);</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>c</I>) a foreign national who is a government official of a foreign state, or a senior associate of such an official, is responsible for, or complicit in, ordering, controlling, or otherwise directing, acts of significant corruption, including the expropriation of private or public assets for personal gain, corruption related to government contracts or the extraction of natural resources, bribery or the facilitation or transfer of the proceeds of corruption to foreign jurisdictions; or</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>d</I>) a foreign national has materially assisted, sponsored, or provided financial, material or technological support for, or goods or services in support of, an activity described in paragraph (<I>c</I>).</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote> 	Factors<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(3) The Governor in Council may take into account information obtained by other countries and non-governmental organizations that monitor violations of human rights.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Restricted or prohibited activities<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(4) Orders and regulations may be made under paragraph (1)(<I>a</I>) with respect to the restriction or prohibition of any of the following activities, whether carried out in or outside Canada:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>a</I>) the dealing, directly or indirectly, by any person in Canada or Canadian outside Canada in any property, wherever situated, of the foreign national;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>b</I>) the entering into or facilitating, directly or indirectly, by any person in Canada or Canadian outside Canada, of any financial transaction related to a dealing referred to in paragraph (<I>a</I>); and</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>c</I>) the provision by any person in Canada or Canadian outside Canada of financial serv­ices or other related services in respect of property of the foreign national.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Duration<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>5.</B> An order or regulation made under section 4 in respect of a foreign national ceases to have effect on the day that is five years after the day on which it comes into force unless the Governor in Council, by order, extends it for the period specified in the order. It may be extended more than once.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Tabling of order<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>6.</B> A copy of each order or regulation made under section 4 must be tabled in each House of Parliament within 15 days after it is made. It may be sent to the Clerk of the House if the House is not sitting.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:DUTY TO DETERMINE--><Para TopMargin="10" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">DUTY TO DETERMINE</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Determination<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>7.</B> Each of the following entities must determine on a continuing basis whether it is in possession or control of property that they have reason to believe is the property of a foreign national who is the subject of an order or regulation made under section 4:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>a</I>) authorized foreign banks, as defined in section 2 of the <I>Bank Act</I>, in respect of their business in Canada or banks to which that Act applies;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>b</I>) cooperative credit societies, savings and credit unions and caisses populaires regulated by a provincial Act and associations regulated by the <I>Cooperative Credit Associations Act</I>;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>c</I>) foreign companies, as defined in subsection 2(1) of the <I>Insurance Companies Act</I>, in respect of their insurance business in Canada;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>d</I>) companies, provincial companies and societies, as those terms are defined in subsection 2(1) of the <I>Insurance Companies Act</I>;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>e</I>) fraternal benefit societies regulated by a provincial Act in respect of their insurance activities and insurance companies and other entities engaged in the business of insuring risks that are regulated by a provincial Act;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>f</I>) companies to which the <I>Trust and Loan Companies Act</I> applies;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>g</I>) trust companies regulated by a provincial Act;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>h</I>) loan companies regulated by a provincial Act;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>i</I>) entities that engage in any activity described in paragraph 5(<I>h</I>) of the <I>Proceeds of Crime (Money Laundering) and Terrorist Financing Act</I> if the activity involves the opening of an account for a client;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>j</I>) entities authorized under provincial legislation to engage in the business of dealing in securities or to provide portfolio management or investment counselling services; and</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>k</I>) other entities of a prescribed class of entities.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:RIGHTS OF PERSONS WHO ARE SUBJECT TO AN ORDER OR REGULATION--><Para TopMargin="10" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">RIGHTS OF PERSONS WHO ARE SUBJECT TO AN ORDER OR REGULATION</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Application<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>8.</B> (1) A person who is the subject of an order or regulation made under section 4 may apply in writing to the Minister to cease being the subject of the order or regulation on the grounds that the person is not a foreign national.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Recommendation<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(2) If the Minister has reasonable grounds to believe that the applicant is not a foreign national, the Minister must recommend to the Governor in Council that the order or regulation be amended or repealed, as the case may be, so that the applicant is no longer the subject of the order or regulation.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Notice if application rejected<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(3) The Minister must give notice without delay to the applicant of any decision to reject the application.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:APPLICATION FOR A CERTIFICATE--><Para TopMargin="10" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">APPLICATION FOR A CERTIFICATE</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Mistaken identity<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>9.</B> (1) A person claiming not to be a foreign national may apply to the Minister in writing for a certificate stating that they are not a foreign national who is the subject of an order or regulation made under section 4. </Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Certificate — time frame<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(2) If the Minister determines that the person is not a foreign national, the Minister must issue a certificate to the applicant as soon as feasible.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Reasonable expenses<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>10.</B> (1) A person who is the subject of an order or regulation made under section 4 may apply to the Minister in writing for a certificate to exempt property from the application of the order or regulation if the property is necessary to meet the reasonable expenses of the person and their dependents.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Certificate — time frame<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(2) If the Minister determines that the property is necessary to meet the reasonable expenses of the applicant and their dependents, the Minister must issue a certificate to the applicant as soon as feasible.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:GENERAL--><Para TopMargin="10" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">GENERAL</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>No civil liability<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>11.</B> A person who, in relation to any property that is the subject of an order or regulation made under section 4, acts reasonably in taking, or omitting to take, measures to comply with the order or regulation is not liable in any civil action arising from having taken or omitted to take the measures if they took all reasonable steps to satisfy themselves that the property was property that is the subject of the order or regulation.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Existing equities maintained<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>12.</B> All secured and unsecured rights and interests in any property that is the subject of an order or regulation made under section 4 that are held by a person, other than the foreign national who is the subject of the order or regulation, are entitled to the same ranking that they would have been entitled to had the order or regulation not been made.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Proceedings not precluded<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>13.</B> The making of an order or regulation under section 4 does not preclude the commencement of proceedings under any Act of Parliament other than this Act, or any civil proceedings, in respect of any property that is the subject of the order or regulation.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Regulations<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>14.</B> The Governor in Council may make regulations for carrying out the purposes and provisions of this Act, including regulations prescribing anything that by this Act is to be prescribed.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:REVIEW AND REPORT--><Para TopMargin="10" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">REVIEW AND REPORT</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Review<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>15.</B> (1) Within five years after this section comes into force, a comprehensive review of the provisions and operation of this Act and of the <I>Special Economic Measures Act</I> must be undertaken by the committee of the Senate and of the House of Commons that may be designated or established by the Senate and the House of Commons for that purpose.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote> 	Report<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(2) The committees referred to in subsection (1) must, within a year after a review is undertaken pursuant to that subsection or within the further time that may be authorized by the Senate or the House of Commons, as the case may be, submit a report on the review to Parliament, including a statement of any changes that the committees recommend.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:RELATED AMENDMENTS--><MarginalNote>1992, c. 17<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="10" Bold="Yes" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">RELATED AMENDMENTS</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:Special Economic Measures Act--><Para TopMargin="5" Bold="Yes" SmallCaps="Yes" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">Special Economic Measures Act</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>3.</B> (1) The portion of subsection 4(1) of the <I>Special Economic Measures Act</I> before paragraph (<I>a</I>) is replaced by the following:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Orders and regulations<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>4.</B> (1) The Governor in Council may, <change>if he or she is satisfied, based on reliable and appropriate evidence, that the circumstances described in subsection (1.1) have occurred</change>,</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes">(2) Section 4 of the Act is amended by adding the following after subsection (1):</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Circumstances<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><change>(1.1) The circumstances referred to in subsection (1) are the following:</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0"><change>(<I>a</I>) the implementation of a decision, resolution or recommendation of an international organization of states or association of states, of which Canada is a member, that calls on its members to take economic measures against a foreign state;</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0"><change>(<I>b</I>) in the Governor in Council's opinion, a grave breach of international peace and security has occurred that has resulted or is likely to result in a serious international crisis; </change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0"><change>(<I>c</I>) a foreign state is responsible for extrajudicial killings, torture or other gross violations of internationally recognized human rights committed against individuals in any foreign country who seek</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="4" FirstLineIndent="0"><change>(i) to expose illegal activity carried out by government officials, or</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="4" FirstLineIndent="0"><change>(ii) to obtain, exercise, defend or promote internationally recognized human rights and freedoms, such as the freedoms of religion, expression, association and assembly, and the rights to a fair trial and democratic elections;</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0"><change>(<I>d</I>) a person acts as an agent or on behalf of a foreign state in a matter relating to an activity described in paragraph (<I>c</I>);</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0"><change>(<I>e</I>) a government official of a foreign state, or a senior associate of such an official, is responsible for, or complicit in, ordering, controlling, or otherwise directing, acts of significant corruption, including the expropriation of private or public assets for personal gain, corruption related to government contracts or the extraction of natural resources, bribery or the facilitation or transfer of the proceeds of corruption to foreign jurisdictions; or</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0"><change>(<I>f</I>) a foreign state has materially assisted, sponsored, or provided financial, material or technological support for, or goods or services in support of, an activity described in paragraph (<I>e</I>).</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:Immigration and Refugee Protection Act--><MarginalNote>2001, c. 27<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="10" Bold="Yes" SmallCaps="Yes" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">Immigration and Refugee Protection Act</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>4.</B> Subsection 35(1) of the <I>Immigration and Refugee Protection Act</I> is amended by striking out “or” at the end of paragraph (<I>b</I>), by adding “or” at the end of paragraph (<I>c</I>) and by adding the following after paragraph (<I>c</I>):</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0"><change>(<I>d</I>) engaging in or instigating an act described in paragraphs 4(1.1)(<I>c</I>) to (<I>e</I>) of the <I>Special Economic Measures Act</I>; or</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0"><change>(<I>e</I>) being a foreign national who is subject to an order or regulation made under section 4 of the <I>Global Human Rights Accountability Act</I>.</change></Para></Block><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="BPT_ImprintE"><br /><br />Published under authority of the Speaker of the House of Commons</Para></Block><Block Align="Yes" LineCnt="N"><Para NoLineBreak="Yes" NoHtml="Yes" Leading="0" Size="0" TopMargin="0" BottomMargin="0"></Para></Block></Bill_Part></Bill>