﻿<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><Bill RHead_reign="62-63-64 Eliz. II" RHead_ParlYear="2013-2014-2015" DocumentTitle="BILL C-681" Bill_No="C-681" Document_No="412182" xml:lang="EN" Bill_Type="Non-amending" Stage_Name="First-Reading-House" Reprint="No" xml:space="preserve" ChapterNo_E="C. " ChapterNo_F="ch. " Bill-Origin="commons"><Bill_Part Part_Type="Cover" CountLines="No"><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="CovBillNo">C-681</Para></Block><Block><Para TopMargin="24" Size="9" Leading="10" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0" TextAlign="Center">Second Session, Forty-first Parliament,</Para></Block><Block><Para Size="9" Leading="10" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0" TextAlign="Center">62-63-64 Elizabeth II, 2013-2014-2015</Para></Block><Block><Para TopMargin="48" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0" Bold="Yes" TextAlign="Center">HOUSE OF COMMONS OF CANADA</Para></Block><Block><Para TopMargin="42" Size="18" Leading="20" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0" Bold="Yes" TextAlign="Center">BILL C-681</Para></Block><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="CovLongTitle">An Act to amend the Competition Act (Competition Prosecution Service)</Para></Block><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="COV_StageLine"></Para></Block><Block><Para Size="9" AllCaps="Yes" Hyphenate="OFF">first reading, May 26, 2015</Para></Block><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="COV_StageLine"></Para></Block><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="Cover_Sponsors"><SC SC_PerCent="85">Ms. Papillon</SC></Para></Block><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="Cover_DocNo">412182</Para></Block></Bill_Part><Bill_Part CountLines="No" Part_Type="InsideCover"><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="BPT_InsideCoverE">Available on the Parliament of Canada Web Site at the following address:<br /><B>http://www.parl.gc.ca</B></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><Para TopMargin="108" BottomMargin="4" Size="10" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">SUMMARY</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" Size="8" Leading="9" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">This enactment amends the <I>Competition Act</I> to add a new part that provides for the appointment of the Director of the Competition Prosecution Service and one or more Deputy Directors. That Part gives the Director the authority to initiate and conduct, on behalf of the Attorney General of Canda, prosecutions under any Act for the enforcement of which the Commissioner of Competition is responsible. That Part also provides that the Director has the power to make binding and final decisions as to whether to prosecute, unless the Attorney General of Canada directs otherwise, and that any such directive must be in writing and published in the <I>Canada Gazette</I>. The Director holds office for a non-renewable term of seven years during good behaviour and is the Deputy Attorney General of Canada for the purposes of carrying out the work of the office.</Para></Block></Bill_Part><Bill_Part Part_Type="MainText" CountLines="Yes" RunningHead_E="Competition (Competition Prosecution Service)"><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="MainText_DocNo">412182</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes"><Para Style="Session_Reign">2nd Session, 41st Parliament,</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes"><Para Style="Session_Reign">62-63-64 Elizabeth II, 2013-2014-2015</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes"><Para Style="MainBillOrigin">house of commons of canada</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes"><Para Bold="Yes" Style="MAIN@BillNo_Title">BILL C-681</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes"><Para Style="MAIN@ti;04">An Act to amend the Competition Act (Competition Prosecution Service)</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">Her Majesty, by and with the advice and consent of the Senate and House of Commons of Canada, enacts as follows:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:SHORT TITLE--><Para TopMargin="10" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">SHORT TITLE</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Short title<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>1.</B> This Act may be cited as the <I>Competition Prosecution Service Act</I>.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:COMPETITION ACT--><MarginalNote>R.S., c. C-34; <keep>R.S., c.19</keep> (2nd Supp.), s. 19<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="10" Bold="Yes" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">COMPETITION ACT</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>2.</B> The <I>Competition Act</I> is amended by adding the following after section 29.2:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:PART II.1--><Para TopMargin="10" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">PART II.1</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:COMPETITION PROSECUTION SERVICE--><Para TopMargin="5" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">COMPETITION PROSECUTION SERVICE</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:Interpretation--><Para TopMargin="5" SmallCaps="Yes" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">Interpretation</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Definition of “prosecution”<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><change><B>29.21</B> In this Part, “prosecution” means a prosecution under the jurisdiction of the Attorney General of Canada, a proceeding respecting any offence, the prosecution — or prospective prosecution — of which is under the  jurisdiction of the Attorney General of Canada, and any appeal related to such a prosecution or proceeding.</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:Director of the Competition Prosecution Service--><Para TopMargin="10" SmallCaps="Yes" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center"><change>Director of the Competition Prosecution Service</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Appointment<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><change><B>29.22</B> (1) The Governor in Council shall, on the recommendation of the Attorney General of Canada, appoint a Director of the Competition Prosecution Service (in this Act referred to as the “Director”).</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Rank and status<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><change>(2) The Director has the rank and status of a deputy head of a department.</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Duties and functions<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><change>(3) The Director, under and on behalf of the Attorney General of Canada,</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0"><change>(<I>a</I>) initiates and conducts prosecutions under any Act for the enforcement of which the Commissioner is responsible on behalf of the Crown, except where the Attorney General of Canada has assumed conduct of a prosecution under section 29.33;</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0"><change>(<I>b</I>) intervenes in any matter that raises a question of public interest that may affect the conduct of prosecutions or related investigations under any Act for the enforcement of which the Commissioner is responsible, except in proceedings in which the Attorney General of Canada has decided to intervene under section 29.32;</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0"><change>(<I>c</I>) issues guidelines to persons acting as prosecutors respecting the conduct of prosecutions under any Act for the enforcement of which the Commissioner is responsible;</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0"><change>(<I>d</I>) advises law enforcement agencies or investigative bodies in respect of prosecutions generally — or in respect of a particular investigation that may lead <keep>to a prosecution</keep> — under any Act for the enforcement of which the Commissioner is responsible;</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0"><change>(<I>e</I>) communicates with the media and the public on all matters respecting the initiation and conduct of prosecutions under any Act for the enforcement of which the Commissioner is responsible; and</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0"><change>(<I>f</I>) exercises any other power or carries out any other duty or function assigned to the Director by the Attorney General of Canada that is compatible with the office of Director.</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Deputy Attorney General of Canada<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><change>(4) For the purpose of exercising the powers and performing the duties and functions referred to in subsection (3), the Director is the Deputy Attorney General of Canada.</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Guidelines not statutory instruments<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><change>(5) For greater certainty, guidelines referred to in paragraph (3)(<I>c</I>) are not statutory instruments within the meaning of the <I>Statutory Instruments Act</I>.</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Publication<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><change>(6) Any assignment under paragraph (3)(<I>f</I>) must be in writing and be published by the Attorney General of Canada in the <I>Canada Gazette</I>.</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Agreements and arrangements<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><change>(7) The Director may, for the purposes of exercising the powers and performing the duties and functions referred to in subsection (3), enter into an agreement or arrangement on behalf of the Attorney General of Canada with the government of a province.</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Tenure and term<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><change><B>29.23</B> (1) The Director holds office, during good behaviour, for a term of seven years, but may be removed by the Governor in Council at any time for cause with the support of a resolution of the House of Commons to that effect. The Director is not eligible to be reappointed for a further term of office.</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>End of term<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><change>(2) At the end of the Director’s term, the Director shall continue in office until his or her successor is appointed.</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Full-time<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><change>(3) The Director shall engage exclusively in the duties and functions of his or her office under this Act or any other Act of Parliament and shall not hold any other office for reward or engage in any other employment for reward.</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Incapacity or vacancy<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><change>(4) In the event of the incapacity of the Director or a vacancy in that office, the Governor in Council may authorize a Deputy Director of the Competition Prosecution Service to act as Director, but no person may act as Director for a period exceeding 12 months without the approval of the Governor in Council.</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Remuneration and expenses<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><change>(5) The Director shall be paid the remuneration and expenses that are fixed by the Governor in Council. Once fixed, the remuneration may not be reduced.</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:Deputy Directors, Prosecutors and Other Staff--><Para TopMargin="10" SmallCaps="Yes" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center"><change>Deputy Directors, Prosecutors and Other Staff</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Deputy Director<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><change><B>29.24</B> (1) The Governor in Council shall, on the recommendation of the Attorney General of Canada, appoint one or more members of at least 10 years’ standing at the bar of any province to be Deputy Directors of the Competition Prosecution Service.</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Selection committee<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><change>(2) The Attorney General of Canada may only make the recommendation after consultation with a selection committee consisting of the Director, a person representing the Federation of Law Societies of Canada and the Deputy Minister of Justice.</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Powers, duties <keep>and functions</keep> — <keep>lawful deputy</keep><br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><change>(3) Under the supervision of the Director, a Deputy Director may exercise any of the powers and perform any of the duties or functions referred to in subsection 29.22(3) and, for that purpose, is a lawful deputy of the Attorney General of Canada.</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Other powers, duties and functions<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><change>(4) Under the supervision of the Director, a Deputy Director may also act for or on behalf of the Director in the exercise of any of the other powers or the performance of any of the other duties or functions that the Director is authorized to exercise or perform under this or any other Act of Parliament.</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Employed prosecutors<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><change><B>29.25</B> (1) The prosecutors that are necessary to enable the Director to perform any of the duties or functions of his or her office shall be appointed in accordance with the <I>Public Service Employment Act</I>.</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Non-employed prosecutors<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><change>(2) The Director may also for that purpose retain, on behalf of Her Majesty, the services of barristers and, in the Province of Quebec, advocates to act as prosecutors and, with the approval of the Treasury Board, may fix and pay their fees, expenses and other remuneration.</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Qualification<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><change>(3) A person appointed under subsection (1) or whose services are retained under subsection (2) must be a member of the bar of a province.</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Other staff<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><change><B>29.26</B> (1) Any other officers and employees that are necessary to enable the Director to perform any of the duties and functions of his or her office shall be appointed in accordance with the <I>Public Service Employment Act</I>.</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Technical assistance<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><change>(2) The Director may engage the services of persons having technical or specialized knowledge of any matter relating to the Director’s work to advise and assist the Director in performing any of the duties and functions of his or her office and, with the approval of the Treasury Board, may fix and pay the remuneration and expenses of those persons.</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:Delegation--><Para TopMargin="10" SmallCaps="Yes" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center"><change>Delegation</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Delegation<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><change><B>29.27</B> (1) The Director may, subject to any restrictions or limitations that the Director specifies, authorize a prosecutor, a person acting as a prosecutor under subsection 29.25(2) or any person referred to in subsection 29.26(1) to act for or on behalf of the Director in the exercise of any of the powers or the performance of any of the duties or functions that the Director is authorized to exercise or perform under this or any other Act of Parliament, except the power to delegate under this subsection.</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Agency<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><change>(2) Every person who is authorized under subsection (1) acts as an agent of the Director and is not required to prove such authorization.</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Designation<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><change>(3) The Director, a Deputy Director and any person referred to in subsection 29.25(3) may be designated as an agent of the Minister of Public Safety and Emergency Preparedness under section 185 of the <I>Criminal Code</I>.</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:Directives--><Para TopMargin="10" SmallCaps="Yes" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center"><change>Directives</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Directive from Attorney General of Canada —specific <keep>prosecution</keep><br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><change><B>29.28</B> (1) Any directive that the Attorney General of Canada issues to the Director with respect to the initiation or conduct of any specific prosecution must be in writing and be published in the <I>Canada Gazette</I>.</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Directive —<keep>generally </keep><keep>applicable</keep><br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><change>(2) The Attorney General of Canada may, after consulting the Director, issue directives respecting the initiation or conduct of prosecutions generally. Any such directives must be in writing and be published in the <I>Canada Gazette</I>.</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Delay in publication —directive<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><change><B>29.29</B> (1) The Attorney General of Canada or the Director may, if he or she considers it to be in the interests of the administration of justice, direct that the publication in the <I>Canada Gazette</I> of a directive referred to in subsection 29.28(1) be delayed.</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Limit on delay<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><change>(2) The publication of a directive may not be delayed beyond the completion of the prosecution or any related prosecution.</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Directives not statutory instruments<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><change><B>29.3</B> For greater certainty, directives issued under section 29.28 are not statutory instruments within the meaning of the <I>Statutory Instruments Act</I>.</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:Issues of General or Public Interest--><Para TopMargin="10" SmallCaps="Yes" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center"><change>Issues of General or Public Interest</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Duty to inform<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><change><B>29.31</B> The Director must inform the Attorney General of Canada in a timely manner of any prosecution, or intervention that the Director intends to make, that raises important questions of general interest.</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Intervention<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><change><B>29.32</B> When, in the opinion of the Attorney General of Canada, proceedings raise questions of public interest, the Attorney General of Canada may, after notifying the Director, intervene in first instance or on appeal.</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:Assuming Conduct of Prosecution--><Para TopMargin="10" SmallCaps="Yes" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center"><change>Assuming Conduct of Prosecution</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Taking conduct of prosecution<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><change><B>29.33</B> (1) The Attorney General of Canada may only assume conduct of a prosecution after first consulting the Director. The Attorney General of Canada must then give to the Director a notice of intent to assume conduct of the prosecution and publish it in the <I>Canada Gazette</I> without delay.</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Transfer of file<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><change>(2) The Director is required to turn the prosecution file over to the Attorney General of Canada and to provide any information that the Attorney General of Canada requires within the time specified.</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Delay in publication<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><change>(3) However, publication may be delayed if the Attorney General of Canada or the Director considers it to be in the interests of the administration of justice.</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:Annual Report--><Para TopMargin="10" SmallCaps="Yes" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center"><change>Annual Report</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Annual report<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><change><B>29.34</B> (1) The Director shall, not later than June 30 of each year, report to the Attorney General of Canada in respect of the activities of the office of the Director in the immediately preceding fiscal year.</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Tabling in Parliament<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><change>(2) The Attorney General of Canada shall cause a copy of the Director’s report to be laid before each House of Parliament on any of the first 15 days on which that House is sitting after he or she receives the report.</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:TRANSITIONAL PROVISIONS--><Para TopMargin="10" Bold="Yes" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">TRANSITIONAL PROVISIONS</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Continuation of prosecutions<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>3.</B> (1) Any prosecution under any Act for the enforcement of which the Commissioner of Competition is responsible, to which the Attorney General of Canada is a party and that is ongoing on the day on which this Act comes into force is continued by the Director of the Competition Prosecution Service without further formality.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Definition of “prosecution”<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes">(2) In subsection (1), “prosecution” has the same meaning as in section 29.21 of the <I>Competition Act</I>, as enacted by section 2 of this Act.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Non-employed prosecutors<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>4.</B> Any barrister or, in the Province of Quebec, any advocate whose services were retained, immediately before the day on which this Act comes into force, to act as a prosecutor for the Crown in connection with any matter under any Act for the enforcement of which the Commissioner of Competition is responsible is deemed, on that day, to have had his or her services retained under subsection 29.25 of the <I>Competition Act</I>, as enacted by section 2 of this Act, to act in connection with that matter.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:CONSEQUENTIAL AMENDMENTS--><Para TopMargin="10" Bold="Yes" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">CONSEQUENTIAL AMENDMENTS</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:Access to Information Act--><MarginalNote>R.S., c. A-1<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" SmallCaps="Yes" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center"><B>Access to Information Act</B></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>5.</B> Schedule I to the <I>Access to Information Act</I> is amended by adding the following in alphabetical order under the heading “OTHER GOVERNMENT INSTITUTIONS”:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><Para TopMargin="2" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="-2"><change>Office of the Director of the Competition Prosecution Service </change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="0" LeftMargin="4" FirstLineIndent="-2" Italic="Yes"><AltLang xml:lang="fr"><change><I>Bureau du directeur du Service des poursuites en matière de concurrence</I></change></AltLang></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:Department of Justice Act--><MarginalNote>R.S., c. J-2<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="10" SmallCaps="Yes" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center"><B>Department of Justice Act</B></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>6.</B> Subsection 3(2) of the <I>Department of Justice Act</I> is replaced by the following:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Deputy Attorney General<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(2) The Deputy Minister is <I>ex officio</I> the Deputy Attorney General of Canada except in respect of the powers, duties and functions</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0"><change>(<I>a</I>)</change> that the Director of Public Prosecutions is authorized to exercise or perform under subsection 3(3) of the <I>Director of Public Prosecutions Act;</I> and</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0"><change>(<I>b</I>) that the Director of the Competition Prosecution Service is authorized to exercise or perform under subsection 29.22(3) of the <I>Competition Act.</I></change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:Financial Administration Act--><MarginalNote>R.S., c. F-11<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="10" Bold="Yes" SmallCaps="Yes" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">Financial Administration Act</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>7.</B> Schedule I.1 to the <I>Financial Administration Act</I> is amended by <keep>adding the fol-</keep>lowing in alphabetical order in column I:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><Para TopMargin="2" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="-2"><change>Office of the Director of the Competition Prosecution Service</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="0" LeftMargin="4" FirstLineIndent="-2" Italic="Yes"><AltLang xml:lang="fr"><change><I>Bureau du directeur du Service des poursuites en matière de concurrence</I></change></AltLang></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0" Bold="Yes"><B>and a corresponding reference in column II to the “Minister of Justice”.</B></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>8.</B> Schedule IV to the Act is amended by adding the following in alphabetical order:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><Para TopMargin="2" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="-2"><change>Office of the Director of the Competition Prosecution Service</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="0" LeftMargin="4" FirstLineIndent="-2" Italic="Yes"><AltLang xml:lang="fr"><change><I>Bureau du directeur du Service des poursuites en matière de concurrence</I></change></AltLang></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:Privacy Act--><MarginalNote>R.S., c. P-21<br /></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="10" Bold="Yes" SmallCaps="Yes" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">Privacy Act</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>9.</B> The schedule to the <I>Privacy Act</I> is amended by adding the following in alphabetical order under the heading “OTHER GOVERNMENT INSTITUTIONS”:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><Para TopMargin="2" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="-2"><change>Office of the Director of the Competition Prosecution Service </change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="0" LeftMargin="4" FirstLineIndent="-2" Italic="Yes"><AltLang xml:lang="fr"><change><I>Bureau du directeur du Service des poursuites en matière de concurrence</I></change></AltLang></Para></Block><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="BPT_ImprintE"><br /><br />Published under authority of the Speaker of the House of Commons</Para></Block><Block Align="Yes" LineCnt="N"><Para NoLineBreak="Yes" NoHtml="Yes" Leading="0" Size="0" TopMargin="0" BottomMargin="0"></Para></Block></Bill_Part></Bill>