<?xml version="1.0"?>
<Bill RHead_reign="62-63-64 Eliz. II" RHead_ParlYear="2013-2014-2015" DocumentTitle="BILL S-229" Bill_No="S-229" Document_No="3910707" xml:lang="EN" Bill_Type="Non-amending" Stage_Name="First-Reading-Senate" Reprint="No" xml:space="preserve" ChapterNo_E="C. " ChapterNo_F="ch. " Bill-Origin="senate"><Bill_Part Part_Type="Cover" CountLines="No"><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="CovBillNo">S-229</Para></Block><Block><Para TopMargin="24" Size="9" Leading="10" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0" TextAlign="Center">Second Session, Forty-first Parliament,</Para></Block><Block><Para Size="9" Leading="10" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0" TextAlign="Center">62-63-64 Elizabeth II, 2013-2014-2015</Para></Block><Block><Para TopMargin="48" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0" Bold="Yes" TextAlign="Center">SENATE OF CANADA</Para></Block><Block><Para TopMargin="42" Size="18" Leading="20" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0" Bold="Yes" TextAlign="Center">BILL S-229</Para></Block><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="CovLongTitle">An Act for the advancement of the aboriginal languages of Canada and to recognize and respect aboriginal language rights</Para></Block><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="COV_StageLine"></Para></Block><Block><Para Size="9" AllCaps="Yes" Hyphenate="OFF">first reading, June 9, 2015</Para></Block><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="COV_StageLine"></Para></Block><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="Cover_Sponsors">THE HONOURABLE SENATOR JOYAL, P.C.</Para></Block><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="Cover_DocNo">3910707</Para></Block></Bill_Part><Bill_Part CountLines="No" Part_Type="InsideCover"><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="BPT_InsideCoverE">Available on the Parliament of Canada Web Site at the following address:<br/><B>http://www.parl.gc.ca</B></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><Para TopMargin="108" BottomMargin="4" Size="10" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">SUMMARY</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" Size="8" Leading="9" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">This enactment recognizes the right of the aboriginal peoples of Canada to use, preserve, revitalize and promote their languages and expresses the Government of Canada芒聙聶s commitment to preserve, revitalize and promote aboriginal languages in Canada by protecting them and using them where appropriate.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" Size="8" Leading="9" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">It requires the designated Minister to take measures to implement that commitment, including measures to recognize and support the right of aboriginal governments to use and promote aboriginal languages; to encourage and support provincial and territorial governments and municipal, local and educational authorities to support aboriginal languages; to increase opportunities for aboriginal persons to learn and become more proficient in using their languages; to increase the number of circumstances in which aboriginal languages are used and supported; and to foster a positive attitude among all Canadians toward aboriginal languages.</Para></Block></Bill_Part><Bill_Part Part_Type="MainText" CountLines="Yes" RunningHead_E="Aboriginal Languages of Canada"><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="MainText_DocNo">3910707</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes"><Para Style="Session_Reign">2nd Session, 41st Parliament,</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes"><Para Style="Session_Reign">62-63-64 Elizabeth II, 2013-2014-2015</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes"><Para Style="MainBillOrigin">senate of canada</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes"><Para Bold="Yes" Style="MAIN@BillNo_Title">BILL S-229</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes"><Para Style="MAIN@ti;04">An Act for the advancement of the aboriginal languages of Canada and to recognize and respect aboriginal language rights</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Preamble<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">Whereas the historical existence and continued presence of aboriginal peoples in Canada is one of its fundamental characteristics and the varied and diverse voices of the aboriginal peoples of Canada have echoed across this land since time immemorial;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">Whereas language is an integral part of culture and an essential tool of identification, cohesion, communication and creative expression;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">Whereas, following their discussions, exchanges, studies and reports, several aboriginal groups have recommended that formal legislative recognition be given to aboriginal languages;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">Whereas it is desirable to support aboriginal peoples and persons in Canada in preserving and revitalizing their languages as living languages and to ensure that aboriginal language speakers have equal opportunities to obtain education and employment and to participate in their governance and otherwise meaningfully engage in society at every level;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">And whereas the Parliament of Canada is committed to assisting the aboriginal peoples of Canada to preserve and revitalize their languages by protecting and promoting them and by recognizing and respecting aboriginal language rights, a commitment consistent with the policies of the Government of Canada regarding aboriginal self-government and supportive of the individual rights and freedoms of aboriginal persons and the collective rights and freedoms of aboriginal peoples in Canada;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">Now, therefore, Her Majesty, by and with the advice and consent of the Senate and House of Commons of Canada, enacts as follows:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:SHORT TITLE--><Para TopMargin="10" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">SHORT TITLE</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Short title<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>1.</B> This Act may be cited as the <I>Aboriginal Languages of Canada Act</I>.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:INTERPRETATION--><Para TopMargin="10" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">INTERPRETATION</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Definitions<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>2.</B> The following definitions apply in this Act.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><MarginalNote>芒聙聹aboriginal languages芒聙聺<br/>脗芦 <I>langues autochtones</I> 脗禄<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0">芒聙聹aboriginal languages芒聙聺 means the historical and traditional languages spoken by the aboriginal peoples of Canada.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><MarginalNote>芒聙聹aboriginal peoples of Canada芒聙聺<br/>脗芦 <I>peuples autochtones du Canada</I> 脗禄<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0">芒聙聹aboriginal peoples of Canada芒聙聺 means the Indian, Inuit and M脙漏tis peoples of Canada.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><MarginalNote>芒聙聹Minister芒聙聺<br/>脗芦 <I>ministre</I> 脗禄<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0">芒聙聹Minister芒聙聺 means the member of the Queen芒聙聶s Privy Council for Canada designated by the Governor in Council as the Minister for the purposes of this Act.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>English- and French-language education<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>3.</B> For greater certainty, nothing in this Act shall be construed so as to limit or preclude the funding of English or French language education or training programs for aboriginal persons.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:ABORIGINAL AND TREATY RIGHTS--><Para TopMargin="10" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">ABORIGINAL AND TREATY RIGHTS</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Non-derogation<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>4.</B> For greater certainty, nothing in this Act shall be construed so as to abrogate or derogate from any existing aboriginal or treaty rights of the aboriginal peoples of Canada under section 35 of the <I>Constitution Act, 1982</I>.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:ADVANCEMENT OF ABORIGINAL LANGUAGES OF CANADA--><Para TopMargin="10" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">ADVANCEMENT OF ABORIGINAL LANGUAGES OF CANADA</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Recognition of rights<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>5.</B> It is hereby recognized that the aboriginal peoples of Canada have the right to use, preserve, revitalize and promote their aboriginal languages and the freedom to share their cultural heritage through the use of those languages.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Government policy<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>6.</B> The Government of Canada is committed to</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>a</I>) recognizing and respecting the right of aboriginal peoples and persons to use, preserve, revitalize and promote the languages of the aboriginal peoples of Canada, and their freedom to share their cultural heritage through the use of their aboriginal languages;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>b</I>) preserving, revitalizing and promoting aboriginal languages in Canada by pro-tecting them and using them where appropriate;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>c</I>) encouraging and promoting respect and appreciation for aboriginal languages; and</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>d</I>) making use, where appropriate, of the language skills and cultural understanding of aboriginal persons.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Specific mandate of Minister<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>7.</B> The Minister shall take the measures that the Minister considers appropriate to implement the commitments set out in section 6 and otherwise give effect to and carry out the objectives of this Act and, without restricting the generality of the foregoing, the Minister may take measures to</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>a</I>) recognize and support the right of aboriginal governments to take action on using and giving official status to aboriginal languages for the purposes of conducting local governance activities;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>b</I>) recognize and support the right of aboriginal governments to use aboriginal languages as the medium of instruction in all schools that are operated on reserve, or under tuition agreements for aboriginal students, and funded by the Government of Canada;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>c</I>) encourage and support provincial and territorial governments to encourage and support the certification of aboriginal language teachers and instructors, linguists, interpreters and translators, and the use of aboriginal languages as a medium of instruction;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>d</I>) encourage and support provincial, territorial, municipal and local authorities in working with aboriginal partners to implement programs for the purposes of carrying out and giving effect to this Act;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>e</I>) encourage and support institutions of elementary, secondary and higher education to include the study or use of aboriginal languages in their curriculum and to grant full academic credit for proficiency in an aboriginal language equal to that granted for proficiency in either of the official languages of Canada;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>f</I>) encourage and support programs that increase the opportunities for aboriginal persons to learn their languages;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>g</I>) encourage and support an increase in the proficiency levels of aboriginal persons speaking, listening to, reading and writing in aboriginal languages through the development of culturally appropriate curricula and materials;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>h</I>) increase the number of circumstances, situations and activities in which aboriginal languages are used and supported, including their use in broadcasting, telecommunications and other media; and</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>i</I>) foster and support among aboriginal and non-aboriginal peoples a positive attitude towards aboriginal languages as a source of pride in Canadian society.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Agreements<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>8.</B> The Minister, or any other minister of the Crown, may enter into an agreement or arrangement with any province, territory or government of an aboriginal people in Canada the purpose of which is to implement the commitments set out in section 6 or otherwise give effect to or carry out the objectives of this Act.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Consultation<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>9.</B> The Minster shall take such measures as the Minister considers appropriate to ensure consultation with the leaders and governing bodies of aboriginal peoples in Canada in the design, development and implementation of policies and programs under this Act.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:REGULATIONS--><Para TopMargin="10" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">REGULATIONS</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Regulations<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>10.</B> The Governor in Council may make regulations to give effect to and carry out the objectives of this Act.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:ANNUAL REPORT--><Para TopMargin="10" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">ANNUAL REPORT</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Report<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>11.</B> (1) The Minister shall, as soon as possible after the end of each fiscal year, prepare and cause to be laid before each House of Parliament a report on the operation of this Act for that year.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Contents<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(2) The Minister shall include in the annual report</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>a</I>) a description of the measures taken to give effect to and carry out the objectives of this Act;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>b</I>) an evaluation of the impact those measures have had and of the progress made in achieving the objectives of this Act;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>c</I>) a description of the consultations undertaken by the Minister respecting the design, development and implementation of policies and programs under this Act;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>d</I>) an evaluation regarding compliance with the provisions of this Act;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>e</I>) recommendations the Minister may have for better achieving the objectives of this Act; and</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>f</I>) a statement of plans for giving effect to this Act, according to its spirit and intent, in the next year.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:COMING INTO FORCE--><Para TopMargin="10" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">COMING INTO FORCE</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Coming into force<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>12.</B> This Act comes into force on a day, not later than two years after the day on which it receives royal assent, to be fixed by the Governor in Council.</Para></Block><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="BPT_ImprintE"><br/><br/>Published under authority of the Senate of Canada</Para></Block><Block Align="Yes" LineCnt="N"><Para NoLineBreak="Yes" NoHtml="Yes" Leading="0" Size="0" TopMargin="0" BottomMargin="0">脗聞</Para></Block></Bill_Part></Bill>
