<?xml version="1.0"?>
<Bill RHead_reign="62-63-64 Eliz. II" RHead_ParlYear="2013-2014-2015" DocumentTitle="BILL S-3" Bill_No="S-3" Document_No="90647" xml:lang="EN" Bill_Type="Non-amending" Stage_Name="Assented-to" Reprint="No" xml:space="preserve" ChapterNo_E="C. 18" ChapterNo_F="ch. 18" Bill-Origin="senate"><Bill_Part Part_Type="Cover" CountLines="No"><Block><Para TopMargin="24" Size="9" Leading="10" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0" TextAlign="Center">Second Session, Forty-first Parliament,</Para></Block><Block><Para Size="9" Leading="10" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0" TextAlign="Center">62-63-64 Elizabeth II, 2013-2014-2015</Para></Block><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="COV@StatutesTitle">STATUTES OF CANADA 2015<br/>CHAPTER 18</Para></Block><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="CovLongTitle">An Act to amend the Coastal Fisheries Protection Act</Para></Block><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="COV_StageLine"></Para></Block><Block><Para BottomMargin="14" Size="11" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0" Bold="Yes" TextAlign="Center">ASSENTED TO</Para></Block><Block><Para Size="8" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0" TextAlign="Center">18th JUNE, 2015</Para></Block><Block><Para TopMargin="4" Size="8" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0" TextAlign="Center">BILL S-3</Para></Block><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="COV_StageLine"></Para></Block></Bill_Part><Bill_Part CountLines="No" Part_Type="InsideCover"><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="BPT_InsideCoverE">Available on the Parliament of Canada Web Site at the following address:<br/><B>http://www.parl.gc.ca</B></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><Para TopMargin="108" BottomMargin="4" Size="10" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">SUMMARY</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" Size="8" Leading="9" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">This enactment amends the <I>Coastal Fisheries Protection Act</I> to implement the Port State Measures Agreement, to prohibit the importation of fish caught and marine plants harvested in the course of illegal, unreported and unregulated fishing and to clarify certain powers in respect of the administration and enforcement of the Act.</Para></Block></Bill_Part><Bill_Part Part_Type="MainText" CountLines="No" RunningHead_E="Coastal Fisheries Protection"><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="MAIN@RoyalAssentTitle">62-63-64 ELIZABETH II</Para></Block><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="MAIN@RoyalAssentTitle">——————</Para></Block><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="MAIN@RoyalAssentTitle">CHAPTER 18</Para></Block><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="LongTitleAssent">An Act to amend the Coastal Fisheries Protection Act</Para></Block><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="MAIN@RoyalAssentDate">[<I>Assented to 18th June, 2015</I>]</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">Her Majesty, by and with the advice and consent of the Senate and House of Commons of Canada, enacts as follows:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:ALTERNATIVE TITLE--><Para TopMargin="10" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">ALTERNATIVE TITLE</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Alternative title<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>1.</B> This Act may be cited as the <I>Port State Measures Agreement Implementation Act</I>.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:COASTAL FISHERIES PROTECTION ACT--><MarginalNote>R.S., c. C-33<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="10" Bold="Yes" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">COASTAL FISHERIES PROTECTION ACT</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>1999, c. 19, s. 1(4)<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>2.</B> (1) The definitions “Agreement”, “fishing vessel of a participating state” and “participating state” in subsection 2(1) of the <I>Coastal Fisheries Protection Act</I> are repealed.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes">(2) The definitions “fish” and “fishing vessel” in subsection 2(1) of the Act are replaced by the following:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>“fish”<br/>« <I>poisson</I> »<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0">“fish” includes</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>a</I>) any part or derivative of a fish,</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>b</I>) shellfish, crustaceans, marine animals and any part or derivative of any of them, and</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>c</I>) the eggs, sperm, spawn, larvae, spat or juvenile stages, as the case may be, of fish, shellfish, crustaceans and marine animals;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><MarginalNote>“fishing vessel”<br/>« <I>bateau de pêche</I> »<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0">“fishing vessel” means any of the following:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>a</I>) a ship, boat or any other description of vessel that is used in or equipped for</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="4" FirstLineIndent="0">(i) fishing, processing fish or transporting fish from fishing grounds,</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="4" FirstLineIndent="0">(ii) taking, processing or transporting marine plants, or</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="4" FirstLineIndent="0">(iii) provisioning, servicing, repairing or maintaining any vessels of a foreign fishing fleet while at sea,</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>b</I>) a ship, boat or any other description of vessel that is used in transhipping fish, or marine plants, that have not been previously landed;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes">(3) Subsection 2(1) of the Act is amended by adding the following in alphabetical order:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>“fisheries management organization”<br/>« <I>organisation de gestion des pêches</I> »<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0">“fisheries management organization” means an organization or arrangement established by two or more states, or by one or more states and an organization of states, for the purpose of the conservation and management of fish stocks in the sea or any area of the sea;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><MarginalNote>“fishing vessel of a state party to the Fish Stocks Agreement”<br/>« <I>bateau de pêche d’un État assujetti à l’Accord sur les stocks de poissons</I> »<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0">“fishing vessel of a state party to the Fish Stocks Agreement” means a foreign fishing vessel that is entitled to fly the flag of a state party to the Fish Stocks Agreement;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><MarginalNote>“Fish Stocks Agreement”<br/>« <I>Accord sur les stocks de poissons</I> »<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0">“Fish Stocks Agreement” means the Agreement for the Implementation of the Provisions of the United Nations Convention on the Law of the Sea of 10 December 1982 Relating to the Conservation and Management of Straddling Fish Stocks and Highly Migratory Fish Stocks, adopted by the United Nations Conference on Straddling Fish Stocks and Highly Migratory Fish Stocks in New York on August 4, 1995;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><MarginalNote>“flag state”<br/>« <I>État du pavillon</I> »<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0">“flag state” means the state whose flag a fishing vessel is entitled to fly; </Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><MarginalNote>“marine plant”<br/>« <I>plante marine</I> »<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0">“marine plant” means a saltwater plant, including benthic and detached algae, flowering plants, brown algae, red algae, green algae and phytoplankton, and any part or derivative of a saltwater plant;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><MarginalNote>“Port State Measures Agreement”<br/>« <I>Accord sur les mesures de l’État du port</I> »<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0">“Port State Measures Agreement” means the Agreement on Port State Measures to Prevent, Deter and Eliminate Illegal, Unreported and Unregulated Fishing, approved by the Conference of the Food and Agriculture Organization of the United Nations in Rome on November 22, 2009;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><MarginalNote>“state party to the Fish Stocks Agreement”<br/>« <I>État assujetti à l’Accord sur les stocks de poissons</I> »<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0">“state party to the Fish Stocks Agreement” means a foreign state or an organization of foreign states that is prescribed by regulation;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>1999, c. 19, s. 2<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>3.</B> The portion of section 5.3 of the Act before paragraph (<I>a</I>) is replaced by the following:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Prohibition — Fish Stocks Agreement<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>5.3</B> No fishing vessel of a state party to the Fish Stocks Agreement shall, in an area of the sea designated under subparagraph 6(<I>e</I>)(ii),</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>4.</B> The Act is amended by adding the following after section 5.5:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:PROHIBITED IMPORT--><Para TopMargin="10" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">PROHIBITED IMPORT</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Prohibition — importation<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>5.6</B> (1) No person shall import any fish or marine plant knowing it to have been taken, harvested, possessed, transported, distributed or sold contrary to any of the following:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>a</I>) an international fisheries treaty or arrangement to which Canada is party, including any conservation, management or enforcement measures taken under the treaty or arrangement;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>b</I>) any conservation or management measures of a fisheries management organization of which Canada is not a member that is prescribed by regulation;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>c</I>) a law related to fisheries of a foreign state.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Prohibition — other<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(2) No person shall, in connection with the importation of any fish or marine plant, transport, sell, distribute, buy or accept the delivery of the fish or marine plant knowing that it was taken, harvested, possessed, transported, distributed or sold contrary to any of the following:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>a</I>) an international fisheries treaty or arrangement to which Canada is party, including any conservation, management or enforcement measures taken under the treaty or arrangement;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>b</I>) any conservation or management measures of a fisheries management organization of which Canada is not a member that is prescribed by regulation;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>c</I>) a law related to fisheries of a foreign state.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Prohibition — importation<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(3) No person shall import any fish or marine plant that is not accompanied by the documentation required by regulation.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>5.</B> (1) Paragraph 6(<I>a</I>) of the Act is amended by striking out “or” at the end of subparagraph (i), by adding “or” at the end of subparagraph (ii) and by adding the following after subparagraph (ii):</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="4" FirstLineIndent="0">(iii) foreign fishing vessels that have been ordered to proceed to a Canadian port by their flag state, or foreign fishing vessels that have been ordered to proceed to a port by their flag state and that proceed to a Canadian port, to enter Canadian fisheries waters for any purpose related to verifying compliance with a law related to fisheries of a foreign state, with any conservation or management measures of a fisheries management organization or with any international fisheries treaty or arrangement to which Canada is party, including any conservation, management or enforcement measures taken under the treaty or arrangement;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes">(2) Section 6 of the Act is amended by adding the following after paragraph (<I>b.3</I>):</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>b.31</I>) prescribing a fisheries management organization of which Canada is not a member for the purposes of paragraphs 5.6(1)(<I>b</I>) and (2)(<I>b</I>);</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes">(3) Section 6 of the Act is amended by adding the following after paragraph (<I>d</I>):</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>d.1</I>) respecting documentation required for the importation of fish and marine plants;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>1999, c. 19, s. 3(2)<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes">(4) The portion of paragraph 6(<I>e</I>) of the Act before subparagraph (ii) is replaced by the following:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>e</I>) for the implementation of the Fish Stocks Agreement, including regulations</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="4" FirstLineIndent="0">(i) incorporating by reference, or carrying out and giving effect to, any conservation or management measures, as of a fixed date or as they are amended from time to time, of a regional fisheries management organization or arrangement established by two or more states, or by one or more states and an organization of states, for the purpose of the conservation or management of a straddling fish stock or highly migratory fish stock, and designating from among the measures incorporated by reference or regulations made under this subparagraph those the contravention of which is prohibited by paragraph 5.3(<I>a</I>),</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>1999, c. 19, s. 3(2)<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes">(5) Subparagraphs 6(<I>e</I>)(iii) and (iv) of the Act are replaced by the following:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="4" FirstLineIndent="0">(iii) setting out the circumstances in which a person engaged or employed in the administration or enforcement of this Act may exercise, in a manner consistent with the Fish Stocks Agreement and the measures incorporated by reference and the regulations made under subparagraph (i), the powers conferred by or under this Act and setting out any procedures to be followed in doing so,</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="4" FirstLineIndent="0">(iv) empowering the Minister to authorize a state party to the Fish Stocks Agreement to take enforcement action in respect of a Canadian fishing vessel,</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>1999, c. 19, s. 3(2)<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes">(6) Subparagraphs 6(<I>e</I>)(vi) and (vii) of the Act are replaced by the following:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="4" FirstLineIndent="0">(vi) permitting Her Majesty in right of Canada to recover any reasonable costs incurred as a result of the detention in port of a fishing vessel of a state party to the Fish Stocks Agreement, and</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="4" FirstLineIndent="0">(vii) prescribing a state party to the Fish Stocks Agreement for the purposes of this Act; and</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>1999, c. 19, s. 3(2)<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes">(7) Subparagraph 6(<I>f</I>)(i) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="4" FirstLineIndent="0">(i) incorporating by reference, or carrying out and giving effect to, any of those measures as of a fixed date or as they are amended from time to time and designating from among the measures incorporated by reference or regulations made under this subparagraph those the contravention of which is prohibited by section 5.4,</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>1994, c. 14, s. 4; 1999, c. 19, s. 4<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>6.</B> Sections 7 to 7.1 of the Act are replaced by the following:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Definition of “place”<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>7.</B> For the purposes of sections 7.1, 7.4, 7.6 and 9, “place” includes</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>a</I>) a fishing vessel found within Canadian fisheries waters or the NAFO Regulatory Area;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>b</I>) any other vehicle, including a vessel or aircraft; and</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>c</I>) a container.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Entry — any place<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>7.1</B> (1) A protection officer may, for a purpose related to verifying compliance with this Act, enter any place in which the protection officer has reasonable grounds to believe that</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>a</I>) there is any fish, marine plant or other thing in respect of which this Act applies;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>b</I>) there has been carried on, is being carried on or is likely to be carried on any activity in respect of which this Act applies; or</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>c</I>) there are any records, books or other documents, including documents in electronic form, concerning anything referred to in paragraphs (<I>a</I>) and (<I>b</I>).</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Entry — fishing vessel within Canadian fisheries waters or NAFO Regulatory Area<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(2) Despite subsection (1), a protection officer may board a fishing vessel found within Canadian fisheries waters or the NAFO Regulatory Area for a purpose related to verifying compliance with this Act.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Powers on entry<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(3) The protection officer referred to in subsection (1) or (2) may, for a purpose related to verifying compliance with this Act,</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>a</I>) examine anything in the place;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>b</I>) use any means of communication in the place or cause it to be used;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>c</I>) use any computer system in the place, or cause it to be used, to examine data contained in or available to it;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>d</I>) prepare a document, or cause one to be prepared, based on the data;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>e</I>) use any copying equipment in the place or cause it to be used;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>f</I>) conduct tests or analyses of anything in the place;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>g</I>) take measurements or samples of anything in the place;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>h</I>) take photographs or make recordings or sketches of anything in the place;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>i</I>) remove anything found in the place;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>j</I>) direct any person to put any machinery, vehicle or equipment in the place into operation or to cease operating it; and</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>k</I>) prohibit or limit access to all or part of the place or to anything in the place.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Entry — fishing vessels ordered to port by flag state<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(4) A protection officer may, for a purpose related to verifying compliance with a law related to fisheries of a foreign state, with any conservation or management measures of a fisheries management organization or with an international fisheries treaty or arrangement to which Canada is party, including any conservation, management or enforcement measures taken under the treaty or arrangement, board a foreign fishing vessel that was authorized to enter Canadian fisheries waters under subparagraph 6(<I>a</I>)(iii).</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Powers on entry<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(5) The protection officer may, for the purpose referred to in subsection (4), exercise the powers referred to in subsection (3) to the extent that the exercise of those powers is authorized by the foreign state or is provided for in the measures, treaty or arrangement in question.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Duty to assist<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(6) The owner or person in charge of a place and every person in the place shall give all assistance that is reasonably required to enable a protection officer to perform his or her functions under this section and shall provide any document or information, and access to any data, that is reasonably required for that purpose.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Person accompanying protection officer<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>7.2</B> A protection officer may be accompanied by any other person that the protection officer believes is necessary to help him or her perform his or her functions under this Act.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Stopping and detaining vehicle<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>7.3</B> A protection officer may, for a purpose related to verifying compliance with this Act, direct that any vehicle, including a fishing vessel found within Canadian fisheries waters or the NAFO Regulatory Area, be stopped and moved to another location and may detain it for a reasonable time. The person in charge of the vehicle shall comply with the directions.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Warrant to enter dwelling place<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>7.4</B> (1) If a place is a dwelling place, a protection officer may enter it without the occupant’s consent only under the authority of a warrant issued under subsection (2).</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Authority to issue warrant<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(2) On <I>ex parte</I> application, a justice of the peace may issue a warrant authorizing a protection officer to enter a dwelling place, subject to any conditions specified in the warrant, and authorizing any other person named in the warrant to accompany the protection officer, if the justice is satisfied by information on oath that</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>a</I>) the dwelling place is a place referred to in section 7.1;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>b</I>) entry to the dwelling place is necessary to verify compliance with this Act; and</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>c</I>) entry was refused by the occupant or there are reasonable grounds to believe that entry will be refused by, or that consent to entry cannot be obtained from, the occupant.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Enforcement on high seas for unauthorized fishing in Canadian fisheries waters<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>7.5</B> (1) If a protection officer has reasonable grounds to believe that a fishing vessel of a state party to the Fish Stocks Agreement or of a state that is party to a treaty or arrangement described in paragraph 6(<I>f</I>) has engaged in unauthorized fishing in Canadian fisheries waters and the vessel is in an area of the sea designated under subparagraph 6(<I>e</I>)(ii) or (<I>f</I>)(ii), the officer may, with the consent of that state, take any enforcement action that is consistent with this Act.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Powers not affected in case of pursuit<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(2) Subsection (1) does not affect any powers the protection officer has in the case of a pursuit that began while the vessel was in Canadian fisheries waters.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Search<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>7.6</B> (1) A justice, as defined in section 2 of the <I>Criminal Code</I>, who on <I>ex parte</I> application is satisfied by information on oath that there are reasonable grounds to believe that there is in a place any fish, marine plant or other thing that was obtained by or used in, or that will afford evidence in respect of, a contravention of this Act, may issue a warrant authorizing the protection officer named in the warrant to enter and search the place for the fish, marine plant or other thing, subject to any conditions specified in the warrant.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Search without warrant<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(2) A protection officer may exercise the powers referred to in subsection (1) without a warrant if the conditions for obtaining a warrant exist but, by reason of exigent circumstances, it would not be practical to obtain a warrant.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Search — fishing vessels ordered to port by flag state<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(3) A justice, as defined in section 2 of the <I>Criminal Code</I>, on <I>ex parte</I> application by a protection officer, may issue a warrant authorizing the protection officer named in the warrant to board a foreign fishing vessel that was authorized to enter Canadian fisheries waters under subparagraph 6(<I>a</I>)(iii) and search the vessel, or to enter any other place and search the other place, for any fish, marine plant or other thing, subject to any conditions specified in the warrant, if the justice is satisfied by information on oath that</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>a</I>) there are reasonable grounds to believe that there is in the vessel any fish, marine plant or other thing that was obtained by or used in, or that will afford evidence in respect of, a contravention of a law related to fisheries of a foreign state, any conservation or management measures of a fisheries management organization or an international fisheries treaty or arrangement to which Canada is party, including any conservation, management or enforcement measures taken under the treaty or arrangement, or there is in the other place any such fish, marine plant or other thing and that fish, marine plant or other thing is from the vessel; and</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>b</I>) the vessel’s flag state does not object to the search of the vessel.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Presumption<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(4) The foreign fishing vessel’s flag state is deemed to not object to the search if the protection officer has informed the flag state of his or her intention to apply for the warrant referred to in subsection (3) and the flag state has not communicated its objection within the period prescribed by regulation.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>7.</B> (1) Paragraph 9(<I>b</I>) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>b</I>) any goods aboard a fishing vessel described in paragraph (<I>a</I>) or in any other place, including fish, marine plants, tackle, rigging, apparel, furniture, stores and cargo; or</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes">(2) Paragraph 9(<I>c</I>) of the French version of the Act is replaced by the following:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0"><AltLang xml:lang="fr"><I>c</I>) à la fois le bateau de pêche et les biens visés à l’alinéa <I>b</I>).</AltLang></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes">(3) Section 9 of the Act is renumbered as subsection 9(1) and is amended by adding the following:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Seizure — fishing vessels ordered to port by flag state<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(2) A justice, as defined in section 2 of the <I>Criminal Code</I>, on <I>ex parte</I> application by a protection officer, may issue a warrant authorizing the protection officer named in the warrant to seize any fish, marine plant or other thing in a foreign fishing vessel that was authorized to enter Canadian fisheries waters under subparagraph 6(<I>a</I>)(iii) or in any other place, subject to any conditions specified in the warrant, if the justice is satisfied by information on oath that</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>a</I>) there are reasonable grounds to believe that there is in the vessel any fish, marine plant or other thing that was obtained by or used in, or that will afford evidence in respect of, a contravention of a law related to fisheries of a foreign state, any conservation or management measures of a fisheries management organization or an international fisheries treaty or arrangement to which Canada is party, including any conservation, management or enforcement measures taken under the treaty or arrangement, or there is in the other place any such fish, marine plant or other thing and that fish, marine plant or other thing is from the vessel; and</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>b</I>) the vessel’s flag state does not object to the seizure.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Presumption<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(3) The foreign fishing vessel’s flag state is deemed to not object to the seizure if the protection officer has informed the flag state of his or her intention to apply for the warrant and the flag state has not communicated its objection within the period prescribed by regulation.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Notice<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(4) Before issuing a warrant under subsection (2), the justice may require that notice of the application be given to any person who has an interest in the application in order to allow that person the opportunity to make representations.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>8.</B> Sections 11 to 13 of the Act are replaced by the following:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Disposition<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>11.</B> If any fish, marine plant or other thing that is perishable or susceptible to deterioration is seized under section 9, the protection officer or other person having the custody of the thing may dispose of it in any manner that he or she considers appropriate and any proceeds shall be paid to the Receiver General or deposited in a bank to the credit of the Receiver General.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Return — things seized under subsection 9(1)<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>12.</B> (1) Any fishing vessel or goods seized under subsection 9(1) or the proceeds realized from a sale of the vessel or goods under section 11 shall be returned or paid to the person from whom the fishing vessel or goods were seized if the Minister decides not to institute a prosecution in respect of an offence under this Act and, in any event, shall be so returned or paid on the expiry of three months after the day on which the seizure is made unless before that time proceedings in respect of the offence are instituted.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Return or payment subject to section 16.7<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(2) In any event, the return of the fishing vessel or goods or the payment of the proceeds from the sale of the fishing vessel or goods are subject to section 16.7.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Order to extend period of detention<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(3) A court may, by order, permit the vessel or goods seized under subsection 9(1) or the proceeds realized from a sale of the vessel or goods under section 11 to be detained for any further period that may be specified in the order if the Minister makes a request to that effect before the end of the period of detention in question and if the court is satisfied that it is justified in the circumstances.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Return — things seized under subsection 9(2)<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>12.1</B> (1) Subject to section 16.7, any fish, marine plant or other thing seized under subsection 9(2) or the proceeds realized from a sale of the fish, marine plant or other thing under section 11 shall be returned or paid to the person from whom the fish, marine plant or other thing was seized on the expiry of three months after the day on which the seizure is made unless before that time an application referred to in subsection 16.01(1) is filed.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Order to extend period of detention<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(2) A court may, by order, permit the fish, marine plant or other thing seized under subsection 9(2) or the proceeds realized from a sale of the fish, marine plant or other thing under section 11 to be detained for any further period that may be specified in the order if the Minister makes a request to that effect before the end of the period of detention in question and if the court is satisfied that it is justified in the circumstances.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Redelivery pending proceedings<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>13.</B> If a fishing vessel or goods have been seized under subsection 9(1) and proceedings in respect of an offence under this Act have been instituted, the court or judge may, with the consent of the protection officer who made the seizure, order redelivery of the fishing vessel or goods to the person from whom the fishing vessel or goods were seized on security by bond, with two sureties, in an amount and form satisfactory to the Minister, being given to Her Majesty.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>9.</B> Paragraphs 14(<I>a</I>) to (<I>c</I>) of the Act are replaced by the following:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>a</I>) any fishing vessel seized under paragraph 9(1)(<I>a</I>) by means of or in relation to which the offence was committed, or, if the vessel has been sold, the proceeds of the sale,</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>b</I>) any goods aboard a fishing vessel described in paragraph (<I>a</I>), including fish, marine plants, tackle, rigging, apparel, furniture, stores and cargo, or, if any of the goods have been sold under section 11, the proceeds of the sale,</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>b.1</I>) any goods seized under paragraph 9(1)(<I>b</I>) in any other place, including fish, marine plants, tackle, rigging, apparel, furniture, stores and cargo, by means of or in relation to which the offence was committed, or that were obtained by or used in the commission of the offence, or, if any of the goods have been sold under section 11, the proceeds of the sale, or</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>c</I>) any fishing vessel described in paragraph (<I>a</I>), or the proceeds of the sale of the vessel, and any of the goods described in paragraph (<I>b</I>) or (<I>b.1</I>), or the proceeds of the sale of the goods,</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>10.</B> Subsection 16(1) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Return if no forfeiture ordered<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>16.</B> (1) If a fishing vessel or goods have been seized under subsection 9(1) and proceedings in respect of an offence under this Act have been instituted, but the fishing vessel or goods or any proceeds realized from a sale of the fishing vessel or goods under section 11 are not ordered to be forfeited at the final conclusion of the proceedings, they shall, subject to subsection (2) and to section 16.7, be returned or the proceeds shall be paid to the person from whom the fishing vessel or goods were seized.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>11.</B> The Act is amended by adding the following after section 16:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Forfeiture — seizure under subsection 9(2)<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>16.01</B> (1) A justice, as defined in section 2 of the <I>Criminal Code</I>, on <I>ex parte</I> application by a protection officer, may order the forfeiture to Her Majesty in right of Canada of any fish, marine plant or other thing seized under subsection 9(2) or of the proceeds realized from a sale under section 11 of that fish, marine plant or other thing, if the justice is satisfied by information on oath that</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>a</I>) there are reasonable grounds to believe that the fish, marine plant or other thing was obtained by or used in, or will afford evidence in respect of, a contravention of a law related to fisheries of a foreign state, any conservation or management measures of a fisheries management organization or an international fisheries treaty or arrangement to which Canada is party, including any conservation, management or enforcement measures taken under the treaty or arrangement; and</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>b</I>) the foreign fishing vessel’s flag state does not object to the forfeiture.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Presumption<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(2) The foreign fishing vessel’s flag state is deemed to not object to the forfeiture if the protection officer has informed the flag state of his or her intention to request the forfeiture and the flag state has not communicated its objection within the period prescribed by regulation.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Notice<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(3) Before making the order, the justice may require that notice of the application be given to any person who has an interest in the application in order to allow that person the opportunity to make representations.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Disposal<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(4) Once forfeited, the fish, marine plant or other thing shall be disposed of as the Minister directs.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Return if no forfeiture ordered<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(5) Any fish, marine plant or other thing seized under subsection 9(2) or the proceeds realized from a sale of the fish, marine plant or other thing under section 11 that are not ordered to be forfeited shall, subject to section 16.7, be returned, or the proceeds shall be paid, to the person from whom the fish, marine plant or other thing was seized.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>1999, c. 19. s. 8<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>12.</B> The portion of section 16.1 of the Act before paragraph (<I>b</I>) is replaced by the following:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Protection officer’s powers<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>16.1</B> Any power conferred on a protection officer by or under this Act may be exercised by the officer</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>a</I>) subject to section 16.2 and to any regulation made under subparagraph 6(<I>e</I>)(iii), in respect of a fishing vessel of a state party to the Fish Stocks Agreement that is found in an area of the sea designated under subparagraph 6(<I>e</I>)(ii);</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>1999, c. 19. s. 8<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>13.</B> Section 16.2 of the Act is replaced by the following:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Protection officer’s powers<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>16.2</B> (1) A protection officer may, in an area of the sea designated under subparagraph 6(<I>e</I>)(ii), for a purpose related to verifying compliance with section 5.3 and any regulations made under subparagraph 6(<I>e</I>)(i), board a fishing vessel of a state party to the Fish Stocks Agreement and exercise the powers referred to in subsection 7.1(3).</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Search<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(1.1) If the protection officer has reasonable grounds to believe that the fishing vessel has contravened section 5.3, the officer may, with a warrant issued under section 7.6 or without a warrant in exigent circumstances, search the fishing vessel and exercise the power under subsection 9(1) to seize evidence.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Notice<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(2) If the protection officer has reasonable grounds to believe that the fishing vessel has contravened section 5.3, the officer shall without delay inform the state party to the Fish Stocks Agreement.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Consent<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(3) In addition to the powers referred to in subsections (1) and (1.1), a protection officer may, with the consent of the state party to the Fish Stocks Agreement, exercise any powers referred to in section 16.1. The officer is deemed to have received the consent of the state if the state has not responded within the period prescribed by regulation or has responded but is not fully investigating the alleged contravention.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Forfeiture — treaty or arrangement<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>16.3</B> (1) A justice, as defined in section 2 of the <I>Criminal Code</I>, on <I>ex parte</I> application by a protection officer, may order the forfeiture to Her Majesty in right of Canada of any fish or marine plant detained by a protection officer if the justice is satisfied by information on oath that</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>a</I>) the detention of the fish or marine plant is consistent with an international fisheries treaty or arrangement to which Canada is party, including any conservation, management or enforcement measures taken under the treaty or arrangement;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>b</I>) the forfeiture of the fish or marine plant is consistent with the treaty or arrangement; and</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>c</I>) the foreign fishing vessel’s flag state has not provided the Minister, within the time period required by the treaty or arrangement, with the information required by the treaty or the arrangement to prevent the forfeiture.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Notice<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(2) Before making the order, the justice may require that notice of the application be given to any person who has an interest in the application in order to allow that person the opportunity to make representations.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Disposal<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(3) Once forfeited, the fish or marine plant shall be disposed of as directed by the Minister.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:INFORMATION--><Para TopMargin="10" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">INFORMATION</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Disclosure<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>16.4</B> The Minister may disclose to a foreign fishing vessel’s flag state, to the state of nationality of the foreign fishing vessel’s master or to a coastal state, fisheries management organization, organization of states or international organization information that relates to any of the following:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>a</I>) a refusal to authorize the foreign fishing vessel to enter Canadian fisheries waters;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>b</I>) a suspension, amendment or cancellation of an authorization granted to the foreign fishing vessel;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>c</I>) a change to a decision referred to in paragraph (<I>a</I>) or (<I>b</I>);</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>d</I>) the outcome of any proceeding relating to a decision referred to in any of paragraphs (<I>a</I>) to (<I>c</I>);</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>e</I>) an inspection report in respect of the foreign fishing vessel;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>f</I>) an enforcement action taken by a protection officer in respect of the foreign fishing vessel.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Measures — Canadian fishing vessel<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>16.5</B> The Minister may disclose to a party to the Port State Measures Agreement, coastal state, fisheries management organization or international organization information relating to any measure that is taken under the <I>Fisheries Act</I> in respect of a Canadian fishing vessel in response to a measure that is taken, in respect of that vessel, by another state under the Port State Measures Agreement .</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Canada Border Services Agency<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>16.6</B> For a purpose related to verifying compliance with this Act, the Minister may disclose to the Canada Border Services Agency information relating to the importation of any fish or marine plant.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Sending abroad<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>16.7</B> (1) A justice, as defined in section 2 of the <I>Criminal Code</I>, on <I>ex parte</I> application by a protection officer, may order that anything seized under this Act be sent to a foreign state if the justice is satisfied by information on oath that the foreign state has requested that the thing be sent to it for the purpose of administering or enforcing its laws.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Terms and conditions<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(2) The justice may include in the order any terms and conditions that he or she considers appropriate, including those that are necessary to give effect to the request and those that relate to the preservation and return to Canada of the thing or the protection of the interests of third parties.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Requirement to bring before justice<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(3) The justice may require that the thing be brought before him or her.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Notice<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(4) Before making the order, the justice may require that notice of the application be given to any person who has an interest in the application in order to allow that person the opportunity to make representations.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>1999, c. 19, s. 9<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>14.</B> Paragraph 17(2)(<I>a</I>) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>a</I>) a state party to the Fish Stocks Agreement if the vessel or official, as the case may be, is acting in the performance of their duties in relation to the Fish Stocks Agreement; or</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>1999, c. 19, s. 11<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>15.</B> (1) Subsection 18.01(1) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Proof of offence — Fish Stocks Agreement<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>18.01</B> (1) In a prosecution of a fishing vessel of a state party to the Fish Stocks Agreement or a state that is party to a treaty or arrangement described in paragraph 6(<I>f</I>) or of a fishing vessel without nationality for an offence under this Act, it is sufficient proof of the offence to establish that it was committed by a person on board the vessel, whether or not the person is identified or has been prosecuted for the offence.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>1999, c. 19, s. 11<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes">(2) Subsection 18.01(2) of the English version of the Act is replaced by the following:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Appearance of vessel<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(2) A fishing vessel on which a summons is served shall appear by counsel or agent.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>1999, c. 19, s. 11<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>16.</B> Section 18.02 of the Act is replaced by the following:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Fines<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>18.02</B> If a fishing vessel of a state party to the Fish Stocks Agreement or a state that is party to a treaty or arrangement described in paragraph 6(<I>f</I>) or a fishing vessel without nationality is convicted of an offence under this Act, the amount of the fine imposed on the vessel is a debt due to Her Majesty in right of Canada owed by the person who, at the time the offence was committed, was lawfully entitled to possession of the vessel, whether as owner or as charterer.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Offence and punishment<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>18.03</B> (1) Every person who contravenes subsection 5.6(1) or (2) is guilty of an offence and liable</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>a</I>) on conviction on indictment, to a fine of not more than $500,000; or</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>b</I>) on summary conviction, to a fine of not more than $100,000.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Subsequent offences<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(2) If a person is convicted of an offence under subsection (1) a subsequent time, the amount of the fine for the subsequent offence may be up to double the amount set out in that subsection.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Offence and punishment<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(3) Every person who contravenes subsection 5.6(3) is guilty of an offence and liable</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>a</I>) on conviction on indictment, to a fine of not more than $500,000; or</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>b</I>) on summary conviction, to a fine of not more than $100,000.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Additional fine<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>18.04</B> If a person is convicted of an offence under this Act and the court is satisfied that, as a result of committing the offence, financial benefits accrued to the person, the court may, despite the maximum amount of any fine that may otherwise be imposed under this Act, order the person to pay an additional fine in an amount equal to the court’s estimation of those benefits.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>1999, c. 19, s. 12<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>17.</B> Paragraph 18.1(<I>a.1</I>) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>a.1</I>) in an area of the sea designated under subparagraph 6(<I>e</I>)(ii) on board or by means of a fishing vessel of a state party to the Fish Stocks Agreement or of a fishing vessel without nationality;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>1994, c. 14, s. 7<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>18.</B> (1) The portion of subsection 18.2(1) of the French version of the Act before paragraph (<I>a</I>) is replaced by the following:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Exercice des pouvoirs d’arrestation, d’entrée, etc.<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><AltLang xml:lang="fr"><B>18.2</B> (1) Les pouvoirs — arrestation, entrée, perquisition, saisie et autres — pouvant être exercés au Canada à l’égard d’un fait visé à l’article 18.1 peuvent l’être à cet égard et dans les circonstances mentionnées à cet article :</AltLang></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>1994, c. 14, s. 7<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes">(2) Subsection 18.2(2) of the French version of the Act is replaced by the following:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Pouvoir des tribunaux<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><AltLang xml:lang="fr">(2) Un juge de paix ou un juge a compétence pour autoriser les mesures d’enquête et autres mesures accessoires à l’égard d’une infraction visée à l’article 18.1, notamment en matière d’arrestation, d’entrée, de perquisition et de saisie, comme si l’infraction avait été perpétrée dans son ressort.</AltLang></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:COMING INTO FORCE--><Para TopMargin="10" Bold="Yes" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">COMING INTO FORCE</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Order in council<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>19.</B> This Act comes into force on a day to be fixed by order of the Governor in Council.</Para></Block><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="BPT_ImprintE"><br/><br/>Published under authority of the Senate of Canada</Para></Block><Block Align="Yes" LineCnt="N"><Para NoLineBreak="Yes" NoHtml="Yes" Leading="0" Size="0" TopMargin="0" BottomMargin="0"></Para></Block></Bill_Part></Bill>
