<?xml version="1.0"?>
<Bill RHead_reign="62-63-64 Eliz. II" RHead_ParlYear="2013-2014-2015" DocumentTitle="BILL S-7" Bill_No="S-7" Document_No="90746" xml:lang="EN" Bill_Type="Non-amending" Stage_Name="Assented-to" Reprint="No" xml:space="preserve" ChapterNo_E="C. 29" ChapterNo_F="ch. 29" Bill-Origin="senate"><Bill_Part Part_Type="Cover" CountLines="No"><Block><Para TopMargin="24" Size="9" Leading="10" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0" TextAlign="Center">Second Session, Forty-first Parliament,</Para></Block><Block><Para Size="9" Leading="10" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0" TextAlign="Center">62-63-64 Elizabeth II, 2013-2014-2015</Para></Block><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="COV@StatutesTitle">STATUTES OF CANADA 2015<br/>CHAPTER 29</Para></Block><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="CovLongTitle">An Act to amend the Immigration and Refugee Protection Act, the Civil Marriage Act and the Criminal Code and to make consequential amendments to other Acts</Para></Block><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="COV_StageLine"></Para></Block><Block><Para BottomMargin="14" Size="11" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0" Bold="Yes" TextAlign="Center">ASSENTED TO</Para></Block><Block><Para Size="8" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0" TextAlign="Center">18th JUNE, 2015</Para></Block><Block><Para TopMargin="4" Size="8" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0" TextAlign="Center">BILL S-7</Para></Block><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="COV_StageLine"></Para></Block></Bill_Part><Bill_Part CountLines="No" Part_Type="InsideCover"><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="BPT_InsideCoverE">Available on the Parliament of Canada Web Site at the following address:<br/><B>http://www.parl.gc.ca</B></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><Para TopMargin="108" BottomMargin="4" Size="10" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">SUMMARY</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" Size="8" Leading="9" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">Part 1 amends the <I>Immigration and Refugee Protection Act</I> to specify that a permanent resident or foreign national is inadmissible on grounds of practising polygamy in Canada.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" Size="8" Leading="9" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">Part 2 amends the <I>Civil Marriage Act</I> to provide for the legal requirements for a free and enlightened consent to marriage and for any previous marriage to be dissolved or declared null before a new marriage is contracted. Those requirements are currently provided for in the <I>Federal Law—Civil Law Harmonization Act, No. 1</I> only in respect of Quebec and under the common law in the other provinces. It also amends the <I>Civil Marriage Act</I> to provide for the requirement of a minimum age of 16 years for marriage. This requirement is currently provided for in the <I>Federal Law—Civil Law Harmonization Act, No. 1</I> only in respect of Quebec.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" Size="8" Leading="9" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">Part 3 amends the <I>Criminal Code</I> to</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" Size="8" Leading="9" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">(<I>a</I>) clarify that it is an offence for an officiant to knowingly solemnize a marriage in contravention of federal law;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" Size="8" Leading="9" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">(<I>b</I>) provide that it is an offence to celebrate, aid or participate in a marriage rite or ceremony knowing that one of the persons being married is doing so against their will or is under the age of 16 years;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" Size="8" Leading="9" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">(<I>c</I>) provide that it is an offence to remove a child from Canada with the intention that an act be committed outside Canada that, if it were committed in Canada, would constitute the offence of celebrating, aiding or participating in a marriage rite or ceremony knowing that the child is doing so against their will or is under the age of 16 years;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" Size="8" Leading="9" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">(<I>d</I>) provide that a judge may order a person to enter into a recognizance with conditions to keep the peace and be of good behaviour for the purpose of preventing the person from committing an offence relating to the marriage of a person against their will or the marriage of a person under the age of 16 years or relating to the removal of a child from Canada with the intention of committing an act that, if it were committed in Canada, would be such an offence; and</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" Size="8" Leading="9" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">(<I>e</I>) 	provide that the defence of provocation is restricted to circumstances in which the victim engaged in conduct that would constitute an indictable offence under the <I>Criminal Code</I> that is punishable by five years or more in prison.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" Size="8" Leading="9" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">Finally, the enactment also makes consequential amendments to other Acts.</Para></Block></Bill_Part><Bill_Part Part_Type="MainText" CountLines="No" RunningHead_E=" Immigration and Refugee Protection, Civil Marriage and Criminal Code"><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="MAIN@RoyalAssentTitle">62-63-64 ELIZABETH II</Para></Block><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="MAIN@RoyalAssentTitle">——————</Para></Block><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="MAIN@RoyalAssentTitle">CHAPTER 29</Para></Block><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="LongTitleAssent">An Act to amend the Immigration and Refugee Protection Act, the Civil Marriage Act and the Criminal Code and to make consequential amendments to other Acts</Para></Block><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="MAIN@RoyalAssentDate">[<I>Assented to 18th June, 2015</I>]</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">Her Majesty, by and with the advice and consent of the Senate and House of Commons of Canada, enacts as follows:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:SHORT TITLE--><Para TopMargin="10" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">SHORT TITLE</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Short title<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>1.</B> This Act may be cited as the <I>Zero Tolerance for Barbaric Cultural Practices Act</I>.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><Para TopMargin="10" Bold="Yes" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">PART 1</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:IMMIGRATION AND REFUGEE PROTECTION ACT--><MarginalNote>2001, c. 27<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" Bold="Yes" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">IMMIGRATION AND REFUGEE PROTECTION ACT</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:Amendment to the Act--><Para TopMargin="5" Bold="Yes" SmallCaps="Yes" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">Amendment to the Act</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>2.</B> The <I>Immigration and Refugee Protection Act</I> is amended by adding the following after section 41:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Polygamy<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>41.1</B> (1) A permanent resident or a foreign national is inadmissible on grounds of practising polygamy if they are or will be practising polygamy with a person who is or will be physically present in Canada at the same time as the permanent resident or foreign national.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Interpretation<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(2) For the purposes of subsection (1), polygamy shall be interpreted in a manner consistent with paragraph 293(1)(<I>a</I>) of the <I>Criminal Code</I>.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:Coming into Force--><Para TopMargin="10" Bold="Yes" SmallCaps="Yes" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">Coming into Force</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Order in council<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>3.</B> This Part comes into force on a day to be fixed by order of the Governor in Council.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><Para TopMargin="10" Bold="Yes" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">PART 2</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:CIVIL MARRIAGE ACT--><MarginalNote>2005, c. 33<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" Bold="Yes" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">CIVIL MARRIAGE ACT</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>4.</B> The <I>Civil Marriage Act</I> is amended by adding the following after section 2:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Consent required<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>2.1</B> Marriage requires the free and enlightened consent of two persons to be the spouse of each other.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Minimum age<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>2.2</B> No person who is under the age of 16 years may contract marriage.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Previous marriage<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>2.3</B> No person may contract a new marriage until every previous marriage has been dissolved by death or by divorce or declared null by a court order.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>2013, c. 30, s. 3<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>5.</B> Subsection 5(3) of the English version of the Act is replaced by the following:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Order dissolving marriage<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(3) Any court order, made in Canada or elsewhere before the coming into force of this subsection, that declares the marriage to be null or that grants a divorce to the spouses dissolves the marriage, for the purposes of Canadian law, as of the day on which the order takes effect.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><Para TopMargin="10" Bold="Yes" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">PART 3</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:CRIMINAL CODE--><MarginalNote>R.S., c. C-46<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" Bold="Yes" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">CRIMINAL CODE</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:Amendments to the Act--><Para TopMargin="5" Bold="Yes" SmallCaps="Yes" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">Amendments to the Act</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>2008, c. 6, s. 13(1)<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>6.</B> (1) Subsection 150.1(2.1) of the <I>Criminal Code</I> is replaced by the following:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Exception — complainant aged 14 or 15<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(2.1) If an accused is charged with an offence under section 151 or 152, subsection 173(2) or section 271 in respect of a complainant who is 14 years of age or more but under the age of 16 years, it is a defence that the complainant consented to the activity that forms the subject-matter of the charge if the accused</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>a</I>) is less than five years older than the complainant; and </Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>b</I>) is not in a position of trust or authority towards the complainant, is not a person with whom the complainant is in a relationship of dependency and is not in a relationship with the complainant that is exploitative of the complainant.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes">(2) Section 150.1 of the Act is amended by adding the following after subsection (2.2):</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Exception for transitional purposes<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(2.3) If, immediately before the day on which this subsection comes into force, the accused referred to in subsection (2.1) is married to the complainant, it is a defence that the complainant consented to the activity that forms the subject-matter of the charge.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>7.</B> (1) Subsection 232(2) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>What is provocation<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(2) Conduct of the victim that would constitute an indictable offence under this Act that is punishable by five or more years of imprisonment and that is of such a nature as to be sufficient to deprive an ordinary person of the power of self-control is provocation for the purposes of this section, if the accused acted on it on the sudden and before there was time for their passion to cool.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes">(2) Paragraph 232(3)(<I>a</I>) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>a</I>) whether the conduct of the victim amounted to provocation under subsection (2), and</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>8.</B> Subsection 273.3(1) of the Act is amended by striking out “or” at the end of paragraph (<I>b</I>), by adding “or” at the end of paragraph (<I>c</I>) and by adding the following after paragraph (<I>c</I>):</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>d</I>) under the age of 18 years, with the intention that an act be committed outside Canada that, if it were committed in Canada, would be an offence against section 293.1 in respect of that person or under the age of 16 years, with the intention that an act be committed outside Canada that, if it were committed in Canada, would be an offence against section 293.2 in respect of that person.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>9.</B> The Act is amended by adding the following after section 293:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Forced marriage<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>293.1</B> Everyone who celebrates, aids or participates in a marriage rite or ceremony knowing that one of the persons being married is marrying against their will is guilty of an indictable offence and liable to imprisonment for a term not exceeding five years.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Marriage under age of 16 years<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>293.2</B> Everyone who celebrates, aids or participates in a marriage rite or ceremony knowing that one of the persons being married is under the age of 16 years is guilty of an indictable offence and liable to imprisonment for a term not exceeding five years.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>10.</B> Section 295 of the Act is replaced by the following:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Marriage contrary to law<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>295.</B> Everyone who, being lawfully authorized to solemnize marriage, knowingly solemnizes a marriage in contravention of federal law or the laws of the province in which the marriage is solemnized is guilty of an indictable offence and liable to imprisonment for a term not exceeding two years.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>11.</B> The Act is amended by adding the following after section 810.01:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Fear of forced marriage or marriage under age of 16 years<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>810.02</B> (1) A person who fears on reasonable grounds that another person will commit an offence under paragraph 273.3(1)(<I>d</I>) or section 293.1 or 293.2 may lay an information before a provincial court judge.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Appearances<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(2) The judge who receives the information may cause the parties to appear before a provincial court judge.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Adjudication<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(3) If the provincial court judge before whom the parties appear is satisfied by the evidence adduced that the informant has reasonable grounds for the fear, the judge may order that the defendant enter into a recognizance to keep the peace and be of good behaviour for a period of not more than 12 months.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Duration extended<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(4) However, if the provincial court judge is also satisfied that the defendant was convicted previously of an offence referred to in subsection (1), the judge may order that the defendant enter into the recognizance for a period of not more than two years.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Refusal to enter into recognizance<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(5) The provincial court judge may commit the defendant to prison for a term not exceeding 12 months if the defendant fails or refuses to enter into the recognizance.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Conditions in recognizance<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(6) The provincial court judge may add any reasonable conditions to the recognizance that the judge considers desirable to secure the good conduct of the defendant, including conditions that</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>a</I>) prohibit the defendant from making agreements or arrangements for the marriage, whether in or outside Canada, of the person in respect of whom it is feared that the offence will be committed;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>b</I>) prohibit the defendant from taking steps to cause the person in respect of whom it is feared that the offence will be committed to leave the jurisdiction of the court;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>c</I>) require the defendant to deposit, in the specified manner, any passport or any other travel document that is in their possession or control, whether or not such passport or document is in their name or in the name of any other specified person;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>d</I>) prohibit the defendant from communicating, directly or indirectly, with any specified person, or refrain from going to any specified place, except in accordance with any specified conditions that the judge considers necessary;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>e</I>) require the defendant to participate in a treatment program, including a family violence counselling program;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>f</I>) require the defendant to remain within a specified geographic area unless written permission to leave that area is obtained from the provincial court judge; and</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>g</I>) require the defendant to return to and remain at their place of residence at specified times.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Conditions — firearms<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(7) The provincial court judge shall consider whether it is desirable, in the interests of the defendant’s safety or that of any other person, to prohibit the defendant from possessing any firearm, cross-bow, prohibited weapon, restricted weapon, prohibited device, ammunition, prohibited ammunition or explosive substance, or all of those things. If the judge decides that it is desirable to do so, the judge shall add that condition to the recognizance and specify the period during which the condition applies.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Surrender, etc.<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(8) If the provincial court judge adds a condition described in subsection (7) to a recognizance, the judge shall specify in the recognizance how the things referred to in that subsection that are in the defendant’s possession are to be surrendered, disposed of, detained, stored or dealt with and how the authorizations, licences and registration certificates that are held by the defendant are to be surrendered.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Variance of conditions<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(9) A provincial court judge may, on application of the informant or the defendant, vary the conditions fixed in the recognizance.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>2001, c. 41, s. 23<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>12.</B> The portion of section 811 of the Act before paragraph (<I>a</I>) is replaced by the following:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Breach of recognizance<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>811.</B> A person bound by a recognizance under section 83.3, 810, 810.01, 810.02, 810.1 or 810.2 who commits a breach of the recognizance is guilty of</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:Consequential Amendments--><Para TopMargin="10" Bold="Yes" SmallCaps="Yes" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">Consequential Amendments</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:Prisons and Reformatories Act--><MarginalNote>R.S., c. P-20<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" Bold="Yes" Italic="Yes" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">Prisons and Reformatories Act</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>1997, c. 17, s. 39(2)<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>13.</B> The portion of the definition “prisoner” in subsection 2(1) of the <I>Prisons and Reformatories Act</I> after paragraph (<I>b</I>) is replaced by the following:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0">who is confined in a prison pursuant to a sentence for an offence under a provision of an Act of Parliament or any of its regulations, or pursuant to a committal for failure or refusal to enter into a recognizance under section 810, 810.02, 810.1 or 810.2 of the <I>Criminal Code;</I></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:Youth Criminal Justice Act--><MarginalNote>2002, c. 1<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="10" Bold="Yes" Italic="Yes" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">Youth Criminal Justice Act</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>14.</B> Subsection 14(2) of the <I>Youth Criminal Justice Act</I> is replaced by the following:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Orders<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(2) A youth justice court has jurisdiction to make orders against a young person under sections 810 (recognizance — fear of injury or damage), 810.01 (recognizance — fear of criminal organization offence), 810.02 (recognizance — fear of forced marriage or marriage under age of 16 years) and 810.2 (recognizance — fear of serious personal injury offence) of the <I>Criminal Code</I>. If the young person fails or refuses to enter into a recognizance referred to in any of those sections, the court may impose any one of the sanctions set out in subsection 42(2) (youth sentence) except that, in the case of an order under paragraph 42(2)(<I>n</I>) (custody and supervision order), it shall not exceed 30 days.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>15.</B> Paragraph 142(1)(<I>a</I>) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>a</I>) in respect of an order under section 810 (recognizance — fear of injury or damage), 810.01 (recognizance — fear of criminal organization offence), 810.02 (recognizance — fear of forced marriage or marriage under age of 16 years) or 810.2 (recognizance — fear of serious personal injury offence) of that Act or an offence under section 811 (breach of recognizance) of that Act;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:Coming into Force--><Para TopMargin="10" Bold="Yes" SmallCaps="Yes" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">Coming into Force</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Order in council<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>16.</B> This Part comes into force on a day to be fixed by order of the Governor in Council.</Para></Block><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="BPT_ImprintE"><br/><br/>Published under authority of the Senate of Canada</Para></Block><Block Align="Yes" LineCnt="N"><Para NoLineBreak="Yes" NoHtml="Yes" Leading="0" Size="0" TopMargin="0" BottomMargin="0"></Para></Block></Bill_Part></Bill>
