<?xml version="1.0"?>
<Bill RHead_reign="53 Eliz. II" RHead_ParlYear="2004" DocumentTitle="BILL C-19" Bill_No="C-19" Document_No="90287" xml:lang="EN" Bill_Type="Non-amending" Stage_Name="First-Reading-House" Reprint="No" xml:space="preserve" ChapterNo_E="C. " ChapterNo_F="ch. " Bill-Origin="commons"><Bill_Part Part_Type="Cover" CountLines="No"><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="CovBillNo">C-19</Para></Block><Block><Para TopMargin="24" Size="9" Leading="10" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0" TextAlign="Center">First Session, Thirty-eighth Parliament,</Para></Block><Block><Para Size="9" Leading="10" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0" TextAlign="Center">53 Elizabeth II, 2004</Para></Block><Block><Para TopMargin="48" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0" Bold="Yes" TextAlign="Center">HOUSE OF COMMONS OF CANADA</Para></Block><Block><Para TopMargin="42" Size="18" Leading="20" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0" Bold="Yes" TextAlign="Center">BILL C-19</Para></Block><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="CovLongTitle">An Act to amend the Competition Act and to make consequential amendments to other Acts</Para></Block><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="COV_StageLine"></Para></Block><Block><Para Size="9" AllCaps="Yes" Hyphenate="OFF">first reading, November 2, 2004</Para></Block><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="COV_StageLine"></Para></Block><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="Cover_Sponsors">THE MINISTER OF INDUSTRY</Para></Block><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="Cover_DocNo">90287</Para></Block></Bill_Part><Bill_Part CountLines="No" Part_Type="InsideCover"><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="BPT_InsideCoverE">Also available on the Parliament of Canada Web Site at the following address:<br/><B>http://www.parl.gc.ca</B></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><Para TopMargin="108" BottomMargin="4" Size="10" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">SUMMARY</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" Size="8" Leading="9" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">This enactment amends the <I>Competition Act</I> and includes the introduction of an administrative monetary penalty in respect of cases of abuse of dominant position, an increase in the amount of administrative monetary penalties in respect of deceptive marketing cases and the repeal of all airline industry specific provisions and criminal provisions dealing with price discrimination, predatory pricing, discriminatory promotional allowances and geographic price discrimination. This enactment also provides that the court may make an order in respect of cases of false or misleading representations to require the person who engaged in the reviewable conduct to compensate persons affected by the conduct and issue an interim injunction order to freeze assets where the Commissioner of Competition intends to ask for that order. This enactment also provides for consequential amendments to other Acts.</Para></Block></Bill_Part><Bill_Part Part_Type="MainText" CountLines="Yes" RunningHead_E="Competition"><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="MainText_DocNo">90287</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes"><Para Style="Session_Reign">1st Session, 38th Parliament,</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes"><Para Style="Session_Reign">53 Elizabeth II, 2004</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes"><Para Style="MainBillOrigin">house of commons of canada</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes"><Para Bold="Yes" Style="MAIN@BillNo_Title">BILL C-19</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes"><Para Style="MAIN@ti;04">An Act to amend the Competition Act and to make consequential amendments to other Acts</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">Her Majesty, by and with the advice and consent of the Senate and House of Commons of Canada, enacts as follows:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:AMENDMENTS TO THE COMPETITION ACT--><MarginalNote>R.S. , c. C-34; c. 19 (2nd Supp.), s. 19<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="10" Bold="Yes" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">AMENDMENTS TO THE COMPETITION ACT</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>2000, c. 15, s. 11<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>1.</B> Section 4.1 of the <I>Competition Act</I> is repealed.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>1999, c. 31, s. 50(F)<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>2.</B> Sections 50 and 51 of the Act are repealed.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>1999, c. 2, s. 19<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>3.</B> The portion of section 66 of the Act before paragraph (<I>a</I>) is replaced by the following:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Contravention of Part VII.1 or VIII order<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>66.</B> Every person who contravenes an order made under Part VII.1, except paragraph 74.1(1)(<I>c</I>) <change>and subsection 74.1(1.1)</change>, or under Part VIII, <change>except subsection 79(3.1)</change>, is guilty of an offence and liable</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>2002, c. 8, par. 198(c), c. 16, s. 8<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>4.</B> Subsection 73(1) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Jurisdiction of Federal Court<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>73.</B> (1) Subject to this section, the Attorney General of Canada may institute and conduct any prosecution or other proceedings under section 34, any of sections 45 to <change>49</change> and section 61 or, where the proceedings are on indictment, under section 52, 52.1, 53, 55, 55.1 or 66, in the Federal Court, and for the purposes of the prosecution or other proceedings, the Federal Court has all the powers and jurisdiction of a superior court of criminal jurisdiction under the <I>Criminal Code</I> and under this Act.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>1999, c. 2, s. 22<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B></B> (1) The portion of subsection 74.1(1) of the French version of the Act before paragraph (<I>a</I>) is replaced by the following:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Décision et ordonnance<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><AltLang xml:lang="fr"><B>74.1</B> (1) Le tribunal qui conclut, à la <change>suite d’une</change> demande du commissaire, qu’une personne a ou a eu un comportement susceptible d’examen <change>visé par</change> la présente partie peut ordonner à celle-ci :</AltLang></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>1999, c. 2, s. 22<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes">(2) Subparagraphs 74.1(1)(<I>c</I>)(i) and (ii) of the Act are replaced by the following:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="4" FirstLineIndent="0">(i) in the case of an individual, <change>$750,000</change> and, for each subsequent order, <change>$1,000,000</change>, or</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="4" FirstLineIndent="0">(ii) in the case of a corporation, <change>$10,000,000</change> and, for each subsequent order, <change>$15,000,000</change>.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes">(3) Section 74.1 of the Act is amended by adding the following after subsection (1):</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Order<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><change>(1.1) Where the court determines that a person is engaging in or has engaged in reviewable conduct under paragraph 74.01(1)(<I>a</I>), the court may also order the person to pay an amount, not exceeding the total of the amounts paid for the products that were the object of the conduct, to be distributed among the persons to whom the products were sold — not including those persons who bought the products for resale or distribution — in any manner and on any terms that the court considers appropriate. The court may specify in the order any terms that it considers necessary to implement its decision, including</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0"><change>(<I>a</I>) specifying how the payment is to be administered;</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0"><change>(<I>b</I>) appointing an administrator to administer the payment and specifying the terms of administration;</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0"><change>(<I>c</I>) requiring the person against whom the order is made to pay the administrative costs related to the payment as well as the fees to be paid to an administrator;</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0"><change>(<I>d</I>) requiring that potential claimants be notified in the time and manner specified by the court;</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0"><change>(<I>e</I>) specifying the time and manner for making claims; and</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0"><change>(<I>f</I>) specifying the conditions for the admissibility of claimants.</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Not-for-profit organization<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><change>(1.2) The court may also designate in the order a not-for-profit organization in Canada that benefits persons who have been affected or are likely to be affected by reviewable conduct under this Part — or any other person or organization that the court considers appropriate in the circumstances — to receive any or all of the amount of the payment that remains unclaimed or undistributed in the manner and on the terms set out in the order.</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Variation of order<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><change>(1.3) The court may vary the order on application by the Commissioner or the person against whom the order was made.</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>1999, c. 2, s. 22<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes">(4) Subsections 74.1(3) and (4) of the Act are replaced by the following:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Saving<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(3) No order may be made against a person under paragraph (1)(<I>b</I>) or (<I>c</I>) <change>or subsection (1.1)</change> where the person establishes that the person exercised due diligence to prevent the reviewable conduct from occurring.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Purpose of order<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(4) The terms of an order made against a person under paragraph (1)(<I>b</I>) or (<I>c</I>) <change>or subsection (1.1)</change> shall be determined with a view to promoting conduct by that person that is in conformity with the purposes of this Part and not with a view to punishment.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>1999, c. 2, s. 22<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes">(5) Subsection 74.1(5) of the Act is amended by striking out the word “and” at the end of paragraph (<I>g</I>) and by replacing paragraph (<I>h</I>) with the following:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>h</I>) <change>the gross revenue from sales affected by the conduct</change>;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0"><change>(<I>i</I>) the financial position of the person against whom the order is made;</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0"><change>(<I>j</I>) any decision of the court in relation to an application for an order under subsection (1.1);</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0"><change>(<I>k</I>) whether any restitution has been made voluntarily; and</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0"><change>(<I>l</I>)</change> any other relevant factor.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>6.</B> The Act is amended by adding the following after section 74.11:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Interim injunction<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><change><B>74.111</B> (1) Where a court finds, on application by the Commissioner, a strong <I>prima facie</I> case that a person is engaging in or has engaged in reviewable conduct under paragraph 74.01(1)(<I>a</I>) and the court is satisfied that the person, being the owner or the person having possession or control of articles within the jurisdiction of the court, is disposing of or is likely to dispose of those articles by any means, the court may issue an interim injunction forbidding the owner or any person having possession or control of the articles from disposing of or otherwise dealing with the articles other than in the manner and on the terms specified in the injunction.</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Statement to be included <br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><change>(2) Any application for an injunction under subsection (1) shall include a statement that the Commissioner has applied, or intends to apply, for an order under subsection 74.1(1.1).</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Where court shall not issue injunction<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><change>(3) The court shall not issue an injunction where the person in respect of whom the injunction is sought establishes that the disposal of the articles will not render an order under subsection 74.1(1.1) unenforceable.</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Duration<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><change>(4) Subject to subsection (7), the injunction has effect, or may be extended on application by the Commissioner, for any period that the court considers necessary and sufficient to meet the circumstances of the case.</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Notice of application by Commissioner<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><change>(5) Subject to subsection (6), at least forty-eight hours’ notice of an application referred to in subsection (1) or (4) shall be given by or on behalf of the Commissioner to the person in respect of whom the injunction or extension is sought.</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote><I>Ex parte</I> application<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><change>(6) The court may proceed <I>ex parte</I> with an application made under subsection (1) where it is satisfied that subsection (5) cannot reasonably be complied with, where the urgency of the situation is such that service of the notice in accordance with subsection (5) would not be in the public interest or where service of the notice might defeat the purpose of the injunction.</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Duration of <I>ex parte</I> injunction <br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><change>(7) An injunction issued <I>ex parte</I> has effect for the period that is specified in it, not exceeding seven days, unless, on further application made on notice as provided in subsection (5), the court extends the injunction for any additional period that it considers necessary and sufficient.</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Submissions to set aside<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><change>(8) On application of the person against whom an <I>ex parte</I> injunction is made, the court may make an order setting aside the injunction or varying it subject to any conditions that it considers appropriate if the person establishes that the disposal of the articles will not render an order under subsection 74.1(1.1) unenforceable.</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Notice of application<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><change>(9) A person who makes an application under subsection (8) shall give the Commissioner forty-eight hours written notice of the application.</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Duty of Commissioner<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><change>(10) Where an injunction issued under this section is in effect, the Commissioner shall proceed as expeditiously as possible to complete the inquiry under section 10 arising out of the conduct in respect of which the injunction was issued.</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Definition of “dispose”<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><change>(11) For the purposes of this section, “dispose” includes removing from the jurisdiction of the court, depleting the value of or disposing of by lease.</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>2000, c. 15, s. 13(2)<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>7.</B> (1) Subsection 78(1) of the Act is amended by adding the word “and” at the end of paragraph (<I>h</I>) and by repealing paragraphs (<I>j</I>) and (<I>k</I>).</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>2000, c. 15, s. 13(3)<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes">(2) Subsection 78(2) of the Act is repealed.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>2002, c. 16, s. 11.4<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>8.</B> Subsections 79(3.1) to (3.3) of the Act are replaced by the following:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Administrative monetary penalty<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(3.1) Where the Tribunal makes an order against a <change>person</change> under subsection (1) or (2), it may also order <change>them</change> to pay, in <change>any</change> manner <change>that</change> the Tribunal may specify, an administrative monetary penalty in an amount not greater than <change>$10,000,000 and, for each subsequent order under either of those subsections, an amount not greater than</change> $15,000,000.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Aggravating or mitigating factors<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(3.2) In determining the amount of an administrative monetary penalty, the Tribunal shall take into account the following:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>a</I>) the frequency and duration of the practice;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>b</I>) injury to competition in the relevant market;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>c</I>) the history of compliance with this Act by the <change>person against whom the order is made</change>;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>d</I>) <change>the gross revenue from sales affected by the practice;</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>e</I>) <change>any actual or anticipated profits generated by the practice</change>;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0"><change>(<I>f</I>)</change> <change>the financial position of the person against whom the order is made</change>; and</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0"><change>(<I>g</I></change>) any other relevant factor.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote> Purpose of order<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(3.3) The purpose of an order <change>made against a person</change> under subsection (3.1) is to promote practices <change>by that person</change> that are in conformity with <change>the purposes of</change> this section <change>and</change> not to punish <change>that person</change>.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>2002, c. 16, s. 11.5<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>9.</B> Section 79.1 of the English version of the Act is replaced by the following:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Unpaid monetary penalty<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>79.1</B> The amount of an administrative monetary penalty imposed on <change>a person</change> under subsection 79(3.1) is a debt due to Her Majesty in right of Canada and may be recovered as such from that <change>person</change> in a court of competent jurisdiction.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>2000, c. 15, s. 15; 2002, c. 16, s. 13.1<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>10.</B> Section 104.1 of the Act is repealed.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>2002, c. 16, s. 14<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>11.</B> Subsection 105(1) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Consent agreement<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>105.</B> (1) The Commissioner and a person in respect of whom the Commissioner has applied or may apply for an order under this Part, other than an interim order under section 103.3, may sign a consent agreement.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>2002, c. 16, s. 14<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>12.</B> The portion of subsection 106(1) of the Act before paragraph (<I>a</I>) is replaced by the following:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Rescission or variation of consent agreement or order<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>106.</B> (1) The Tribunal may rescind or vary a consent agreement or an order made under this Part other than an order under section 103.3 or a consent agreement under section 106.1, on application by the Commissioner or the person who consented to the agreement, or the person against whom the order was made, if the Tribunal finds that</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:CONSEQUENTIAL AMENDMENTS--><Para TopMargin="10" Bold="Yes" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">CONSEQUENTIAL AMENDMENTS</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:Competition Tribunal Act--><MarginalNote>R.S., c. 19 (2nd Supp.)<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" Bold="Yes" SmallCaps="Yes" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">Competition Tribunal Act</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>2002, c. 16, s. 19<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>13.</B> Subsection 11(1) of the <I>Competition Tribunal Act</I> is replaced by the following:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Hearing of applications<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>11.</B> (1) The Chairman of the Tribunal, sitting alone, or a judicial member designated by the Chairman, sitting alone, may hear and dispose of applications under <change>section 74.111</change>, subsection 100(1) <change>or</change> section 103.1 or 103.3 of the <I>Competition Act</I> and any related matters.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:Public Service Modernization Act--><MarginalNote>2003, c. 22<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="10" Bold="Yes" SmallCaps="Yes" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">Public Service Modernization Act</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>14.</B> Paragraph 224(<I>z.18</I>) of the <I>Public Service Modernization Act</I> is repealed.</Para></Block><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="BPT_ImprintE">Published under authority of the Speaker of the House of Commons<br/>Available from:<br/>Publishing and Depository Services<br/>Public Works and Government Services Canada<br/>Ottawa, Ontario K1A 0S5<br/>Telephone: 613-941-5995 or 1-800-635-7943<br/>Fax: 613-954-5779 or 1-800-565-7757<br/>publications@tpsgc-pwgsc.gc.ca<br/>http://publications.gc.ca</Para></Block><Block Align="Yes" LineCnt="N"><Para NoLineBreak="Yes" NoHtml="Yes" Leading="0" Size="0" TopMargin="0" BottomMargin="0"></Para></Block></Bill_Part></Bill>
