<?xml version="1.0"?>
<Bill RHead_reign="53-54 Eliz. II" RHead_ParlYear="2004-2005" DocumentTitle="BILL C-28" Bill_No="C-28" Document_No="90295" xml:lang="EN" Bill_Type="Non-amending" Stage_Name="Assented-to" Reprint="No" xml:space="preserve" ChapterNo_E="C. 42" ChapterNo_F="ch. 42" Bill-Origin="commons"><Bill_Part Part_Type="Cover" CountLines="No"><Block><Para TopMargin="24" Size="9" Leading="10" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0" TextAlign="Center">First Session, Thirty-eighth Parliament,</Para></Block><Block><Para Size="9" Leading="10" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0" TextAlign="Center">53-54 Elizabeth II, 2004-2005</Para></Block><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="COV@StatutesTitle">STATUTES OF CANADA 2005<br/>CHAPTER 42</Para></Block><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="CovLongTitle">An Act to amend the Food and Drugs Act</Para></Block><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="COV_StageLine"></Para></Block><Block><Para BottomMargin="14" Size="11" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0" Bold="Yes" TextAlign="Center">ASSENTED TO</Para></Block><Block><Para Size="8" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0" TextAlign="Center">25th NOVEMBER, 2005</Para></Block><Block><Para TopMargin="4" Size="8" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0" TextAlign="Center">BILL C-28</Para></Block><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="COV_StageLine"></Para></Block></Bill_Part><Bill_Part CountLines="No" Part_Type="InsideCover"><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="BPT_InsideCoverE">Also available on the Parliament of Canada Web Site at the following address:<br/><B>http://www.parl.gc.ca</B></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><Para TopMargin="108" BottomMargin="4" Size="10" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">SUMMARY</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" Size="8" Leading="9" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">This enactment would amend the <I>Food and Drugs Act</I> to provide the Minister of Health with the authority to issue interim marketing authorizations for foods that contain certain substances at specified levels, and to exempt the foods from the applicable requirements of that Act and its regulations relating to the sale of those foods.</Para></Block></Bill_Part><Bill_Part Part_Type="MainText" CountLines="No" RunningHead_E="Food and Drugs"><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="MAIN@RoyalAssentTitle">53-54 ELIZABETH II</Para></Block><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="MAIN@RoyalAssentTitle">——————</Para></Block><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="MAIN@RoyalAssentTitle">CHAPTER 42</Para></Block><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="LongTitleAssent">An Act to amend the Food and Drugs Act</Para></Block><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="MAIN@RoyalAssentDate">[<I>Assented to 25th November, 2005</I>]</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>R.S., c. F-27<br/></MarginalNote><Para LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">Her Majesty, by and with the advice and consent of the Senate and House of Commons of Canada, enacts as follows:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>1.</B> Section 4 of the <I>Food and Drugs Act</I> is renumbered as subsection 4(1) and is amended by adding the following:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Exemptions<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(2) A food is not adulterated for the purposes of paragraph (1)(<I>d</I>)</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>a</I>) by an agricultural chemical or its components or derivatives, if the sale of the food is subject to an interim marketing authorization issued under subsection 30.2(1) and the amount of the agricultural chemical and the components or derivatives, singly or in any combination, in or on the food does not exceed the maximum residue limit that is set out in the authorization;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>b</I>) by a veterinary drug or its metabolites, if the sale of the food is subject to an interim marketing authorization issued under subsection 30.2(1) and the amount of the veterinary drug and the metabolites, singly or in any combination, in the food does not exceed the maximum residue limit that is set out in the authorization; and</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>c</I>) by a pest control product as defined in subsection 2(1) of the <I>Pest Control Products Act</I>, chapter 28 of the Statutes of Canada, 2002, or its components or derivatives, if the amount of the pest control product or the components or derivatives in or on the food being sold does not exceed the maximum residue limit specified under section 9 or 10 of that Act.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote> <br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>2.</B> Subsection 30(1) of the Act is amended by striking out the word “and” at the end of paragraph (<I>o</I>) and by adding the following after paragraph (<I>p</I>):</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>q</I>) defining “agricultural chemical”, “food additive”, “mineral nutrient”, “veterinary drug” and “vitamin” for the purposes of this Act; and</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>r</I>) respecting interim marketing authorizations, including applications for authorizations.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>3.</B> The Act is amended by adding the following after section 30.1:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:Interim Marketing Authorizations--><Para TopMargin="10" Italic="Yes" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">Interim Marketing Authorizations</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Interim marketing authorization<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>30.2</B> (1) The Minister may issue an interim marketing authorization for a food that provides for any matter referred to in subsection (2), and may exempt the food from the application, in whole or in part, of sections 5 to 6.1 and the applicable requirements of the regulations, if the Minister determines that the food would not be harmful to the health of the purchaser or consumer.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Types of authorization<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(2) An authorization may provide for any of the following that are applicable to the food:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>a</I>) the maximum residue limit in respect of an agricultural chemical and its components or derivatives, singly or in any combination;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>b</I>) the maximum residue limit in respect of a veterinary drug and its metabolites, singly or in any combination;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>c</I>) the maximum level of use in respect of a food additive; and</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>d</I>) the minimum or maximum level, or both, in respect of a vitamin, a mineral nutrient or an amino acid.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Limitation<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(3) An authorization may provide for a maximum residue limit in respect of an agricultural chemical or veterinary drug, or a maximum level of use in respect of a food additive, only if</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>a</I>) in the case of an agricultural chemical, the regulations allow the agricultural chemical and its components or derivatives, singly or in any combination, to be present in or on a food at or below a prescribed maximum residue limit and the authorization would allow the agricultural chemical and its components or derivatives, singly or in any combination, to be present in or on the food in an amount that exceeds that limit, or to be present in or on a different food;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>b</I>) in the case of a veterinary drug, the regulations allow the veterinary drug and its metabolites, singly or in any combination, to be present in a food at or below a prescribed maximum residue limit and the authorization would allow the veterinary drug and its metabolites, singly or in any combination, to be present in the food in an amount that exceeds that limit, or to be present in a different food; and</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>c</I>) in the case of a food additive, the regulations allow the food additive to be present in or on a food at or below a prescribed maximum level of use and the authorization would allow it to be used in or on the food in an amount that exceeds that level of use, or would allow it to be used in or on a different food.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Terms and conditions<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(4) An authorization may contain any terms and conditions specified by the Minister.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Exemption from <I>Statutory Instruments Act</I><br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(5) An authorization and any notice cancelling the authorization</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>a</I>) are exempt from the application of sections 3, 5 and 11 of the <I>Statutory Instruments Act</I>; and</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>b</I>) shall be published in the <I>Canada Gazette</I>.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>When effective<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(6) An authorization has effect beginning on the day on which it is published in the <I>Canada Gazette</I>, and ceases to have effect on the earliest of</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>a</I>) the day on which a notice cancelling the authorization is published in the <I>Canada Gazette</I>,</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>b</I>) the day on which a regulation made under this Act, that has the same effect as the authorization, comes into force, and</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>c</I>) two years after the day on which the authorization is published.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Deeming provision<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>4.</B> A Notice of Interim Marketing Author­ization that is issued under the <I>Food and Drug Regulations</I> before the day on which this section comes into force, in respect of any matter referred to in subsection 30.2(2) of the <I>Food and Drugs Act</I>, as enacted by section 3 of this Act, and that is in effect on the day on which this section comes into force, is deemed to be an interim marketing authorization issued under subsection 30.2(1) of that Act.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Pest control products<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>5.</B> (1) The maximum residue limit established for an agricultural chemical and its derivatives under the <I>Food and Drug Regulations</I>, as those regulations read immediately before the coming into force of this subsection, is deemed, if the agricultural chemical is a pest control product as defined in subsection 2(1) of the <I>Pest Control Products Act</I>, chapter 28 of the Statutes of Canada, 2002, to have been specified by the Minister under section 9 or 10 of that Act as the maximum residue limit for that agricultural chemical and its derivatives.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Coming into force<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes">(2) Subsection (1) comes into force on the later of the coming into force of sections 1 to 4 of this Act and the coming into force of section 89 of the <I>Pest Control Products Act</I>, chapter 28 of the Statutes of Canada, 2002.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Order in council<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>6.</B> This Act, other than section 5, comes into force on a day to be fixed by order of the Governor in Council.</Para></Block><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="BPT_ImprintE">Published under authority of the Speaker of the House of Commons<br/>Available from:<br/>Publishing and Depository Services<br/>Public Works and Government Services Canada<br/>Ottawa, Ontario K1A 0S5<br/>Telephone: 613-941-5995 or 1-800-635-7943<br/>Fax: 613-954-5779 or 1-800-565-7757<br/>publications@tpsgc-pwgsc.gc.ca<br/>http://publications.gc.ca</Para></Block><Block Align="Yes" LineCnt="N"><Para NoLineBreak="Yes" NoHtml="Yes" Leading="0" Size="0" TopMargin="0" BottomMargin="0"></Para></Block></Bill_Part></Bill>
