<?xml version="1.0"?>
<Bill RHead_reign="53-54 Eliz. II" RHead_ParlYear="2004-2005" DocumentTitle="BILL C-53" Bill_No="C-53" Document_No="90324" xml:lang="EN" Bill_Type="Non-amending" Stage_Name="Assented-to" Reprint="No" xml:space="preserve" ChapterNo_E="C. 44" ChapterNo_F="ch. 44" Bill-Origin="commons"><Bill_Part Part_Type="Cover" CountLines="No"><Block><Para TopMargin="24" Size="9" Leading="10" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0" TextAlign="Center">First Session, Thirty-eighth Parliament,</Para></Block><Block><Para Size="9" Leading="10" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0" TextAlign="Center">53-54 Elizabeth II, 2004-2005</Para></Block><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="COV@StatutesTitle">STATUTES OF CANADA 2005<br/>CHAPTER 44</Para></Block><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="CovLongTitle">An Act to amend the Criminal Code (proceeds of crime) and the Controlled Drugs and Substances Act and to make consequential amendments to another Act</Para></Block><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="COV_StageLine"></Para></Block><Block><Para BottomMargin="14" Size="11" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0" Bold="Yes" TextAlign="Center">ASSENTED TO</Para></Block><Block><Para Size="8" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0" TextAlign="Center">25th NOVEMBER, 2005</Para></Block><Block><Para TopMargin="4" Size="8" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0" TextAlign="Center">BILL C-53</Para></Block><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="COV_StageLine"></Para></Block></Bill_Part><Bill_Part CountLines="No" Part_Type="InsideCover"><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="BPT_InsideCoverE">Also available on the Parliament of Canada Web Site at the following address:<br/><B>http://www.parl.gc.ca</B></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><Para TopMargin="108" BottomMargin="4" Size="10" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">SUMMARY</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" Size="8" Leading="9" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">This enactment amends the <I>Criminal Code</I>, and makes consequential amendments to another Act, to provide a reverse onus of proof in proceeds of crime applications involving offenders who have been convicted of a criminal organization offence or certain offences under the <I>Controlled Drugs and Substances Act</I>. The enactment provides that a court shall make an order of forfeiture against any property of an offender that is identified in an application if the court is satisfied that the offender has engaged in a pattern of criminal activity or has an income unrelated to crime that cannot reasonably account for all of the offender’s property. A court may not, however, make an order of forfeiture against a property that the offender has shown, on a balance of probabilities, not to be proceeds of crime. A court may also decline to make an order of forfeiture against a property if the court considers it in the interests of justice.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" Size="8" Leading="9" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">The enactment also amends the <I>Criminal Code</I> to clarify the authority of the Attorney General of Canada in regards to proceeds of crime and to clarify the definition “designated offence” in regards to offences that may be prosecuted by indictment or on summary conviction. It also amends a provision of the <I>Criminal Code</I> to ensure the equivalency of the English and French versions.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" Size="8" Leading="9" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">The enactment also amends the <I>Controlled Drugs and Substances Act</I> to clarify the authority of a justice under that Act to issue warrants in respect of investigations of drug-related money laundering and the possession of property obtained by drug-related crime.</Para></Block></Bill_Part><Bill_Part Part_Type="MainText" CountLines="No" RunningHead_E="Criminal Code (proceeds of crime) and Controlled Drugs and Substances"><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="MAIN@RoyalAssentTitle">53-54 ELIZABETH II</Para></Block><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="MAIN@RoyalAssentTitle">——————</Para></Block><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="MAIN@RoyalAssentTitle">CHAPTER 44</Para></Block><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="LongTitleAssent">An Act to amend the Criminal Code (proceeds of crime) and the Controlled Drugs and Substances Act and to make consequential amendments to another Act</Para></Block><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="MAIN@RoyalAssentDate">[<I>Assented to 25th November, 2005</I>]</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">Her Majesty, by and with the advice and consent of the Senate and House of Commons of Canada, enacts as follows:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:CRIMINAL CODE--><MarginalNote>R.S., c. C-46<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="10" Bold="Yes" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">CRIMINAL CODE</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>2001, ch. 32, s. 12(1), (5)(F) and (6)(E)<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>1.</B> (1) The definition “designated offence” in subsection 462.3 (1) of the <I>Criminal Code</I> is replaced by the following:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>“designated offence”<br/>« <I>infraction désignée</I> »<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0">“designated offence” means</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>a</I>) any offence that may be prosecuted as an indictable offence under this or any other Act of Parliament, other than an indictable offence prescribed by regulation, or</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>b</I>) a conspiracy or an attempt to commit, being an accessory after the fact in relation to, or any counselling in relation to, an offence referred to in paragraph (<I>a</I>);</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>2001, c. 32, s. 12(7)<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes">(2) Subsection 462.3(3) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Powers of Attorney General of Canada<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(3) Despite the definition “Attorney General” in section 2, the Attorney General of Canada may</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>a</I>) exercise all the powers and perform all the duties and functions assigned to the Attorney General by or under this Act in respect of a designated offence if the alleged offence arises out of conduct that in whole or in part is in relation to an alleged contravention of an Act of Parliament or a regulation made under such an Act, other than this Act or a regulation made under this Act; and</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>b</I>) conduct proceedings and exercise all the powers and perform all the duties and functions assigned to the Attorney General by or under this Act in respect of</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="4" FirstLineIndent="0">(i) an offence referred to in section 354 or 462.31 if the alleged offence arises out of conduct that in whole or in part is in relation to an alleged contravention of an Act of Parliament or a regulation made under such an Act, other than this Act or a regulation made under this Act, and</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="4" FirstLineIndent="0">(ii) an offence under subsection 462.33(11) if the restraint order was made on application of the Attorney General of Canada.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>1997, c. 18, s. 28(1)<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>2.</B> The portion of subsection 462.31(1) of the French version of the Act before paragraph (<I>a</I>) is replaced by the following:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Recyclage des produits de la criminalité<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><AltLang xml:lang="fr"><B>462.31</B> (1) Est coupable d’une infraction quiconque — de quelque façon que ce soit — utilise, enlève, envoie, livre à une personne ou à un endroit, transporte ou modifie des biens ou leurs produits, en dispose, en transfère la possession ou prend part à toute autre forme d’opération à leur égard, dans l’intention de les cacher ou de les convertir sachant ou croyant qu’ils ont été obtenus ou proviennent, en totalité ou en partie, directement ou indirectement :</AltLang></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>2001, c. 32, s. 14(1)<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>3.</B> Subsection 462.32(1) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Special search warrant<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>462.32</B> (1) Subject to subsection (3), if a judge, on application of the Attorney General, is satisfied by information on oath in Form 1 that there are reasonable grounds to believe that there is in any building, receptacle or place, within the province in which the judge has jurisdiction or any other province, any property in respect of which an order of forfeiture may be made under subsection 462.37(1) or (2.01) or 462.38(2), in respect of a designated offence alleged to have been committed within the province in which the judge has jurisdiction, the judge may issue a warrant authorizing a person named in the warrant or a peace officer to search the building, receptacle or place for that property and to seize that property and any other property in respect of which that person or peace officer believes, on reasonable grounds, that an order of forfeiture may be made under that subsection.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>R.S., c. 42 (4th Supp.), s. 2<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>4.</B> (1) Paragraph 462.33(2)(<I>c</I>) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>c</I>) the grounds for the belief that an order of forfeiture may be made under subsection 462.37(1) or (2.01) or 462.38(2) in respect of the property;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>2001, c. 32, s. 15(1)<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes">(2) Subsection 462.33(3) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Restraint order<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(3) A judge who hears an application for a restraint order made under subsection (1) may — if the judge is satisfied that there are reasonable grounds to believe that there exists, within the province in which the judge has jurisdiction or any other province, any property in respect of which an order of forfeiture may be made under subsection 462.37(1) or (2.01) or 462.38(2), in respect of a designated offence alleged to have been committed within the province in which the judge has jurisdiction — make an order prohibiting any person from disposing of, or otherwise dealing with any interest in, the property specified in the order otherwise than in the manner that may be specified in the order.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>R.S., c. 42 (4th Supp.), s. 2<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes">(3) Subsection 462.33(5) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Notice<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(5) Before making an order under subsection (3) in relation to any property, a judge may require notice to be given to and may hear any person who, in the opinion of the judge, appears to have a valid interest in the property unless the judge is of the opinion that giving such notice before making the order would result in the disappearance, dissipation or reduction in value of the property or otherwise affect the property so that all or a part thereof could not be subject to an order of forfeiture under subsection 462.37(1) or (2.01) or 462.38(2).</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>R.S., c. 42 (4th Supp.), s. 2<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes">(4) Paragraph 462.33(10)(<I>c</I>) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>c</I>) an order of forfeiture or restoration of the property is made under subsection 462.37(1) or (2.01), 462.38(2) or 462.41(3) or any other provision of this or any other Act of Parliament.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>1999, c. 5, s. 14<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>5.</B> Section 462.341 of the Act is replaced by the following:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Application of property restitution provisions<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>462.341</B> Subsection 462.34(2), paragraph 462.34(4)(<I>c</I>) and subsections 462.34(5), (5.1) and (5.2) apply, with any modifications that the circumstances require, to a person who has an interest in money or bank-notes that are seized under this Act or the <I>Controlled Drugs and Substances Act</I> and in respect of which proceedings may be taken under subsection 462.37(1) or (2.01) or 462.38(2).</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>6.</B> (1) Section 462.37 of the Act is amended by adding the following after subsection (2):</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Order of forfeiture — particular circumstances<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(2.01) A court imposing sentence on an offender convicted of an offence described in subsection (2.02) shall, on application of the Attorney General and subject to this section and sections 462.4 and 462.41, order that any property of the offender that is identified by the Attorney General in the application be forfeited to Her Majesty to be disposed of as the Attorney General directs or otherwise dealt with in accordance with the law if the court is satisfied, on a balance of probabilities, that</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>a</I>) within 10 years before the proceedings were commenced in respect of the offence for which the offender is being sentenced, the offender engaged in a pattern of criminal activity for the purpose of directly or indirectly receiving a material benefit, including a financial benefit; or</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>b</I>) the income of the offender from sources unrelated to designated offences cannot reasonably account for the value of all the property of the offender.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Offences<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(2.02) The offences are the following:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>a</I>) a criminal organization offence punishable by five or more years of imprisonment; and</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>b</I>) an offence under section 5, 6 or 7 of the <I>Controlled Drugs and Substances Act</I> — or a conspiracy or an attempt to commit, being an accessory after the fact in relation to, or any counselling in relation to an offence under those sections — prosecuted by indictment.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Offender may establish that property is not proceeds of crime<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(2.03) A court shall not make an order of forfeiture under subsection (2.01) in respect of any property that the offender establishes, on a balance of probabilities, is not proceeds of crime.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Pattern of criminal activity<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(2.04) In determining whether the offender has engaged in a pattern of criminal activity described in paragraph (2.01)(<I>a</I>), the court shall consider</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>a</I>) the circumstances of the offence for which the offender is being sentenced;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>b</I>) any act or omission — other than an act or omission that constitutes the offence for which the offender is being sentenced — that the court is satisfied, on a balance of probabilities, was committed by the offender and constitutes an offence punishable by indictment under any Act of Parliament;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>c</I>) any act or omission that the court is satisfied, on a balance of probabilities, was committed by the offender and is an offence in the place where it was committed and, if committed in Canada, would constitute an offence punishable by indictment under any Act of Parliament; and</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>d</I>) any other factor that the court considers relevant.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Conditions — pattern of criminal activity<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(2.05) A court shall not determine that an offender has engaged in a pattern of criminal activity unless the court is satisfied, on a balance of probabilities, that the offender committed, within the period referred to in paragraph (2.01)(<I>a</I>),</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>a</I>) acts or omissions — other than an act or omission that constitutes the offence for which the offender is being sentenced — that constitute at least two serious offences or one criminal organization offence;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>b</I>) acts or omissions that are offences in the place where they were committed and, if committed in Canada, would constitute at least two serious offences or one criminal organization offence; or</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>c</I>) an act or omission described in paragraph (<I>a</I>) that constitutes a serious offence and an act or omission described in paragraph (<I>b</I>) that, if committed in Canada, would constitute a serious offence.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Application under subsection (1) not prevented<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(2.06) Nothing in subsection (2.01) shall be interpreted as preventing the Attorney General from making an application under subsection (1) in respect of any property.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Exception<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(2.07) A court may, if it considers it in the interests of justice, decline to make an order of forfeiture against any property that would otherwise be subject to forfeiture under subsection (2.01). The court shall give reasons for its decision.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>R.S., c. 42 (4th Supp.), s. 2<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes">(2) Subsection 462.37(3) of the English version of the Act is replaced by the following:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Fine instead of forfeiture<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(3) If a court is satisfied that an order of forfeiture under subsection (1) or (2.01) should be made in respect of any property of an offender but that the property or any part of or interest in the property cannot be made subject to an order, the court may, instead of ordering the property or any part of or interest in the property to be forfeited, order the offender to pay a fine in an amount equal to the value of the property or the part of or interest in the property. In particular, a court may order the offender to pay a fine if the property or any part of or interest in the property</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>a</I>) cannot, on the exercise of due diligence, be located;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>b</I>) has been transferred to a third party;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>c</I>) is located outside Canada;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>d</I>) has been substantially diminished in value or rendered worthless; or</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>e</I>) has been commingled with other property that cannot be divided without difficulty.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>R.S., c. 42 (4th Supp.), s. 2<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>7.</B> Paragraph 462.4(<I>a</I>) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>a</I>) prior to ordering property to be forfeited under subsection 462.37(1) or (2.01) or 462.38(2), and</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>R.S., c. 42 (4th Supp.), s. 2<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>8.</B> (1) Subsection 462.41(1) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Notice<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>462.41</B> (1) Before making an order under subsection 462.37(1) or (2.01) or 462.38(2) in relation to any property, a court shall require notice in accordance with subsection (2) to be given to and may hear any person who, in the opinion of the court, appears to have a valid interest in the property.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes">(2) Subsection 462.41(3) of the Act is amended by replacing the reference to “subsection 462.37(1)” with a reference to “subsection 462.37(1) or (2.01)”.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>R.S., c. 42 (4th Supp.), s. 2; 2001, c. 32, s. 23(1)<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>9.</B> Subsection 462.42(1) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Application by person claiming interest for relief from forfeiture<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>462.42</B> (1) Any person who claims an interest in property that is forfeited to Her Majesty under subsection 462.37(1) or (2.01) or 462.38(2) may, within thirty days after the forfeiture, apply by notice in writing to a judge for an order under subsection (4) unless the person is</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>a</I>) a person who is charged with, or was convicted of, a designated offence that resulted in the forfeiture; or</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>b</I>) a person who acquired title to or a right of possession of the property from a person referred to in paragraph (<I>a</I>) under circumstances that give rise to a reasonable inference that the title or right was transferred from that person for the purpose of avoiding the forfeiture of the property.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>R.S., c. 42 (4th Supp.), s. 2<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>10.</B> The portion of section 462.45 of the Act before paragraph (<I>a</I>) is replaced by the following:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Suspension of forfeiture pending appeal<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>462.45</B> Despite anything in this Part, the operation of an order of forfeiture or restoration of property under subsection 462.34(4), 462.37(1) or (2.01), 462.38(2) or 462.41(3) or section 462.43 is suspended pending</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>R.S., c. 42 (4th Supp.), s. 2<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>11.</B> Subsection 462.46(1) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Copies of documents returned or forfeited<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>462.46</B> (1) If any document is returned or ordered to be returned, forfeited or otherwise dealt with under subsection 462.34(3) or (4), 462.37(1) or (2.01), 462.38(2) or 462.41(3) or section 462.43, the Attorney General may, before returning the document or complying with the order, cause a copy of the document to be made and retained.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>2002, c. 13, s. 69<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>12.</B> The portion of subsection 689(1) of the Act before paragraph (<I>a</I>) is replaced by the following:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Restitution or forfeiture of property<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>689.</B> (1) If the trial court makes an order for compensation or for the restitution of property under section 738 or 739 or an order of forfeiture of property under subsection 164.2(1) or 462.37(1) or (2.01), the operation of the order is suspended</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:CONTROLLED DRUGS AND SUBSTANCES ACT--><MarginalNote>1996, c. 19<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="10" Bold="Yes" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">CONTROLLED DRUGS AND SUBSTANCES ACT</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>13.</B> Paragraph 11(1)(<I>d</I>) of the <I>Controlled Drugs and Substances Act</I> is replaced by the following:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>d</I>) any thing that will afford evidence in respect of an offence under this Act or an offence, in whole or in part in relation to a contravention of this Act, under section 354 or 462.31 of the <I>Criminal Code</I></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:CONSEQUENTIAL AMENDMENTS--><Para TopMargin="10" Bold="Yes" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">CONSEQUENTIAL AMENDMENTS</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:Seized Property Management Act--><MarginalNote>1993, c. 37<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" Bold="Yes" SmallCaps="Yes" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">Seized Property Management Act</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>2000, c. 17, s. 95; 2001, c. 41, s. 110<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>14.</B> Paragraph 10(1)(<I>a</I>) of the <I>Seized Property Management Act</I> is replaced by the following:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>a</I>) the forfeiture to Her Majesty of property pursuant to section 83.14, subsection 462.37(1), (2) or (2.01) or 462.38(2), subparagraph 462.43(<I>c</I>)(iii) or subsection 490.1(1) or 490.2(2) of the <I>Criminal Code</I> or subsection 16(1) or 17(2) of the <I>Controlled Drugs and Substances Act</I>;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>2001, c. 41, s. 137(4)<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>15.</B> Subparagraph 11(<I>a</I>)(i) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="4" FirstLineIndent="0">(i) property forfeited to Her Majesty pursuant to section 83.14, subsection 462.37(1), (2) or (2.01) or 462.38(2), subparagraph 462.43(<I>c</I>)(iii) or subsection 490.1(1) or 490.2(2) of the <I>Criminal Code</I> or subsection 16(1) or 17(2) of the <I>Controlled Drugs and Substances Act</I>, or</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>1997, c. 23, s. 25<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>16.</B> Section 14 of the Act is replaced by the following:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>If costs are greater than proceeds<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>14.</B> If the proceeds of disposition available to Her Majesty from the forfeiture of any property pursuant to subsection 462.37(1), (2) or (2.01) or 462.38(2), subparagraph 462.43(<I>c</I>)(iii) or subsection 490(9) of the <I>Criminal Code</I> or subsection 16(1) or 17(2) of the <I>Controlled Drugs and Substances Act</I> are insufficient to cover the outstanding amounts charged to the Working Capital Account pursuant to subsection 12(2), and any interest on it, in respect of the property, there shall be charged to the Proceeds Account and credited to the Working Capital Account, or to interest revenue, as the case may be, an amount equal to the amount of the shortfall.</Para></Block><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="BPT_ImprintE">Published under authority of the Speaker of the House of Commons<br/>Available from:<br/>Publishing and Depository Services<br/>Public Works and Government Services Canada<br/>Ottawa, Ontario K1A 0S5<br/>Telephone: 613-941-5995 or 1-800-635-7943<br/>Fax: 613-954-5779 or 1-800-565-7757<br/>publications@tpsgc-pwgsc.gc.ca<br/>http://publications.gc.ca</Para></Block><Block Align="Yes" LineCnt="N"><Para NoLineBreak="Yes" NoHtml="Yes" Leading="0" Size="0" TopMargin="0" BottomMargin="0"></Para></Block></Bill_Part></Bill>
