<?xml version="1.0"?>
<Bill RHead_reign="53-54 Eliz. II" RHead_ParlYear="2004-2005" DocumentTitle="BILL C-73" Bill_No="C-73" Document_No="90352" xml:lang="EN" Bill_Type="Amending" Stage_Name="First-Reading-House" Reprint="No" xml:space="preserve" ChapterNo_E="C. " ChapterNo_F="ch. " Bill-Origin="commons"><Bill_Part Part_Type="Cover" CountLines="No"><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="CovBillNo">C-73</Para></Block><Block><Para TopMargin="24" Size="9" Leading="10" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0" TextAlign="Center">First Session, Thirty-eighth Parliament,</Para></Block><Block><Para Size="9" Leading="10" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0" TextAlign="Center">53-54 Elizabeth II, 2004-2005</Para></Block><Block><Para TopMargin="48" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0" Bold="Yes" TextAlign="Center">HOUSE OF COMMONS OF CANADA</Para></Block><Block><Para TopMargin="42" Size="18" Leading="20" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0" Bold="Yes" TextAlign="Center">BILL C-73</Para></Block><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="CovLongTitle">An Act to amend the Telecommunications Act (No. 2)</Para></Block><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="COV_StageLine"></Para></Block><Block><Para Size="9" AllCaps="Yes" Hyphenate="OFF">first reading, November 14, 2005</Para></Block><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="COV_StageLine"></Para></Block><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="Cover_Sponsors">THE MINISTER OF INDUSTRY</Para></Block><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="Cover_DocNo">90352</Para></Block></Bill_Part><Bill_Part CountLines="No" Part_Type="InsideCover"><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="BPT_InsideCoverE">Also available on the Parliament of Canada Web Site at the following address:<br/><B>http://www.parl.gc.ca</B></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><Para TopMargin="108" BottomMargin="4" Size="10" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">SUMMARY</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" Size="8" Leading="9" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">This enactment amends the <I>Telecommunications Act</I> to provide the Canadian Radio-television and Telecommunications Commission with the authority to create and administer an administrative monetary penalty scheme for contraventions of its decisions or of the Act. It also streamlines existing summary conviction provisions and raises the associated penalties, and enables the Commission to share confidential information with the Commissioner of Competition.</Para></Block></Bill_Part><Bill_Part Part_Type="MainText" CountLines="Yes" RunningHead_E="Telecommunications"><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="MainText_DocNo">90352</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes"><Para Style="Session_Reign">1st Session, 38th Parliament,</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes"><Para Style="Session_Reign">53-54 Elizabeth II, 2004-2005</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes"><Para Style="MainBillOrigin">house of commons of canada</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes"><Para Bold="Yes" Style="MAIN@BillNo_Title">BILL C-73</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes"><Para Style="MAIN@ti;04">An Act to amend the Telecommunications Act (No. 2)</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>1993, c. 38<br/></MarginalNote><Para LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">Her Majesty, by and with the advice and consent of the Senate and House of Commons of Canada, enacts as follows:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>2003, c. 22, par. 224(<I>z.81</I>)(E)<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>1.</B> Subsections 39(3) and (4) of the <I>Telecommunications Act</I> are replaced by the following:</Para><ExplNote><Para Align="Yes" TopMargin="10" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><I>Clause 1</I>: Existing text of subsections 39(3) and (4):</Para><Para Align="Yes" TopMargin="5" Size="8" Leading="9" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(3) Subsection (2) applies to</Para><Para Align="No" TopMargin="5" Size="8" Leading="9" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>a</I>) any member of, or person employed by, the Commission, and</Para><Para Align="No" TopMargin="5" Size="8" Leading="9" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>b</I>) in respect of information provided under subsection 37(3), the Minister, the Chief Statistician of Canada and any person employed in the federal public administration,</Para><Para Align="No" TopMargin="5" Size="8" Leading="9" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0">who comes into possession of designated information while holding that office or being so employed, whether or not the person has ceased to hold that office or be so employed.</Para><Para Align="Yes" TopMargin="5" Size="8" Leading="9" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(4) Where designated information is submitted in the course of proceedings before the Commission, the Commission may disclose or require its disclosure where it determines, after considering any representations from interested persons, that the disclosure is in the public interest.</Para></ExplNote></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Persons who must not disclose information<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(3) Subsection (2) applies to <change>any person referred to in the following paragraphs</change> who comes into possession of designated information while holding <change>the office or employment described in that paragraph</change>, whether or not the person has ceased to hold that office or be so employed:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>a</I>) <change>a</change> member of, or person employed by, the Commission;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0"><change>(<I>b</I>) in respect of information disclosed under paragraph (4)(<I>b</I>), the Commissioner of Competition appointed under the <I>Competition Act</I> or a person whose duties involve the carrying out of that Act and who is referred to in section 25 of that Act; and</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0"><change>(<I>c</I>)</change> in respect of information provided under subsection 37(3), the Minister, the Chief Statistician of Canada and <change>a</change> person employed in the federal public administration.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Disclosure of information submitted in proceedings<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(4) <change>If</change> designated information is submitted in the course of proceedings before the Commission</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0"><change>(<I>a</I>)</change> the Commission may disclose or require its disclosure <change>if</change> it determines, after considering any representations from interested persons, that the disclosure is in the public interest; <change>and</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0"><change>(<I>b</I>) the Commission may disclose or require its disclosure to the Commissioner of Competition if the Commission determines, after considering any representations from interested parties, that the information is relevant to competition issues being considered in the proceedings and that, despite the fact that it is not disclosed to other parties in the proceeding, its disclosure to the Commissioner is in the public interest.</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Use of information disclosed to Commissioner of Competition<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><change>(4.1) Neither the Commissioner of Competition nor any person whose duties involve the carrying out of the <I>Competition Act</I> and who is referred to in section 25 of that Act shall use information disclosed under paragraph (4)(<I>b</I>) other than to facilitate the Commissioner’s participation in those proceedings.</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>2.</B> The Act is amended by adding the following after section 72:</Para><ExplNote><Para Align="Yes" TopMargin="10" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><I>Clause 2</I>: New.</Para></ExplNote></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:Administrative Monetary Penalties--><Para TopMargin="10" SmallCaps="Yes" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center"><change>Administrative Monetary Penalties</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Commission of violation<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><change><B>72.1</B> Every contravention of a provision of this Act, other than section 17 or 69.2, and every contravention of a regulation, or a decision, made by the Commission under this Act, other than a prohibition or a requirement of the Commission under section 41, constitutes a violation and the person who commits the violation is liable</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0"><change>(<I>a</I>) in the case of an individual, to an administrative monetary penalty not exceeding $25,000 and, for each subsequent contravention of the same provision of this Act or the same regulation or decision, not exceeding $50,000; or</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0"><change>(<I>b</I>) in the case of a corporation, to an administrative monetary penalty not exceeding $10,000,000 and, for each subsequent contravention of the same provision of this Act or the same regulation or decision, not exceeding $15,000,000.</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Criteria for penalty<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><change><B>72.2</B> (1) The amount of the penalty is to be determined taking into account the following matters:</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0"><change>(<I>a</I>) the nature of the violation;</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0"><change>(<I>b</I>) the frequency and duration of the conduct constituting the violation;</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0"><change>(<I>c</I>) the history of compliance with this Act by the person who committed the violation;</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0"><change>(<I>d</I>) the financial position of the person who committed the violation;</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0"><change>(<I>e</I>) the question of whether any compensation has been made voluntarily to any affected party; and</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0"><change>(<I>f</I>) any other relevant factor.</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Purpose of penalty<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><change>(2) The purpose of the penalty is to promote compliance with this Act and not to punish.</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Vicarious liability — acts of employees, agents and mandataries<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><change><B>72.3</B> A person is liable for a violation that is committed by an employee of the person acting in the course of the employee’s employment, or by an agent or mandatary of the person acting within the scope of the agent’s or mandatary’s authority, whether or not the employee, agent or mandatary who actually committed the violation is identified or proceeded against in accordance with this Act.</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Continuing violation<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><change><B>72.4</B> A violation that is continued on more than one day constitutes a separate violation in respect of each day during which it is continued.</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Issuance and service<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><change><B>72.5</B> (1) If the Commission believes on reasonable grounds that a person has committed a violation, the Commission may issue, and shall cause to be served on the person, a notice of violation.</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Contents of notice<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><change>(2) The notice of violation must name the person believed to have committed a violation, identify the violation and include</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0"><change>(<I>a</I>) the penalty that the Commission proposes to impose for the violation;</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0"><change>(<I>b</I>) a statement as to the right of the person, within 30 days after the day on which the notice is served, or within any longer period that the Commission specifies, to pay the proposed penalty or to make representations to the Commission with respect to the violation and the proposed penalty, and the manner for doing so; and</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0"><change>(<I>c</I>) a statement indicating that, if the person does not pay the proposed penalty or make representations in accordance with the notice, the person will be deemed to have committed the violation and the Commission may impose that penalty.</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Payment<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><change><B>72.6</B> (1) If a person who is served with a notice of violation pays the penalty proposed in the notice, the person is deemed to have committed the violation and proceedings in respect of it are ended.</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Representations to Commission<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><change>(2) If a person who is served with a notice of violation makes representations in accordance with the notice, the Commission shall decide, on a balance of probabilities, after considering any other representations that it considers appropriate, whether the person committed the violation and, if it so decides, it may impose the penalty proposed in the notice, a lesser penalty or no penalty.</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Failure to pay or make representations<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><change>(3) If a person who is served with a notice of violation neither pays the proposed penalty nor makes representations in accordance with the notice, the person is deemed to have committed the violation and the Commission may impose that penalty.</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Copy of decision and notice of rights<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><change>(4) The Commission shall cause a copy of any decision made under subsection (2) or (3) to be issued and served on the person together with a notice of the person’s right to apply for a review under section 62 and to appeal under section 64.</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Defence<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><change><B>72.7</B> (1) It is a defence for a person in a proceeding in relation to a violation to establish that the person exercised due diligence to prevent the violation.</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Common law principles<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><change>(2) Every rule and principle of the common law that renders any circumstance a justification or excuse in relation to a charge for an offence under a relevant provision of this Act applies in respect of a violation to the extent that the rule or principle is not inconsistent with this Act.</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Evidence<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><change><B>72.8</B> In a proceeding in respect of a violation, a notice purporting to be served under subsection 72.5(1) or a copy of a decision purporting to be served under subsection 72.6(4) is admissible in evidence without proof of the signature or official character of the person appearing to have signed it.</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Time limit<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><change><B>72.9</B> (1) No proceedings in respect of a violation may be commenced later than two years after the day on which the subject-matter of the proceedings became known to the Commission.</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Certificate of secretary to the Commission<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><change>(2) A document appearing to have been issued by the secretary to the Commission, certifying the day on which the subject-matter of any proceedings became known to the Commission, is admissible in evidence without proof of the signature or official character of the person appearing to have signed the document and is, in the absence of evidence to the contrary, proof of the matter asserted in it.</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Debt to Her Majesty<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><change><B>72.91</B> (1) An administrative monetary penalty constitutes a debt due to Her Majesty in right of Canada that may be recovered as such in the Federal Court.</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Time limit<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><change>(2) No proceedings to recover such a debt may be commenced later than five years after the day on which the debt became payable.</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Proceeds payable to Receiver General<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><change>(3) An administrative monetary penalty paid or recovered in relation to a violation is payable to and shall be remitted to the Receiver General.</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Certificate of default<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><change>(4) The Commission may issue a certificate certifying the unpaid amount of any debt referred to in subsection (1).</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Registration in Federal Court<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><change>(5) When registered in the Federal Court, the certificate has the same effect as if it were a judgment of that Court for a debt of the amount specified in the certificate and all related registration costs.</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>How act or omission may be proceeded with<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><change><B>72.92</B> If a contravention of this Act or of any regulation, or decision, made by the Commission under this Act can be proceeded with either as a violation or as an offence, proceeding in one manner precludes proceeding in the other.</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Section 12 does not apply<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><change><B>72.93</B> Section 12 does not apply in respect of any decision of the Commission made under subsection 72.6(2) or (3).</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>1998, c. 8, ss. 9(1) to (3)<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>3.</B> Subsections 73(1) to (3) of the Act are replaced by the following:</Para><ExplNote><Para Align="Yes" TopMargin="10" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><I>Clause 3</I>: Existing text of subsections 73(1) to (3):</Para><Para Align="Yes" TopMargin="5" Size="8" Leading="9" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>73.</B> (1) Every person who contravenes subsection 16(4) or 16.1(1) or (2) or section 17 is guilty of an offence punishable on summary conviction and liable</Para><Para Align="No" TopMargin="5" Size="8" Leading="9" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>a</I>) in the case of an individual, to a fine not exceeding fifty thousand dollars for a first offence, or one hundred thousand dollars for a subsequent offence; or</Para><Para Align="No" TopMargin="5" Size="8" Leading="9" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>b</I>) in the case of a corporation, to a fine not exceeding five hundred thousand dollars for a first offence, or one million dollars for a subsequent offence.</Para><Para Align="Yes" TopMargin="5" Size="8" Leading="9" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(2) Every person who</Para><Para Align="No" TopMargin="5" Size="8" Leading="9" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>a</I>) contravenes section 25, subsection 27(1) or (2) or section 69.2,</Para><Para Align="No" TopMargin="5" Size="8" Leading="9" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>b</I>) contravenes any condition referred to in section 9 or 24 or subsection 34(1) or (2),</Para><Para Align="No" TopMargin="5" Size="8" Leading="9" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>c</I>) contravenes any prohibition or requirement of the Commission under section 41, or</Para><Para Align="No" TopMargin="5" Size="8" Leading="9" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>d</I>) knowingly makes a material misrepresentation of fact or omits to state a material fact to the Minister, the Commission, a person appointed under section 70 or an inspector appointed under paragraph 69.3(1)(<I>h</I>) or section 71</Para><Para Align="No" TopMargin="5" Size="8" Leading="9" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0">is guilty of an offence punishable on summary conviction and liable, in the case of an individual, to a fine not exceeding ten thousand dollars for a first offence or twenty-five thousand dollars for a subsequent offence, and in the case of a corporation, to a fine not exceeding one hundred thousand dollars for a first offence or two hundred and fifty thousand dollars for a subsequent offence.</Para><Para Align="Yes" TopMargin="5" Size="8" Leading="9" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(3) Every person who</Para><Para Align="No" TopMargin="5" Size="8" Leading="9" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>a</I>) contravenes any other provision of this Act or any special Act or any regulation or decision made under this Act, or</Para><Para Align="No" TopMargin="5" Size="8" Leading="9" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>b</I>) fails to do anything required or does anything prohibited under a provision, regulation or decision referred to in paragraph (<I>a</I>)</Para><Para Align="No" TopMargin="5" Size="8" Leading="9" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0">is guilty of an offence punishable on summary conviction and liable, in the case of an individual, to a fine not exceeding five thousand dollars for a first offence or ten thousand dollars for a subsequent offence, and in the case of a corporation, to a fine not exceeding fifty thousand dollars for a first offence or one hundred thousand dollars for a subsequent offence.</Para></ExplNote></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Offences<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>73.</B> (1) Every person is guilty of an offence punishable on summary conviction and liable, in the case of an individual, to a fine not exceeding <change>$75,000</change> for a first offence or <change>$150,000</change> for a subsequent offence, and in the case of a corporation, to a fine not exceeding <change>$20,000,000</change> for a first offence or <change>$30,000,000</change> for a subsequent offence who</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>a</I>) contravenes subsection 16(4) or 16.1(1) or (2), section 17 or 25, subsection 27(1) or (2), <change>subsection 43(2) or (3)</change> or section 69.2;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>b</I>) contravenes a <change>decision made under</change> section 9 or 24, subsection 34(1) or (2), <change>section 42, subsection 43(4) or (5) or section 44 or 51</change>; or</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>c</I>) knowingly makes a material misrepresentation of fact or omits to state a material fact to the Minister, the Commission, a person appointed under section 70 or an inspector appointed under paragraph 69.3(1)(<I>h</I>) or section 71.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Offences<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><change>(2)</change> Every person who contravenes any other provision of this Act or any other decision made under this Act, or any special Act or any regulation made under this Act, is guilty of an offence punishable on summary conviction and liable, in the case of an individual, to a fine not exceeding <change>$50,000</change> for a first offence or <change>$100,000</change> for a subsequent offence, and in the case of a corporation, to a fine not exceeding <change>$15,000,000</change> for a first offence or <change>$20,000,000</change> for a subsequent offence.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Bill C-37<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>4.</B> (1) Subsections (2) and (3) apply if Bill C-37, introduced in the 1st session of the 38th Parliament and entitled <I>An Act to amend the Telecommunications Act</I> (the “other Act”), receives royal assent.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Bill C-37<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes">(2) If the other Act comes into force before this Act receives royal assent, then, on the day on which this Act receives royal assent,</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0" Bold="Yes">(<I>a</I>) the heading before section 72.01 of the <I>Telecommunications Act</I> is replaced by the following:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes"><!--Heading:Administrative Monetary Penalties for Unsolicited Telecommunications--><Para TopMargin="10" SmallCaps="Yes" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">Administrative Monetary Penalties for Unsolicited Telecommunications</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0" Bold="Yes">(<I>b</I>) section 2 of this Act is replaced by the following:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>2.</B> The Act is amended by adding the following after section 72.15:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:General Administrative Monetary Penalties--><Para TopMargin="10" SmallCaps="Yes" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">General Administrative Monetary Penalties</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Commission of violation<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>72.2</B> Every contravention of a provision of this Act, other than section 17 or 69.2, and every contravention of a regulation, or a decision, made by the Commission under this Act, other than a prohibition or a requirement of the Commission under section 41, constitutes a violation and the person who commits the violation is liable</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>a</I>) in the case of an individual, to an administrative monetary penalty not exceeding $25,000 and, for each subsequent contravention of the same provision of this Act or the same regulation or decision, not exceeding $50,000; or</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>b</I>) in the case of a corporation, to an administrative monetary penalty not exceeding $10,000,000 and, for each subsequent contravention of the same provision of this Act or the same regulation or decision, not exceeding $15,000,000.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Criteria for penalty<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>72.3</B> (1) The amount of the penalty is to be determined taking into account the following matters:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>a</I>) the nature of the violation;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>b</I>) the frequency and duration of the conduct constituting the violation;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>c</I>) the history of compliance with this Act by the person who committed the violation;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>d</I>) the financial position of the person who committed the violation;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>e</I>) the question of whether any compensation has been made voluntarily to any affected party; and</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>f</I>) any other relevant factor.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Purpose of penalty<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(2) The purpose of the penalty is to promote compliance with this Act and not to punish.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Vicarious liability — acts of employees, agents and mandataries<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>72.4</B> A person is liable for a violation that is committed by an employee of the person acting in the course of the employee’s employment, or by an agent or mandatary of the person acting within the scope of the agent’s or mandatary’s authority, whether or not the employee, agent or mandatary who actually committed the violation is identified or proceeded against in accordance with this Act.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Continuing violation<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>72.5</B> A violation that is continued on more than one day constitutes a separate violation in respect of each day during which it is continued.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Issuance and service<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>72.6</B> (1) If the Commission believes on reasonable grounds that a person has committed a violation, the Commission may issue, and shall cause to be served on the person, a notice of violation.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Contents of notice<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(2) The notice of violation must name the person believed to have committed a violation, identify the violation and include</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>a</I>) the penalty that the Commission proposes to impose for the violation;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>b</I>) a statement as to the right of the person, within 30 days after the day on which the notice is served, or within any longer period that the Commission specifies, to pay the proposed penalty or to make representations to the Commission with respect to the violation and the proposed penalty, and the manner for doing so; and</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>c</I>) a statement indicating that, if the person does not pay the proposed penalty or make representations in accordance with the notice, the person will be deemed to have committed the violation and the Commission may impose that penalty.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Payment<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>72.7</B> (1) If a person who is served with a notice of violation pays the penalty proposed in the notice, the person is deemed to have committed the violation and proceedings in respect of it are ended.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Representations to Commission<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(2) If a person who is served with a notice of violation makes representations in accordance with the notice, the Commission shall decide, on a balance of probabilities, after considering any other representations that it considers appropriate, whether the person committed the violation and, if it so decides, it may impose the penalty proposed in the notice, a lesser penalty or no penalty.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Failure to pay or make representations<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(3) If a person who is served with a notice of violation neither pays the proposed penalty nor makes representations in accordance with the notice, the person is deemed to have committed the violation and the Commission may impose that penalty.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Copy of decision and notice of rights<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(4) The Commission shall cause a copy of any decision made under subsection (2) or (3) to be issued and served on the person together with a notice of the person’s right to apply for a review under section 62 and to appeal under section 64.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Defence<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>72.8</B> (1) It is a defence for a person in a proceeding in relation to a violation to establish that the person exercised due diligence to prevent the violation.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Common law principles<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(2) Every rule and principle of the common law that renders any circumstance a justification or excuse in relation to a charge for an offence under a relevant provision of this Act applies in respect of a violation to the extent that the rule or principle is not inconsistent with this Act.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Evidence<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>72.9</B> In a proceeding in respect of a violation, a notice purporting to be served under subsection 72.6(1) or a copy of a decision purporting to be served under subsection 72.7(4) is admissible in evidence without proof of the signature or official character of the person appearing to have signed it.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Time limit<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>72.91</B> (1) No proceedings in respect of a violation may be commenced later than two years after the day on which the subject-matter of the proceedings became known to the Commission.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Certificate of secretary to the Commission<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(2) A document appearing to have been issued by the secretary to the Commission, certifying the day on which the subject-matter of any proceedings became known to the Commission, is admissible in evidence without proof of the signature or official character of the person appearing to have signed the document and is, in the absence of evidence to the contrary, proof of the matter asserted in it.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Debt to Her Majesty<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>72.92</B> (1) An administrative monetary penalty constitutes a debt due to Her Majesty in right of Canada that may be recovered as such in the Federal Court.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Time limit<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(2) No proceedings to recover such a debt may be commenced later than five years after the day on which the debt became payable.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Proceeds payable to Receiver General<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(3) An administrative monetary penalty paid or recovered in relation to a violation is payable to and shall be remitted to the Receiver General.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Certificate of default<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(4) The Commission may issue a certificate certifying the unpaid amount of any debt referred to in subsection (1).</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Registration in Federal Court<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(5) When registered in the Federal Court, the certificate has the same effect as if it were a judgment of that Court for a debt of the amount specified in the certificate and all related registration costs.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>How act or omission may be proceeded with<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>72.93</B> If a contravention of this Act or of any regulation, or decision, made by the Commission under this Act can be proceeded with either as a violation or as an offence, proceeding in one manner precludes proceeding in the other.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Section 12 does not apply<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>72.94</B> Section 12 does not apply in respect of any decision of the Commission made under subsection 72.7(2) or (3).</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Bill C-37<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes">(3) If this Act receives royal assent before the other Act comes into force, then, on the day on which the other Act comes into force,</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0" Bold="Yes">(<I>a</I>) the heading before section 72.01 of the <I>Telecommunications Act</I> is replaced by the following:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes"><!--Heading:Administrative Monetary Penalties for Unsolicited Telecommunications--><Para TopMargin="10" SmallCaps="Yes" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">Administrative Monetary Penalties for Unsolicited Telecommunications</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0" Bold="Yes">(<I>b</I>) the heading before section 72.1 and sections 72.1 to 72.93 of the Act, as enacted by section 2 of this Act, are replaced by the following:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:General Administrative Monetary Penalties--><Para TopMargin="10" SmallCaps="Yes" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">General Administrative Monetary Penalties</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Commission of violation<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>72.2</B> Every contravention of a provision of this Act, other than section 17 or 69.2, and every contravention of a regulation, or a decision, made by the Commission under this Act, other than a prohibition or a requirement of the Commission under section 41, constitutes a violation and the person who commits the violation is liable</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>a</I>) in the case of an individual, to an administrative monetary penalty not exceeding $25,000 and, for each subsequent contravention of the same provision of this Act or the same regulation or decision, not exceeding $50,000; or</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>b</I>) in the case of a corporation, to an administrative monetary penalty not exceeding $10,000,000 and, for each subsequent contravention of the same provision of this Act or the same regulation or decision, not exceeding $15,000,000.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Criteria for penalty<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>72.3</B> (1) The amount of the penalty is to be determined taking into account the following matters:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>a</I>) the nature of the violation;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>b</I>) the frequency and duration of the conduct constituting the violation;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>c</I>) the history of compliance with this Act by the person who committed the violation;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>d</I>) the financial position of the person who committed the violation;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>e</I>) the question of whether any compensation has been made voluntarily to any affected party; and</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>f</I>) any other relevant factor.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Purpose of penalty<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(2) The purpose of the penalty is to promote compliance with this Act and not to punish.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Vicarious liability — acts of employees, agents and mandataries<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>72.4</B> A person is liable for a violation that is committed by an employee of the person acting in the course of the employee’s employment, or by an agent or mandatary of the person acting within the scope of the agent’s or mandatary’s authority, whether or not the employee, agent or mandatary who actually committed the violation is identified or proceeded against in accordance with this Act.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Continuing violation<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>72.5</B> A violation that is continued on more than one day constitutes a separate violation in respect of each day during which it is continued.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Issuance and service<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>72.6</B> (1) If the Commission believes on reasonable grounds that a person has committed a violation, the Commission may issue, and shall cause to be served on the person, a notice of violation.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Contents of notice<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(2) The notice of violation must name the person believed to have committed a violation, identify the violation and include</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>a</I>) the penalty that the Commission proposes to impose for the violation;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>b</I>) a statement as to the right of the person, within 30 days after the day on which the notice is served, or within any longer period that the Commission specifies, to pay the proposed penalty or to make representations to the Commission with respect to the violation and the proposed penalty, and the manner for doing so; and</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>c</I>) a statement indicating that, if the person does not pay the proposed penalty or make representations in accordance with the notice, the person will be deemed to have committed the violation and the Commission may impose that penalty.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Payment<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>72.7</B> (1) If a person who is served with a notice of violation pays the penalty proposed in the notice, the person is deemed to have committed the violation and proceedings in respect of it are ended.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Representations to Commission<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(2) If a person who is served with a notice of violation makes representations in accordance with the notice, the Commission shall decide, on a balance of probabilities, after considering any other representations that it considers appropriate, whether the person committed the violation and, if it so decides, it may impose the penalty proposed in the notice, a lesser penalty or no penalty.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Failure to pay or make representations<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(3) If a person who is served with a notice of violation neither pays the proposed penalty nor makes representations in accordance with the notice, the person is deemed to have committed the violation and the Commission may impose that penalty.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Copy of decision and notice of rights<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(4) The Commission shall cause a copy of any decision made under subsection (2) or (3) to be issued and served on the person together with a notice of the person’s right to apply for a review under section 62 and to appeal under section 64.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Defence<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>72.8</B> (1) It is a defence for a person in a proceeding in relation to a violation to establish that the person exercised due diligence to prevent the violation.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Common law principles<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(2) Every rule and principle of the common law that renders any circumstance a justification or excuse in relation to a charge for an offence under a relevant provision of this Act applies in respect of a violation to the extent that the rule or principle is not inconsistent with this Act.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Evidence<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>72.9</B> In a proceeding in respect of a violation, a notice purporting to be served under subsection 72.6(1) or a copy of a decision purporting to be served under subsection 72.7(4) is admissible in evidence without proof of the signature or official character of the person appearing to have signed it.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Time limit<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>72.91</B> (1) No proceedings in respect of a violation may be commenced later than two years after the day on which the subject-matter of the proceedings became known to the Commission.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Certificate of secretary to the Commission<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(2) A document appearing to have been issued by the secretary to the Commission, certifying the day on which the subject-matter of any proceedings became known to the Commission, is admissible in evidence without proof of the signature or official character of the person appearing to have signed the document and is, in the absence of evidence to the contrary, proof of the matter asserted in it.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Debt to Her Majesty<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>72.92</B> (1) An administrative monetary penalty constitutes a debt due to Her Majesty in right of Canada that may be recovered as such in the Federal Court.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Time limit<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(2) No proceedings to recover such a debt may be commenced later than five years after the day on which the debt became payable.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Proceeds payable to Receiver General<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(3) An administrative monetary penalty paid or recovered in relation to a violation is payable to and shall be remitted to the Receiver General.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Certificate of default<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(4) The Commission may issue a certificate certifying the unpaid amount of any debt referred to in subsection (1).</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Registration in Federal Court<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(5) When registered in the Federal Court, the certificate has the same effect as if it were a judgment of that Court for a debt of the amount specified in the certificate and all related registration costs.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>How act or omission may be proceeded with<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>72.93</B> If a contravention of this Act or of any regulation, or decision, made by the Commission under this Act can be proceeded with either as a violation or as an offence, proceeding in one manner precludes proceeding in the other.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Section 12 does not apply<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>72.94</B> Section 12 does not apply in respect of any decision of the Commission made under subsection 72.7(2) or (3).</Para></Block><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="BPT_ImprintE">Published under authority of the Speaker of the House of Commons<br/>Available from:<br/>Publishing and Depository Services<br/>Public Works and Government Services Canada<br/>Ottawa, Ontario K1A 0S5<br/>Telephone: 613-941-5995 or 1-800-635-7943<br/>Fax: 613-954-5779 or 1-800-565-7757<br/>publications@tpsgc-pwgsc.gc.ca<br/>http://publications.gc.ca</Para></Block><Block Align="Yes" LineCnt="N"><Para NoLineBreak="Yes" NoHtml="Yes" Leading="0" Size="0" TopMargin="0" BottomMargin="0"></Para></Block></Bill_Part></Bill>
