<?xml version="1.0"?>
<Bill RHead_reign="53-54 Eliz. II" RHead_ParlYear="2004-2005" DocumentTitle="BILL S-27" Bill_No="S-27" Document_No="2538" xml:lang="EN" Bill_Type="Non-amending" Stage_Name="First-Reading-Senate" Reprint="No" xml:space="preserve" ChapterNo_E="C. " ChapterNo_F="ch. " Bill-Origin="senate"><Bill_Part Part_Type="Cover" CountLines="No"><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="CovBillNo">S-27</Para></Block><Block><Para TopMargin="24" Size="9" Leading="10" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0" TextAlign="Center">First Session, Thirty-eighth Parliament,</Para></Block><Block><Para Size="9" Leading="10" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0" TextAlign="Center">53-54 Elizabeth II, 2004-2005</Para></Block><Block><Para TopMargin="48" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0" Bold="Yes" TextAlign="Center">SENATE OF CANADA</Para></Block><Block><Para TopMargin="42" Size="18" Leading="20" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0" Bold="Yes" TextAlign="Center">BILL S-27</Para></Block><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="CovLongTitle">An Act respecting Scouts Canada</Para></Block><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="COV_StageLine"></Para></Block><Block><Para Size="9" AllCaps="Yes" Hyphenate="OFF">first reading, February 17, 2005</Para></Block><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="COV_StageLine"></Para></Block><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="Cover_Sponsors">THE HONOURABLE SENATOR DI NINO</Para></Block><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="Cover_DocNo">2538</Para></Block></Bill_Part><Bill_Part CountLines="No" Part_Type="InsideCover"><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="BPT_InsideCoverE">Available on the Parliament of Canada Web Site at the following address:<br/><B>http://www.parl.gc.ca</B></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><Para TopMargin="108" BottomMargin="4" Size="10" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">SUMMARY</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" Size="8" Leading="9" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">This enactment consolidates and updates the statutes governing the corporation known as the Boy Scouts of Canada in order to reflect more accurately its current status in Canada. It also changes the name of the corporation to “Scouts Canada” and makes other technical and incidental changes relating to the administration of its affairs.</Para></Block></Bill_Part><Bill_Part Part_Type="MainText" CountLines="Yes" RunningHead_E="Scouts Canada"><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="MainText_DocNo">2538</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes"><Para Style="Session_Reign">1st Session, 38th Parliament,</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes"><Para Style="Session_Reign">53-54 Elizabeth II, 2004-2005</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes"><Para Style="MainBillOrigin">senate of canada</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes"><Para Bold="Yes" Style="MAIN@BillNo_Title">BILL S-27</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes"><Para Style="MAIN@ti;04">An Act respecting Scouts Canada</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Preamble<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">WHEREAS the Boy Scouts of Canada (in this Act referred to as the “Corporation”), having its principal place of business in the city of Ottawa, in the Province of Ontario, was incorporated by chapter 130 of the Statutes of Canada, 1914, under the name of The Canadian General Council of the Boy Scouts Association, as a branch of The Boy Scouts Association, which itself had been incorporated in Great Britain in 1912 by a Royal Charter granted in that year during the reign of George V;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">AND WHEREAS The Canadian General Council of the Boy Scouts Association was later renamed the Boy Scouts of Canada, and in French, Scouts du Canada, by chapter 82 of the Statutes of Canada, 1960-61, reflecting the broadening of the scouting movement to enable the development of young people worldwide;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">AND WHEREAS the name in French of the Corporation was later changed from “Scouts du Canada” to “Les Boy Scouts du Canada” by chapter 68 of the Statutes of Canada, 1968-69;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">AND WHEREAS by that same chapter, L’Association des Scouts du Canada was incorporated with its head office in Montreal, in the Province of Quebec, to meet the special needs of the French-speaking Roman Catholic youth in the scouting movement, particularly in the provinces of Quebec, Manitoba and New Brunswick;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">AND WHEREAS L’Association des Scouts du Canada approves of</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">(<I>a</I>) the change of the name of the Corporation to “Scouts Canada” as its corporate name in both official languages, and</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">(<I>b</I>) the repeal of section 1 of chapter 68 of the Statutes of Canada, 1968-69;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">AND WHEREAS the Corporation has set out in its petition that, for the better management of its affairs, it is in the interests of the Corporation that the statutes governing it be consolidated, updated and replaced in order to reflect its current status in Canada and in the international scouting movement;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">AND WHEREAS the Corporation has by its petition prayed that it be enacted as hereinafter set forth, and it is expedient to grant the prayer of the petition;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>1914, c. 130;
1917, c. 73;
1959, c. 71
1960-61, c. 82;
1968-69, c. 68<br/></MarginalNote><Para LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">NOW, THEREFORE, Her Majesty, by and with the advice and consent of the Senate and House of Commons of Canada, enacts as follows:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Corporation continued<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>1.</B> (1) The Corporation created by chapter 130 of the Statutes of Canada, 1914, is continued under the name “Scouts Canada”.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Members<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(2) The Corporation consists of those persons who are members of the Corporation on the coming into force of this Act and their successors as members of the Corporation.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Corporate object<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>2.</B> The object of the Corporation is to promote the mission of scouting among young persons.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Corporate capacity<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>3.</B> The Corporation has the capacity of a natural person and, subject to this Act, all the powers, rights and privileges of a natural person.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Head office<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>4.</B> The head office of the Corporation is in the city of Ottawa, or elsewhere as may be fixed by by-law.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Annual general meeting<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>5.</B> Subject to any by-laws made under section 7, a general meeting of the Corporation shall be held each year in Canada at such time and place as the executive committee may direct.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Executive committee<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>6.</B> At each annual general meeting of the Corporation, the Corporation shall elect an executive committee from among its members, in the manner provided by the by-laws of the Corporation.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>By-laws<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>7.</B> At any annual or special general meeting, the Corporation may make, amend, or repeal by-laws for all purposes of the Corporation and, without limiting the generality of the foregoing, for defining and regulating</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>a</I>) the terms and conditions of membership in the Corporation, and the rights, duties and privileges of all classes of members;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>b</I>) the composition, powers, duties, quorum, term of office, and method of election of the executive committee, and the numbers, powers, and duties of the officers of the Corporation;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>c</I>) the time and place for holding annual and special general meetings of the Corporation, and the notice and other requirements thereof;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>d</I>) the calling of regular and special meetings of the executive committee, the notice to be given thereof, and the quorum and procedure in all respects at or concerning those meetings; and</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>e</I>) the administration and management of the affairs of the Corporation in all respects.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Property holdings<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>8.</B> (1) Without limiting the generality of section 3, the Corporation may, for the purposes of the Corporation,</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>a</I>) receive, acquire, accept, and hold any real property or immovables, by grant, gift, purchase, devise, legacy, lease or otherwise; and</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>b</I>) sell, lease, dispose of, mortgage, invest, or otherwise deal therewith in such manner as it may from time to time deem advisable for those purposes.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>No limitation on real property<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(2) There shall be deemed not to have been in the past any limitation on the annual value of any real or immovable property held by or in trust for the Corporation.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Gifts and grants<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>9.</B> The Corporation may receive and distribute any gift, grant of money, or contribution to the Corporation from the Government of Canada, the government of any province, or any municipality, incorporated body, society, or persons, and shall apply the gift, grant or contribution in accordance with its terms, provisions and conditions, or, if there are no such terms, provisions or conditions, in accordance with the object of the Corporation.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Exclusive title to emblems, etc.<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>10.</B> The Corporation has the sole and exclusive right</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>a</I>) to have and use</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="4" FirstLineIndent="0">(i) all emblems, badges and decorations, and descriptive or designating words or phrases, now or before the coming into force of this Act used by The Canadian General Council of the Boy Scouts Association, The Boy Scouts Association, and Boy Scouts of Canada, and</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="4" FirstLineIndent="0">(ii) the titles “Boy Scouts” and “Scouts Canada”; and</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>b</I>) to have and use any emblem, badge, decoration, and descriptive or designating word or phrase after the coming into force of this Act adopted by the Corporation for carrying out its object, if a statement and description of the emblem, badge, decoration, descriptive or designating word or phrase is filed with and approved by the Minister of the Crown responsible for trade-marks and designs.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Saving existing rights<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>11.</B> (1) The continuation of the Corporation by this Act does not in any way impair, alter or affect the rights or liabilities of the Corporation, nor in any way affect any suit or proceeding now pending, or judgment existing, either by or in favour of or against the Corporation; and any such suit, proceeding or judgment may be prosecuted, continued, completed and enforced as if this Act had not been passed.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Former name<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(2) Any suit or proceeding that might have been commenced or continued by or against the Corporation under its former name may be commenced or continued by or against the Corporation under the name “Scouts Canada”.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote><I>Canada Corporations Act</I><br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>12.</B> Notwithstanding section 158 of the <I>Canada Corporations Act</I>, section 102 of that Act does not apply to the Corporation.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Repeals<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>13.</B> The following Acts or portions of Acts are repealed:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>a</I>) An Act to incorporate The Canadian General Council of The Boy Scouts Association, chapter 130 of the Statutes of Canada, 1914;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>b</I>) An Act to amend An Act to incorporate The Canadian General Council of The Boy Scouts Association, chapter 73 of the Statutes of Canada, 1917;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>c</I>) An Act respecting The Canadian General Council of The Boy Scouts Association, chapter 71 of the Statutes of Canada, 1959;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>d</I>) An Act respecting The Canadian General Council of The Boy Scouts Association, chapter 82 of the Statutes of Canada, 1960-61; and</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>e</I>) section 1 of An Act respecting Boy Scouts of Canada and to incorporate L’Association des Scouts du Canada, chapter 68 of the Statutes of Canada, 1968-69.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Short title<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>14.</B> This Act may be cited as the <I>Scouts Canada Act</I>.</Para></Block><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="BPT_ImprintE"><br/><br/>Published under authority of the Senate of Canada</Para></Block><Block Align="Yes" LineCnt="N"><Para NoLineBreak="Yes" NoHtml="Yes" Leading="0" Size="0" TopMargin="0" BottomMargin="0"></Para></Block></Bill_Part></Bill>
