<?xml version="1.0"?>
<Bill RHead_reign="53-54 Eliz. II" RHead_ParlYear="2004-2005" DocumentTitle="BILL S-33" Bill_No="S-33" Document_No="90322" xml:lang="EN" Bill_Type="Non-amending" Stage_Name="First-Reading-Senate" Reprint="No" xml:space="preserve" ChapterNo_E="C. " ChapterNo_F="ch. " Bill-Origin="senate"><Bill_Part Part_Type="Cover" CountLines="No"><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="CovBillNo">S-33</Para></Block><Block><Para TopMargin="24" Size="9" Leading="10" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0" TextAlign="Center">First Session, Thirty-eighth Parliament,</Para></Block><Block><Para Size="9" Leading="10" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0" TextAlign="Center">53-54 Elizabeth II, 2004-2005</Para></Block><Block><Para TopMargin="48" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0" Bold="Yes" TextAlign="Center">SENATE OF CANADA</Para></Block><Block><Para TopMargin="42" Size="18" Leading="20" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0" Bold="Yes" TextAlign="Center">BILL S-33</Para></Block><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="CovLongTitle">An Act to amend the Aeronautics Act and to make consequential amendments to other Acts</Para></Block><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="COV_StageLine"></Para></Block><Block><Para Size="9" AllCaps="Yes" Hyphenate="OFF">first reading, May 16, 2005</Para></Block><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="COV_StageLine"></Para></Block><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="Cover_Sponsors">THE LEADER OF THE GOVERNMENT IN THE SENATE</Para></Block><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="Cover_DocNo">90322</Para></Block></Bill_Part><Bill_Part CountLines="No" Part_Type="InsideCover"><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="BPT_InsideCoverE">Available on the Parliament of Canada Web Site at the following address:<br/><B>http://www.parl.gc.ca</B></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><Para TopMargin="108" BottomMargin="4" Size="10" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">SUMMARY</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" Size="8" Leading="9" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">This enactment deals with integrated management systems and authorizes the establishment of voluntary reporting programs under which information relating to aviation safety and security may be reported. It also authorizes the designation of industry bodies to certify persons undertaking certain aeronautical activities. Other powers are enhanced or added to improve the proper administration of the Act, in particular powers granted to certain members of the Canadian Forces to investigate aviation accidents involving both civilians and a military aircraft or aeronautical facility.</Para></Block></Bill_Part><Bill_Part Part_Type="MainText" CountLines="Yes" RunningHead_E="Aeronautics"><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="MainText_DocNo">90322</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes"><Para Style="Session_Reign">1st Session, 38th Parliament,</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes"><Para Style="Session_Reign">53-54 Elizabeth II, 2004-2005</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes"><Para Style="MainBillOrigin">senate of canada</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes"><Para Bold="Yes" Style="MAIN@BillNo_Title">BILL S-33</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes"><Para Style="MAIN@ti;04">An Act to amend the Aeronautics Act and to make consequential amendments to other Acts</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">Her Majesty, by and with the advice and consent of the Senate and House of Commons of Canada, enacts as follows:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:AERONAUTICS ACT--><MarginalNote>R.S., c. A-2<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="10" Bold="Yes" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">AERONAUTICS ACT</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>R.S., c. 33 (1st Supp.), s. 1; 2004, c. 15, s. 2(2)<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>1.</B> (1) The definitions “aircraft”, “Canadian aviation document”, “commercial air service” and “Minister” in subsection 3(1) of the <I>Aeronautics Act</I> are replaced by the following:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>“aircraft”<br/>« <I>aéronef</I> »<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0">“aircraft” means any machine capable of deriving support in the atmosphere from reactions of the air, and includes a rocket;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><MarginalNote>“Canadian aviation document”<br/>« <I>document d’aviation canadien</I> »<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0">“Canadian aviation document” means, subject to subsection (3), any licence, permit, accreditation, certificate or other document issued by the Minister under Part I to or with respect to any person or in respect of any aeronautical product, aerodrome, <change>other</change> facility, <change>equipment</change> or service;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><MarginalNote>“commercial air service”<br/>« <I>service aérien commercial</I> »<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0">“commercial air service” means any use of aircraft for hire or reward <change>but does not include use of an aircraft that</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0"><change>(<I>a</I>) is being used for private purposes under a fractional ownership program, or</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0"><change>(<I>b</I>) is operated on a cost-recovery basis and is being used for the conduct of services of Her Majesty in right of Canada or of a province, of an agency of Her Majesty in either of those rights, of other governments, of public organizations that provide services relating to aeronautics in Canada or abroad or of organizations responsible for doing so pursuant to an Act of Parliament or of a province;</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><MarginalNote>“Minister”<br/>« <I>ministre</I> »<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0">“Minister” means</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>a</I>) subject to paragraph (<I>b</I>), the Minister of Transport, and</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>b</I>) the Minister of National Defence — or, under the direction of the Minister of National Defence, the Chief of the Defence Staff appointed under the <I>National Defence Act</I> — with respect to any matter relating to defence, including any matter relating to <change>any of the following:</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="4" FirstLineIndent="0"><change>(i)</change> military personnel, a military <change>aeronautical product</change>, a military aerodrome, <change>any other military</change> facility <change>relating to aeronautics or military equipment</change>, of Canada or a foreign state, and</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="4" FirstLineIndent="0"><change>(ii) a service relating to aeronautics provided by such personnel, by means of such an aeronautical product or such equipment or at such an aerodrome or other facility;</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes">(2) Subsection 3(1) of the Act is amended by adding the following in alphabetical order:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>“fractional ownership program”<br/>« <I>programme de multipropriété</I> »<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0"><change>“fractional ownership program” means a program that conforms with the regulations and in which two or more aircraft are available, subject to certain conditions, for use by the participants in the program, who each own at least part of one of the aircraft;</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><MarginalNote>“instrument”<br/>« <I>texte d’application</I> »<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0"><change>“instrument” means a regulation made under this Act, an order made under this Act by the Minister or a person authorized by the Minister to do so or a notice issued under section 5.1;</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><MarginalNote>“violation”<br/>« <I>violation</I> »<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0"><change>“violation” means a contravention of this Act or of an instrument, a security measure or an emergency direction made under this Act that is designated as a violation by regulations made under paragraph 8(<I>a</I>).</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>R.S., c. 33 (1st Supp.), s. 1<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes">(3) Subsection 3(2) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Other Minister<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><change>(2) Despite paragraph (<I>a</I>) of the definition “Minister” in subsection (1), the Governor in Council may designate any Minister other than the Minister of Transport as the Minister for the purposes of this Act.</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>2.</B> The Act is amended by adding the following after section 3:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:PURPOSE OF THE ACT--><Para TopMargin="10" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center"><change>PURPOSE OF THE ACT</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Purpose<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><change><B>3.1</B> The purpose of this Act is to provide for safe, efficient and environmentally responsible aeronautical activities, by means including</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0"><change>(<I>a</I>) promoting and providing for the safety and security of the public and persons who perform aeronautical activities or work in aerodromes or other facilities relating to aeronautics;</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0"><change>(<I>b</I>) recognizing the responsibility of persons regulated under this Act for the safety and security of their activities;</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0"><change>(<I>c</I>) encouraging the cooperation and participation of persons regulated under this Act and of other interested persons in the development and implementation of modern, flexible and efficient policies, programs and laws for the continuing enhancement of the safety and security of aeronautical activities;</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0"><change>(<I>d</I>) establishing effective and efficient compliance and enforcement processes; and</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0"><change>(<I>e</I>) ensuring that Canada can meet its international obligations relating to aeronautical activities.</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>1992, c. 4, s. 2<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>3.</B> Subsection 4(1) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Application of Part<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>4.</B> (1) Subject to any regulations made <change>under</change> paragraph 4.9<change>(<I>z</I>)</change>, this Part applies in respect of aeronautics to all persons and to all aeronautical products and other things in Canada, to all persons outside Canada who hold Canadian aviation documents and to all Canadian aircraft and passengers and crew members on <change>those aircraft</change> outside Canada.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>R.S., c. 33 (1st Supp.), s. 1<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>4.</B> (1) Section 4.2 of the Act is renumbered as subsection 4.2(1).</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>R.S., c. 33 (1st Supp.), s. 1<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes">(2) Paragraphs 4.2(1)(<I>b</I>) and (<I>c</I>) of the Act are replaced by the following:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>b</I>) construct, operate and maintain aerodromes and, <change>subject to section 10 of the <I>Civil Air Navigation Services Commercialization Act</I>, construct, operate and maintain</change> other facilities <change>relating to aeronautics</change> and establish and provide services relating to aeronautics;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>c</I>) establish and provide facilities and services, <change>subject to section 10 of the <I>Civil Air Navigation Services Commercialization Act</I></change>, for the collection, publication or dissemination of information relating to aeronautics and enter into <change>agreements</change> with any person or branch of government for the collection, publication and dissemination of that information;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>R.S., c. 33 (1st Supp.), s. 1<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes">(3) Paragraphs 4.2(1)(<I>e</I>) and (<I>f</I>) of the Act are replaced by the following:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>e</I>) control and manage aircraft and <change>aeronautical</change> equipment <change>used</change> for the conduct of services of Her Majesty in right of Canada <change>or of a province, of other governments, of public organizations that provide services relating to aeronautics in Canada or abroad or of organizations responsible for doing so pursuant to an Act of Parliament or of a province</change>;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>R.S., c. 33 (1st Supp.), s. 1<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes">(4) Paragraph 4.2(1)(<I>g</I>) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0"><change>(<I>g</I>) provide services relating to aeronautics to Her Majesty in right of Canada or of a province, to other governments, to public organizations that provide services relating to aeronautics in Canada or abroad or organizations responsible for doing so pursuant to an Act of Parliament or of a province, or to international organizations;</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>R.S., c. 33 (1st Supp.), s. 1<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes">(5) Paragraphs 4.2(1)(<I>j</I>) and (<I>k</I>) of the Act are replaced by the following:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>j</I>) cooperate with <change>the</change> aeronautics authorities of other governments or <change>with organizations acting on behalf of other governments, in Canada or abroad,</change> or enter into administrative arrangements with <change>them</change>, with respect to any matter relating to aeronautics;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>k</I>) investigate, examine and report on the operation and development of <change>aeronautical activities</change>;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>R.S., c. 33 (1st Supp.), s. 1<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes">(6) Paragraph 4.2(1)(<I>n</I>) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>n</I>) <change>subject to subsection (3),</change> investigate matters concerning aviation safety <change>or security</change>; and</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes">(7) Section 4.2 of the Act is amended by adding the following after subsection (1):</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Investigations by Minister of Transport<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><change>(2) An investigation carried out by the Minister of Transport under paragraph (1)(<I>n</I>) may not have as its purpose the making of findings as to the causes and contributing factors of an aviation accident or incident.</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Exception — investigations of military-civilian occurrences<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><change>(3) Investigations into military-civilian occurrences within the meaning of Part II shall be carried out in accordance with that Part by the Airworthiness Investigative Authority, designated by the Minister of National Defence under section 11.</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>5.</B> The Act is amended by adding the following after section 4.3:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Subdelegation<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><change><B>4.31</B> Any person whom the Minister of National Defence has authorized to exercise or perform powers, duties or functions relating to airworthiness may, in accordance with the authorization, subdelegate any of those powers, duties or functions to any person under the person’s authority.</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>R.S., c. 33 (1st Supp.), s. 1<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>6.</B> Subsection 4.4(6) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Security for payment of charges<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(6) The Governor in Council may make regulations requiring <change>persons who are subject to</change> charges imposed under this section to deposit each year with the Minister security, in the form of a bond or letter of credit <change>satisfactory to the Minister</change> and in an amount satisfactory to the Minister, to ensure full payment of the charges to be imposed in the next following year.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Default of payment<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><change>(6.1) The Minister may suspend or refuse to issue, renew or amend a Canadian aviation document, or suspend or refuse to grant, renew or amend any privilege accorded by one, if the applicant for or the holder of the document, or the owner, operator or provider, as the case may be, of the aeronautical product, aerodrome, other facility, equipment or service to which the document relates, is in default of payment of any charge owed to the Minister under this section.</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Notice<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><change>(6.2) The Minister shall serve the applicant, holder, owner, operator or provider, as the case may be, with notice of a decision made under subsection (6.1) and, in the case of a suspension, of the effective date of the suspension, which may not be earlier than 30 days after the notice is served.</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Non-application of certain provisions<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><change>(6.3) Subsections (6.1) and (6.2) do not apply to a member of the Canadian Forces acting in the circumstances in the course of their duties in relation to a Canadian aviation document issued in respect of a military aeronautical product, a military aerodrome, any other military facility relating to aeronautics, military equipment, or a service relating to aeronautics provided by means of such an aeronautical product or such equipment or at such an aerodrome or facility.</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>R.S., c. 33 (1st Supp.), s. 1<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>7.</B> (1) Subsection 4.5(1) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Seizure and detention for charges<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>4.5</B> (1) <change>If</change> the amount of any charge and interest <change>on the charge</change> due by a person that has been imposed under section 4.4 has not been paid, <change>then</change>, in addition to any other remedy available for the collection of the amount and whether or not <change>proceedings in respect of it have already</change> been <change>begun</change>, on application to the superior court of the province in which any aircraft owned or operated by the person is situated the Minister may obtain an order of the court, issued on <change>any</change> terms <change>that it considers</change> necessary, authorizing the Minister to seize and detain the aircraft.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>R.S., c. 33 (1st Supp.), s. 1<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes">(2) Subsection 4.5(2) of the English version of the Act is replaced by the following:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Application <I>ex parte</I><br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(2) <change>If</change> the Minister has reason to believe that <change>a</change> person <change>referred to in subsection (1)</change> is about to leave Canada or take from Canada any aircraft owned or operated by <change>them, then the</change> application <change>referred to in subsection (1) may be made</change> <I>ex parte</I> <change>but all the other provisions of that subsection remain unchanged</change>.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>R.S., c. 33 (1st Supp.), s. 1<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>8.</B> (1) The portion of section 4.9 of the Act before paragraph (<I>a</I>) is replaced by the following:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Aeronautics regulations<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>4.9</B> The Governor in Council may make <change>any regulation</change> respecting aeronautics <change>that prescribes anything that by this Part is to be prescribed or that is generally for the carrying out of the purposes and provisions of this Part, including</change> regulations respecting</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>R.S., c. 33 (1st Supp.), s. 1<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes">(2) Paragraphs 4.9(<I>f</I>) and (<I>g</I>) of the Act are replaced by the following:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>f</I>) noise emanating from aerodromes and aircraft <change>and aircraft engine emissions</change>;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>g</I>) the certification of air carriers <change>and other persons that operate aircraft for passenger transportation</change>;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>R.S., c. 33 (1st Supp.), s. 1<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes">(3) Paragraph 4.9(<I>i</I>) of the English version of the Act is replaced by the following:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>i</I>) the conditions under which persons or goods, <change>including</change> personal belongings, baggage <change>and</change> cargo, may be transported by aircraft;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>R.S., c. 33 (1st Supp.), s. 1; 1992, c. 4, s. 7(4)(F)<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes">(4) Paragraphs 4.9(<I>p</I>) to (<I>s</I>) of the Act are replaced by the following:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>s</I>) the keeping and preservation of records, documents and <change>information</change> relating to aerodromes, to activities with respect to aeronautics of persons who hold Canadian aviation documents and to aeronautical products and equipment and facilities used to provide services relating to aeronautics, <change>and the provision to the Minister of the records, documents and information</change>;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>R.S., c. 33 (1st Supp.), s. 1; 1992, c. 4, s. 7(5)<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes">(5) Paragraphs 4.9(<I>v</I>) and (<I>w</I>) of the Act are replaced by the following:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0"><change>(<I>v</I>) measures to mitigate the negative impact of fatigue in respect of the aeronautical activities of crew members, air traffic controllers, persons engaged in the maintenance or installation of aeronautical products or any other person who provides services relating to aeronautics that have a direct impact on aviation safety or security;</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0"><change>(<I>w</I>) a requirement to subscribe for and carry liability insurance on the part of operators of aerodromes, of other facilities relating to aeronautics and of aeronautical equipment, on the part of providers of services relating to aeronautics and on the part of organizations designated under subsection 5.31(1), and the minimum amount of that insurance;</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0"><change>(<I>x</I>) a requirement to subscribe for and carry liability insurance on the part of registered owners and operators of aircraft, if they are not required to subscribe for and carry liability insurance by regulations made by the Canadian Transportation Agency, and the minimum amount of that insurance;</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0"><change>(<I>y</I>)</change> the provision of aviation weather services by persons other than Her Majesty in right of Canada; and</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0"><change>(<I>z</I>)</change> the application of the Convention on International Civil Aviation signed at Chicago, 7 December 1944, as amended from time to time.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>9.</B> The Act is amended by adding the following after section 4.9:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Investigations by Minister of National Defence<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><change><B>4.901</B> The Governor in Council may make regulations respecting investigations carried out by the Minister of National Defence under paragraph 4.2(1)(<I>n</I>), including regulations respecting:</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0"><change>(<I>a</I>) the preservation, protection and removal of an aircraft involved in an accident, of personal belongings, baggage and cargo on the aircraft, of any records relating to the aircraft or its flight and of any part of the aircraft, as well as the testing of any part of the aircraft and the protection of sites of aircraft accidents;</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0"><change>(<I>b</I>) the investigation of any accident involving an aircraft, any alleged contravention of a provision of this Act or of an instrument made under this Act, or any incident involving an aircraft that, in the opinion of the Minister, endangered the safety of persons; and</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0"><change>(<I>c</I>) the taking of statements by investigators for the purpose of an investigation referred to in paragraph (<I>b</I>).</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>1996, c. 20, s. 101<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>10.</B> Subsection 4.91(1) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Regulations<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>4.91</B> (1) The Governor in Council may make regulations authorizing the Minister to make orders directing the ANS Corporation to maintain or increase the level of civil air navigation services <change>that</change> it provides, <change>or introduce a civil air navigation service</change>, in accordance with <change>any</change> terms and conditions <change>that the Minister specifies</change> in the orders. <change>However, the Minister may make an order directing the introduction of a service only if an aeronautical safety study has been carried out and the Minister is of the opinion that the results of the study justify the introduction of the service.</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>R.S., c. 33 (1st Supp.), s. 1; 1992, c. 4, s. 8; 1996, c. 10, s. 204, c. 20, s. 102; 2004, c. 15, s. 8<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>11.</B> Sections 5 and 5.1 of the Act are replaced by the following:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Service — general<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><change><B>5.</B> (1) Subject to subsection (2), all service of notices or other documents required or authorized to be served under this Act shall be by personal service, by registered mail sent to the recipient’s last known address or by any other means prescribed by regulations made under subsection (3).</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Service on Minister<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><change>(2) All service of notices or other documents required or authorized to be served under this Act on the Minister shall be by registered mail sent to the Minister’s office, by the notice or other document being left at the Minister’s office or by any other means prescribed by regulations made under subsection (3).</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Service — regulations<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><change>(3) The Governor in Council may make regulations respecting the service of notices or other documents required or authorized to be served under this Act, including the manner of serving them, the proof of their service and the circumstances under which they are deemed to have been served.</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Restrictions and prohibitions for safety or security purposes<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>5.1</B> The Minister or any person authorized by the Minister may by notice prohibit or restrict the operation of aircraft on or over any area or within any airspace, either absolutely or subject to any exceptions or conditions that the Minister or <change>authorized</change> person <change>specifies</change>, if, in the opinion of the Minister or <change>authorized</change> person, the prohibition or restriction is necessary for aviation safety or security, <change>is necessary for</change> the protection of the public <change>or is in the public interest</change>.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>12.</B> The Act is amended by adding the following after section 5.3:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:Designated Organizations--><Para TopMargin="10" SmallCaps="Yes" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center"><change>Designated Organizations</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Designation<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><change><B>5.31</B> (1) The Minister of Transport may designate, from among organizations that meet the conditions prescribed by regulation, one or more organizations whose activities relate to aeronautics to exercise or perform any of the powers, duties and functions set out in subsection (2). The Minister shall give a designated organization a certificate of designation setting out its powers, duties and functions and the terms and conditions under which they may be exercised or performed.</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Designated organizations<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><change>(2) A designated organization may exercise or perform the powers, duties and functions set out in its certificate of designation, which may be any of the following:</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0"><change>(<I>a</I>) the establishment of standards for the certification of persons undertaking aeronautical activities prescribed by regulation, and the certification of the persons;</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0"><change>(<I>b</I>) the establishment of rules governing the prescribed aeronautical activities; and</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0"><change>(<I>c</I>) the establishment of standards for the issuing of approvals and authorizations for activities that are subject to the rules or any regulations or orders made under this Part, and the issuing of the approvals and authorizations.</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Powers necessary<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><change>(3) A designated organization has all the powers necessary to monitor compliance with the standards and rules that it establishes.</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Certification<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><change>(4) A designated organization that is authorized under its certificate of designation to certify persons undertaking prescribed aeronautical activities may, in accordance with the certification standards that it has established, renew, amend, endorse, suspend or cancel the certification.</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Authorizations and approvals<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><change>(5) A designated organization that is authorized under its certificate of designation to issue approvals and authorizations may, in accordance with the standards that it has established for issuing approvals and authorizations, renew, amend, suspend or cancel the approvals or authorizations.</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Exercise of powers<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><change>(6) The designated organization shall exercise the powers and perform the duties and functions conferred on it in the manner prescribed by regulation.</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Request for review<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><change><B>5.32</B> (1) An applicant for or holder of a certificate, approval or authorization may file a written request with the Tribunal for a review of a decision made by a designated organization under subsection 5.31(2) not to certify them or not to issue them an approval or authorization, or of a decision made by a designated organization under subsections 5.31(4) or (5), within 30 days after the day on which they were served with the notice of the decision or within any further time that the Tribunal allows on application.</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Non-payment of charges<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><change>(2) An applicant or holder may not request under subsection (1) a review of a decision relating to the non-payment of charges imposed under section 5.35.</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Time and place for review<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><change>(3) On receipt of a request filed under subsection (1), the Tribunal shall appoint a time and place for the review hearing and shall notify the designated organization and the person who filed the request of the time and place in writing.</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Review procedure<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><change>(4) The member of the Tribunal assigned to conduct the review shall provide the designated organization and the person who filed the request with an opportunity consistent with procedural fairness and natural justice to present evidence and make representations.</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Determination by member<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><change>(5) The member of the Tribunal may determine the matter by confirming the designated organization’s decision or referring the matter to the Minister for consideration.</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Right of appeal<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><change><B>5.33</B> (1) Within 30 days after the day on which they received notice of the determination made under subsection 5.32(5), the applicant for or holder of a certificate, approval or authorization may appeal the determination to the Tribunal.</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Loss of right of appeal<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><change>(2) An applicant or holder who does not appear at a review hearing may not appeal the determination, unless they establish that there was sufficient reason to justify their absence.</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Disposition of appeal<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><change>(3) The appeal panel of the Tribunal may dismiss the appeal or refer the matter to the Minister for consideration.</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Minister<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><change><B>5.34</B> If a matter is referred to the Minister for consideration under subsection 5.32(5) or 5.33(3), the Minister may confirm, revise or rescind the designated organization’s decision. The Minister’s decision is final.</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Charges<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><change><B>5.35</B> A designated organization may impose on persons — or classes of persons — undertaking prescribed aeronautical activities charges that relate to costs reasonably incurred by the designated organization in the performance or exercise of its powers, duties and functions and that it establishes in accordance with any charging principles prescribed by regulation.</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Consultation<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><change><B>5.36</B> (1) Before establishing or revising a standard or rule referred to in subsection 5.31(2) or a charge referred to in section 5.35, a designated organization shall consult with persons undertaking the prescribed aeronautical activities.</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Publication<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><change>(2) The designated organization shall publish those standards and rules and the amount of any charge on any Internet site that it uses to describe its activities, and shall make all information about the standards, rules and charges available to the public for consultation at its offices.</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Review by the Minister<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><change><B>5.37</B> (1) The Minister may, on application by a directly affected person brought within 60 days after the day on which the amount of any charge referred to in subsection 5.36(2) was published, review the amount of the charge.</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Notice<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><change>(2) The Minister shall as soon as possible notify the designated organization of the application.</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Effect of application<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><change>(3) An application for review does not prevent the charge from becoming effective or prevent the designated organization from imposing the charge pending the outcome of the review.</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Minister’s decision<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><change>(4) After examining the application and any supporting documentation, the Minister may confirm the amount of the charge or direct the designated organization to revise the amount and to refund any overpayment.</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Notification of decision<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><change>(5) The Minister shall as soon as practicable notify the applicant and the designated organization of the decision and provide written reasons for it.</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Compliance<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><change>(6) The designated organization shall comply with the Minister’s decision. If the Minister has directed the designated organization to revise the amount of a charge it need not conduct the consultation referred to in subsection 5.36(1), but shall publish the revised amount in accordance with subsection 5.36(2).</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Decision final<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><change>(7) The Minister’s decision is final.</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Regulations<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><change><B>5.38</B> The Governor in Council may make regulations</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0"><change>(<I>a</I>) prescribing the conditions an organization must meet for the Minister to designate it under subsection 5.31(1);</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0"><change>(<I>b</I>) respecting the manner in which a designated organization is to exercise or perform its powers, duties and functions;</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0"><change>(<I>c</I>) prescribing aeronautical activities for the purposes of section 5.31; and</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0"><change>(<I>d</I>) establishing charging principles for the establishment of charges referred to in section 5.35.</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:Management Systems--><Para TopMargin="10" SmallCaps="Yes" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center"><change>Management Systems</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Regulations<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><change><B>5.39</B> The Governor in Council may make regulations respecting</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0"><change>(<I>a</I>) the establishment and implementation of management systems by holders of Canadian aviation documents to provide for the safety of aeronautical activities and compliance with this Part;</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0"><change>(<I>b</I>) the designation by a holder of a Canadian aviation document of an individual responsible for the establishment and implementation of management systems on the holder’s behalf; and</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0"><change>(<I>c</I>) reviews and audits by holders of Canadian aviation documents of their management systems.</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Order<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><change><B>5.391</B> (1) The Minister may by order require a holder of a Canadian aviation document to enhance its management systems, or to take corrective measures respecting the systems, if the Minister considers that the systems have deficiencies that risk compromising the safety of aeronautical activities.</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Compliance<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><change>(2) The holder of a Canadian aviation document shall comply with the order.</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote><I>Statutory Instruments Act</I><br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><change>(3) The <I>Statutory Instruments Act</I> does not apply to an order made under subsection (1).</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Information confidential<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><change><B>5.392</B> (1) If a holder of a Canadian aviation document has a management system with a process that requires or encourages its employees to disclose to it any thing or circumstance that could present a risk to the safety of aeronautical activities, including the fact that there has been a contravention of a provision of this Act or of an instrument made under this Act, then any information disclosed under the process that comes into the Minister’s possession is confidential, and the Minister shall not disclose it or make it available except in the following circumstances:</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0"><change>(<I>a</I>) a court or other body that has jurisdiction to compel the production or discovery of information orders its disclosure;</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0"><change>(<I>b</I>) the information is disclosed or made available in a form that prevents it from being related to an identifiable person; or</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0"><change>(<I>c</I>) the Minister considers that disclosing the information or making it available is necessary for the purposes of section 7.1.</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Use of information in proceedings<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><change>(2) Information disclosed under a process referred to in subsection (1) may not be used in the taking of any measure, or in any proceedings, against the document holder or the employee who disclosed it for a contravention of this Act or of an instrument made under this Act.</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Information confidential<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><change><B>5.393</B> (1) If an operator of aircraft has a management system with a process for the collection, analysis and use of information derived from a flight data recorder, then any information collected under the process that comes into the Minister’s possession is confidential, and the Minister shall not disclose it or make it available except in the following circumstances:</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0"><change>(<I>a</I>) a court or other body that has jurisdiction to compel the production or discovery of information orders its disclosure;</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0"><change>(<I>b</I>) the information is disclosed or made available in a form that prevents it from being related to an identifiable person; or</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0"><change>(<I>c</I>) the Minister considers that disclosing the information or making it available is necessary for the purposes of section 7.1.</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Use of information in proceedings<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><change>(2) Information collected under a process referred to in subsection (1) may not be used in the taking of any measure, or in any proceedings, against the operator, the operator’s crew members or other persons employed or engaged by the operator for a contravention of this Act or of an instrument made under this Act.</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:Flight Data Analysis Agreements--><Para TopMargin="10" SmallCaps="Yes" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center"><change>Flight Data Analysis Agreements</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Agreements<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><change><B>5.394</B> (1) The Minister, for the purpose of promoting aviation safety, may enter into an agreement with an operator of aircraft respecting the collection, analysis, use and disclosure of information derived from a flight data recorder.</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Information confidential<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><change>(2) Information disclosed to the Minister under an agreement referred to in subsection (1) is confidential and shall not knowingly be disclosed or made available except in accordance with the agreement, unless a court or other body that has jurisdiction to compel the production or discovery of information orders its disclosure.</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Use of information<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><change>(3) Information disclosed to the Minister under an agreement referred to in subsection (1) may not be used in the taking of any measure, or in any proceedings, against the operator, the operator’s crew members or other persons employed or engaged by the operator for a contravention of this Act or of an instrument made under this Act.</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:Voluntary Reporting--><Para TopMargin="10" SmallCaps="Yes" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center"><change>Voluntary Reporting</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Aviation safety and security program<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><change><B>5.395</B> (1) The Minister may establish, in accordance with the regulations, a program to promote aviation safety and security under which a person may report in accordance with the regulations any information relating to aviation safety and security, including the fact that they have contravened a provision of this Act or of an instrument or a security measure made under this Act.</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Designation<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><change>(2) The Minister may designate a person or body to administer, in accordance with the regulations, the program set out in subsection (1).</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Protection<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><change><B>5.396</B> (1) If a person reports a contravention under the program referred to in subsection 5.395(1), they may not, except in the circumstances specified in subsection (2), be found to have committed the contravention in any proceedings under this Act before any court or other body that has jurisdiction to hear the matter.</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Exceptions<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><change>(2) A person does not have the protection of subsection (1) if</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0"><change>(<I>a</I>) the contravention that they committed was</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="4" FirstLineIndent="0"><change>(i) a contravention of this Act, or of an instrument or a security measure made under this Act, that relates to an aviation accident the reporting of which is mandatory under regulations made under section 24.1 of this Act or made under section 31 of the <I>Canadian Transportation Accident Investigation and Safety Board Act</I>,</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="4" FirstLineIndent="0"><change>(ii) an offence set out in subsection 7.3(1) or 7.41(1), or any other contravention of this Act, or of an instrument or a security measure made under this Act, that was committed wilfully, or</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="4" FirstLineIndent="0"><change>(iii) a contravention of any provision that is prescribed by regulation;</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0"><change>(<I>b</I>) within the two-year period before the contravention, they have been found to have contravened this Act, or an instrument or a security measure made under this Act, or they have made use of the protection of subsection (1) in any proceeding before a competent tribunal in respect of a contravention of this Act or of an instrument or a security measure made under this Act;</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0"><change>(<I>c</I>) their employer has a management system established under regulations made under section 5.39 with a process that requires or encourages employees to disclose to their employer any thing or circumstance that could present a risk to the safety of aeronautical activities, and they did not disclose the contravention to their employer in accordance with that process; or</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0"><change>(<I>d</I>) their employer has a security management system established under regulations made under section 4.71 with a process that requires or encourages employees to disclose to their employer any thing or circumstance that could present a risk to aeronautical security, and they did not disclose the contravention to their employer in accordance with that process.</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Use of information<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><change><B>5.397</B> (1) The Minister and any person or body designated under subsection 5.395(2) may, subject to this section, make any use that they consider necessary in the interests of aviation safety and security of any information reported under the program referred to in subsection 5.395(1).</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Information confidential<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><change>(2) Information reported under the program referred to in subsection 5.395(1) that could be related to an identifiable person is confidential and shall not knowingly be disclosed or made available.</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Legal proceedings<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><change>(3) No person may be required, in connection with any legal, disciplinary or other proceedings, to give evidence relating to any information referred to in subsection (2) or to make any oral statement or produce any written statement containing such information.</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Use prohibited<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><change>(4) Information reported under the program referred to in subsection 5.395(1) may not be used against the person who reported it in any legal, disciplinary or other proceedings.</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Regulations<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><change><B>5.398</B> The Governor in Council may, by regulation,</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0"><change>(<I>a</I>) provide for the manner in which the program referred to in subsection 5.395(1) is to be established and administered;</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0"><change>(<I>b</I>) establish, for the program referred to in subsection 5.395(1), the time within which reports are to be made, the manner in which they are to be made and the manner in which they are to be dealt with; and</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0"><change>(<I>c</I>) specify, for the purpose of subparagraph 5.396(2)(<I>a</I>)(iii), contraventions for which a person does not have the protection of subsection 5.396(1).</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>R.S., c. 33 (1st Supp.), s. 1<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>13.</B> The heading before section 5.4 of the Act is replaced by the following:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes"><!--Heading:Aerodrome Zoning--><Para TopMargin="10" SmallCaps="Yes" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center"><change>Aerodrome</change> Zoning</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>1992, c. 4, s. 10(1)<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>14.</B> (1) The portion of subsection 5.4(1) of the Act before the definition “airport site” is replaced by the following:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Definitions<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>5.4</B> (1) <change>The following definitions apply</change> in this section and sections 5.5 to <change>5.85.</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>R.S., c. 33 (1st Supp.), s. 1<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes">(2) The definitions “airport site” and “federal airport” in subsection 5.4(1) of the Act are repealed.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>R.S., c. 33 (1st Supp.), s. 1<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes">(3) The definition “<AltLang xml:lang="fr">éléments</AltLang>” in subsection 5.4(1) of the French version of the Act is repealed.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>R.S., c. 33 (1st Supp.), s. 1<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes">(4) The definition “owner” in subsection 5.4(1) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>“owner”<br/>« <I>propriétaire</I> »<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0">“owner”, in respect of land or a building, structure or object, includes any person — other than a lessee — who has a right, title or interest in the land, building, structure or object, <change>or in the province of Quebec has a real right in it or is a trustee in respect of it</change>;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes">(5) Subsection 5.4(1) of the Act is amended by adding the following in alphabetical order:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>“aerodrome site”<br/>« <I>aérodrome désigné</I> »<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0"><change>“aerodrome site” means any land that is not part of an existing aerodrome, that is declared by order of the Governor in Council to be required for use as an aerodrome and that is either</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0"><change>(<I>a</I>) federal real property or a federal immovable within the meaning of section 2 of the <I>Federal Real Property and Federal Immovables Act</I>, or</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0"><change>(<I>b</I>) the subject of a notice of intention to expropriate registered under section 5 of the <I>Expropriation Act</I>;</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><MarginalNote>“federal aerodrome”<br/>« <I>aérodrome fédéral</I> »<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0"><change>“federal aerodrome” means an aerodrome owned by the federal government and operated either by the federal government or by an airport authority pursuant to a lease;</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes">(6) Subsection 5.4(1) of the French version of the Act is amended by adding the following in alphabetical order:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>« ouvrages »<br/>“<I>object</I>”<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0"><AltLang xml:lang="fr"><change>« ouvrages » Est assimilée à un ouvrage la végétation.</change></AltLang></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>R.S., c. 33 (1st Supp.), s. 1<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes">(7) Subsections 5.4(2) and (3) of the Act are replaced by the following:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Zoning regulation<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(2) The Governor in Council may make regulations for the purposes of</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>a</I>) preventing lands adjacent to or in the vicinity of a federal <change>aerodrome</change> or <change>an aerodrome</change> site from being used or developed in a manner that is, in the <change>Minister’s</change> opinion, incompatible with the operation of an <change>aerodrome</change>;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>b</I>) preventing lands adjacent to or in the vicinity of an <change>aerodrome</change> or <change>aerodrome</change> site from being used or developed in a manner that is, in the <change>Minister’s</change> opinion, incompatible with the safe operation of an <change>aerodrome</change> or aircraft; and</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>c</I>) preventing lands adjacent to or in the vicinity of <change>equipment or</change> facilities used to provide services relating to aeronautics from being used or developed in a manner that would, in the <change>Minister’s</change> opinion, cause interference with signals or communications to and from aircraft, <change>that equipment or</change> those facilities.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Conditions precedent<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(3) The Governor in Council <change>may</change> not make a zoning regulation under paragraph (2)(<I>a</I>) unless</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>a</I>) the Minister, after making a reasonable attempt to do so, has been unable to reach an agreement with the government of the province in which the lands are situated providing for the use or development of the lands in a manner that is compatible with the operation of an <change>aerodrome</change>; or</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>b</I>) in the <change>Minister’s</change> opinion, it is necessary to immediately prevent the use or development of the lands in a manner that is incompatible with the operation of an <change>aerodrome</change>.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>R.S., c. 33 (1st Supp.), s. 1<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>15.</B> Subsection 5.6(1) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Publication of zoning regulations<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>5.6</B> (1) In addition to the publication required by the <I>Statutory Instruments Act</I>, <change>there</change> shall be published <change>as soon as</change> a zoning regulation is made, in two successive issues of at least one newspaper, if any, serving the area to which <change>the zoning regulation</change> relates, <change>either</change> a copy of the zoning regulation <change>or a notice indicating that the zoning regulation has been made and that its text is available at the official Internet site of the <I>Canada Gazette</I></change>.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>R.S., c. 33 (1st Supp.), s. 1; 1992, c. 1, s. 5; 2001, c. 4, s. 54(F)<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>16.</B> (1) Subsections 5.7(1) to (3) of the Act are replaced by the following:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Notice of entry to enforce compliance<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>5.7</B> (1) The Minister may by notice in writing to an owner or lessee who <change>is using lands, or has or is using</change> a building, structure or object on any lands, in contravention of a zoning regulation, advise the owner or lessee that the Minister intends to enter on the lands and take <change>any</change> steps <change>that might</change> be reasonably necessary to prevent the continuation of the contravening use or to remove, alter <change>or destroy</change> the building, structure or object unless, <change>before the</change> date <change>that</change> the Minister <change>specifies</change> in the notice — <change>which may not be</change> earlier than <change>30</change> days after the <change>day on which</change> the notice is served or last published <change>under</change> subsection (2) — the contravening use is permanently discontinued or the building, structure or object is removed, altered <change>or destroyed</change> to the extent described by the Minister in the notice, as the case may require.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Notice to contain statement<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(2) <change>The</change> notice shall</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>a</I>) contain a statement of the provisions of subsection (3); and</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>b</I>) be served on the owner or lessee or, <change>if</change> the Minister is unable to <change>serve the notice</change> after reasonable attempts <change>to do so</change>, be</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="4" FirstLineIndent="0">(i) posted on the land, building, structure or object to which the notice relates, and</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="4" FirstLineIndent="0">(ii) published in two successive issues of at least one newspaper, if any, serving the area in which the land, building, structure or object is situated and in two successive issues of the <I>Canada Gazette</I>.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Objection<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(3) <change>The</change> owner or lessee may, within <change>30</change> days after the <change>day on which</change> the notice <change>is served</change> or last <change>published</change> under subsection (2), serve on the Minister an objection in writing indicating the nature of the objection and the grounds on which <change>it</change> is based.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>R.S., c. 33 (1st Supp.), s. 1; 1992, c. 1, s. 5<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes">(2) Subsections 5.7(5) and (6) of the Act are replaced by the following:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Notice of intentions after objections<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(5) The Minister shall, <change>as soon as possible</change> after providing a full opportunity to be heard to <change>the</change> owner or lessee in relation to <change>the</change> objection, <change>serve notice on them indicating</change> whether the Minister intends to give effect to the objection, and <change>if</change> not, <change>the reasons why not</change>.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Entry<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(6) The Minister may, subject to subsection 8.7(4), enter on lands and take <change>any</change> steps <change>that the Minister considers</change> reasonably necessary to prevent the continuation of <change>a</change> contravening use, or to remove, alter <change>or destroy a contravening</change> building, structure or object, <change>if</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>a</I>) a notice to <change>the</change> owner or lessee under subsection (1) has been served, or posted and published, in accordance with subsection (2);</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>b</I>) <change>no</change> notice of objection by the owner or lessee has been served on the Minister in accordance with subsection (3) or, <change>if one has been</change>, a full opportunity to be heard <change>has been provided</change> to the owner or lessee and the Minister has notified <change>them in accordance with</change> subsection (5) that the Minister does not intend to give effect to the objection; and</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>c</I>) the owner or lessee continues to use <change>the</change> lands, <change>or to have or use</change> any building, structure or object <change>on the lands</change>, in contravention of the zoning regulation in respect of which the notice was issued.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Claims of Her Majesty<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><change>(6.1) The expenses incurred by the Minister in taking steps to prevent the continuation of the contravening use or to remove, alter or destroy any building, structure or object referred to in subsection (1), and all associated costs, are claims of Her Majesty and are recoverable as such against the person referred to in subsection (1) in a court of competent jurisdiction.</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>1992, c. 4, s. 11<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>17.</B> Section 5.81 of the Act is replaced by the following:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Agreements with a provincial authority<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>5.81</B> (1) The Minister may enter into an agreement with a provincial authority <change>authorizing</change> it to regulate the use <change>and development</change> of lands within its jurisdiction for the <change>purposes</change> of</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0"><change>(<I>a</I>)</change> <change>preventing</change> lands adjacent to or in the vicinity of an <change>aerodrome</change> or <change>aerodrome</change> site <change>from being used or developed in a manner that is</change> incompatible with the safe operation of an <change>aerodrome</change> or aircraft; and</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0"><change>(<I>b</I>) preventing lands adjacent to or in the vicinity of equipment or facilities used to provide services relating to aeronautics from being used or developed in a manner that would cause interference with signals or communications to and from aircraft, to and from that equipment or to and from those facilities.</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Procedures for provincial regulations<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><change>(2) The provincial authority may, under the agreement, exercise and administer the power to make regulations referred to in subsection (1) as if the power were within its jurisdiction, and make those regulations in accordance with that province’s applicable procedures for making regulations regulating the use or development of lands.</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Regulations already in force<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><change>(3) If an agreement is made under subsection (1), any regulations made under paragraph 5.4(2)(<I>b</I>) or (<I>c</I>) continue to apply to the lands that are the subject of the agreement until regulations made by the provincial authority for the purposes set out in paragraph (1)(<I>a</I>) or (<I>b</I>) come into force, at which time the corresponding regulations made under paragraph 5.4(2)(<I>b</I>) or (<I>c</I>) cease to apply to those lands for the period in which the agreement is in effect.</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Saving<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><change>(4) During the period in which the agreement remains in effect, subsections 5.4(4) and (5) do not apply in respect of the lands that are subject to the agreement unless the agreement provides otherwise, and sections 5.5 to 5.7 do not apply in respect of those lands at all.</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote><I>Statutory Instruments Act</I><br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><change>(5) The <I>Statutory Instruments Act</I> does not apply to regulations made by the provincial authority under the agreement.</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Contravention<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><change>(6) Every person who contravenes a regulation made by a provincial authority under an agreement made under subsection (1) is guilty of an offence punishable on summary conviction.</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Agreement for cutting natural growth<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><change><B>5.82</B> (1) If natural growth situated on lands adjacent to or in the vicinity of an airport is not subject to a zoning regulation or to a regulation made under an agreement made under subsection 5.81(1), and the Minister considers that the natural growth affects the safe operation of the airport or of aircraft at the airport, the Minister may after consultation with the operator of the airport enter into an agreement providing for the cutting and removal of the natural growth with the owner or lessee of the lands, and with the owner of the natural growth if not the same as the owner of the lands.</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Compensation by the Minister<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><change>(2) The Minister shall pay for the cutting and removal of the natural growth that is affected by the agreement, shall compensate the owner or lessee for any reduction in the value of their interest or right in the lands that results from the cutting and, if the owner of the natural growth is not the same as the owner of the lands, shall compensate the owner of the natural growth for any reduction in the value of their interest or right in the natural growth that results from the cutting.</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Operator of airport to pay<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><change>(3) The operator of the airport shall reimburse the Minister for every expense that the Minister incurs under subsection (2).</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Debts due to Her Majesty<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><change>(4) An amount that the operator of the airport is required to reimburse to the Minister under subsection (3) constitutes a debt due to Her Majesty in right of Canada that may be recovered in a court of competent jurisdiction.</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>If no agreement<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><change><B>5.83</B> (1) If no agreement has been made under subsection 5.82(1) within a period that the Minister considers reasonable, the Minister may serve notice on the owner or lessee of the lands referred to in that subsection, and on the owner of the natural growth on the lands if not the same as the owner of the lands, advising them that the natural growth on the lands affects the safe operation of the airport or of aircraft at the airport, that the Minister intends to enter on the lands in order to cut the natural growth and that the Minister will compensate them for the natural growth’s cutting. The notice shall include a statement of the provisions of subsection (3).</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Time of entry<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><change>(2) The Minister may not enter on the lands earlier than 30 days after the day on which the notice was served and, if the owner or lessee of the lands — or the owner of the natural growth if not the same as the owner of the lands — objects to the Minister’s entering under subsection (3), then the Minister may not enter on the lands earlier than 30 days after the day on which the notice of the Minister’s intention not to give effect to the objection under subsection (5) was served.</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Objection<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><change>(3) The owner or lessee of the lands — or the owner of the natural growth if not the same as the owner of the lands — may, within 30 days after the day on which the notice was served on them, serve on the Minister an objection to the Minister’s entering on the lands or to the Minister’s proposed steps referred to in subsection (1), indicating the nature of the objection and the grounds on which it is based.</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Representations or objections<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><change>(4) On receipt of an objection under subsection (3), the Minister shall, within a reasonable time, provide the owner or lessee who made the objection with a full opportunity to be heard before the Minister concerning the objection’s nature and grounds.</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Notice of intentions after objections<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><change>(5) The Minister shall, as soon as possible after providing a full opportunity to the owner or lessee to be heard, serve notice on them indicating whether the Minister intends to give effect to the objection and, if not, the reasons why not.</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Notices not statutory instruments<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><change>(6) A notice under this section is not a statutory instrument for the purposes of the <I>Statutory Instruments Act</I>.</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Entry on lands<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><change><B>5.84</B> The Minister may enter on lands in order to cut natural growth that affects the safe operation of an airport or of aircraft at the airport if the following conditions are met:</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0"><change>(<I>a</I>) a notice under subsection 5.83(1) has been served in accordance with that subsection; and</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0"><change>(<I>b</I>) no notice of objection has been served on the Minister in accordance with subsection 5.83(3) or, if one has been, a full opportunity to be heard has been provided to the owner or lessee who made the objection and the Minister has notified them in accordance with subsection 5.83(5) that the Minister does not intend to give effect to the objection.</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Compensation by the Minister<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><change><B>5.85</B> (1) The Minister shall pay for the cutting and removal of the natural growth that is affected by the notice, shall compensate the owner or lessee for any reduction in the value of their interest or right in the lands that results from the cutting and, if the owner of the natural growth is not the same as the owner of the lands, shall compensate the owner of the natural growth for any reduction in the value of their interest or right in the natural growth that results from the cutting.</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Operator of airport to pay<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><change>(2) The operator of the airport shall reimburse the Minister for every expense that the Minister incurs under subsection (1).</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Debts due to Her Majesty<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><change>(3) An amount that the operator of the airport is required to reimburse to the Minister under subsection (2) constitutes a debt due to Her Majesty in right of Canada that may be recovered in a court of competent jurisdiction.</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>2004, c. 15, s. 9<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>18.</B> Subsection 5.9(3) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Incorporation by reference<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(3) A regulation, an order, a security measure or an emergency direction made under this Part <change>may</change> incorporate <change>any material</change> by reference<change>, regardless of its source and either as it exists on a particular date or</change> as it is amended from time to time.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Incorporated material is not a regulation<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><change>(3.1) Material does not become a regulation for the purposes of the <I>Statutory Instruments Act</I> merely because it is incorporated by reference under subsection (3).</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>19.</B> The Act is amended by adding the following after section 5.9:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Exemption by Minister of National Defence<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><change><B>5.91</B> (1) With respect to any matter relating to defence, the Minister of National Defence or an officer of the Department of National Defence or an officer of the Canadian Forces authorized by the Minister may, on any terms and conditions that the Minister or officer, as the case may be, considers necessary, exercise any of the powers set out in subsection 5.9(2).</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Exemption from <I>Statutory Instruments Act</I><br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><change>(2) An exemption made under subsection (1) is exempt from the application of sections 3, 5 and 11 of the <I>Statutory Instruments Act</I>.</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>20.</B> The Act is amended by adding the following after section 6.2:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Certificate<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><change><B>6.21</B> A certificate purporting to be signed by the Minister of National Defence or the Chief of the Defence Staff and stating that a notice containing the regulation or notice referred to in paragraph 6.2(1)(<I>a</I>) was given to persons likely to be affected by it is, in the absence of evidence to the contrary, proof that notice was given to those persons.</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>R.S., c. 33 (1st Supp.), s. 1; 1989, c. 3, ss. 39 and 40<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>21.</B> The heading before section 6.3 and sections 6.3 and 6.4 of the Act are repealed.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>R.S., c. 33 (1st Supp.), s. 1<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>22.</B> (1) Subsections 6.5(1) and (2) of the English version of the Act are replaced by the following:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Minister to be provided with information<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>6.5</B> (1) <change>If</change> a physician or an optometrist believes on reasonable grounds that a patient is a flight crew member, an air traffic controller or other holder of a Canadian aviation document that imposes standards of medical or optometric fitness, the physician or optometrist shall, if in his <change>or her</change> opinion the patient has a medical or optometric condition that is likely to constitute a hazard to aviation safety, inform a medical adviser designated by the Minister <change>without delay</change> of that opinion and the reasons <change>for it</change>.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Patient to advise<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(2) The holder of a Canadian aviation document that imposes standards of medical or optometric fitness shall, prior to any medical or optometric examination of his <change>or her</change> person by a physician or optometrist, advise the physician or optometrist that he <change>or she</change> is the holder of such a document.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>R.S., c. 33 (1st Supp.), s. 1<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes">(2) Subsection 6.5(4) of the English version of the Act is replaced by the following:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>No proceedings lie<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(4) No legal, disciplinary or other proceedings lie against a physician or optometrist for anything done by him <change>or her</change> in good faith in compliance with this section.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>2001, c. 29, s. 34<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>23.</B> Sections 6.6 and 6.7 of the Act are replaced by the following:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Canadian aviation document<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><change><B>6.6</B> A reference to the suspension or cancellation of a Canadian aviation document, or to the refusal to issue, renew or amend one, under sections 6.71 to 7.21 may be a reference to the suspension or cancellation of any or all of the privileges granted under one or to the refusal to issue, renew or amend any or all of them.</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Non-application of certain provisions<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>6.7</B> Sections 6.71 to 7.21 do not apply to a member of the Canadian Forces acting in <change>the circumstances in the course of their duties</change> in relation to a Canadian aviation document issued in respect of a military <change>aeronautical product</change>, a military aerodrome, <change>any other military</change> facility <change>relating to aeronautics, military equipment</change> or <change>a service relating to aeronautics provided by means of such an aeronautical product or such equipment or at such an aerodrome or facility</change>.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>2001, c. 29, s. 34<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>24.</B> Subsections 6.71(1) and (2) of the Act are replaced by the following:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Refusal to issue Canadian aviation document<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>6.71</B> (1) The Minister may refuse to issue or <change>to</change> amend a Canadian aviation document on the grounds that</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>a</I>) the applicant is incompetent;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>b</I>) the applicant or any <change>aeronautical product</change>, aerodrome, other facility, <change>equipment or service</change> in respect of which the application is made does not meet the qualifications or fulfil the conditions necessary for the issuance or amendment of the document; or</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>c</I>) the Minister <change>considers</change> that the public interest — <change>which may include considering</change> the aviation record of the applicant or of any principal of the applicant, as defined in regulations made under paragraph (3)(<I>a</I>) — warrants the refusal.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Notice<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(2) The Minister shall <change>serve notice</change> of a decision made under subsection (1) <change>on</change> the applicant, or the owner, operator <change>or provider, as the case may be</change>, of the <change>aeronautical product</change>, aerodrome, other facility, <change>equipment or service in respect of which the application is made</change>. The Governor in Council <change>may</change> by regulation prescribe the form that the notice <change>is to</change> be in <change>as well as</change> information <change>that it is to contain, but in any case the notice</change> shall indicate, as the case requires,</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>a</I>) the nature of the <change>applicant’s</change> incompetence;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>b</I>) the qualifications or conditions referred to in paragraph (1)(<I>b</I>) that are not met or fulfilled;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>c</I>) <change>the elements of the public interest on which the Minister’s decision is based</change>; and</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>d</I>) except in the case of a document or class of documents prescribed under paragraph (3)(<I>b</I>), the date, <change>which shall be 30</change> days after <change>the day on which</change> the notice is served, on or before which and the address at which the applicant, owner, operator <change>or provider</change> may file a request for a review of the Minister’s decision.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>2001, c. 29, s. 34<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>25.</B> Subsection 6.72(1) of the English version of the Act is replaced by the following:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Request for review<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>6.72</B> (1) Subject to any regulations made under paragraph 6.71(3)(<I>b</I>), an applicant, owner, operator <change>or provider</change> who is served with a notice under subsection 6.71(2) and who wishes to have the Minister’s decision reviewed shall, on or before the date specified in the notice or within any further time that the Tribunal <change>allows</change> on application, file a written request for a review of the decision with the Tribunal at the address set out in the notice.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>2001, c. 29, s. 34<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>26.</B> Section 6.8 of the Act is replaced by the following:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Suspensions, etc., generally<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>6.8</B> In addition to any <change>grounds</change> referred to in any of sections <change>4.4</change>, 6.71, 6.9 to 7.1 and 7.21, the Minister may suspend, cancel or refuse to issue, renew or amend a Canadian aviation document in the circumstances and on the grounds prescribed by regulation of the Governor in Council.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>2004, c. 15, s. 12(1)<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>27.</B> (1) Subsections 6.9(1) and (2) of the Act are replaced by the following:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Suspension, etc., where contravention<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>6.9</B> (1) If the Minister decides to suspend or cancel a Canadian aviation document <change>because the Minister has reasonable grounds to believe</change> that the holder, or the owner, operator <change>or provider, as the case may be</change>, of any <change>aeronautical product</change>, <change>aerodrome</change>, other facility, <change>equipment or service</change> in respect of which the document was issued, has contravened any provision of this Part or of any <change>instrument,</change> security measure or emergency direction made under this Part, the Minister shall <change>serve on</change> the holder, owner, operator <change>or provider notice of the</change> decision and of <change>its</change> effective date, <change>which may not be</change> earlier than <change>30</change> days after <change>the day on which</change> the notice is served.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Contents of notice<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(2) The Governor in Council may by regulation prescribe the form that the notice <change>is to</change> be in <change>as well as the</change> information <change>that it is to contain, but in any case the notice shall</change> indicate</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>a</I>) the provision of this Part or of the <change>instrument,</change> security measure or emergency direction made under this Part that the Minister believes has been contravened; and</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>b</I>) the date, <change>which shall be 30</change> days after <change>the day on which</change> the notice is served, on or before which and the address at which a request for a review of the <change>Minister’s</change> decision <change>may</change> be filed.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>R.S., c. 33 (1st Supp.), s. 1<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes">(2) Subsections 6.9(3) and (4) of the English version of the Act are replaced by the following:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Request for review of Minister’s decision<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(3) <change>A</change> holder of a Canadian aviation document, or the owner, operator <change>or provider, as the case may be</change>, of any <change>aeronautical product, aerodrome</change>, other facility, <change>equipment or service</change> in respect of which a Canadian aviation document is issued, who is affected by a decision of the Minister referred to in subsection (1) <change>may</change> file with the Tribunal at the address set out in the notice, and <change>within the period set out in</change> the notice or <change>any</change> further time <change>that</change> the Tribunal <change>allows</change> on application by the holder, owner, operator <change>or provider</change>, a request for a review of the decision.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Request for review not a stay of suspension, etc.<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(4) A request for a review of the <change>Minister’s</change> decision under subsection (3) does not operate as a stay of the suspension or cancellation of the Canadian aviation document to which the decision relates, but <change>if</change> a request for a review has been filed with the Tribunal, a member of the Tribunal assigned for the purpose may, subject to subsection (5) <change>and</change> on <change>any</change> notice to the Minister <change>that</change> the member <change>considers</change> necessary, direct that the suspension or cancellation of the document be stayed until the review of the <change>Minister’s</change> decision has been concluded. <change>However, the member’s direction may be made only</change> on application in writing by the holder of the document or the owner, operator <change>or provider</change> affected by the decision, as the case may be, and <change>only</change> after considering <change>any</change> representations by the holder, owner, operator <change>or provider</change> and the Minister <change>that</change> they wish to make in that behalf.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>2004, c. 15, s. 12(2)<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes">(3) Subsection 6.9(5) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Exception — stay direction<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(5) No direction of a stay of a suspension or cancellation shall be made under subsection (4) if the member of the Tribunal <change>considers</change> that the stay would result in a threat to aviation safety or security.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>R.S., c. 33 (1st Supp.), s. 1; 2001, c. 29, s. 35, par. 45(1)(<I>a</I>) and (2)(<I>a</I>)(F)<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes">(4) Subsections 6.9(7) and (7.1) of the English version of the Act are replaced by the following:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Review procedure<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(7) At the time and place appointed under subsection (6) for the review of the decision, the member of the Tribunal assigned to conduct the review shall provide the Minister and the holder of the Canadian aviation document or the owner, operator <change>or provider</change> affected by the decision, as the case may be, with an opportunity consistent with procedural fairness and natural justice to present evidence and make representations in relation to the suspension or cancellation under review.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Holder, etc., not compelled to testify<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(7.1) In a review under this section, a holder, owner, operator <change>or provider</change> referred to in subsection (1) is not required, and shall not be compelled, to give any evidence or testimony in the matter.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>R.S., c. 33 (1st Supp.), s. 1; 2001, c. 29, s. 36(1); 2004, c. 15, ss. 13(1) and (2)(E)<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>28.</B> (1) Subsections 7(1) to (2.1) of the Act are replaced by the following:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Suspension where immediate threat to aviation safety or security<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>7.</B> (1) If the Minister decides to suspend a Canadian aviation document on the grounds that an immediate threat to aviation safety or security exists or is likely to occur as a result of an act or thing that was or is being done under the authority of the document or that is proposed to be done under the authority of the document, the Minister shall without delay <change>serve notice of the decision on</change> the holder of the document or the owner, operator <change>or provider, as the case may be</change>, of the <change>aeronautical product, aerodrome</change>, other facility, <change>equipment or service</change> in respect of which the document was issued.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Contents of notice<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(2) The Governor in Council may by regulation prescribe the form that a notice under subsection (1) <change>is to</change> be in <change>as well as</change> the information <change>that it is to contain, but in any case the notice shall</change> indicate</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>a</I>) the threat and the nature of <change>the</change> act or thing; and</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>b</I>) the <change>date, which shall be 30</change> days after <change>the day on which</change> the notice is served, on or before which and the address at which a request for a review of the <change>Minister’s</change> decision <change>may</change> be filed.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Effective date of Minister’s decision<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(2.1) The Minister’s decision takes effect on the date of receipt of the notice under subsection (1) by the person on whom it is served, <change>or</change> on <change>any</change> later date <change>that</change> the notice <change>specifies</change>.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>R.S., c. 33 (1st Supp.), s. 1<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes">(2) Subsection 7(3) of the English version of the Act is replaced by the following:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Request for review of Minister’s decision<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(3) <change>A</change> holder of a Canadian aviation document, or the owner, operator <change>or provider, as the case may be</change>, of any <change>aeronautical product, aerodrome</change>, other facility, <change>equipment or service</change> in respect of which a Canadian aviation document is issued, who is affected by a decision of the Minister referred to in subsection (1) <change>may</change> file with the Tribunal, <change>within the period and</change> at the address set out in the notice, a request for a review of the decision.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>R.S., c. 33 (1st Supp.), s. 1; 2001, c. 29, par. 45(1)(<I>b</I>)<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes">(3) Subsection 7(6) of the English version of the Act is replaced by the following:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Review procedure<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(6) At the time and place appointed under subsection (5) for the review of the decision, the member of the Tribunal assigned to conduct the review shall provide the Minister and the holder of the Canadian aviation document or the owner, operator <change>or provider</change> affected by the decision, as the case may be, with an opportunity consistent with procedural fairness and natural justice to present evidence and make representations in relation to the suspension under review.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>2004, c. 15, s. 111(1)<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes">(4) Subsections 7(7) to (8) of the Act are replaced by the following:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Determination of Tribunal member<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(7) The member of the Tribunal conducting the review may determine the matter by confirming the <change>suspension</change> or by referring the matter back to the Minister for reconsideration.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Effect of decision pending reconsideration<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(7.1) If <change>the matter</change> is referred back to the Minister for reconsideration under <change>subsection (7)</change>, the <change>suspension</change> remains in effect <change>pending the conclusion of</change> the reconsideration.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Request for reconsideration<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(8) If</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0"><change>(<I>a</I>)</change> no appeal from a determination under subsection (7) confirming the Minister’s decision is taken under section 7.2 within the time limited for doing so under that section, or</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0"><change>(<I>b</I>)</change> an appeal panel has, on an appeal under section <change>7.2</change>, confirmed the Minister’s decision under this section,</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0">the holder of the <change>Canadian aviation</change> document or the owner, operator <change>or provider affected by the decision, as the case may be</change>, may, in writing, request the Minister to reconsider whether the immediate threat to aviation safety or security that <change>led to</change> the suspension continues to exist or is likely to occur as described in that subsection.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>R.S., c. 33 (1st Supp.), s. 1<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes">(5) Subsection 7(9) of the English version of the Act is replaced by the following:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Reconsideration<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(9) On receipt of a request under subsection (8), the Minister shall <change>without delay</change> reconsider the matter and give a notice of his <change>or her</change> decision to the holder, owner, operator <change>or provider</change> who made the request, and the provisions of this section and section 7.2 providing for a review of a decision of the Minister and an appeal from a determination on a review apply, with <change>any</change> modifications <change>that</change> the circumstances require, to and in respect of a decision of the Minister under this subsection.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>R.S., c. 33 (1st Supp.), s. 1; 1992, c. 4, s. 15(2); 2001, c. 29, ss. 37(1) to (3)<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>29.</B> (1) Subsections 7.1(1) to (2.1) of the Act are replaced by the following:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Suspension, etc., on other grounds<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>7.1</B> (1) If the Minister decides to suspend, cancel or refuse to renew a Canadian aviation document on the grounds that</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>a</I>) the holder of the document is incompetent,</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>b</I>) the holder or any <change>aeronautical product, aerodrome</change>, other facility, <change>equipment or service</change> in respect of which the document was issued ceases to meet the qualifications necessary for the issuance of the document or to fulfil the conditions subject to which the document was issued, or</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>c</I>) the Minister <change>considers</change> that the public interest — <change>which may include considering</change> the aviation record of the holder or of any principal of the holder, as defined in regulations made under paragraph 6.71(3)(<I>a</I>) — warrants it,</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0">the Minister shall <change>serve notice of the decision on</change> the holder or the owner, operator <change>or provider</change>, as the case may be, of the <change>aeronautical product, aerodrome, other</change> facility, <change>equipment or service in respect of which the document was issued</change>.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Contents of notice<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(2) The Governor in Council may by regulation prescribe <change>the</change> form that a notice under subsection (1) <change>is to</change> be in <change>as well as</change> information <change>that it is to contain, but in any case the notice</change> shall indicate</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>a</I>) the nature of the incompetence, the qualifications or conditions that are no longer being met or <change>fulfilled</change> or the elements of the public interest on which the <change>Minister’s</change> decision is based; and</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>b</I>) the date, <change>which shall be 30</change> days after <change>the day on which</change> the notice is served, on or before which and the address at which a request for a review of the <change>Minister’s</change> decision <change>may</change> be filed.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Effective date of Minister’s decision<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(2.1) The Minister’s decision takes effect on the date of receipt of the notice under subsection (1) by the person on whom it is served, <change>or on any later date that the notice specifies</change>.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>R.S., c. 33 (1st Supp.), s. 1<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes">(2) Subsection 7.1(3) of the English version of the Act is replaced by the following:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Request for review of Minister’s decision<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(3) <change>A</change> holder of a Canadian aviation document, or the owner, operator <change>or provider, as the case may be</change>, of any <change>aeronautical product, aerodrome</change>, other facility, <change>equipment or service</change> in respect of which a Canadian aviation document is issued, who is affected by a decision of the Minister referred to in subsection (1) <change>may</change> file with the Tribunal, at the address and <change>within the period set out in</change> the notice or within <change>any</change> further time <change>that</change> the Tribunal <change>allows</change> on application by the holder, owner, operator <change>or provider</change>, a request for a review of the decision.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>R.S., c. 33 (1st Supp.), s. 1; 2001, c. 29, par. 45(1)(<I>c</I>)<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes">(3) Subsection 7.1(6) of the English version of the Act is replaced by the following:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Review procedure<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(6) At the time and place appointed under subsection (5) for the review of the decision, the member of the Tribunal assigned to conduct the review shall provide the Minister and the holder of the Canadian aviation document or the owner, operator <change>or provider</change> affected by the decision, as the case may be, with an opportunity consistent with procedural fairness and natural justice to present evidence and make representations in relation to the suspension, cancellation or refusal to renew under review.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>2001, c. 29, s. 37(4)<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes">(4) Subsection 7.1(8) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Effect of decision pending reconsideration<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(8) If a decision to suspend or cancel a Canadian aviation document is referred back to the Minister for reconsideration under subsection (7), the <change>Minister’s</change> decision remains in effect <change>pending the conclusion of</change> the reconsideration. However, the member, after considering any representations made by the parties, may grant a stay of the decision until the reconsideration is concluded if satisfied that granting a stay would not <change>result in</change> a threat to aviation safety <change>or security</change>.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>2004, c. 15, s. 111(2)<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>30.</B> (1) Subsection 7.2(1) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Right of appeal<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>7.2</B> (1) Within 30 days after <change>the day on which</change> the determination <change>was made</change>, a determination made under subsection 6.72(4), <change>7(7)</change> or 7.1(7) may <change>be appealed</change> to the Tribunal by a person affected, and a determination made under subsection 6.9(8) may <change>be appealed</change> to the Tribunal by a person affected or <change>by</change> the Minister.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>2004, c. 15, s. 111(2)<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes">(2) Subsections 7.2(3) and (4) of the Act are replaced by the following:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Disposition of appeal<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(3) The appeal panel of the Tribunal assigned to hear the appeal may</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>a</I>) in the case of a determination made under subsection 6.72(4), <change>7(7)</change> or 7.1(7), dismiss the appeal or refer the matter back to the Minister for reconsideration; or</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>b</I>) in the case of a determination made under subsection 6.9(8), dismiss the appeal, or allow the appeal and substitute its own decision.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Effect of decision pending reconsideration<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(4) If a decision to suspend or cancel a Canadian aviation document is referred back to the Minister for reconsideration under paragraph (3)(<I>a</I>), the <change>Minister’s</change> decision remains in effect <change>pending the conclusion of</change> the reconsideration. However, the appeal panel, after considering any representations made by the parties, may grant a stay of <change>a</change> decision <change>by the Minister under subsection 7.1(1)</change> until the reconsideration is concluded, if it is satisfied that granting a stay would not <change>result in</change> a threat to aviation safety or security.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>2001, c. 29, s. 38<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>31.</B> Section 7.21 of the Act is replaced by the following:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Default of payment<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>7.21</B> (1) The Minister may suspend, or refuse to issue, renew or amend, a Canadian aviation document <change>if a debt has been certified under subsection 7.9(1)</change> in respect of the applicant for, or the holder of, the document or in respect of the owner, operator <change>or provider, as the case may be</change>, of an <change>aeronautical product</change>, an aerodrome, another facility, <change>equipment or a service</change> to which the document relates, <change>or if they have been convicted of an offence under this Part but have not paid any fine that was imposed within the required period for paying it</change>.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Notice<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(2) The Minister shall <change>serve</change> the applicant, holder, owner, operator <change>or provider</change>, as the case may be, <change>with notice</change> of a decision made under subsection (1) and, in the case of a suspension, of the effective date of the suspension, which shall not be earlier than <change>30</change> days after <change>the day on which</change> the notice is served.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>R.S., c. 33 (1st Supp.), s. 1; 1996, c. 20, s. 103; 2004, c. 15, s. 15<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>32.</B> (1) Subsections 7.3(3.1) to (6) of the Act are replaced by the following:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Punishment — individuals<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(4) An individual who is convicted of an offence under this Part punishable on summary conviction is liable to a fine not exceeding <change>$100,000 or</change>, in the case of an offence referred to in subsection (1), to imprisonment for a term not exceeding one year or to both fine and imprisonment.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Punishment — corporations<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(5) A corporation that is convicted of an offence under this Part punishable on summary conviction is liable to a fine not exceeding <change>one million</change> dollars.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>R.S., c. 33 (1st Supp.), s. 1; 1992, c. 4, s. 16<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes">(2) Subsections 7.3(7) to (8) of the French version of the Act are replaced by the following:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Exclusion de l’emprisonnement<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><AltLang xml:lang="fr">(7) La personne déclarée coupable d’une infraction à la présente partie punissable sur déclaration de culpabilité par procédure sommaire ne peut encourir d’emprisonnement pour cette infraction ni pour défaut de paiement de l’amende imposée, sauf s’il s’agit d’une infraction visée au paragraphe (1).</AltLang></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Exclusion de l’emprisonnement<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><AltLang xml:lang="fr">(7.1) La personne poursuivie en application de l’article 8.4 et déclarée coupable d’une infraction à la présente partie ne peut encourir d’emprisonnement pour cette infraction ni pour défaut de paiement de l’amende imposée.</AltLang></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Recouvrement des amendes<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><AltLang xml:lang="fr">(8) Lorsqu’une personne déclarée coupable d’une infraction à la présente partie ne paie pas l’amende dans le délai imparti, la déclaration de culpabilité, sur présentation devant la juridiction supérieure, y est enregistrée. Dès lors, elle devient exécutoire, et toute procédure d’exécution peut être engagée, la condamnation étant assimilée à un jugement de cette juridiction obtenu par Sa Majesté du chef du Canada contre la personne en cause pour une dette dont le montant équivaut à l’amende.</AltLang></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>1992, c. 4, s. 17<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>33.</B> Section 7.31 of the Act is replaced by the following:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Continuing violation or offence<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>7.31</B> A <change>violation or</change> offence under this Part committed or continued on more than one <change>day constitutes</change> a separate <change>violation or</change> offence for <change>each day on which the violation or offence is committed or continued or, in the case of a violation or offence</change> committed or continued on <change>a</change> flight, for each flight or segment of a flight on which the <change>violation or</change> offence is committed or continued.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>R.S., c. 33 (1st Supp.), s. 1<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>34.</B> Subsection 7.5(1) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Prohibition by court<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>7.5</B> (1) <change>If</change> a person is convicted of an offence under this Part, the court may, in addition to any other punishment it may impose, make an order</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>a</I>) where the person is the holder of a Canadian aviation document or is the owner, operator <change>or provider, as the case may be</change>, of any <change>aeronautical product, aerodrome</change>, other facility, <change>equipment or service</change> in respect of which a Canadian aviation document was issued, prohibiting the person from doing any act or thing authorized by the document at all times while the document is in force or for <change>any</change> period or at <change>any</change> times or places <change>that</change> the order <change>specifies</change>; or</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>b</I>) prohibiting the person from operating an aircraft or providing services essential to the operation of an aircraft for <change>any</change> period or at <change>any</change> times or places <change>that</change> the order <change>specifies</change>.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Return of document<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><change>(2) A person who is subject to an order under paragraph (1)(<I>a</I>) shall, at the Minister’s request, return the document to the Minister for the period of the prohibition.</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>R.S., c. 33 (1st Supp.), s. 1; 1992, c. 4, s. 21; 2001, c. 29, ss. 39, 40(E), 41 and 42; 2004, c. 15, s. 18<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>35.</B> The heading before section 7.6 and sections 7.6 to 8.2 of the Act are replaced by the following:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:Administrative Penalties--><Para TopMargin="10" SmallCaps="Yes" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center"><change>Administrative Penalties</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:Notices of Violation Without Penalty, Assurances of Compliance and Notices of Monetary Penalty--><Para TopMargin="5" Italic="Yes" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center"><change>Notices of Violation Without Penalty, Assurances of Compliance and Notices of Monetary Penalty</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Violation<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><change><B>7.6</B> (1) If the Minister has reasonable grounds to believe that a person has committed a violation, the Minister may</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0"><change>(<I>a</I>) serve on the person a notice of violation without penalty that identifies the violation but indicates that no further proceedings will be taken against the person, and further sets out</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="4" FirstLineIndent="0"><change>(i) the period, which shall be 30 days after the day on which the notice is served, within which a review may be requested, and</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="4" FirstLineIndent="0"><change>(ii) particulars of how to request the review;</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0"><change>(<I>b</I>) enter into an assurance of compliance with the person that</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="4" FirstLineIndent="0"><change>(i) identifies the violation and provides that the person will comply with the provision to which the violation relates during the period, and be subject to the terms and conditions, specified in the assurance,</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="4" FirstLineIndent="0"><change>(ii) sets out the amount and form of any security that, pending compliance with the assurance, must be deposited with the Minister, and</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="4" FirstLineIndent="0"><change>(iii) sets out the amount that the Minister determines in accordance with the regulations that the person would have had to pay as the penalty for the violation if the assurance had not been entered into; or</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0"><change>(<I>c</I>) serve on the person a notice of monetary penalty that identifies the violation and sets out</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="4" FirstLineIndent="0"><change>(i) the amount that the Minister determines in accordance with the regulations that the person must pay as the penalty for the violation,</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="4" FirstLineIndent="0"><change>(ii) the date, which shall be 30 days after the day on which the notice is served, on or before which the penalty must be paid or a review requested, and</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="4" FirstLineIndent="0"><change>(iii) particulars of how the penalty is to be paid or the review requested.</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Extension of period<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><change>(2) The Minister may extend the period specified under subparagraph (1)(<I>b</I>)(i) if the Minister is satisfied that the person with whom the assurance of compliance was entered into is unable to comply with it within that period for reasons beyond their control.</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Short-form descriptions<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><change>(3) The Minister may establish, in respect of any violation, a short-form description to be used in notices of violation without penalty, assurances of compliance and notices of monetary penalty.</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Assurance of compliance complied with<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><change><B>7.61</B> If the Minister considers that an assurance of compliance has been complied with, the Minister shall serve a notice to that effect on the person and, on the service of the notice,</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0"><change>(<I>a</I>) no further proceedings may be taken against the person with respect to the violation; and</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0"><change>(<I>b</I>) any security deposited under subparagraph 7.6(1)(<I>b</I>)(ii) shall be returned to the person.</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Assurance of compliance not complied with<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><change><B>7.62</B> (1) If the Minister considers that a person who has entered into an assurance of compliance has not complied with it, the Minister may serve a notice of default on the person to the effect that, unless there is a determination under section 7.63 or a decision under section 7.68 that the assurance has been complied with,</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0"><change>(<I>a</I>) the person is liable to pay double the amount of the penalty set out in the assurance; or</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0"><change>(<I>b</I>) the security deposited under subparagraph 7.6(1)(<I>b</I>)(ii) is forfeited to Her Majesty in right of Canada.</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Contents of notice<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><change>(2) A notice of default shall include the date, which shall be 30 days after the day on which the notice is served, on or before which a request for review may be filed and particulars of how the request may be filed.</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>No set-off or compensation<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><change>(3) On the service of a notice of default, the person served has no right of set-off or compensation against any amount that they spent under the assurance of compliance.</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Request for review<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><change><B>7.63</B> (1) A person served with a notice of default under subsection 7.62(1) may, on or before the date specified in the notice or within any further time that the Tribunal on application allows, file a request for a review.</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Time and place for review<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><change>(2) On receipt of the request, the Tribunal shall appoint a time and place for the review and notify the Minister and the person who filed the request of the time and place in writing.</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Review procedure<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><change>(3) The member of the Tribunal assigned to conduct the review shall provide the Minister and the person with an opportunity consistent with procedural fairness and natural justice to present evidence and make representations.</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Burden of proof<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><change>(4) The burden is on the Minister to establish that the person did not comply with the assurance of compliance referred to in the notice. The person is not required, and may not be compelled, to give any evidence or testimony in the matter.</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Due diligence not a defence<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><change>(5) A person named in a notice of default does not have a defence that they exercised all due diligence to comply with the assurance of compliance.</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Determination<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><change>(6) The member of the Tribunal may determine the matter by confirming the Minister’s decision or by determining that the person has complied with the assurance of compliance.</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Return of security<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><change><B>7.64</B> Any security deposited under subparagraph 7.6(1)(<I>b</I>)(ii) shall be returned to the person if</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0"><change>(<I>a</I>) the person pays double the amount of the penalty set out in the assurance of compliance in accordance with a notice of default under section 7.62; or</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0"><change>(<I>b</I>) there is a determination under section 7.63 or a decision under section 7.68 that the assurance of compliance has been complied with.</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Deemed violation<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><change><B>7.65</B> (1) A person who is served with a notice of violation without penalty or who enters into an assurance of compliance is, unless a review is requested under subsection (2) or (3), deemed to have committed the violation in respect of which the notice was served or the assurance was entered into.</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Request for review — notice of violation without penalty<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><change>(2) A person served with a notice of violation without penalty may, within the period set out in the notice or within any further time that the Tribunal on application allows, file with the Tribunal a request for a review of the facts of the violation, in which case sections 7.67 and 7.68 apply.</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Request for review — assurance of compliance<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><change>(3) A person who enters into an assurance of compliance may, within 48 hours after the assurance is signed, and unless a notice of default is served within that period under section 7.62, request a review of the facts of the violation, in which case the assurance is deemed to be a notice of monetary penalty served under paragraph 7.6(1)(<I>c</I>) and they are deemed to have requested a review under paragraph 7.66(1)(<I>b</I>) of the facts of the violation and the amount of the penalty.</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Notice of monetary penalty<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><change><B>7.66</B> (1) A person served with a notice of monetary penalty under paragraph 7.6(1)(<I>c</I>) shall</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0"><change>(<I>a</I>) pay the amount of the penalty on or before the date set out in the notice; or</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0"><change>(<I>b</I>) at the address and on or before the date set out in the notice or within any further time that the Tribunal on application allows, file with the Tribunal a request for a review of the facts of the violation or the amount of the penalty.</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>When review of facts not requested<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><change>(2) If a review of the facts of a violation is not requested, the person is deemed to have committed the violation.</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Time and place for review<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><change><B>7.67</B> (1) On receipt of a request filed under subsection 7.65(2) or paragraph 7.66(1)(<I>b</I>), the Tribunal shall appoint a time and place for the review and notify the Minister and the person who filed the request of the time and place in writing.</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Review procedure<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><change>(2) The member of the Tribunal assigned to conduct the review shall provide the Minister and the person with an opportunity consistent with procedural fairness and natural justice to present evidence and make representations.</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Burden of proof<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><change>(3) The burden is on the Minister to establish that the person committed the violation referred to in the notice. The person is not required, and may not be compelled, to give any evidence or testimony in the matter.</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Determination<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><change>(4) The member of the Tribunal may determine the matter by confirming the Minister’s decision or, subject to regulations made under paragraph 8(<I>b</I>), substitute his or her own determination.</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Right of appeal<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><change><B>7.68</B> (1) The Minister or the person who requested the review may appeal a determination made under subsection 7.63(6) or 7.67(4) to the Tribunal within 30 days after the day on which the determination was made.</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Loss of right of appeal<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><change>(2) A party that does not appear at a review hearing may not appeal a determination, unless they establish that there was sufficient reason to justify their absence.</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Disposition of appeal<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><change>(3) The appeal panel of the Tribunal may</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0"><change>(<I>a</I>) in the case of a determination made under subsection 7.63(6), dismiss the appeal or allow the appeal and substitute its own decision; or</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0"><change>(<I>b</I>) in the case of a determination made under subsection 7.67(4), dismiss the appeal, or allow the appeal and, subject to regulations made under paragraph 8(<I>b</I>), substitute its own decision.</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>How contravention may be dealt with<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><change><B>7.69</B> If a contravention may be dealt with as a violation or as an offence or dealt with under section 6.9, proceedings may be commenced in respect of it as a violation or as an offence or it may be dealt with under section 6.9, but dealing with it in one of those three ways precludes dealing with it in the other two.</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Violations are not offences<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><change><B>7.7</B> For greater certainty, a violation is not an offence and, accordingly, section 126 of the <I>Criminal Code</I> does not apply.</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:Recovery of Debts--><Para TopMargin="10" Italic="Yes" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center"><change>Recovery of Debts</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Debts due to Her Majesty<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><change><B>7.8</B> The following amounts constitute debts due to Her Majesty in right of Canada that may be recovered in a court of competent jurisdiction:</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0"><change>(<I>a</I>) unless a review of the amount of the penalty is requested under paragraph 7.66(1)(<I>b</I>), the amount of a penalty set out in a notice of monetary penalty, beginning on the day on which the notice was served;</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0"><change>(<I>b</I>) the amount that a notice of default served under subsection 7.62(1) provides that a person is liable to pay, beginning on the day on which the notice was served;</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0"><change>(<I>c</I>) the amount of a penalty determined by a member after a review under section 7.67 or decided by the Tribunal after an appeal under section 7.68, beginning on the day on which the respective determination or decision was made; and</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0"><change>(<I>d</I>) the amount of any reasonable expenses incurred in attempting to recover an amount referred to in any of paragraphs (<I>a</I>) to (<I>c</I>).</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Certificate<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><change><B>7.9.</B> (1) All or part of a debt referred to in section 7.8 in respect of which there is a default of payment may be certified by the Minister or the Tribunal, as the case may be.</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Judgments<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><change>(2) On production to the Federal Court, a certificate made under subsection (1) is to be registered in that Court and, when registered, has the same force and effect, and all proceedings may be taken on it, as if it were a judgment obtained in that Court for a debt of the amount specified in it and all reasonable costs and charges attendant in its registration.</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:Regulations--><Para TopMargin="10" Italic="Yes" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center"><change>Regulations</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Regulations<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><change><B>8.</B> The Governor in Council may, by regulation,</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0"><change>(<I>a</I>) designate, as a violation that may be dealt with under this section and sections 7.6 to 7.9, the contravention of any provision of this Act or of any instrument, security measure or emergency direction made under this Act; and</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0"><change>(<I>b</I>) prescribe, in respect of a violation, the maximum amount payable, which may not exceed</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="4" FirstLineIndent="0"><change>(i) $50,000, in the case of an individual, or</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="4" FirstLineIndent="0"><change>(ii) $250,000, in the case of a corporation.</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:General Provisions--><Para TopMargin="10" SmallCaps="Yes" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center"><change>General Provisions</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Disclosure of notations of violations<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><change><B>8.1</B> The Minister shall keep a public record of notations of suspension or cancellation of a Canadian aviation document under section 6.9, notations of violation and notations of notices of default under subsection 7.62(1) kept on any record that the Minister keeps respecting a person.</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>R.S., c. 33 (1st Supp.), s. 1; 1992, c. 1, s. 5; 2004, c. 15, s. 19<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>36.</B> (1) Subsections 8.3(1) and (2) of the Act are replaced by the following:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Records<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>8.3</B> (1) Any notation of a suspension by the Minister of a Canadian aviation document under <change>section 6.9, notation of a violation or notation of a notice of default under subsection 7.62(1)</change> shall, on application by the person affected, be removed from the record respecting that person kept by the Minister <change>if</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>a</I>) <change>at any time</change> after <change>the expiry of</change> the suspension, <change>the service of a notice of violation without</change> penalty <change>or notice of compliance or the payment of the amount of the monetary penalty, there has been a period of at least two years in which there has been no notation of a suspension under section 6.9 or violation in</change> respect of that person; <change>and</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>b</I>) in the opinion of the Minister, the removal from the record would not be <change>contrary to</change> the interests of aviation safety or security.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Notice of decision<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(2) The Minister shall, as soon as <change>possible</change> after <change>receiving</change> the application, <change>serve a notice on</change> the applicant of the <change>Minister’s</change> decision in relation <change>to the application</change>.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes">(2) Section 8.3 of the Act is amended by adding the following after subsection (4):</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Minister’s decision overturned<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><change>(5) The Minister shall remove from the affected person’s record any notation of a decision relating to a Canadian aviation document, of a violation or of a notice of default under subsection 7.62(1), as the case may be, in any of the following cases:</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0"><change>(<I>a</I>) a member of the Tribunal has substituted his or her determination for the Minister’s on review under subsection 6.9(8) or 7.67(4), as the case may be, with regard to whether the contravention or violation was committed, and the period for an appeal has expired;</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0"><change>(<I>b</I>) a member of the Tribunal has determined that the person has complied with an assurance of compliance under subsection 7.63(6), and the period for an appeal has expired;</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0"><change>(<I>c</I>) the Tribunal has on appeal substituted its decision for the Minister’s with regard to whether the contravention or violation was committed, or with regard to whether the assurance of compliance referred to in subsection 7.62(1) has been complied with; or</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0"><change>(<I>d</I>) the Minister has rescinded the decision on reconsideration of the matter.</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>R.S., c. 33 (1st Supp.), s. 1; 2004, c. 15, s. 20<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>37.</B> Sections 8.4 and 8.5 of the Act are replaced by the following:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Owner of aircraft may be found liable<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>8.4</B> (1) The registered owner of an aircraft may be proceeded against in respect of, and found to have committed, <change>a violation or</change> offence under this Part in relation to the aircraft for which another person is subject to be proceeded against unless, at the time of the <change>violation or</change> offence, the aircraft was in the possession of a person other than the owner without the owner’s consent, and, <change>if</change> found to have committed the <change>violation or</change> offence, the owner is liable to the penalty provided as punishment <change>for it</change>.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Operator of aircraft may be found liable<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(2) The operator of an aircraft may be proceeded against in respect of, and found to have committed, <change>a violation or</change> offence under this Part in relation to the aircraft for which another person is subject to be proceeded against unless, at the time of the <change>violation or</change> offence, the aircraft was in the possession of a person other than the operator without the operator’s consent, and, <change>if</change> found to have committed the <change>violation or</change> offence, the operator is liable to the penalty provided as punishment <change>for it</change>.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Pilot-in-command may be found liable<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(3) The pilot-in-command of an aircraft may be proceeded against in respect of, and found to have committed, <change>a violation or</change> offence under this Part in relation to the aircraft for which another person is subject to be proceeded against unless the <change>violation or</change> offence was committed without the consent of the pilot-in-command, and, <change>if</change> found to have committed the <change>violation or</change> offence, the pilot-in-command is liable to the penalty provided as punishment <change>for it</change>.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Operator of aerodrome, etc., may be found liable<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(4) The operator of an aerodrome or other facility <change>relating to aeronautics</change> may be proceeded against in respect of, and found to have committed, <change>a violation or</change> offence under this Part in relation to the aerodrome or <change>other</change> facility for which another person is subject to be proceeded against unless the <change>violation or</change> offence was committed without the consent of the operator, and, <change>if</change> found to have committed the <change>violation or</change> offence, the operator is liable to the penalty provided as punishment <change>for it</change>.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Provider of service may be found liable<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><change>(5) The provider of a service relating to aeronautics may be proceeded against in respect of, and found to have committed, a violation or offence under this Part in relation to the service for which another person is subject to be proceeded against unless the violation or offence was committed without the consent of the provider, and, if found to have committed the violation or offence, the provider is liable to the penalty provided as punishment for it.</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Defence<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>8.5</B> No person <change>may</change> be found to have contravened a provision of this Part or <change>of</change> any <change>instrument,</change> security measure or emergency direction made under this Part<change>, other than a provision set out in subsection 7.3(1) or 7.41(1),</change> if <change>they</change> exercised all due diligence to prevent the contravention.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>R.S., c. 33 (1st Supp.), s. 1; 2004, c. 15, s. 21(1)<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>38.</B> (1) Subsection 8.7(1) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Powers to enter, seize and detain<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>8.7</B> (1) Subject to subsection (4), the Minister may</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>a</I>) enter, for the purposes of making inspections or audits relating to <change>compliance</change> with this Part, any aircraft, aerodrome or other facility <change>relating to aeronautics</change>, any premises used for the design, manufacture, distribution, maintenance or installation of aeronautical products or any premises used by the Canadian Air Transport Security Authority, regardless of whether the inspection or audit relates to that place or to the person who possesses or controls it;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>a.1</I>) remove any document or other thing from the place where the inspection or audit is being carried out for examination or copying;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>b</I>) enter any place for the purposes of an investigation of matters concerning aviation safety <change>or security</change>;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>c</I>) seize anything found in any place referred to in paragraph (<I>a</I>) or (<I>b</I>) that the Minister believes on reasonable grounds <change>might be</change> evidence with respect to a <change>contravention of</change> this Part or <change>of an instrument, a security measure or an emergency direction made under this Part</change>; and</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>d</I>) detain any aircraft that the Minister believes on reasonable grounds is unsafe or is likely to be operated in an unsafe manner <change>or without the Canadian aviation documents required for the lawful operation of the aircraft,</change> and take reasonable steps to ensure its continued detention.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Matters relating to Defence<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><change>(1.01) The Minister of Transport may exercise the powers set out in subsection (1) with regard to any matter relating to defence with the authorization of the Minister of National Defence.</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>2004, c. 15, s. 21(2)<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes">(2) Paragraph 8.7(1.1)(<I>a</I>) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>a</I>) use or cause to be used any computer system, data processing system <change>or other electronic system</change> at the place to examine any data contained in, or available to, the system;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>R.S., c. 33 (1st Supp.), s. 1<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes">(3) Subsection 8.7(2) of the French version of the Act is replaced by the following:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Mandats<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><AltLang xml:lang="fr">(2) Les articles 487 à 492 du <I>Code criminel</I> s’appliquent aux infractions — prétendues ou commises — à la présente partie.</AltLang></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>2004, c. 15, s. 22<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>39.</B> Paragraph 8.8(<I>b</I>) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>b</I>) provide the Minister with any information relevant to the administration of this <change>Part and</change> the <change>instruments</change>, security measures or emergency directions made under this Part that the Minister <change>might</change> reasonably require.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>40.</B> The Act is amended by adding the following after section 8.8:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Application of <I>Canadian Transportation Accident Investigation and Safety Board Act</I><br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><change><B>8.9</B> The provisions of section 28 of the <I>Canadian Transportation Accident Investigation and Safety Board Act</I> relating to on-board recordings — within the meaning of that section — originating from the flight deck of an aircraft, or received on or in the flight deck of an aircraft, apply with any necessary modifications in respect of an investigation by the Minister concerning aviation safety or security.</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>41.</B> The Act is amended by adding the following after section 9:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><Para TopMargin="10" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center"><change>PART II</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:MILITARY INVESTIGATIONS INVOLVING CIVILIANS--><Para TopMargin="5" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center"><change>MILITARY INVESTIGATIONS INVOLVING CIVILIANS</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:Interpretation--><Para TopMargin="5" SmallCaps="Yes" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center"><change>Interpretation</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Definitions<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><change><B>10.</B> (1) The following definitions apply in this Part.</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><MarginalNote>“civilian”<br/>« <I>civil</I> »<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0"><change>“civilian” means a person who is not subject to the Code of Service Discipline set out in Part III of the <I>National Defence Act</I>, or who is subject to the Code of Service Discipline but in the circumstances is not acting in the course of their duties.</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><MarginalNote>“department”<br/>« <I>ministère</I> »<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0"><change>“department” means</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0"><change>(<I>a</I>) any department of the Government of Canada, including the minister responsible for it and any person acting on behalf of that minister;</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0"><change>(<I>b</I>) any body listed in the schedule to the <I>Canadian Transportation Accident Investigation and Safety Board Act</I>; and</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0"><change>(<I>c</I>) any fact-finding authority, body or person established or appointed by such a department, minister, person or body.</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><MarginalNote>“military- civilian occurrence”<br/>« <I>accident militaro-civil</I> »<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0"><change>“military-civilian occurrence” means</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0"><change>(<I>a</I>) any accident or incident involving</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="4" FirstLineIndent="0"><change>(i) an aircraft operated by or on behalf of the Department of National Defence, the Canadian Forces or a visiting force, or an installation operated by or on behalf of any of the above that is designed or used to manufacture an aircraft or other aeronautical product, or that is being used for the operation or maintenance of an aircraft or other aeronautical product, and</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="4" FirstLineIndent="0"><change>(ii) a civilian; or</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0"><change>(<I>b</I>) any situation or condition that the Airworthiness Investigative Authority has reasonable grounds to believe could, if left unattended, induce an accident or incident described in paragraph (<I>a</I>).</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><MarginalNote>“visiting force”<br/>« <I>force étrangère présente au Canada</I> »<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0"><change>“visiting force” means a visiting force as defined in section 2 of the <I>Visiting Forces Act</I>.</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Application<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><change>(2) This section and sections 11 to 24.6 apply in respect of military-civilian occurrences</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0"><change>(<I>a</I>) in or over Canada;</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0"><change>(<I>b</I>) in or over any place that is under Canadian air traffic control; and</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0"><change>(<I>c</I>) in or over any other place in any of the following cases:</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="4" FirstLineIndent="0"><change>(i) Canada is requested to investigate the occurrence by an appropriate authority,</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="4" FirstLineIndent="0"><change>(ii) the civilians involved are employed in that place by the Department of National Defence or by the Canadian Forces, or</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="4" FirstLineIndent="0"><change>(iii) the civilians involved are in Canada.</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:Airworthiness Investigative Authority--><Para TopMargin="10" SmallCaps="Yes" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center"><change>Airworthiness Investigative Authority</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Airworthiness Investigative Authority<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><change><B>11.</B> (1) The Minister shall designate from among the members of the Canadian Forces or the employees of the Department of National Defence an individual to be the Airworthiness Investigative Authority, who is to be responsible for advancing aviation safety by</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0"><change>(<I>a</I>) investigating military-civilian occurrences in order to find their causes and contributing factors;</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0"><change>(<I>b</I>) identifying safety deficiencies as evidenced by military-civilian occurrences;</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0"><change>(<I>c</I>) making recommendations designed to eliminate or reduce any of those safety deficiencies; and</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0"><change>(<I>d</I>) publishing reports on the investigations and the findings in relation to them.</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Restriction<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><change>(2) In making findings in an investigation of a military-civilian occurrence, it is not the Airworthiness Investigative Authority’s function to assign fault or determine civil or criminal liability, but the Airworthiness Investigative Authority shall not refrain from making a full report merely because fault or liability might be inferred from the Airworthiness Investigative Authority’s findings.</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Restriction<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><change>(3) No finding of the Airworthiness Investigative Authority may be construed as assigning fault or determining civil or criminal liability.</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Findings not binding<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><change>(4) The Airworthiness Investigative Authority’s findings are not binding on the parties to any legal, disciplinary or other proceedings.</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:Investigations of Military-Civilian Occurrences--><Para TopMargin="10" SmallCaps="Yes" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center"><change>Investigations of Military-Civilian Occurrences</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:Investigations--><Para TopMargin="5" Italic="Yes" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center"><change>Investigations</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Investigators<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><change><B>12.</B> (1) The Airworthiness Investigative Authority may act as an investigator under this Part with respect to a military-civilian occurrence, and may designate as an investigator to investigate such an occurrence in accordance with this Part on the Airworthiness Investigative Authority’s behalf any person, or member of a class of persons, that the Airworthiness Investigative Authority considers qualified.</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Certificate<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><change>(2) The Airworthiness Investigative Authority shall give a designated investigator a certificate specifying the terms and conditions of their designation.</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Report<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><change>(3) A designated investigator shall report to the Airworthiness Investigative Authority with respect to the investigation of a military-civilian occurrence.</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Definitions<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><change><B>13.</B> (1) The following definitions apply in this section.</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><MarginalNote>“information”<br/>« <I>renseignement</I> »<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0"><change>“information” includes a record regardless of form and a copy of a record.</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><MarginalNote>“place”<br/>« <I>lieu</I> »<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0"><change>“place” includes an aircraft, any premises and any building or other structure erected on those premises.</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Powers of investigators<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><change>(2) If an investigator believes on reasonable grounds that there is or might be, at or in any place, any thing relevant to the investigation of a military-civilian occurrence, the investigator may, subject to subsection (3), enter and search that place for such a thing, and seize any such thing that is found in the course of that search.</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Conditions for exercise of powers<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><change>(3) An investigator shall not exercise the powers referred to in subsection (2) in relation to a particular place without the consent of the person apparently in charge of that place unless</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0"><change>(<I>a</I>) those powers are exercised under the authority of a warrant; or</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0"><change>(<I>b</I>) by reason of exigent circumstances, it would not be practical for the investigator to obtain a warrant.</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Warrant<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><change>(4) If a justice of the peace is satisfied by information on oath that an investigator believes on reasonable grounds that there is or might be, at or in any place, any thing relevant to the investigation of a military-civilian occurrence, the justice may, on <I>ex parte</I> application, issue a warrant signed by the justice authorizing the investigator to enter and search that place for such a thing and to seize any such thing that is found in the course of that search.</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Warrants may be obtained by telephone, etc.<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><change>(5) The procedure set out in section 487.1 of the <I>Criminal Code</I> applies in relation to the obtaining of warrants under this section, subject to regulations made under paragraph 24.4(1)(<I>g</I>).</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Power to test things seized, etc.<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><change>(6) If any thing is seized by an investigator under subsection (2), the investigator</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0"><change>(<I>a</I>) may, subject to paragraph (<I>b</I>), cause to be conducted on the thing any tests, including tests to destruction, that are necessary for the purposes of the investigation;</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0"><change>(<I>b</I>) shall, to the extent practical and safe to do so without unreasonably impeding the progress of the investigation,</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="4" FirstLineIndent="0"><change>(i) take all reasonable measures to invite the owner of the thing, and any person who appears on reasonable grounds to be entitled to it, to be present at such tests, and</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="4" FirstLineIndent="0"><change>(ii) allow them to be present at those tests; and</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0"><change>(<I>c</I>) subject to the need to conduct such tests, shall cause the thing to be preserved pending its return under section 15.</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Power to exclude persons from particular areas<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><change>(7) An investigator may, in the course of an investigation of a military-civilian occurrence, and for the purposes of preserving and protecting any thing involved or likely to have been involved, whether or not the thing has been seized under this section, prohibit or limit access to the area immediately surrounding the place at which the thing is located for any period that is necessary for the purposes of the investigation.</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Disruption to be minimized<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><change>(8) In exercising the power conferred by subsection (7), an investigator shall have regard to the desirability of minimizing any resulting disruption to transportation services.</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Offence in respect of exclusion order<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><change>(9) No person shall knowingly enter an area in contravention of a prohibition or limitation of access under subsection (7).</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Additional powers of investigators<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><change>(10) An investigator may do any of the following by notice signed by them, if their belief is based on reasonable grounds:</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0"><change>(<I>a</I>) if the investigator believes that a person has information relevant to an investigation,</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="4" FirstLineIndent="0"><change>(i) require the person to produce the information to the investigator or to attend before the investigator and give a statement referred to in section 24, under oath or solemn affirmation if required by the investigator, and</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="4" FirstLineIndent="0"><change>(ii) make any copies of and take any extracts from the information that the investigator considers necessary for the purposes of the investigation;</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0"><change>(<I>b</I>) require a person who is directly or indirectly involved in the operation of an aircraft to submit to a medical examination, if the investigator believes that the examination is or might be relevant to the investigation;</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0"><change>(<I>c</I>) require a physician or practitioner to provide information concerning a patient to the investigator, if the investigator believes that the information is or might be relevant to the investigation; or</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0"><change>(<I>d</I>) require the person who has custody of the body of a deceased person or other human remains to permit the performance of an autopsy on the body or another medical examination on the remains, and cause it to be performed, if the investigator believes that the autopsy or other medical examination is or might be relevant to the investigation.</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Offence — paragraph (10)(<I>a</I>), (<I>c</I>) or (<I>d</I>)<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><change>(11) No person shall refuse or fail to produce information to an investigator, or to attend before an investigator and give a statement, in accordance with a requirement imposed under paragraph (10)(<I>a</I>), to provide information in accordance with a requirement imposed under paragraph (10)(<I>c</I>) or to make the body of a deceased person or other human remains available for the performance of an autopsy or medical examination in accordance with a requirement imposed under paragraph (10)(<I>d</I>).</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Offence — paragraph (10)(<I>b</I>)<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><change>(12) No person shall refuse or fail to submit to a medical examination in accordance with a requirement imposed under paragraph (10)(<I>b</I>), but information obtained as a result of such an examination is privileged and, subject to the Airworthiness Investigative Authority’s power to make any use of it that the Airworthiness Investigative Authority considers necessary in the interests of aviation safety, no person shall knowingly communicate it or permit it to be communicated to any person.</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Legal proceedings<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><change>(13) No person may be required to produce information referred to in subsection (12) or to give evidence relating to it in any legal, disciplinary or other proceedings.</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Certificate to be produced<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><change>(14) Before acting under this section, an investigator shall, on request, produce their certificate of designation to any person in relation to whom the investigator acts.</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Meaning of medical examination<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><change>(15) The requirement under paragraph (10)(<I>b</I>) that a person submit to a medical examination does not require the person to submit to any procedure involving surgery, perforation of the skin or any external tissue or the entry into the body of any drug or foreign substance.</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Things seized<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><change>(16) For greater certainty, a thing seized under subsection (2) may be an aircraft or part of one.</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Use of force<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><change>(17) In executing a warrant under this section, an investigator shall not use force unless the investigator is accompanied by a peace officer and the use of force is specifically authorized in the warrant.</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Failure to produce document, etc.<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><change>(18) If an investigator has required a person to do something under paragraph (10)(<I>a</I>), (<I>b</I>), (<I>c</I>) or (<I>d</I>) and the person has refused or failed to do as required, the investigator may make an application to the Federal Court or a superior court of a province setting out the facts, and the court may inquire into the matter and, after giving the person an opportunity to comply with the requirement, take steps for their punishment as if they had been guilty of contempt of the court, or may make any other order that it finds appropriate.</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Limitation<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><change><B>14.</B> An investigator may exercise the powers granted under section 13 only in respect of a civilian.</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Return of seized property<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><change><B>15.</B> (1) Anything seized under section 13 — except on-board recordings as defined in subsection 22(1) — shall, as soon as possible after it has served the purpose for which it was seized, be returned to the owner or the person who appears on reasonable grounds to be entitled to it, or to the person from whom it was seized, unless</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0"><change>(<I>a</I>) the owner or the person who appears on reasonable grounds to be entitled to it consents otherwise in writing; or</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0"><change>(<I>b</I>) a court of competent jurisdiction orders otherwise.</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Application for return<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><change>(2) A person from whom anything was seized under section 13 — except on-board recordings as defined in subsection 22(1) — or the owner or any other person who appears on reasonable grounds to be entitled to it may apply to a court of competent jurisdiction for an order that the seized thing be returned to them.</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Order for return<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><change>(3) If, on an application under subsection (2), the court is satisfied that the seized thing has served the purpose for which it was seized or should, in the interests of justice, be returned to the applicant, the court may grant the application and order the seized thing to be returned to the applicant, subject to any terms or conditions that appear necessary or desirable to ensure that the thing is safeguarded and preserved for any purpose for which it might subsequently be required by the Airworthiness Investigative Authority under this Act.</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Exception<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><change>(4) This section does not apply in respect of anything seized and tested to destruction in accordance with subsection 13(6).</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:Administration--><Para TopMargin="10" Italic="Yes" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center"><change>Administration</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Notification of Airworthiness Investigative Authority<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><change><B>16.</B> (1) If a department is notified of a military-civilian occurrence, the department shall</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0"><change>(<I>a</I>) immediately provide the Airworthiness Investigative Authority with particulars of the occurrence; and</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0"><change>(<I>b</I>) as soon as possible after complying with paragraph (<I>a</I>), advise the Airworthiness Investigative Authority of any investigation that it plans to conduct and of any remedial measures that it plans to take.</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Investigator as observer<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><change>(2) An investigator authorized by the Airworthiness Investigative Authority may attend as an observer at an investigation conducted by the department or during the taking of remedial measures by the department following a military-civilian occurrence.</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Airworthiness Investigative Authority may review and comment<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><change>(3) Subject to any other Act or law, the Airworthiness Investigative Authority shall, on request, be provided with, and may review and comment on, any interim or final report prepared in respect of an investigation conducted by the department.</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Notification by Airworthiness Investigative Authority<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><change><B>17.</B> (1) If the Airworthiness Investigative Authority is notified of a military-civilian occurrence, the Airworthiness Investigative Authority shall</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0"><change>(<I>a</I>) immediately provide particulars of the occurrence to any minister responsible for a department that has a direct interest in the occurrence; and</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0"><change>(<I>b</I>) as soon as possible after complying with paragraph (<I>a</I>), advise the ministers referred to in paragraph (<I>a</I>) of any investigation that the Airworthiness Investigative Authority plans to conduct and of its scope.</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Observers<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><change>(2) Subject to any conditions that the Airworthiness Investigative Authority imposes, a person may attend as an observer at an investigation of a military-civilian occurrence conducted by the Airworthiness Investigative Authority if the person</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0"><change>(<I>a</I>) is designated as an observer by the minister responsible for a department that has a direct interest in the subject-matter of the investigation;</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0"><change>(<I>b</I>) has observer status or is an accredited representative or an adviser to an accredited representative, pursuant to an international agreement or convention relating to transportation to which Canada is a party; or</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0"><change>(<I>c</I>) is invited by the Airworthiness Investigative Authority to attend as an observer because, in the Airworthiness Investigative Authority’s opinion, the person has a direct interest in the subject-matter of the investigation and is likely to contribute to achieving its object.</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Observer may be removed<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><change>(3) The Airworthiness Investigative Authority may remove an observer from an investigation if the observer contravenes a condition imposed by the Airworthiness Investigative Authority on the observer’s presence or if, in the Airworthiness Investigative Authority’s opinion, the observer’s participation is likely to create a situation of conflict of interest that will impede the conduct of the investigation.</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Report made public<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><change><B>18.</B> (1) On completion of an investigation, the Airworthiness Investigative Authority shall prepare and make available to the public a report on the Airworthiness Investigative Authority’s findings, including any safety deficiencies that the Airworthiness Investigative Authority has identified and any recommendations that the Airworthiness Investigative Authority considers appropriate and that relate to aviation safety.</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Representations on draft report<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><change>(2) Before publishing a report under subsection (1), the Airworthiness Investigative Authority shall, on a confidential basis, send a copy of the draft report on the investigation’s findings and any safety deficiencies identified to each minister responsible for a department that has a direct interest in the findings, as well as to any other person who, in the Airworthiness Investigative Authority’s opinion, has a direct interest in the findings, and shall give that minister or other person a reasonable opportunity to make representations to the Airworthiness Investigative Authority with respect to the draft report before the final report is prepared.</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Confidentiality of draft report<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><change>(3) No person shall communicate or use the draft report, or permit its communication or use, for any purpose — other than the taking of remedial measures — that is not strictly necessary to the study of the draft report or to the preparation of representations concerning it.</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Manner of dealing with representations<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><change>(4) The Airworthiness Investigative Authority shall</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0"><change>(<I>a</I>) receive representations made under subsection (2) in any manner the Airworthiness Investigative Authority considers appropriate;</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0"><change>(<I>b</I>) keep a record of those representations;</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0"><change>(<I>c</I>) consider those representations before publishing the final report; and</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0"><change>(<I>d</I>) notify in writing each of the persons who made those representations, indicating how the Airworthiness Investigative Authority has disposed of the representations that that person made.</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Protection of representations<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><change>(5) A representation is privileged, except for one made by a minister responsible for a department that has a direct interest in the findings of the investigation. Subject to any other provisions of this Part or to a written authorization from the author of a representation, no person, including any person to whom access is provided under this section, shall knowingly communicate it or permit it to be communicated to any person.</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Use by Airworthiness Investigative Authority<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><change>(6) The Airworthiness Investigative Authority may use representations as the Airworthiness Investigative Authority considers necessary in the interests of aviation safety.</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Making representations available to coroner<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><change>(7) If requested to do so by a coroner conducting an investigation into any circumstances in respect of which representations were made to the Airworthiness Investigative Authority, the Airworthiness Investigative Authority shall make them available to the coroner.</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Prohibition of use<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><change>(8) Except for use by a coroner for the purpose of an investigation, no person may use representations in any legal, disciplinary or other proceedings.</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Notification of findings and recommendations<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><change>(9) The Airworthiness Investigative Authority shall</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0"><change>(<I>a</I>) during an investigation of a military-civilian occurrence, immediately notify in writing any minister or person who, in the Airworthiness Investigative Authority’s opinion, has a direct interest in the investigation’s findings of any of its findings and recommendations, whether interim or final, that, in the Airworthiness Investigative Authority’s opinion, require urgent action; and</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0"><change>(<I>b</I>) on completion of the investigation, notify in writing those ministers and persons of its findings as to the causes and contributing factors of the military-civilian occurrence, any safety deficiencies it has identified and any recommendations resulting from its findings.</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Minister to reply to Airworthiness Investigative Authority<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><change>(10) A minister who is notified of the findings and recommendations of an investigation under paragraph (9)(<I>a</I>) or (<I>b</I>) shall, within 90 days after the day on which they were notified,</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0"><change>(<I>a</I>) advise the Airworthiness Investigative Authority in writing of any action taken or proposed to be taken in response to those findings and recommendations; or</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0"><change>(<I>b</I>) provide written reasons to the Airworthiness Investigative Authority if no action will be taken or if the action to be taken differs from the action that was recommended.</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0"><change>In either case, that minister shall make the reply available to the public.</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Restrictions<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><change>(11) If obligations are imposed on the Minister of National Defence under subsection (10), those obligations are subject to any restrictions in the interests of national security that are provided by the <I>National Defence Act</I> or by regulations made under that Act, or that the Governor in Council prescribes by order, which the Governor in Council is hereby authorized to do.</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Extension of time<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><change>(12) If the Airworthiness Investigative Authority is satisfied that a minister is unable to reply within the period referred to in subsection (10), the period may be extended as the Airworthiness Investigative Authority considers necessary.</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Interim report<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><change><B>19.</B> (1) The Airworthiness Investigative Authority shall, on a confidential basis, provide an interim report on the progress and findings of an investigation</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0"><change>(<I>a</I>) to any minister responsible for a department that has a direct interest in the subject-matter of the investigation, on written request made in respect of that investigation; and</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0"><change>(<I>b</I>) to any coroner investigating the military-civilian occurrence, if it involved a death and significant progress has been made in the investigation.</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Limited purpose only<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><change>(2) A person, other than a minister, who is provided with an interim report under subsection (1) shall not use the report, or permit its use, for any purpose not strictly necessary to its examination.</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Power to reconsider<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><change><B>20.</B> (1) The Airworthiness Investigative Authority may, at any time, reconsider any findings and recommendations made pursuant to an investigation of a military-civilian occurrence under this Part, whether or not the Airworthiness Investigative Authority has made public a report of those findings and recommendations.</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Duty to reconsider<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><change>(2) The Airworthiness Investigative Authority shall reconsider the findings and recommendations made pursuant to an investigation under this Part if, in the Airworthiness Investigative Authority’s opinion, new material facts appear.</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Delegation of powers<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><change><B>21.</B> (1) Subject to subsection (2), the Airworthiness Investigative Authority may authorize any person, subject to any limitations specified in the authorization, to exercise or perform any of the powers, duties or functions conferred or imposed on the Airworthiness Investigative Authority under this Part, other than the power of authorization under this subsection.</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Revocation<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><change>(2) The authorization may be revoked by the Airworthiness Investigative Authority in writing at any time.</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:Privilege--><Para TopMargin="10" Italic="Yes" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center"><change>Privilege</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Definition of “on-board recording”<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><change><B>22.</B> (1) In this section, “on-board recording” means the whole or any part of</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0"><change>(<I>a</I>) a recording of voice communications originating from an aircraft, or received on or in the flight deck of an aircraft, or</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0"><change>(<I>b</I>) a video recording of the activities of the operating personnel of an aircraft,</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0"><change>that is made, using recording equipment that is intended to not be controlled by the operating personnel, on the flight deck of the aircraft, and includes a transcript or substantial summary of such a recording.</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Privilege for on-board recordings<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><change>(2) Every on-board recording is privileged and, except as provided by this section, no person, including any person to whom access is provided under this section, shall knowingly communicate an on-board recording or permit it to be communicated to any person.</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Legal proceedings<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><change>(3) Except as provided by this section, no person may be required to produce an on-board recording or to give evidence relating to it in any legal, disciplinary or other proceedings.</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Access by investigator<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><change>(4) Any on-board recording that relates to a military-civilian occurrence being investigated under this Part shall be released to an investigator who requests it for the purposes of the investigation.</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Use by Airworthiness Investigative Authority<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><change>(5) The Airworthiness Investigative Authority may make any use that the Airworthiness Investigative Authority considers necessary in the interests of aviation safety of any on-board recording obtained by an investigator under this Part but, subject to subsection (6), shall not knowingly communicate or permit to be communicated to anyone any portion of it that is unrelated to the causes or contributing factors of the military-civilian occurrence under investigation or to the identification of safety deficiencies.</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Access by coroners and other investigators<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><change>(6) The Airworthiness Investigative Authority shall make available any on-board recording obtained in the course of an investigation of a military-civilian occurrence to</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0"><change>(<I>a</I>) a coroner who requests access to it for the purpose of an investigation that the coroner is conducting; or</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0"><change>(<I>b</I>) any person carrying out a coordinated investigation under section 18 of the <I>Canadian Transportation Accident Investigation and Safety Board Act</I>.</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Power of court or coroner<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><change>(7) Despite anything in this section, if, in any proceedings before a court or coroner, a request for the production and discovery of an on-board recording is made, the court or coroner shall</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0"><change>(<I>a</I>) cause notice of the request to be given to the Airworthiness Investigative Authority, if the Airworthiness Investigative Authority is not a party to the proceedings;</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0"><change>(<I>b</I>) <I>in camera</I>, examine the on-board recording and give the Airworthiness Investigative Authority a reasonable opportunity to make representations with respect to it; and</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0"><change>(<I>c</I>) if the court or coroner concludes in the circumstances of the case that the public interest in the proper administration of justice outweighs in importance the privilege attached to the on-board recording by virtue of this section, order the production and discovery of the on-board recording, subject to any restrictions or conditions that the court or coroner considers appropriate, and may require any person to give evidence that relates to it.</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Use prohibited<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><change>(8) An on-board recording may not be used against any of the following persons in disciplinary proceedings, in proceedings relating to the capacity or competence of an officer or employee to perform the officer’s or employee’s functions, or in legal or other proceedings: air traffic controllers, aircraft crew members, airport vehicle operators, flight service station specialists and persons who relay messages respecting air traffic control or related matters.</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Definition of “court”<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><change>(9) For the purposes of subsection (7), “court” includes a person or persons appointed or designated to conduct a public inquiry into a military-civilian occurrence under the <I>Inquiries Act</I>.</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Definition of “communication record”<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><change><B>23.</B> (1) In this section, “communication record” means the whole or any part of any record, recording, copy, transcript or substantial summary of any type of communications respecting air traffic control or related matters that take place between any of the following persons: air traffic controllers, aircraft crew members, airport vehicle operators, flight service station specialists and persons who relay messages respecting air traffic control or related matters.</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Use prohibited<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><change>(2) A communication record obtained in the course of an investigation of a military-civilian occurrence under this Part may not be used against any person referred to in subsection (1) in any legal proceedings or, subject to any applicable collective agreement, in any disciplinary proceedings.</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Definition of “statement”<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><change><B>24.</B> (1) For the purposes of this section and section 13, “statement” means</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0"><change>(<I>a</I>) the whole or any part of an oral, written or recorded statement relating to a military-civilian occurrence and given by the author of the statement to the Airworthiness Investigative Authority, an investigator or any person acting for the Airworthiness Investigative Authority;</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0"><change>(<I>b</I>) a transcription or substantial summary of a statement referred to in paragraph (<I>a</I>); or</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0"><change>(<I>c</I>) conduct that could reasonably be taken to be intended as such a statement.</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Statement privileged<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><change>(2) A statement and the identity of the person who made it are privileged, and, except as provided by this Part or as authorized in writing by the person who made the statement, no person, including any person to whom access is provided under this section, shall knowingly communicate a statement or permit it to be communicated to any person, or disclose the identity of the person who made it.</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Use by Airworthiness Investigative Authority<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><change>(3) The Airworthiness Investigative Authority may use any statement as he or she considers necessary in the interests of aviation safety.</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Access by coroners and other investigators<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><change>(4) The Airworthiness Investigative Authority shall make statements available to</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0"><change>(<I>a</I>) a coroner who requests access to them for the purpose of an investigation that the coroner is conducting; and</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0"><change>(<I>b</I>) any person carrying out a coordinated investigation under section 18 of the <I>Canadian Transportation Accident Investigation and Safety Board Act</I>.</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Power of court or coroner<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><change>(5) Despite anything in this section, if, in any proceedings before a court or coroner, a request for the production and discovery of a statement is contested on the ground that it is privileged, the court or coroner shall</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0"><change>(<I>a</I>) <I>in camera</I>, examine the statement; and</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0"><change>(<I>b</I>) if the court or coroner concludes in the circumstances of the case that the public interest in the proper administration of justice outweighs in importance the privilege attached to the statement by virtue of this section, order the production and discovery of the statement, subject to any restrictions or conditions that the court or coroner considers appropriate, and may require any person to give evidence that relates to it.</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Use prohibited<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><change>(6) A statement may not be used against the person who made it in any legal, disciplinary or other proceedings except in a prosecution for perjury or for giving contradictory evidence or a prosecution under section 24.5.</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Definition of “court”<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><change>(7) For the purposes of subsection (5), “court” includes a person or persons appointed or designated to conduct a public inquiry into a military-civilian occurrence under the <I>Inquiries Act</I>.</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Reporting of military-civilian occurrences<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><change><B>24.1</B> (1) The Governor in Council may, on the recommendation of the Minister of National Defence, make regulations for the establishment and administration of systems for the mandatory or voluntary reporting by civilians to the Airworthiness Investigative Authority of military-civilian occurrences or any classes of them that are specified in the regulations.</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Use of reports<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><change>(2) The Airworthiness Investigative Authority may, subject to this section, use any report made under regulations made under subsection (1) as the Airworthiness Investigative Authority considers necessary in the interests of aviation safety.</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Protection of identity<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><change>(3) Regulations made under subsection (1) may provide for the protection of the identity of persons who report military-civilian occurrences.</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Certain information privileged<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><change>(4) If a person’s identity is protected by provisions referred to in subsection (3), information that could reasonably be expected to reveal that identity is privileged, and no person shall knowingly communicate it or permit it to be communicated to any person.</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Legal proceedings<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><change>(5) No person may be required to produce information that could reasonably be expected to reveal the identity of a person who has made a report under regulations made under subsection (1), or to give evidence relating to the information in any legal, disciplinary or other proceedings.</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Use prohibited<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><change>(6) A report made under a voluntary reporting system established by regulations made under subsection (1) may not be used against the person who made the report in any legal, disciplinary or other proceedings if the person’s identity is protected by provisions referred to in subsection (3).</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:Evidence of Airworthiness Investigative Authority and of Investigators--><Para TopMargin="10" Italic="Yes" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center"><change>Evidence of Airworthiness Investigative Authority and of Investigators</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Appearance of investigator<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><change><B>24.2</B> Except for proceedings before and investigations by a coroner, neither the Airworthiness Investigative Authority nor an investigator is competent or compellable to appear as a witness in any proceedings unless the court or other person or body before whom the proceedings are conducted orders so for special cause.</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Opinions inadmissible<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><change><B>24.3</B> An opinion of the Airworthiness Investigative Authority or an investigator is not admissible in evidence in any legal, disciplinary or other proceedings.</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:Regulations--><Para TopMargin="10" Italic="Yes" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center"><change>Regulations</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Regulations<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><change><B>24.4</B> (1) The Governor in Council may, on the recommendation of the Minister of National Defence, make regulations</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0"><change>(<I>a</I>) prescribing the manner of exercising or carrying out any of the powers, duties and functions of an investigator designated under subsection 12(1);</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0"><change>(<I>b</I>) respecting the keeping and preservation of records, documents and other evidence relating to military-civilian occurrences;</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0"><change>(<I>c</I>) respecting the attendance of interested persons at tests to destruction conducted under subsection 13(6);</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0"><change>(<I>d</I>) defining, for the purposes of an investigation of a military-civilian occurrence, the site or sites of such an occurrence and prescribing rules for the protection of those sites;</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0"><change>(<I>e</I>) defining the rights or privileges of persons attending investigations as observers or with observer status;</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0"><change>(<I>f</I>) respecting the tariff of fees and expenses to be paid to any witness attending at an investigation of a military-civilian occurrence, and the conditions under which a fee or expenses may be paid to such a witness; and</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0"><change>(<I>g</I>) respecting the forms of warrants issued under section 13 and the modifications to be made to section 487.1 of the <I>Criminal Code</I> in its application to section 13.</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Publication of proposed regulations<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><change>(2) Subject to subsection (3), a copy of each regulation that the Governor in Council proposes to make under subsection (1) or section 24.1 shall be published in the <I>Canada Gazette</I> at least 60 days before its proposed effective date, and interested persons shall be given a reasonable opportunity within those 60 days to make representations with respect to it to the Minister of National Defence.</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Exceptions<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><change>(3) Subsection (2) does not apply in respect of a proposed regulation that</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0"><change>(<I>a</I>) has previously been published under that subsection, whether or not it has been changed as a result of representations made under that subsection; or</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0"><change>(<I>b</I>) makes no substantive change to an existing regulation.</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:Offences--><Para TopMargin="10" Italic="Yes" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center"><change>Offences</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Offences<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><change><B>24.5</B> (1) Every person who</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0"><change>(<I>a</I>) contravenes subsection 13(9), (11) or (12),</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0"><change>(<I>b</I>) without lawful excuse, wilfully resists or otherwise obstructs an investigator in the execution of powers or duties under this Part,</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0"><change>(<I>c</I>) knowingly gives false or misleading information at any investigation of a military-civilian occurrence under this Part, or</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0"><change>(<I>d</I>) makes a report under section 24.1 that they know to be false or misleading</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0"><change>is guilty of an indictable offence and liable on conviction to a term of imprisonment not exceeding two years, or is guilty of an offence punishable on summary conviction.</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Offences<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><change>(2) Every person who contravenes a provision of this Part, or of the regulations made under this Part, for which no punishment is specified is guilty of an offence punishable on summary conviction.</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Evidence<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><change><B>24.6</B> (1) Subject to subsections (2) and (3),</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0"><change>(<I>a</I>) a report purporting to have been signed by an investigator stating that the investigator has exercised any power under section 13 and stating the results of the exercise of the power, or</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0"><change>(<I>b</I>) a document purporting to have been certified by an investigator as a true copy of or extract from a document produced to the investigator under subsection 13(10)</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0"><change>is admissible in evidence in any prosecution for an offence under this Part without proof of the signature or official character of the person appearing to have signed the report or certified the document and is, in the absence of evidence to the contrary, proof of the statements contained in the report or proof of the contents of the document.</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Notice<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><change>(2) No report or document shall be received in evidence under subsection (1) unless the party intending to produce it has, at least seven days before producing it, served on the party against whom it is intended to be produced a notice of that intention, together with a copy of the report or document.</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Cross- examination<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><change>(3) The party against whom a report or document is produced under subsection (1) may require the attendance, for the purposes of cross-examination, of the person who appears to have signed the report or certified the document as a true copy or extract.</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:Military Investigations under Part I--><Para TopMargin="10" SmallCaps="Yes" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center"><change>Military Investigations under Part I</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Application of subsections 18(1) to (9) and sections 22 to 24.1<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><change><B>24.7</B> Subsections 18(1) to (9), the provisions of sections 22, 23 and 24 relating to on-board recordings, communication records and statements, within the meaning of those respective sections, and the provisions of section 24.1 relating to reporting by civilians under that section apply, with any necessary modifications, in respect of an investigation of an accident or incident relating to aeronautics that the Minister of National Defence has directed the Airworthiness Investigative Authority to carry out other than an investigation of a military-civilian occurrence.</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>R.S., c. 33 (1st Supp.), s. 4; 1992, c. 4, s. 24(F); 1996, c. 10, s. 205<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>42.</B> Sections 26 to 28 of the Act are replaced by the following:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Limitation period<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>26.</B> <change>(1)</change> No <change>measures</change> under <change>section 6.9</change>, <change>proceedings for a violation or</change> proceedings by way of summary conviction under this Act may be instituted <change>later than 12</change> months <change>after</change> the time when the subject-matter of the <change>measures or</change> proceedings arose.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Exception<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><change>(2) The Governor in Council may by regulation specify provisions in respect of which measures under section 6.9, proceedings for a violation or proceedings by way of summary conviction may be instituted within 12 months after the day on which the Minister became aware of the subject-matter of the measures or proceedings.</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Certificate of Minister<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><change>(3) A document that purports to have been issued by the Minister and certifies the day on which the Minister became aware of the subject-matter of the contravention, violation or offence is evidence, without proof of the signature or official character of the person appearing to have signed the document, that the Minister became aware of the subject-matter on that day.</change></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Proof of documents<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>27.</B> (1) In any action or proceeding under this Act, any document purporting to be certified by the Minister <change>of Transport</change>, the Secretary of the Department of Transport or the Secretary of the Canadian Transportation Agency <change>— or, with respect to any matter relating to defence, by the Minister of National Defence or the Chief of the Defence Staff —</change> to be a true copy of a document made, given or issued under this Act is, without proof of the signature or of the official character of the person appearing to have signed the document,</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>a</I>) evidence of the original document of which it purports to be a copy;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>b</I>) evidence that the original document was made, given or issued by or by the authority of or deposited with the person named <change>in it</change> and was made, given, issued or deposited at the time stated in the certified copy, if <change>the certified copy states</change> a time; and</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>c</I>) evidence that the original document was signed, certified, attested or executed by the persons and in the manner shown in the certified copy.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Certificate<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(2) In any action or proceeding under this Act, any certificate purporting to be signed by the Minister <change>of Transport</change> or the Secretary of the Department of Transport <change>— or, with respect to any matter relating to defence, by the Minister of National Defence or the Chief of the Defence Staff —</change> stating that a document, authorization or exemption under this Act</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>a</I>) has or has not been issued to or in respect of any person named in the certificate or in respect of any <change>aeronautical product,</change> aerodrome, other facility, <change>equipment or service</change> identified in the certificate, or</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>b</I>) having been issued to or in respect of any person named in the certificate or in respect of any <change>aeronautical product</change>, aerodrome, other facility, <change>equipment or service</change> identified in the certificate, has expired, or has been cancelled or suspended as of a date stated in the certificate, and stating, in the case of a suspension, the period of the suspension,</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0">is evidence of the facts stated <change>in it</change>, without proof of the signature or of the official character of the person appearing to have signed the certificate and without further proof <change>of the certificate</change>.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Document entries as proof<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>28.</B> In any action or proceeding under this Act, an entry in any record required under this Act to be kept is, in the absence of evidence to the contrary, proof of the matters stated <change>in it</change> as against the person who made the entry or was required to keep the record or, <change>if</change> the record was kept in respect of an aeronautical product, an aerodrome, <change>another</change> facility <change>relating to aeronautics, aeronautical equipment or a service relating to aeronautics</change>, against the owner, operator <change>or provider, as the case may be,</change> of the product, aerodrome, other facility, <change>equipment or service</change>.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:CONSEQUENTIAL AMENDMENTS--><Para TopMargin="10" Bold="Yes" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">CONSEQUENTIAL AMENDMENTS</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:Access to Information Act--><MarginalNote>R.S., c. A-1<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" Bold="Yes" SmallCaps="Yes" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">Access to Information Act</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>43.</B> Schedule II to the <I>Access to Information Act</I> is amended by replacing the reference to “subsections 4.79(1) and 6.5(5)” opposite the reference to the “Aeronautics Act” with a reference to “subsection 4.79(1), sections 5.392 and 5.393, subsections 5.394(2), 5.397(2), 6.5(5), 22(2) and 24.1(4) and section 24.7”.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:Canada Transportation Act--><MarginalNote>1996, c. 10<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="10" Bold="Yes" SmallCaps="Yes" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">Canada Transportation Act</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>2001, c. 29, s. 52(1)<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>44.</B> The portion of subsection 180(2) of the <I>Canada Transportation Act</I> before paragraph (<I>a</I>) is replaced by the following:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Application of <I>Aeronautics Act</I><br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(2) Sections 7.8 to 8.2 of the <I>Aeronautics Act</I><change>, as those sections read on May 1, 2005,</change> apply to the contravention of a provision, requirement or condition designated under section 177, with any modifications that are necessary, and a reference in any of those provisions or in any document issued under any of those provisions to</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:Canadian Transportation Accident Investigation and Safety Board Act--><MarginalNote>1989, c. 3<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="10" Bold="Yes" SmallCaps="Yes" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">Canadian Transportation Accident Investigation and Safety Board Act</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>45.</B> Subsection 18(4) of the <I>Canadian Transportation Accident Investigation and Safety Board Act</I> is replaced by the following:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Investigations to be coordinated<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(4) Where a transportation occurrence referred to in subsection (3) is being investigated by the Board and by the Department of National Defence, the Canadian Forces or a visiting force, the Board and the Minister of National Defence <change>— or the Airworthiness Investigative Authority designated under section 11 of the <I>Aeronautics Act</I>, as the case may be —</change> shall take all reasonable measures to ensure that the investigations are coordinated.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:Public Service Superannuation Act--><MarginalNote>R.S., c. P-36<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="10" Bold="Yes" SmallCaps="Yes" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">Public Service Superannuation Act</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>46.</B> The definition “air traffic controller” in section 15 of the <I>Public Service Superannuation Act</I> is replaced by the following:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>“air traffic controller”<br/>« <I>contrôleur de la circulation aérienne</I> »<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0">“air traffic controller” means a contributor who is or was licensed as an air traffic controller pursuant to regulations made under <change>subparagraph 4.9(<I>a</I>)(i)</change> of the <I>Aeronautics Act</I>;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:TRANSITIONAL PROVISIONS--><Para TopMargin="10" Bold="Yes" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">TRANSITIONAL PROVISIONS</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Existing investigations — military-civilian occurrences<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>47.</B> (1) On the coming into force of Part II of the <I>Aeronautics Act</I> (referred to in this section as “the Act”), as enacted by section 41 of this Act, that Part applies to any investigation already begun of an accident or incident relating to aeronautics that would have been a military-civilian occurrence within the meaning of that Part, and the Airworthiness Investigative Authority designated by the Minister of National Defence under section 11 of the Act shall continue the investigation in accordance with that Part.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Completed investigations — military-civilian occurrences<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes">(2) If, on the coming into force of Part II of the Act, an investigation referred to in subsection (1) has been completed but no report on it has been made, then, on the coming into force of that Part, subsections 18(1) to (9) of the Act and the provisions of sections 22, 23 and 24 of the Act relating to on-board recordings, communication records and statements, within the meaning of those respective sections, and the provisions of section 24.1 of the Act relating to reporting by civilians under that section 24.1 apply.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Existing military investigations<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>48.</B> If, on the coming into force of Part II of the <I>Aeronautics Act</I> (referred to in this section as “the Act”), as enacted by section 41 of this Act, an investigation by or under the authority of the Minister of National Defence of an accident or incident relating to aeronautics that would not have been a military-civilian occurrence within the meaning of that Part has been begun, or one has been completed but no report on it has been made, then, on the coming into force of that Part, subsections 18(1) to (9) of the Act and the provisions of sections 22, 23 and 24 of the Act relating to on-board recordings, communication records and statements, within the meaning of those respective sections, and the provisions of section 24.1 of the Act relating to reporting by civilians under that section 24.1 apply.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:COORDINATING AMENDMENT--><Para TopMargin="10" Bold="Yes" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">COORDINATING AMENDMENT</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>1996, c. 10<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>49.</B> If Bill C-44, introduced in the 1st Session of the 38th Parliament and entitled the <I>Transportation Amendment Act</I> (the “other Act”), receives royal assent, then, on the later of the coming into force of section 35 of this Act and section 68 of the other Act, section 180.1 of the <I>Canada Transportation Act</I> is replaced by the following:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Delegation by Minister<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>180.1</B> In the case of a violation referred to in subsection 177(2), the Minister may delegate to the Agency any power, duty or function conferred on the Minister under this Part and under sections 7.8 to 8.2 of the <I>Aeronautics Act</I>, as those sections read on May 1, 2005.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:COMING INTO FORCE--><Para TopMargin="10" Bold="Yes" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">COMING INTO FORCE</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Order in council<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>50.</B> This Act, other than section 49, comes into force on a day or days to be fixed by order of the Governor in Council.</Para></Block><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="BPT_ImprintE"><br/><br/>Published under authority of the Senate of Canada</Para></Block><Block Align="Yes" LineCnt="N"><Para NoLineBreak="Yes" NoHtml="Yes" Leading="0" Size="0" TopMargin="0" BottomMargin="0"></Para></Block></Bill_Part></Bill>
