<?xml version="1.0"?>
<Bill RHead_reign="53-54 Eliz. II" RHead_ParlYear="2004-2005" DocumentTitle="BILL S-37" Bill_No="S-37" Document_No="90332" xml:lang="EN" Bill_Type="Non-amending" Stage_Name="Assented-to" Reprint="No" xml:space="preserve" ChapterNo_E="C. 40" ChapterNo_F="ch. 40" Bill-Origin="senate"><Bill_Part Part_Type="Cover" CountLines="No"><Block><Para TopMargin="24" Size="9" Leading="10" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0" TextAlign="Center">First Session, Thirty-eighth Parliament,</Para></Block><Block><Para Size="9" Leading="10" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0" TextAlign="Center">53-54 Elizabeth II, 2004-2005</Para></Block><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="COV@StatutesTitle">STATUTES OF CANADA 2005<br/>CHAPTER 40</Para></Block><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="CovLongTitle">An Act to amend the Criminal Code and the Cultural Property Export and Import Act</Para></Block><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="COV_StageLine"></Para></Block><Block><Para BottomMargin="14" Size="11" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0" Bold="Yes" TextAlign="Center">ASSENTED TO</Para></Block><Block><Para Size="8" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0" TextAlign="Center">25th NOVEMBER, 2005</Para></Block><Block><Para TopMargin="4" Size="8" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0" TextAlign="Center">BILL S-37</Para></Block><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="COV_StageLine"></Para></Block></Bill_Part><Bill_Part CountLines="No" Part_Type="InsideCover"><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="BPT_InsideCoverE">Available on the Parliament of Canada Web Site at the following address:<br/><B>http://www.parl.gc.ca</B></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><Para TopMargin="108" BottomMargin="4" Size="10" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">SUMMARY</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" Size="8" Leading="9" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">This enactment amends the <I>Criminal Code</I> to prohibit certain offences, including theft, robbery, mischief and arson against cultural property protected under the 1954 Convention for the Protection of Cultural Property in the Event of Armed Conflict. Those amendments allow for the prosecution of such offences when committed outside Canada by Canadians.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" Size="8" Leading="9" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">It also amends the <I>Cultural Property Export and Import Act</I> to prohibit Canadians from illegally exporting or otherwise removing protected cultural property from an occupied territory. Those amendments allow for the prosecution of such offences when committed outside Canada by Canadians and provide for a mechanism for the restitution of cultural property.</Para></Block></Bill_Part><Bill_Part Part_Type="MainText" CountLines="No" RunningHead_E="Criminal Code and Cultural Property Export and Import"><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="MAIN@RoyalAssentTitle">53-54 ELIZABETH II</Para></Block><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="MAIN@RoyalAssentTitle">ГўВЂВ”ГўВЂВ”ГўВЂВ”ГўВЂВ”ГўВЂВ”ГўВЂВ”</Para></Block><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="MAIN@RoyalAssentTitle">CHAPTER 40</Para></Block><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="LongTitleAssent">An Act to amend the Criminal Code and the Cultural Property Export and Import Act</Para></Block><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="MAIN@RoyalAssentDate">[<I>Assented to 25th November, 2005</I>]</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">Her Majesty, by and with the advice and consent of the Senate and House of Commons of Canada, enacts as follows:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:CRIMINAL CODE--><MarginalNote>R.S., c. C-46<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="10" Bold="Yes" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">CRIMINAL CODE</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>2001, c. 41, s. 2(1)<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>1.</B> (1) Paragraph (<I>a</I>) of the definition ГўВЂВњAttorney GeneralГўВЂВќ in section 2 of the <I>Criminal Code</I> is replaced by the following:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>a</I>) subject to paragraphs (<I>b.1</I>) to (<I>f</I>), with respect to proceedings to which this Act applies, means the Attorney General or Solicitor General of the province in which those proceedings are taken and includes his or her lawful deputy,</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes">(2) The definition ГўВЂВњAttorney GeneralГўВЂВќ in section 2 of the Act is amended by adding the following after paragraph (<I>b</I>):</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>b.1</I>) with respect to proceedings in relation to an offence under subsection 7(2.01), means either the Attorney General of Canada or the Attorney General or Solicitor General of the province in which those proceedings are taken and includes the lawful deputy of any of them,</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>2.</B> Section 7 of the Act is amended by adding the following after subsection (2):</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Offences in relation to cultural property<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(2.01) Despite anything in this Act or any other Act, a person who commits an act or omission outside Canada that if committed in Canada would constitute an offence under section 322, 341, 344, 380, 430 or 434 in relation to cultural property as defined in Article 1 of the Convention, or a conspiracy or an attempt to commit such an offence, or being an accessory after the fact or counselling in relation to such an offence, is deemed to have committed that act or omission in Canada if the person</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>a</I>) is a Canadian citizen;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>b</I>) is not a citizen of any state and ordinarily resides in Canada; or</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>c</I>) is a permanent resident within the meaning of subsection 2(1) of the <I>Immigration and Refugee Protection Act</I> and is, after the commission of the act or omission, present in Canada.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Definition of ГўВЂВњConventionГўВЂВќ<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(2.02) For the purpose of subsection (2.01), ГўВЂВњConventionГўВЂВќ means the Convention for the Protection of Cultural Property in the Event of Armed Conflict, done at The Hague on May 14, 1954. Article 1 of the Convention is set out in the schedule to the <I>Cultural Property Export and Import Act</I>.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>3.</B> Section 430 of the Act is amended by adding the following after subsection (4.1):</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Mischief in relation to cultural property<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(4.2) Every one who commits mischief in relation to cultural property as defined in Article 1 of the Convention for the Protection of Cultural Property in the Event of Armed Conflict, done at The Hague on May 14, 1954, as set out in the schedule to the <I>Cultural Property Export and Import Act</I>,</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>a</I>) is guilty of an indictable offence and liable to imprisonment for a term not exceeding ten years; or</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>b</I>) is guilty of an offence punishable on summary conviction.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:CULTURAL PROPERTY EXPORT AND IMPORT ACT--><MarginalNote>R.S., c. C-51<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="10" Bold="Yes" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">CULTURAL PROPERTY EXPORT AND IMPORT ACT</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>4.</B> The <I>Cultural Property Export and Import Act</I> is amended by adding the following after section 36:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:CONVENTION FOR THE PROTECTION OF CULTURAL PROPERTY IN THE EVENT OF ARMED CONFLICT AND ITS PROTOCOLS--><Para TopMargin="10" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">CONVENTION FOR THE PROTECTION OF CULTURAL PROPERTY IN THE EVENT OF ARMED CONFLICT AND ITS PROTOCOLS</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Definitions<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>36.1</B> (1) The following definitions apply in this section.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><MarginalNote>ГўВЂВњConventionГўВЂВќ<br/>Г‚В« <I>convention</I> Г‚В»<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0">ГўВЂВњConventionГўВЂВќ means the Convention for the Protection of Cultural Property in the Event of Armed Conflict, done at The Hague on May 14, 1954. Article 1 of the Convention is set out in the schedule.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><MarginalNote>ГўВЂВњFirst ProtocolГўВЂВќ<br/>Г‚В« <I>premier protocole</I> Г‚В»<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0">ГўВЂВњFirst ProtocolГўВЂВќ means the first protocol, done at The Hague on May 14, 1954, to the Convention.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><MarginalNote>ГўВЂВњSecond ProtocolГўВЂВќ<br/>Г‚В« <I>deuxiГѓВЁme protocole</I> Г‚В»<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0">ГўВЂВњSecond ProtocolГўВЂВќ means the second protocol, done at The Hague on March 26, 1999, to the Convention. </Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><MarginalNote>ГўВЂВњState PartyГўВЂВќ<br/>Г‚В« <I>ГѓВ‰tat partie</I> Г‚В»<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0">ГўВЂВњState PartyГўВЂВќ means a state that is a party to the Convention and the First or Second Protocol.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Export or removal of cultural property<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(2) No person shall knowingly export or otherwise remove cultural property as defined in subparagraph (<I>a</I>) of Article 1 of the Convention from an occupied territory of a State Party to the Second Protocol, unless the export or removal conforms with the applicable laws of that territory or is necessary for the propertyГўВЂВ™s protection or preservation.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Offence outside Canada deemed in Canada<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(3) Despite anything in this Act or any other Act, a person who commits an act or omission outside Canada that if committed in Canada would constitute an offence under subsection (2), or a conspiracy or an attempt to commit such an offence, or being an accessory after the fact or counselling in relation to such an offence, is deemed to have committed that act or omission in Canada if the person</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>a</I>) is a Canadian citizen;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>b</I>) is not a citizen of any state and ordinarily resides in Canada; or</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>c</I>) is a permanent resident within the meaning of subsection 2(1) of the <I>Immigration and Refugee Protection Act</I> and is, after the commission of the act or omission, present in Canada.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Action for recovery of cultural property<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(4) If the government of a State Party submits a request in writing to the Minister for the recovery and return of any cultural property that has been exported from an occupied territory of that State Party and that is in Canada in the possession of or under the control of any person, institution or public authority, the Attorney General of Canada may institute an action in the Federal Court or in a superior court of a province for the recovery of the property by the State Party.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Notice<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(5) Notice of the commencement of an action under this section on behalf of a State Party shall be served by the Attorney General of Canada on such persons and given in such manner as is provided by the rules of the court in which the action is taken, or, if the rules do not so provide, served on such persons and given in such manner as is directed by a judge of the court.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Order for recovery of cultural property<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(6) The court in which an action has been taken under this section may, after affording all persons that it considers to have an interest in the action a reasonable opportunity to be heard, make an order for the recovery of the property in respect of which the action has been taken or any other order sufficient to ensure the return of the property to the State Party, if the court is satisfied that the property was exported in contravention of the applicable laws of the occupied territory of the State Party or was imported into Canada for its protection or preservation and that the amount fixed under subsection (7), if any, has been paid.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Compensation<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(7) The court in which an action has been taken under this section may fix any amount that it considers just in the circumstances to be paid as compensation by the State Party to a person, institution or public authority that establishes to the satisfaction of the court that the person, institution or public authority is a <I>bona fide</I> purchaser for value or has a valid title to the property in respect of which the action has been taken and had no knowledge at the time the property was purchased or the title to the property was acquired that the property</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>a</I>) had been exported in contravention of the applicable laws of the occupied territory of the State Party; or</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>b</I>) had been imported into Canada for its protection or preservation.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Safe-keeping<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(8) The court may, at any time in the course of an action under this section, order that the property in respect of which the action has been taken be turned over to the Minister for safe-keeping and conservation pending final disposition of the action.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Permit to export<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(9) The Minister shall, on receipt of a copy of a court order made under subsection (6), issue a permit authorizing any person authorized by the State Party on behalf of which the action was taken to export the property in respect of which the order was made to that State.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Limitations inapplicable<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(10) Section 39 of the <I>Federal Courts Act</I> does not apply in respect of any action taken under this section.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>5.</B> The portion of subsection 45(1) of the Act before paragraph (<I>a</I>) is replaced by the following:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Offences and punishment<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>45.</B> (1) Every person who contravenes any of the provisions of subsection 36.1(2) and sections 40 to 44 is guilty of an offence and liable</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>6.</B> The Act is amended by adding, after section 52, the schedule set out in the schedule to this Act.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:COORDINATING AMENDMENT--><Para TopMargin="10" Bold="Yes" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">COORDINATING AMENDMENT</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>2004, c. 3<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>7.</B> On the later of the coming into force of this Act and the coming into force of section 1 of <I>An Act to amend the Criminal Code (capital markets fraud and evidence-gathering)</I>, chapter 3 of the Statutes of Canada, 2004, paragraph (<I>a</I>) of the definition ГўВЂВњAttorney GeneralГўВЂВќ in section 2 of the <I>Criminal Code</I> is replaced by the following:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>a</I>) subject to paragraphs (<I>b.1</I>) to (<I>g</I>), with respect to proceedings to which this Act applies, means the Attorney General or Solicitor General of the province in which those proceedings are taken and includes his or her lawful deputy,</Para></Block><Block Align="Yes" LineCnt="N"><Para NoLineBreak="Yes" NoHtml="Yes" Leading="0" Size="0" TopMargin="0" BottomMargin="0">Г‚В„</Para></Block></Bill_Part><Bill_Part Part_Type="Schedule" CountLines="No" RunningHead_E="Criminal Code and Cultural Property Export and Import ГўВЂВ” Schedule"><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><Para TopMargin="10" Size="9" Leading="10" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0" Bold="Yes" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">SCHEDULE </Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><Para Size="9" Leading="10" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0" Bold="Yes" Italic="Yes" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">(Section 6)</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><Para TopMargin="10" Size="9" Leading="10" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">SCHEDULE </Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><Para Size="9" Leading="10" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0" Italic="Yes" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">(Subsection 36.1(1))</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:ARTICLE 1 OF THE CONVENTION FOR THE PROTECTION OF CULTURAL PROPERTY IN THE EVENT OF ARMED CONFLICT DONE AT THE HAGUE ON MAY 14, 1954--><Para TopMargin="5" Size="9" Leading="10" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">ARTICLE 1 OF THE CONVENTION FOR THE PROTECTION OF CULTURAL PROPERTY IN THE EVENT OF ARMED CONFLICT DONE AT THE HAGUE ON MAY 14, 1954</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><Para TopMargin="10" Size="9" Leading="10" SmallCaps="Yes" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">Article 1</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:Definition of Cultural Property--><Para TopMargin="5" Size="9" Leading="10" SmallCaps="Yes" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">Definition of Cultural Property</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" Size="9" Leading="10" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">For the purposes of the present Convention, the term ГўВЂВњcultural propertyГўВЂВќ shall cover, irrespective of origin or ownership:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" Size="9" Leading="10" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">(<I>a</I>) movable or immovable property of great importance to the cultural heritage of every people, such as monuments of architecture, art or history, whether religious or secular; archaeological sites; groups of buildings which, as a whole, are of historical or artistic interest; works of art; manuscripts, books and other objects of artistic, historical or archaeological interest; as well as scientific collections and important collections of books or archives or of reproductions of the property defined above;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" Size="9" Leading="10" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">(<I>b</I>) buildings whose main and effective purpose is to preserve or exhibit the movable cultural property defined in subparagraph (<I>a</I>) such as museums, large libraries and depositories of archives, and refuges intended to shelter, in the event of armed conflict, the movable cultural property defined in subparagraph (<I>a</I>);</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" Size="9" Leading="10" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">(<I>c</I>) centres containing a large amount of cultural property as defined in subparagraphs (<I>a</I>) and (<I>b</I>), to be known as ГўВЂВњcentres containing monumentsГўВЂВќ.</Para></Block><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="BPT_ImprintE"><br/><br/>Published under authority of the Senate of Canada</Para></Block><Block Align="Yes" LineCnt="N"><Para NoLineBreak="Yes" NoHtml="Yes" Leading="0" Size="0" TopMargin="0" BottomMargin="0">Г‚В„</Para></Block></Bill_Part></Bill>
