<?xml version="1.0"?>
<Bill RHead_reign="53-54 Eliz. II" RHead_ParlYear="2004-2005" DocumentTitle="BILL S-38" Bill_No="S-38" Document_No="90333" xml:lang="EN" Bill_Type="Non-amending" Stage_Name="Assented-to" Reprint="No" xml:space="preserve" ChapterNo_E="C. 39" ChapterNo_F="ch. 39" Bill-Origin="senate"><Bill_Part Part_Type="Cover" CountLines="No"><Block><Para TopMargin="24" Size="9" Leading="10" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0" TextAlign="Center">First Session, Thirty-eighth Parliament,</Para></Block><Block><Para Size="9" Leading="10" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0" TextAlign="Center">53-54 Elizabeth II, 2004-2005</Para></Block><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="COV@StatutesTitle">STATUTES OF CANADA 2005<br/>CHAPTER 39</Para></Block><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="CovLongTitle">An Act respecting the implementation of international trade commitments by Canada regarding spirit drinks of foreign countries</Para></Block><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="COV_StageLine"></Para></Block><Block><Para BottomMargin="14" Size="11" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0" Bold="Yes" TextAlign="Center">ASSENTED TO</Para></Block><Block><Para Size="8" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0" TextAlign="Center">3rd NOVEMBER, 2005</Para></Block><Block><Para TopMargin="4" Size="8" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0" TextAlign="Center">BILL S-38</Para></Block><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="COV_StageLine"></Para></Block></Bill_Part><Bill_Part CountLines="No" Part_Type="InsideCover"><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="BPT_InsideCoverE">Available on the Parliament of Canada Web Site at the following address:<br/><B>http://www.parl.gc.ca</B></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><Para TopMargin="108" BottomMargin="4" Size="10" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">SUMMARY</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" Size="8" Leading="9" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">This enactment implements international trade commitments made by Canada regarding the use of names of spirit drinks of foreign countries.</Para></Block></Bill_Part><Bill_Part Part_Type="MainText" CountLines="No" RunningHead_E="Spirit Drinks Trade"><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="MAIN@RoyalAssentTitle">53-54 ELIZABETH II</Para></Block><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="MAIN@RoyalAssentTitle">——————</Para></Block><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="MAIN@RoyalAssentTitle">CHAPTER 39</Para></Block><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="LongTitleAssent">An Act respecting the implementation of international trade commitments by Canada regarding spirit drinks of foreign countries</Para></Block><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="MAIN@RoyalAssentDate">[<I>Assented to 3rd November, 2005</I>]</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Preamble<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">WHEREAS Canada has made international commitments regarding the use of names of spirit drinks of foreign countries;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">AND WHEREAS those commitments are contained in the Agreement between Canada and the European Community on trade in wines and spirit drinks, signed on September 16, 2003, and in side letters to that Agreement, in the North American Free Trade Agreement, signed on December 17, 1992, and in commitments made by Canada at the Commonwealth Heads of Government meeting in Nassau in 1985 to establish an economic and trade development program for the Commonwealth Caribbean countries and territories;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">NOW, THEREFORE, Her Majesty, by and with the advice and consent of the Senate and House of Commons of Canada, enacts as follows:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Short title<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>1.</B> This Act may be cited as the <I>Spirit Drinks Trade Act</I>.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Definitions<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>2.</B> The following definitions apply in this Act.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><MarginalNote>“Minister”<br/>« <I>ministre</I> »<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0">“Minister” means the Minister of Agriculture and Agri-Food.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><MarginalNote>“sell”<br/>« <I>vendre</I> »<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0">“sell” includes offer for sale, expose for sale and have in possession for sale.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Prohibition<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>3.</B> (1) No person shall use the name of a spirit drink referred to in sections 1 to 5 of the schedule to sell a product as a spirit drink except in accordance with those sections.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Exception<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(2) Subsection (1) does not prevent the use of the name of a spirit drink to sell the spirit drink if it has been blended or modified in accordance with the laws of Canada.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Exception<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(3) Subsection (1) does not prevent the use of any registered trademark that was applied for before January 1, 1996.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Prohibition<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>3.1</B> (1) No person shall use the name of a spirit drink referred to in sections 6 to 14 of the schedule to sell a product as that spirit drink except in accordance with those sections.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Exception<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(2) Subsection (1) does not prevent the use of the name of a spirit drink to sell the spirit drink if it has been blended or modified in accordance with the laws of Canada.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Amendment of schedule<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>4.</B> The Governor in Council may, by order, amend the schedule to implement Canada’s international trade obligations regarding the use of names of spirit drinks to sell products as spirit drinks.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Inspectors<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>5.</B> (1) The Minister may designate any persons, or classes of persons, as inspectors for the purpose of the enforcement of this Act.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Certificate to be produced<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(2) Every inspector shall be given a certificate in a form established by the Minister attesting to the inspector’s designation and, on entering any place under subsection 6(1), an inspector shall, if so requested, produce the certificate to the person in charge of that place.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Powers of inspectors<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>6.</B> (1) An inspector may at any reasonable time enter any place, including a conveyance but excluding a dwelling-house, where the inspector believes on reasonable grounds any article to which this Act or the regulations apply is manufactured, prepared, preserved, packaged or stored, and may</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>a</I>) examine the article and take samples of it, and examine anything that the inspector believes on reasonable grounds is used or capable of being used for the article’s manufacture, preparation, preservation, packaging or storing;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>b</I>) open and examine any receptacle or package that the inspector believes on reasonable grounds contains any article to which this Act or the regulations apply;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>c</I>) examine and make copies of, or extracts from, any books, documents or other records found in any place referred to in this subsection that the inspector believes on reasonable grounds contain any information with respect to any article to which this Act or the regulations apply; and</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>d</I>) seize and detain for such time as may be necessary any article by means of or in relation to which the inspector believes on reasonable grounds any provision of this Act or the regulations has been contravened.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Assistance and information to be given inspector<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(2) The owner or person in charge of a place entered by an inspector under subsection (1) and every person found in it shall give the inspector all reasonable assistance and furnish the inspector with any information that they may reasonably require.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Obstruction and false statements<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>7.</B> (1) No person shall obstruct or hinder, or knowingly make any false or misleading statement either orally or in writing to, an inspector while the inspector is carrying out their duties or functions under this Act or the regulations.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Prohibition<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(2) Except with the authority of an inspector, no person shall remove or alter in any way any article seized under this Act.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Storage and removal<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>8.</B> Any article seized under this Act may, at the option of an inspector, be kept or stored in the place where it was seized or, at the direction of an inspector, the article may be removed to any other place.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Release of seized articles<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>9.</B> An inspector who has seized any article under this Act shall release it when they are satisfied that all the provisions of this Act and the regulations with respect to it have been complied with.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Destruction with consent<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>10.</B> (1) If an inspector seizes an article under this Act and its owner or the person in whose possession the article was at the time of seizure consents to its destruction, the article is immediately forfeited to Her Majesty and may be destroyed or otherwise disposed of as the Minister may direct.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Forfeiture<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(2) If a person is convicted of a contravention of this Act or the regulations, the court or judge may order that any article by means of or in relation to which the offence was committed, and any thing of a similar nature belonging to or in the possession of the person or found with the article, be forfeited. On the making of the order, the article and thing are forfeited to Her Majesty and may be disposed of as the Minister may direct.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Order for forfeiture on application of inspector<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(3) Without prejudice to subsection (2), a judge of a superior court of the province in which any article is seized under this Act may, on the application of an inspector and on any notice to those persons that the judge directs, order that the article and any thing of a similar nature found with it be forfeited to Her Majesty, if the judge finds, after making any inquiry that the judge considers necessary, that the article is one by means of or in relation to which any of the provisions of this Act or the regulations have been contravened. On the making of the order, the article or thing may be disposed of as the Minister may direct.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Analysts<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>11.</B> The Minister may designate any persons, or classes of persons, as analysts for the purpose of the enforcement of this Act.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Analysis and examination<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>12.</B> (1) An inspector may submit to an analyst for analysis or examination any article seized by the inspector, any sample from it or any sample taken by the inspector.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Certificate or report<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(2) An analyst after making the analysis or examination may issue a certificate or report setting out the results of the analysis or examination.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Regulations<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>13.</B> The Governor in Council may, on the recommendation of the Minister, make regulations for carrying out the purposes and provisions of this Act and, in particular, may make regulations respecting the powers and duties of inspectors and analysts and the taking of samples and the seizure, detention, forfeiture and disposition of articles.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Contravention of Act or regulations<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>14.</B> Every person who contravenes any provision of this Act or the regulations is guilty of an offence and liable</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>a</I>) on summary conviction, to a fine not exceeding $50,000 or to imprisonment for a term not exceeding six months or to both; and</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>b</I>) on conviction on indictment, to a fine not exceeding $250,000 or to imprisonment for a term not exceeding three years or to both.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Defence<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>15.</B> No person shall be found guilty of an offence under this Act, other than an offence under section 7, if the person establishes that they exercised all due diligence to prevent its commission.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Certificate of analyst<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>16.</B> (1) Subject to this section, in any prosecution for an offence under this Act, a certificate purporting to be signed by an analyst and stating that an article, sample or substance has been submitted to, and analysed or examined by, the analyst and stating the results of the analysis or examination is admissible in evidence and, in the absence of evidence to the contrary, is proof of the statements contained in the certificate without proof of the signature or official character of the person appearing to have signed it.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Requiring attendance of analyst<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(2) The party against whom the analyst’s certificate is produced may, with leave of the court, require the attendance of the analyst for the purposes of cross-examination.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Notice of intention to produce certificate<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(3) No certificate shall be admitted in evidence unless, before the trial, the party intending to produce the certificate has given reasonable notice of that intention, together with a copy of the certificate, to the party against whom it is intended to be produced.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Coming into force<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>17.</B> This Act comes into force on June 1, 2006.</Para></Block><Block Align="Yes" LineCnt="N"><Para NoLineBreak="Yes" NoHtml="Yes" Leading="0" Size="0" TopMargin="0" BottomMargin="0"></Para></Block></Bill_Part><Bill_Part Part_Type="Schedule" CountLines="No" RunningHead_E="Spirit Drinks Trade — Schedule"><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><Para TopMargin="10" Size="9" Leading="10" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">SCHEDULE </Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><Para Size="9" Leading="10" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0" Italic="Yes" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">(Sections 3, 3.1 and 4)</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:USE OF SPIRIT DRINK NAMES--><Para TopMargin="5" Size="9" Leading="10" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">USE OF SPIRIT DRINK NAMES</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" Size="9" Leading="10" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">1. (1) A spirit drink may be sold using the name Grappa if it has been produced exclusively in Italy.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" Size="9" Leading="10" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">(2) A spirit drink may be sold using the name <I>Grappa di Ticino</I> if it has been produced in the Ticino region of Switzerland.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" Size="9" Leading="10" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">2. A spirit drink may be sold using the name <I>Jägertee</I>, <I>Jagertee</I> or <I>Jagatee</I> if it has been produced exclusively in Austria.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" Size="9" Leading="10" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">3. A spirit drink may be sold using the name <I>Korn</I> or <I>Kornbrand</I> if it has been produced exclusively in Germany or Austria.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" Size="9" Leading="10" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">4. A spirit drink may be sold using the name Ouzo or <I>Oύζo</I> if it has been produced exclusively in Greece.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" Size="9" Leading="10" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">5. A spirit drink may be sold using the name <I>Pacharán</I> if it has been produced exclusively in Spain.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" Size="9" Leading="10" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">6. Scotch whisky may be sold under that name if it has been distilled in Scotland as Scotch whisky for domestic consumption in accordance with the laws of the United Kingdom.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" Size="9" Leading="10" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">7. Irish whisky may be sold under that name if it has been distilled in Northern Ireland or in the Republic of Ireland as Irish whisky for domestic consumption in accordance with the laws of Northern Ireland or the Republic of Ireland.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" Size="9" Leading="10" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">8. Armagnac brandy may be sold under that name if it has been manufactured in the Armagnac district of France in accordance with the laws of the French Republic for consumption in that country.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" Size="9" Leading="10" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">9. Cognac brandy may be sold under that name if it has been manufactured in the Cognac district of France in accordance with the laws of the French Republic for consumption in that country.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" Size="9" Leading="10" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">10. Bourbon whiskey may be sold under that name if it has been manufactured in the United States in accordance with the laws and regulations of the United States governing the manufacture of Bourbon whiskey.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" Size="9" Leading="10" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">11. Tennessee whiskey may be sold under that name if it has been manufactured in the United States in accordance with the laws and regulations of the United States governing the manufacture of Tennessee whiskey.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" Size="9" Leading="10" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">12. Tequila may be sold under that name if it has been manufactured in Mexico in accordance with the laws and regulations of Mexico governing the manufacture of Tequila.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" Size="9" Leading="10" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">13. Mezcal may be sold under that name if it has been manufactured in Mexico in accordance with the laws and regulations of Mexico governing the manufacture of Mezcal.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" Size="9" Leading="10" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">14. (1) Caribbean rum may be sold under that name if it has been</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" Size="9" Leading="10" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">(<I>a</I>) made from sugar cane products of a Commonwealth Caribbean country and distilled and fermented in a Commonwealth Caribbean country; or</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" Size="9" Leading="10" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">(<I>b</I>) imported in bulk from a Commonwealth Caribbean country for bottling and sale in Canada as Caribbean rum and blended or modified by</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" Size="9" Leading="10" LeftMargin="4" FirstLineIndent="0" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">(i) blending it with other rum of a Commonwealth Caribbean country,</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" Size="9" Leading="10" LeftMargin="4" FirstLineIndent="0" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">(ii) blending it with Canadian rum in proportions that result in 1 to 1.5% Canadian rum by volume in the final product,</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" Size="9" Leading="10" LeftMargin="4" FirstLineIndent="0" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">(iii) adding distilled or otherwise purified water to adjust the rum to the strength stated on the label applied to the container, or</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" Size="9" Leading="10" LeftMargin="4" FirstLineIndent="0" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">(iv) adding caramel.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" Size="9" Leading="10" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">(2) In this section, “Commonwealth Caribbean country” means Anguilla, Antigua and Barbuda, the Bahamas, Barbados, Belize, Bermuda, the British Virgin Islands, the Cayman Islands, Dominica, Grenada, Guyana, Jamaica, Montserrat, St. Christopher and Nevis, Saint Lucia, St. Vincent and the Grenadines, Trinidad and Tobago and the Turks and Caicos Islands.</Para></Block><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="BPT_ImprintE"><br/><br/>Published under authority of the Senate of Canada</Para></Block><Block Align="Yes" LineCnt="N"><Para NoLineBreak="Yes" NoHtml="Yes" Leading="0" Size="0" TopMargin="0" BottomMargin="0"></Para></Block></Bill_Part></Bill>
