<?xml version="1.0"?>
<Bill RHead_reign="51-52 Eliz. II" RHead_ParlYear="2002-2003" DocumentTitle="BILL S-20" Bill_No="S-20" Document_No="2520" xml:lang="EN" Bill_Type="Amending" Stage_Name="First-Reading-Senate" Reprint="No" xml:space="preserve" ChapterNo_E="C. " ChapterNo_F="ch. " Bill-Origin="senate"><Bill_Part Part_Type="Cover" CountLines="No"><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="CovBillNo">S-20</Para></Block><Block><Para TopMargin="24" Size="9" Leading="10" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0" TextAlign="Center">Second Session, Thirty-seventh Parliament,</Para></Block><Block><Para Size="9" Leading="10" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0" TextAlign="Center">51-52 Elizabeth II, 2002-2003</Para></Block><Block><Para TopMargin="48" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0" Bold="Yes" TextAlign="Center">SENATE OF CANADA</Para></Block><Block><Para TopMargin="42" Size="18" Leading="20" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0" Bold="Yes" TextAlign="Center">BILL S-20</Para></Block><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="CovLongTitle">An Act to amend the Copyright Act</Para></Block><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="COV_StageLine"></Para></Block><Block><Para Size="9" AllCaps="Yes" Hyphenate="OFF">first reading, May 15, 2003</Para></Block><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="COV_StageLine"></Para></Block><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="Cover_Sponsors"><SC SC_PerCent="85">The Honourable Senator Day</SC></Para></Block><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="Cover_DocNo">2520</Para></Block></Bill_Part><Bill_Part CountLines="No" Part_Type="InsideCover"><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="BPT_InsideCoverE">Available on the Parliament of Canada Web Site at the following address:<br/><B>http://www.parl.gc.ca</B></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><Para TopMargin="108" BottomMargin="4" Size="10" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center"><SC SC_PerCent="85">Summary</SC></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" Size="8" Leading="9" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">This enactment amends the <I>Copyright Act</I> to eliminate an exception to the general rule on ownership of copyright.  Under that exception, a person who commissioned a photograph, engraving or portrait for consideration is the first owner of the copyright in the work.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" Size="8" Leading="9" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">It also eliminates a legal fiction that deems the person who owned an initial photograph, negative or plate at the time of its making to be the author of the photograph, and eliminates a related rule that involves a restricted term of copyright in photographs applicable to certain corporations.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" Size="8" Leading="9" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">The effect of these changes is that the photographer is the author of a photograph for the purposes of the <I>Copyright Act</I>, and that photographs, engravings and portraits fall under the general rule that gives first ownership of the copyright in a work to the author.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" Size="8" Leading="9" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">The amendments relating to ownership of copyright apply to photographs, engravings and portraits commissioned after the enactment comes into force; the amendments relating to authorship apply to photographs made after the enactment comes into force; and the amendments relating to the term of copyright apply to photographs not in the public domain at the time the enactment comes into force.</Para></Block></Bill_Part><Bill_Part Part_Type="MainText" CountLines="Yes" RunningHead_E="Copyright Act"><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="MainText_DocNo">2520</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes"><Para Style="Session_Reign">2nd Session, 37th Parliament,</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes"><Para Style="Session_Reign">51-52 Elizabeth II, 2002-2003</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes"><Para Style="MainBillOrigin">senate of canada</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes"><Para Bold="Yes" Style="MAIN@BillNo_Title">BILL S-20</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes"><Para Style="MAIN@ti;04">An Act to amend the Copyright Act</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>R.S., c. C-42<br/></MarginalNote><Para LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">Her Majesty, by and with the advice and consent of the Senate and House of Commons of Canada, enacts as follows:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>1.</B> Section 10 of the <I>Copyright Act</I> is repealed.</Para><ExplNote><Para Align="Yes" TopMargin="10" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0" Italic="Yes" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">Copyright Act</Para><Para Align="Yes" TopMargin="10" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><I>Clause 1</I>: Section 10 reads as follows:</Para><Para Align="Yes" TopMargin="5" Size="8" Leading="9" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>10.</B> (1) Where the owner referred to in subsection (2) is a corporation, the term for which copyright subsists in a photograph shall be the remainder of the year of the making of the initial negative or plate from which the photograph was derived or, if there is no negative or plate, of the initial photograph, plus a period of fifty years.</Para><Para Align="Yes" TopMargin="5" Size="8" Leading="9" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(1.1) Where the owner is a corporation, the majority of the voting shares of which are owned by a natural person who would have qualified as the author of the photograph except for subsection (2), the term of copyright is the term set out in section 6.</Para><Para Align="Yes" TopMargin="5" Size="8" Leading="9" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(2) The person who</Para><Para Align="No" TopMargin="5" Size="8" Leading="9" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(a) was the owner of the initial negative or other plate at the time when that negative or other plate was made, or</Para><Para Align="No" TopMargin="5" Size="8" Leading="9" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(b) was the owner of the initial photograph at the time when that photograph was made, where there was no negative or other plate,</Para><Para Align="No" TopMargin="5" Size="8" Leading="9" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0">is deemed to be the author of the photograph and, where that owner is a body corporate, the body corporate is deemed for the purposes of this Act to be ordinarily resident in a treaty country if it has established a place of business therein.</Para></ExplNote></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>2.</B> Subsection 13(2) of the Act is repealed.</Para><ExplNote><Para Align="Yes" TopMargin="10" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><I>Clause 2</I>: Subsection 13(2) reads as follows:</Para><Para Align="Yes" TopMargin="5" Size="8" Leading="9" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(2) Where, in the case of an engraving, photograph or portrait, the plate or other original was ordered by some other person and was made for valuable consideration, and the consideration was paid, in pursuance of that order, in the absence of any agreement to the contrary, the person by whom the plate or other original was ordered shall be the first owner of the copyright.</Para></ExplNote></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Application of former section 10<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>3.</B> Subject to section 4, section 10 of the <I>Copyright Act</I>, as that section read immediately before the coming into force of this Act, continues to apply in respect of photographs made before the coming into force of this Act.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Term of copyright for unexpired terms<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>4.</B> (1) Where the term of copyright protection for a photograph referred to in section 3 has not expired before the day on which this Act comes into force, the term for which copyright subsists in the photograph shall be the term set out in section 6 of the <I>Copyright Act</I> and, for the purposes of calculating that term, the author of the photograph is deemed to be the natural person who would have qualified as the author except for the application of subsection 10(2) of the <I>Copyright Act</I> as it read immediately before the coming into force of this Act.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Non-application<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes">(2) Subsection (1) does not apply in circumstances where its application would shorten the term for which copyright subsists in a photograph.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Application of former subsection 13(2)<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>5.</B> Subsection 13(2) of the <I>Copyright Act</I>, as that subsection read immediately before the coming into force of this Act, continues to apply, in the circumstances described in that subsection, in respect of engravings, photographs and portraits ordered before that time, whether made before or after that time.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Coming into force<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>6.</B> This Act comes into force on a day to be fixed by order of the Governor in Council.</Para></Block><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="BPT_ImprintE"><br/><br/>Published under authority of the Senate of Canada</Para></Block><Block Align="Yes" LineCnt="N"><Para NoLineBreak="Yes" NoHtml="Yes" Leading="0" Size="0" TopMargin="0" BottomMargin="0"></Para></Block></Bill_Part></Bill>
