<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<Bill bill-origin="commons" bill-type="private-public" xml:lang="en" date-time="2016-05-26 10:06:01">
  <Identification>
    <BillNumber>C-210</BillNumber>
    <Parliament>
      <Session>2</Session>
      <Number>43</Number>
      <RegnalYear>
        <Year-s>69-70</Year-s>
        <Monarch>Elizabeth II</Monarch>
      </RegnalYear>
      <Year-s>2020-2021</Year-s>
    </Parliament>
    <LongTitle>An Act to amend the Canada Revenue Agency Act (organ and tissue donors)</LongTitle>
    <ShortTitle status="unofficial" />
    <RunningHead>An Act to amend the Canada Revenue Agency Act (organ donors)</RunningHead>
    <BillHistory>
      <Stages stage="assented-to">
        <Date>
          <YYYY>2021</YYYY>
          <MM>6</MM>
          <DD>21</DD>
        </Date>
      </Stages>
    </BillHistory>
    
    
    <Chapter><ConsolidatedNumber /><AnnualStatuteId><AnnualStatuteNumber>12</AnnualStatuteNumber><YYYY>2021</YYYY></AnnualStatuteId></Chapter><BillRefNumber date-time="2016-05-26">431055</BillRefNumber>
  </Identification>
  <Introduction>
    <Summary>
      <TitleText>SUMMARY</TitleText>
      <Provision first-line-indent="0" subsequent-line-indent="0">
        <Text>This enactment amends the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Canada Revenue Agency Act</XRefExternal> to authorize the Canada Revenue Agency to enter into an agreement with a province or a territory regarding the collection and disclosure of information required for establishing or maintaining an organ and tissue donor registry in the province or territory.</Text>
      </Provision>
    </Summary>
    <Enacts>
      <Provision first-line-indent="0" subsequent-line-indent="0">
        <Text>Her Majesty, by and with the advice and consent of the Senate and House of Commons of Canada, <Keep>enacts</Keep> as follows:</Text>
      </Provision>
    </Enacts>
  </Introduction>
  <Body>
    <Heading level="1">
      <MarginalNote>
        <HistoricalNote>1999, c. 17; 2005, c. 38, s. 35</HistoricalNote>
      </MarginalNote>
      <TitleText>Canada Revenue Agency Act</TitleText>
    </Heading>
    <Section type="amending">
      <Label>1</Label>
      <Text>The <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Canada Revenue Agency Act</XRefExternal> is amended by adding the following after section 63:</Text>
      <AmendedText>
        <Section>
          <MarginalNote>Agreements 芒聙聰 organ donors</MarginalNote>
          <Label>63.1</Label>
          <Subsection>
            <Label>(1)</Label>
            <Text>The Agency may enter into an agreement with a provincial or territorial government to collect芒聙聣芒聙聰芒聙聣using the returns of income filed under paragraph 150(1)(d) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Income Tax Act</XRefExternal>芒聙聣芒聙聰芒聙聣any information that the province or territory requires for the purpose of  establishing or maintaining an organ and tissue donor registry in the province or territory.</Text>
          </Subsection>
          <Subsection>
            <MarginalNote>Disclosure</MarginalNote>
            <Label>(2)</Label>
            <Text>The Agency may disclose to the province or territory in which an individual resides the information collected in accordance with the agreement if, in their return of income, that individual   authorized the Agency to provide the information to that province or territory.</Text>
          </Subsection>
        </Section>
      </AmendedText>
    </Section>
  </Body>
</Bill>