

<Bill bill-origin="commons" bill-type="private-public" xml:lang="en" date-time="2018-10-25 16:14:29">
  <Identification>
    <BillNumber>C-223</BillNumber>
    <Parliament>
      <Session>1</Session>
      <Number>43</Number>
      <RegnalYear>
        <Year-s>68-69</Year-s>
        <Monarch>Elizabeth II</Monarch>
      </RegnalYear>
      <Year-s>2019-2020</Year-s>
    </Parliament>
    <LongTitle>An Act to amend the Citizenship Act (adequate knowledge of French in Quebec)</LongTitle>
    <ShortTitle status="unofficial" />
    <RunningHead>An Act to amend the Citizenship Act (adequate knowledge of French in Quebec)</RunningHead>
    <BillHistory>
      <Stages stage="first-reading-house">
        <Date>
          <YYYY>2020</YYYY>
          <MM>2</MM>
          <DD>25</DD>
        </Date>
      </Stages>
    </BillHistory>
    <BillSponsor>
      <Emphasis style="smallcaps">Ms. Bérubé</Emphasis>
    </BillSponsor>
    <ReaderNote>
      <Note>
        <Provision justification="center" pointsize="10" topmarginspacing="0">
          <Text>
            <Emphasis style="bold">NOTE</Emphasis>
          </Text>
        </Provision>
        <Provision justification="center">
          <Text>2nd Session, 43rd Parliament</Text>
        </Provision>
        <Provision justification="justify" hyphenation="yes">
          <Text>This bill was introduced during the first session of the 43rd Parliament. Pursuant to the Standing Orders of the House of Commons, it is deemed to have been considered and approved at all stages completed at the time of prorogation of the first session. The number of the bill remains unchanged.</Text>
        </Provision>
      </Note>
    </ReaderNote>
    <BillRefNumber date-time="2018-10-25">431111</BillRefNumber>
  </Identification>
  <Introduction>
    <Summary>
      <TitleText>SUMMARY</TitleText>
      <Provision>
        <Text>This enactment amends the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Citizenship Act</XRefExternal> to require that permanent residents who ordinarily reside in Quebec must have an adequate knowledge of French in order to obtain citizenship.</Text>
      </Provision>
    </Summary>
    <Enacts>
      <Provision>
        <Text>Her Majesty, by and with the advice and consent <Keep>of the</Keep> Senate and House of Commons of Canada, <Keep>enacts</Keep> as follows:</Text>
      </Provision>
    </Enacts>
  </Introduction>
  <Body>
    <Heading level="1">
      <MarginalNote>
        <HistoricalNote>R.S., c. C-29</HistoricalNote>
      </MarginalNote>
      <TitleText>Citizenship Act</TitleText>
    </Heading>
    <Section type="amending">
      <Label>1</Label>
      <Text>Paragraphs 5(1)(d) and (e) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Citizenship Act</XRefExternal> are replaced by the following:</Text>
      <AmendedText>
        <SectionPiece>
          <Paragraph>
            <Label>(d)</Label>
            <Text>if 18 years of age or more but less than <Ins>65</Ins> years of age at the date of his or her application, has an adequate knowledge of one of the official languages of Canada, <Ins>unless the person ordinarily resides in Quebec, in which case he or she must have an adequate knowledge of French</Ins>;</Text>
          </Paragraph>
          <Paragraph>
            <Label>(e)</Label>
            <Text>if 18 years of age or more but less than <Ins>65</Ins> years of age at the date of his or her application, demonstrates in one of the official languages of Canada that he or she has an adequate knowledge of Canada and of the responsibilities and privileges of citizenship, <Ins>unless the person ordinarily resides in Quebec, in which case he or she must demonstrate that knowledge in French</Ins>; and</Text>
          </Paragraph>
        </SectionPiece>
      </AmendedText>
    </Section>
  </Body>
</Bill>