

<Bill bill-origin="commons" bill-type="private-public" xml:lang="en" date-time="2020-02-18 09:09:23"><Identification><BillNumber>C-233</BillNumber><Parliament><Session>1</Session><Number>43</Number><RegnalYear><Year-s>68-69</Year-s><Monarch>Elizabeth II</Monarch></RegnalYear><Year-s>2019-2020</Year-s></Parliament><LongTitle>An Act to amend the Criminal Code (sex-selective abortion)</LongTitle><ShortTitle status="unofficial" /><RunningHead>Sex-selective Abortion Act</RunningHead><BillHistory><Stages stage="first-reading-house"><Date><YYYY>2020</YYYY><MM>2</MM><DD>26</DD></Date></Stages></BillHistory><BillSponsor><Emphasis style="smallcaps">Mrs. Wagantall</Emphasis></BillSponsor><ReaderNote><Note><Provision justification="center" pointsize="10" topmarginspacing="0"><Text><Emphasis style="bold">NOTE</Emphasis></Text></Provision><Provision justification="center"><Text>2nd Session, 43rd Parliament</Text></Provision><Provision justification="justify" hyphenation="yes"><Text>This bill was introduced during the first session of the 43rd Parliament. Pursuant to the Standing Orders of the House of Commons, it is deemed to have been considered and approved at all stages completed at the time of prorogation of the first session. The number of the bill remains unchanged.</Text></Provision></Note></ReaderNote><BillRefNumber date-time="2020-02-18">431098</BillRefNumber></Identification><Introduction><Summary><TitleText>SUMMARY</TitleText><Provision><Text>This enactment amends the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Criminal Code</XRefExternal> to make it an offence for a medical practitioner to perform an abortion knowing that the abortion is sought solely on the grounds of the child’s genetic sex. It also requires the Minister of Health, after consultation with representatives of the provincial governments responsible for health, to establish guidelines respecting information provided by a medical practitioner in relation to a request for an abortion.</Text></Provision></Summary><Preamble><Provision pointsize="10"><MarginalNote>Preamble</MarginalNote><Text>Whereas the Government of Canada is firmly committed to protecting and advancing human rights, both in Canada and abroad; </Text></Provision><Provision><Text>Whereas ending discrimination against any person on the basis of sex is a crucial part of Canada’s efforts to promote and protect human rights, as reflected in its laws and international commitments; </Text></Provision><Provision><Text>Whereas the practice of terminating a pregnancy solely on the grounds of the genetic sex of the child values one sex over the other and is therefore a form of sex-based discrimination;</Text></Provision><Provision><Text>And whereas the Government of Canada believes that abortion performed on the basis of genetic sex is inconsistent with its commitment to the protection of equality rights and that the issue must be addressed by legislation;</Text></Provision><Provision language-align="yes"><Text>Now, therefore, Her Majesty, by and with the advice and consent of the Senate and House of Commons of Canada, enacts as follows:</Text></Provision></Preamble></Introduction><Body><Heading level="1"><TitleText>Short Title</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Short title</MarginalNote><Label>1</Label><Text>This Act may be cited as the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Sex-selective Abortion Act</XRefExternal>.</Text></Section><Heading level="1"><MarginalNote><HistoricalNote>R.S., c. C-46</HistoricalNote></MarginalNote><TitleText>Criminal Code</TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><Label>2</Label><Text>The heading after section 286.5 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Criminal Code</XRefExternal> is replaced by the following:</Text></Section><Heading level="1" change="ins"><TitleText>Abortion — Sex Selection</TitleText></Heading><Section change="ins"><MarginalNote>Definitions</MarginalNote><Label>287</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The following definitions apply in this section.</Text><Definition><Text><DefinedTermEn>genetic sex</DefinedTermEn> means the sex that is capable of being determined at the time of conception by the presence or absence of the Y chromosome. (<DefinedTermFr>sexe génétique</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Definition><Definition><Text><DefinedTermEn>means</DefinedTermEn> includes</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>the prescription or administration of a drug;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>the use of an instrument; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(c)</Label><Text>manipulation of any kind. (<DefinedTermFr>moyen</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Paragraph></Definition><Definition><Text><DefinedTermEn>medical practitioner</DefinedTermEn> means a person who is entitled to practise medicine under the laws of a province. (<DefinedTermFr>médecin</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Definition></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Performing an abortion — sex selection</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>A medical practitioner who uses any means to perform an abortion knowing that the abortion is sought solely on the grounds of the child’s genetic sex is guilty of</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>an indictable offence and liable to imprisonment for a term of not more than five years; or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>an offence punishable on summary conviction and liable to imprisonment for a term of not more than 18 months.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Guidelines</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>The Minister of Health, after consultation with representatives of the provincial governments responsible for health, shall establish guidelines on information provided by a medical practitioner, in relation to a request for an abortion, respecting the offence under subsection (2), as well as the form, manner and time in which the information may be provided.</Text></Subsection></Section></Body></Bill>