<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<Bill bill-origin="commons" bill-type="private-public" xml:lang="en" date-time="2020-02-18 16:05:36"><Identification><BillNumber>C-230</BillNumber><Parliament><Session>2</Session><Number>43</Number><RegnalYear><Year-s>69-70</Year-s><Monarch>Elizabeth II</Monarch></RegnalYear><Year-s>2020-2021</Year-s></Parliament><LongTitle>An Act respecting the development of a national strategy to <Ins>assess, prevent and address</Ins> environmental racism <Ins>and to advance environmental justice</Ins></LongTitle><ShortTitle status="unofficial" /><RunningHead>National Strategy Respecting Environmental Racism and Environmental Justice Act</RunningHead><BillHistory><Stages stage="report-house"><Date><YYYY>2021</YYYY><MM>6</MM><DD>22</DD></Date><StageText>Reprinted as amended by the Standing Committee on Environment and Sustainable Development as a working copy for the use of the House of Commons at Report Stage and as reported to the House on June 22, 2021</StageText></Stages></BillHistory><BillSponsor><Emphasis style="smallcaps">Ms. Zann</Emphasis></BillSponsor><BillRefNumber date-time="2020-02-18">431061</BillRefNumber></Identification><Introduction><Summary><TitleText>SUMMARY</TitleText><Provision><Text>This enactment requires the Minister of the Environment, in consultation or cooperation with any persons, bodies, organizations or communities who are interested, to develop a national strategy to promote efforts across Canada to address the harm caused by environmental racism. It also provides for reporting requirements in relation to the strategy.</Text></Provision></Summary><Preamble><Provision change="ins"><MarginalNote>Preamble</MarginalNote><Text>Whereas the Government of Canada recognizes the need to advance environmental justice across Canada and the importance of continuing to work towards eliminating racism and racial discrimination in all their forms and manifestations;</Text></Provision><Provision pointsize="10"><Text>Whereas a disproportionate number of people who live in environmentally hazardous areas are members of an Indigenous, racialized or <Ins>other marginalized</Ins> community;</Text></Provision><Provision><Text>Whereas the establishing of environmentally hazardous sites, including landfills and polluting industries, in areas inhabited primarily by members of those communities could be considered a form of racial discrimination;</Text></Provision><Provision><Text>Whereas <Ins>the Government of Canada recognizes that it is important to meaningfully involve all Canadians — and, in particular, marginalized</Ins> communities <Ins>— in the development of</Ins> environmental <Ins>policy and that</Ins> racial discrimination <Ins>in the development of environmental policy</Ins> would constitute environmental racism;</Text></Provision><Provision><Text>Whereas the Government of Canada is committed to <Ins>assessing and</Ins> preventing environmental racism and to providing affected communities with the opportunity to participate in, <Ins>among other things</Ins>, finding solutions to <Ins>address</Ins> harm caused by environmental racism;</Text></Provision><Provision><Text>And whereas the Government of Canada recognizes that collaboration and a coordinated national strategy are key to promoting effective change and achieving environmental justice; </Text></Provision><Provision language-align="yes"><Text>Now, therefore, Her Majesty, by and with the advice and consent of the Senate and House of Commons of Canada, enacts as follows:</Text></Provision></Preamble></Introduction><Body><Heading level="1"><TitleText>Short Title</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Short title</MarginalNote><Label>1</Label><Text>This Act may be cited as the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">National Strategy <Ins>Respecting</Ins> Environmental Racism <Ins>and Environmental Justice</Ins> Act</XRefExternal>.</Text></Section><Heading level="1"><TitleText>Interpretation</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Definition of <Emphasis style="italic">Minister</Emphasis></MarginalNote><Label>2</Label><Text>In this Act, <DefinedTermEn>Minister</DefinedTermEn> means the Minister of the Environment.</Text></Section><Heading level="1"><TitleText>National Strategy <Ins>Respecting</Ins> Environmental Racism <Ins>and Environmental Justice</Ins></TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>National strategy</MarginalNote><Label>3</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The Minister must develop a national strategy to promote efforts across Canada to <Ins>advance environmental justice and to assess, prevent and address</Ins> environmental racism.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Consultation</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>In developing the strategy, the Minister must consult <Ins>or cooperate</Ins> with any persons, bodies, <Ins>organizations or</Ins> communities — <Ins>including</Ins> other <Ins>Ministers</Ins>, representatives of governments <Ins>in Canada,</Ins> and Indigenous communities — <Ins>who are interested and ensures that it is consistent with the framework for the Government of Canada's implementation of the United Nations Declaration on the Rights of Indigenous Peoples</Ins>.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Content</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>The strategy must include</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text><Ins>a study that must include</Ins></Text><Subparagraph><Label><Ins>(i)</Ins></Label><Text><Ins>an examination of</Ins> the link between race, socio-economic status and environmental risk, and</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph><Label><Ins>(ii)</Ins></Label><Text>information and statistics relating to the location of environmental hazards; and</Text></Subparagraph></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>measures <Ins>that can be taken to advance environmental justice and assess, prevent and</Ins> address environmental racism <Ins>and that may include</Ins></Text><Subparagraph><Label><Ins>(i)</Ins></Label><Text>possible amendments to federal laws, policies and programs,
</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph><Label><Ins>(ii)</Ins></Label><Text>the involvement of community groups in environmental policy-making,</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph><Label><Ins>(iii)</Ins></Label><Text>compensation for individuals or communities, and
</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph><Label><Ins>(iv)</Ins></Label><Text><Ins>the collection of</Ins> information and statistics relating to health outcomes in communities <Ins>located in proximity to environmental hazards</Ins>.</Text></Subparagraph></Paragraph></Subsection></Section><Heading level="1"><TitleText>Reports to Parliament

</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Tabling of national strategy</MarginalNote><Label>4</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Within two years after the day on which this Act comes into force, the Minister must prepare a report setting out the national strategy and cause it to be tabled in each House of Parliament on any of the first 15 days on which that House is sitting after it is completed.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Publication</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The Minister must publish the report on the website of the Department of the Environment within 10 days after it has been tabled in both Houses of Parliament.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Report</MarginalNote><Label>5</Label><Text>Within five years after the report referred to in <Keep>section 4</Keep> has been tabled in both Houses of Parliament, and every five years after that, the Minister must, in consultation with the parties referred to in subsection 3(2), prepare a report on the effectiveness of the national strategy that sets out the Minister’s conclusions and recommendations, and cause the report to be tabled in each House of Parliament on any of the first 15 days on which that House is sitting after it is completed.</Text></Section></Body></Bill>