

<Bill bill-origin="commons" bill-type="private-public" xml:lang="en" date-time="2016-06-20 08:52:01"><Identification><BillNumber>C-239</BillNumber><Parliament><Session>1</Session><Number>43</Number><RegnalYear><Year-s>68-69</Year-s><Monarch>Elizabeth II</Monarch></RegnalYear><Year-s>2019-2020</Year-s></Parliament><LongTitle>An Act to establish a national cycling strategy</LongTitle><ShortTitle status="unofficial" /><RunningHead>National Cycling Strategy Act</RunningHead><BillHistory><Stages stage="first-reading-house"><Date><YYYY>2020</YYYY><MM>3</MM><DD>11</DD></Date></Stages></BillHistory><BillSponsor><Emphasis style="smallcaps">Mr. Johns</Emphasis></BillSponsor><ReaderNote><Note><Provision justification="center" pointsize="10" topmarginspacing="0"><Text><Emphasis style="bold">NOTE</Emphasis></Text></Provision><Provision justification="center"><Text>2nd Session, 43rd Parliament</Text></Provision><Provision justification="justify" hyphenation="yes"><Text>This bill was introduced during the first session of the 43rd Parliament. Pursuant to the Standing Orders of the House of Commons, it is deemed to have been considered and approved at all stages completed at the time of prorogation of the first session. The number of the bill remains unchanged.</Text></Provision></Note></ReaderNote><BillRefNumber date-time="2016-06-20">431050</BillRefNumber></Identification><Introduction><Summary><TitleText>SUMMARY</TitleText><Provision><Text>This enactment provides for the development and implementation of a national strategy on cycling.</Text></Provision></Summary><Preamble><Provision pointsize="10"><MarginalNote>Preamble</MarginalNote><Text>Whereas cycling provides important environmental, social and economic benefits, including a healthier lifestyle, reduced road traffic and lower greenhouse gas emissions;</Text></Provision><Provision><Text>Whereas all Canadians, regardless of age, ability, gender, economic status or location, should be able to avail themselves of the benefits of cycling;</Text></Provision><Provision><Text>Whereas current conditions for cycling vary significantly across the country and a comprehensive strategy could engage other levels of government to help link cycling networks and create community support for cycling;</Text></Provision><Provision><Text>Whereas Canada’s landscape provides a unique opportunity to encourage cycling tourism from around the globe;</Text></Provision><Provision><Text>Whereas many countries that are members of the Organisation for Economic Co-<Keep>operation and</Keep> Development have comprehensive policies to encourage cycling and, as a result, have seen an increase in the popularity and safety of cycling;</Text></Provision><Provision><Text>Whereas the development of cycling infrastructure has shown significant and positive effects on local economies and has demonstrated significant overall return on investment;</Text></Provision><Provision><Text>Whereas it is in the interest of the federal government to play a significant role in supporting and encouraging cycling in all forms through infrastructure planning, programming, standards and education;</Text></Provision><Provision><Text>And whereas a national cycling strategy would promote research, help create infrastructure projects and establish a clear framework for investment in order to support and increase all types of cycling in Canada, including commuter, tourism and recreational cycling; </Text></Provision><Provision language-align="yes"><Text>Now, therefore, Her Majesty, by and with the advice and consent <Keep>of the</Keep> Senate and House of Commons of Canada, <Keep>enacts</Keep> as follows:</Text></Provision></Preamble></Introduction><Body><Heading level="1"><TitleText>Short Title</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Short title</MarginalNote><Label>1</Label><Text>This Act may be cited as the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">National Cycling Strategy Act</XRefExternal>.</Text></Section><Heading level="1"><TitleText>National Cycling Strategy</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>National cycling strategy</MarginalNote><Label>2</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The Minister of Transport must, in collaboration with the Minister of the Environment and in consultation with the ministers responsible for health, infrastructure, sport, communities, education and intergovernmental affairs, as well as representatives of the provincial and territorial governments responsible for those matters, municipalities, Indigenous communities, cycling organizations, businesses representatives from the cycling industry and other stakeholders interested in cycling, develop and implement a national cycling strategy that includes measures to</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>facilitate the building and maintenance of safe and efficient cycling infrastructure for cyclists of all ages in order to support healthy, vibrant and liveable communities;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>support national programs, standards, education and training to promote cycling;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(c)</Label><Text>identify fiscal and policy requirements to support and promote cycling, encourage commuter, tourism and recreational cycling, and support the cycling industry in Canada;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(d)</Label><Text>review existing policies regarding cycling across the country year-round and the transportation legislation, regulation and standards needed to increase road safety, such as the requirement for mandatory side guards on all vehicles in higher weight categories;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(e)</Label><Text>maximize cycling’s role in reducing greenhouse gas emissions and criteria air contaminants to help meet Canada’s climate goals;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(f)</Label><Text>recognize cycling’s contributions to health and well-being, as well as its role in reducing healthcare spending as a result of increased physical activity and fitness;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(g)</Label><Text>outline clear and achievable targets for the growth of commuter cycling, as well as for increased tourism and recreational cycling;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(h)</Label><Text>facilitate the gathering of data and the monitoring of indicators that illustrate the extent of cycling in communities, such as the number of children who cycle to school and adults who cycle to work; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(i)</Label><Text>identify industry policies that could be used to support Canadian cycle and retail manufacturing while taking into account trade issues impacting the cost of cycling products, including duties and other importation restrictions.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Conference</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Within one year after the day on which this Act comes into force, the Minister of Transport must, in collaboration with the Minister of the Environment, convene a conference with the ministers responsible for health, infrastructure, sport, communities, education and intergovernmental affairs, as well as representatives of the provincial and territorial governments responsible for those matters, municipalities, Indigenous communities, cycling organizations, businesses representatives from the cycling industry and other stakeholders interested in cycling, for the purpose of developing the national strategy.</Text></Subsection></Section><Heading level="1"><TitleText>Reports to Parliament</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Report setting out strategy</MarginalNote><Label>3</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Within two years after the day on which this Act comes into force, the Minister of Transport must prepare a report setting out the national cycling strategy and cause it to be tabled before each House of Parliament on any of the first 15 days on which that House is sitting following the completion of the report.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Publication of report</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The Minister must post the report on the Department of Transport's Web site within 30 days after the day on which the report is tabled in Parliament.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Report on effectiveness</MarginalNote><Label>4</Label><Text>Within five years after the day on which the report referred to in section 3 is tabled and every three years after that, the Minister of Transport must prepare a report on the effectiveness of the national cycling strategy, setting out his or her conclusions and recommendations regarding the strategy, and cause the report to be tabled before each House of Parliament on any of the first 15 days on which that House is sitting following the completion of the report.</Text></Section></Body></Bill>