

<Bill bill-origin="commons" bill-type="private-public" xml:lang="en" date-time="2019-06-03 15:08:33"><Identification><BillNumber>C-246</BillNumber><Parliament><Session>2</Session><Number>43</Number><RegnalYear><Year-s>69</Year-s><Monarch>Elizabeth II</Monarch></RegnalYear><Year-s>2020</Year-s></Parliament><LongTitle>An Act to amend the Income Tax Act and the Canada Student Financial Assistance Act</LongTitle><ShortTitle status="unofficial" /><RunningHead>Post-Secondary Education Financial Assistance for Persons with Disabilities Act</RunningHead><BillHistory><Stages stage="first-reading-house"><Date><YYYY>2020</YYYY><MM>9</MM><DD>30</DD></Date></Stages></BillHistory><BillSponsor><Emphasis style="smallcaps">Mr. Davies</Emphasis></BillSponsor><BillRefNumber date-time="2019-06-03">431047</BillRefNumber></Identification><Introduction><Summary><TitleText>SUMMARY </TitleText><Provision><Text>This enactment provides for financial assistance for Canadians with disabilities to improve their access to post-secondary education.</Text></Provision></Summary><Preamble><Provision pointsize="10"><MarginalNote>Preamble</MarginalNote><Text>Whereas an estimated one in five Canadians aged 15 years and over has one or more disabilities that limit them in their daily activities;</Text></Provision><Provision><Text>Whereas the 2017 Canadian Survey on Disability stated that youth with disabilities are at a higher risk of not being in school or employed and that this risk increases with the severity of the disability;</Text></Provision><Provision><Text>And whereas Parliament recognizes the importance of ensuring that all Canadians with disabilities have access to post-secondary education; </Text></Provision><Provision language-align="yes"><Text>Now, therefore, Her Majesty, by and with the advice and consent of the Senate and House of Commons of Canada, enacts as follows:</Text></Provision></Preamble></Introduction><Body><Heading level="1"><TitleText>Short Title</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Short title</MarginalNote><Label>1</Label><Text>This Act may be cited as the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Post-Secondary Education Financial Assistance for Persons with Disabilities Act</XRefExternal>.</Text></Section><Heading level="1"><MarginalNote><HistoricalNote>R.S., c.1 (5<Sup>th</Sup> Supp.)</HistoricalNote></MarginalNote><TitleText>Income Tax Act</TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><Label>2</Label><Text>Subsection 81(1) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Income Tax Act</XRefExternal> is amended by adding the following after paragraph (h.1):</Text><AmendedText><SectionPiece><Paragraph change="ins"><MarginalNote>Tuition for persons with disabilities</MarginalNote><Label>(h.2)</Label><Text>an amount paid under section 9.3 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Canada Student Financial Assistance Act</XRefExternal>;</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Section><Heading level="1"><MarginalNote><HistoricalNote>1994, c. 28</HistoricalNote></MarginalNote><TitleText>Canada Student Financial Assistance Act</TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><Label>3</Label><Text>The <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Canada Student Financial Assistance Act</XRefExternal> is amended by adding the following after section 9.2:</Text><AmendedText><Heading level="1" change="ins"><TitleText>Tuition for Persons with Disabilities</TitleText></Heading><Section change="ins"><MarginalNote>Payment of tuition</MarginalNote><Label>9.3</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Subject to any prescribed conditions, if an individual in respect of whom an amount is deductible under section 118.3 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Income Tax Act</XRefExternal> is enrolled in a designated educational institution, the Minister shall pay that individual’s tuition fees to that designated educational institution.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Grant</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The amount of any tuition fees paid under subsection (1) is deemed to be a grant to the individual on whose behalf it is paid.</Text></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>4</Label><Text>Subsection 15(1) of the Act is amended by adding the following after paragraph (p):</Text><AmendedText><SectionPiece><Paragraph change="ins"><Label>(p.1)</Label><Text>providing for the conditions to be met before a payment under section 9.3 may be made;</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Section></Body></Bill>