

<Bill bill-origin="commons" bill-type="private-public" xml:lang="en" date-time="2018-05-28 08:28:05"><Identification><BillNumber>C-245</BillNumber><Parliament><Session>1</Session><Number>43</Number><RegnalYear><Year-s>68-69</Year-s><Monarch>Elizabeth II</Monarch></RegnalYear><Year-s>2019-2020</Year-s></Parliament><LongTitle>An Act respecting the development of a national strategy in relation to fresh water</LongTitle><ShortTitle status="unofficial" /><RunningHead>National Freshwater Strategy Act</RunningHead><BillHistory><Stages stage="first-reading-house"><Date><YYYY>2020</YYYY><MM>7</MM><DD>21</DD></Date></Stages></BillHistory><BillSponsor><Emphasis style="smallcaps">Ms. Mathyssen</Emphasis></BillSponsor><ReaderNote><Note><Provision justification="center" pointsize="10" topmarginspacing="0"><Text><Emphasis style="bold">NOTE</Emphasis></Text></Provision><Provision justification="center"><Text>2nd Session, 43rd Parliament</Text></Provision><Provision justification="justify" hyphenation="yes"><Text>This bill was introduced during the first session of the 43rd Parliament. Pursuant to the Standing Orders of the House of Commons, it is deemed to have been considered and approved at all stages completed at the time of prorogation of the first session. The number of the bill remains unchanged.</Text></Provision></Note></ReaderNote><BillRefNumber date-time="2018-05-28">431070</BillRefNumber></Identification><Introduction><Summary><TitleText>SUMMARY</TitleText><Provision><Text>This enactment provides for the development of a national strategy in relation to fresh water.</Text></Provision></Summary><Enacts><Provision><Text>Her Majesty, by and with the advice and consent <Keep>of the</Keep> Senate and House of Commons of Canada, <Keep>enacts</Keep> as follows:</Text></Provision></Enacts></Introduction><Body><Heading level="1"><TitleText>Short Title</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Short title</MarginalNote><Label>1</Label><Text>This Act may be cited as the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">National Fresh­<Keep>water</Keep> Strategy Act</XRefExternal>.</Text></Section><Heading level="1"><TitleText>National Freshwater Strategy</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>National strategy</MarginalNote><Label>2</Label><Text>The Minister of the Environment must, in consultation with representatives of provincial and municipal governments, Indigenous groups, freshwater and climate scientists and researchers, and representatives of civil society organizations, including environmental groups, develop a national strategy for the conservation, protection and use of fresh water, including in relation to</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>drinking water standards and their implementation;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>the consideration of freshwater issues in inter­<Keep>national</Keep> agreements;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(c)</Label><Text>the evaluation of water and wastewater infrastructure in Canada in light of climate change;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(d)</Label><Text>the reduction of eutrophication in Canada’s freshwater lakes;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(e)</Label><Text>the protection of freshwater biodiversity and ecosystems; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(f)</Label><Text>the identification and resolution of knowledge gaps in relation to groundwater.</Text></Paragraph></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Conference</MarginalNote><Label>3</Label><Text>For the purpose of developing the strategy, the Minister of the Environment must hold at least one conference with the persons and groups referred to in section 2.</Text></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Report to Parliament</MarginalNote><Label>4</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Within two years after the day on which this Act receives royal assent, the Minister of the Environment must prepare a report setting out the national strategy and cause it to be tabled in each House of Parliament on any of the first 15 days on which that House is sitting <Keep>after</Keep> it is completed.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Publication of report</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The Minister must post the report on the website of the Department of the Environment within 10 days after it is tabled in both Houses of Parliament.</Text></Subsection></Section><Heading level="1"><TitleText>Review and Report</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Review</MarginalNote><Label>5</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Within five years after the tabling of the report referred to in section 4, a comprehensive review of the strategy must be undertaken by any committee of the Senate, of the House of Commons or of both Houses of Parliament that may be designated or established for that purpose by the Senate, the House of Commons or both Houses of Parliament, as the case may be.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Report</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The committee must, within a year after a review is undertaken under subsection (1) or within any further time authorized by the Senate, the House of Commons or both Houses of Parliament, as the case may be, submit a report on the review to Parliament, including a statement of any changes that the committee recommends.</Text></Subsection></Section></Body></Bill>