<Bill bill-origin="commons" bill-type="private-public" xml:lang="en" date-time="2017-11-16 11:09:37"><Identification><BillNumber>C-255</BillNumber><Parliament><Session>2</Session><Number>43</Number><RegnalYear><Year-s>69</Year-s><Monarch>Elizabeth II</Monarch></RegnalYear><Year-s>2020</Year-s></Parliament><LongTitle>An Act respecting the development of a national employment strategy for persons with disabilities</LongTitle><ShortTitle status="unofficial" /><RunningHead>Employing Persons with Disabilities Act</RunningHead><BillHistory><Stages stage="first-reading-house"><Date><YYYY>2020</YYYY><MM>11</MM><DD>25</DD></Date></Stages></BillHistory><BillSponsor><Emphasis style="smallcaps">Mr. Davies</Emphasis></BillSponsor><BillRefNumber date-time="2017-11-16">432027</BillRefNumber></Identification><Introduction><Summary><TitleText>SUMMARY</TitleText><Provision><Text>This enactment provides for the development of a national employment strategy to increase the economic participation of persons with disabilities.</Text></Provision></Summary><Enacts><Provision><Text>Her Majesty, by and with the advice and consent <Keep>of the</Keep> Senate and House of Commons of Canada, <Keep>enacts</Keep> as follows:</Text></Provision></Enacts></Introduction><Body><Heading level="1"><TitleText>Short Title</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Short title</MarginalNote><Label>1</Label><Text>This Act may be cited as the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Employing Persons with Disabilities Act</XRefExternal>.</Text></Section><Heading level="1"><TitleText>National Strategy</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>National strategy</MarginalNote><Label>2</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The Minister of Employment and Social Development, in consultation with representatives of the provincial governments responsible for matters relating to employment, must develop a national strategy to increase the economic participation of persons with disabilities that includes measures to</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>educate business owners and private sector employers about the potential of persons with disabilities to contribute to the workforce;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>correct the misconceptions that exist in workplaces about employing persons with disabilities;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(c)</Label><Text>encourage private sector employers to adopt more inclusive hiring practices; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(d)</Label><Text>promote the Opportunities Fund for Persons with Disabilities.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Conference</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>For the purpose of developing the national strategy, the Minister must hold at least one conference with <Keep svc="1">representatives</Keep> of the provincial governments responsible for matters relating to employment. </Text></Subsection></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Report to Parliament</MarginalNote><Label>3</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Before the second anniversary of the day on which this Act receives royal assent, the Minister of Employment and Social Development must prepare a report setting out the national strategy and cause the report to be tabled in each House of Parliament on any of the first 15 days on which that House is sitting after the report is completed.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Publication of report</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The Minister must publish the report on the website of the Department of Employment and Social Development within 10 days after the day on which the report is tabled in Parliament.</Text></Subsection></Section><Heading level="1"><TitleText>Review and Report</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Review and report</MarginalNote><Label>4</Label><Text>Within five years of the tabling of the report referred to in section 3 and every five years after that, the Minister of Employment and Social Development must prepare a report on the effectiveness of the national strategy, setting out the Minister's conclusions and recommendations regarding the strategy, and cause the report to be tabled in each House of Parliament on any of the first 15 days on which that House is sitting after the report is completed.</Text></Section></Body></Bill>