

<Bill bill-origin="commons" bill-type="private-public" xml:lang="en" date-time="2016-02-15 14:45:09">
  <Identification>
    <BillNumber>C-258</BillNumber>
    <Parliament>
      <Session>2</Session>
      <Number>43</Number>
      <RegnalYear>
        <Year-s>69</Year-s>
        <Monarch>Elizabeth II</Monarch>
      </RegnalYear>
      <Year-s>2020</Year-s>
    </Parliament>
    <LongTitle>An Act to amend the Canada Labour Code (replacement workers)</LongTitle>
    <ShortTitle status="unofficial" />
    <RunningHead>An Act to amend the Canada Labour Code (replacement workers)</RunningHead>
    <BillHistory>
      <Stages stage="first-reading-house">
        <Date>
          <YYYY>2020</YYYY>
          <MM>12</MM>
          <DD>3</DD>
        </Date>
      </Stages>
    </BillHistory>
    <BillSponsor>
      <Emphasis style="smallcaps">Mr. Duvall</Emphasis>
    </BillSponsor>
    <BillRefNumber date-time="2016-02-15">431100</BillRefNumber>
  </Identification>
  <Introduction>
    <Summary>
      <TitleText>SUMMARY</TitleText>
      <Provision>
        <Text>This enactment amends the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Canada Labour Code</XRefExternal> to make it an offence for employers to use replacement workers to perform all or part of the duties of employees who are on strike or locked out.</Text>
      </Provision>
    </Summary>
    <Enacts>
      <Provision>
        <Text>Her Majesty, by and with the advice and consent <Keep>of the</Keep> Senate and House of Commons of Canada, <Keep>enacts</Keep> as follows:</Text>
      </Provision>
    </Enacts>
  </Introduction>
  <Body>
    <Heading level="1">
      <MarginalNote>
        <HistoricalNote>R.S., c. L-2</HistoricalNote>
      </MarginalNote>
      <TitleText>Canada Labour Code</TitleText>
    </Heading>
    <Section type="amending">
      <Label>1</Label>
      <Text>Section 87.6 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Canada Labour Code</XRefExternal> is replaced by the following:</Text>
      <AmendedText>
        <Section>
          <MarginalNote>Reinstatement of employees after strike or lockout</MarginalNote>
          <Label>87.6</Label>
          <Text>At the end of a strike or lockout not prohibited by this Part, the employer must reinstate employees in the bargaining unit who were on strike or locked out in preference to any <Ins>other</Ins> person.</Text>
        </Section>
      </AmendedText>
    </Section>
    <Section type="amending">
      <Label>2</Label>
      <Text>Subsection 94(2.1) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text>
      <AmendedText>
        <Subsection>
          <MarginalNote>Prohibitions relating to replacement workers</MarginalNote>
          <Label>(2.1)</Label>
          <Text>
            <Ins>Subject to section 87.4, for the duration of a strike or lockout declared in accordance with this Part</Ins>, no employer or person acting on behalf of an employer shall</Text>
          <Paragraph change="off">
            <Label>
              <Ins>(a)</Ins>
            </Label>
            <Text>use the services of a person to perform all or part of the duties of an employee <Ins>who is a member of</Ins> the bargaining unit on strike or locked out, <Ins>if that person</Ins> was hired <Ins>during the period commencing</Ins> on the <Ins>day</Ins> on which notice to bargain collectively was given <Ins>and ending on the last day of the strike or lockout</Ins>;</Text>
          </Paragraph>
          <Paragraph change="ins">
            <Label>(b)</Label>
            <Text>use the services of a person employed by another employer, or the services of a contractor, to perform all or part of the duties of an employee who is a member of the bargaining unit on strike or locked out;</Text>
          </Paragraph>
          <Paragraph change="ins">
            <Label>(c)</Label>
            <Text>subject to section 87.4, use, in the establishment where the strike or lockout has been declared, the <Keep>services of</Keep> an employee who is a member of the bargaining unit on strike or locked out;</Text>
          </Paragraph>
          <Paragraph change="ins">
            <Label>(d)</Label>
            <Text>use, in another establishment of the employer, the services of an employee who is a member of the bargaining unit on strike or locked out;</Text>
          </Paragraph>
          <Paragraph change="ins">
            <Label>(e)</Label>
            <Text>use, in the establishment where the strike or lockout has been declared, the services of a person employed in another establishment of the employer; or</Text>
          </Paragraph>
          <Paragraph change="ins">
            <Label>(f)</Label>
            <Text>use, in the establishment where the strike or lockout has been declared, the services of an employee employed in that establishment to perform all or part of the duties of an employee who is a member of the bargaining unit on strike or locked out.</Text>
          </Paragraph>
        </Subsection>
        <Subsection change="ins">
          <MarginalNote>Protections</MarginalNote>
          <Label>(2.2)</Label>
          <Text>Despite subsection (2.1), the employer may use a replacement worker to perform all or part of the duties of an employee who is a member of the bargaining unit on strike or locked out to the extent necessary to enable the employer to prevent</Text>
          <Paragraph>
            <Label>(a)</Label>
            <Text>a threat to the life, health or safety of any person;</Text>
          </Paragraph>
          <Paragraph>
            <Label>(b)</Label>
            <Text>the destruction, or serious damage to, the employer’s machinery, equipment or premises; and</Text>
          </Paragraph>
          <Paragraph>
            <Label>(c)</Label>
            <Text>serious environmental damage affecting the premises.</Text>
          </Paragraph>
        </Subsection>
        <Subsection change="ins">
          <MarginalNote>Conservation measures</MarginalNote>
          <Label>(2.3)</Label>
          <Text>The measures referred to in subsection (2.2) shall exclusively be conservation measures and not measures to allow the continuation of the production of goods or services otherwise prohibited by subsection (2.1).</Text>
        </Subsection>
        <Subsection change="ins">
          <MarginalNote>Exceptions</MarginalNote>
          <Label>(2.4)</Label>
          <Text>The prohibitions set out in subsection (2.1) do not apply to</Text>
          <Paragraph>
            <Label>(a)</Label>
            <Text>a person employed as a manager, superintendent or foreman or as a representative of the employer in relations between employers and employees; or</Text>
          </Paragraph>
          <Paragraph>
            <Label>(b)</Label>
            <Text>a person serving as a director or officer of a corporation, unless the person has been designated to serve in that capacity for the person’s employer by the employees or by a certified association.</Text>
          </Paragraph>
        </Subsection>
      </AmendedText>
    </Section>
    <Section type="amending">
      <Label>3</Label>
      <Text>Paragraph 99(1)(b.3) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text>
      <AmendedText>
        <SectionPiece>
          <Paragraph>
            <Label>(b.3)</Label>
            <Text>in respect of a failure to comply with subsection 94(2.1), by order, require the employer to stop using, for the duration of the dispute, the services of any person <Ins>described in any of paragraphs 94(2.1)(a) to (f)</Ins>;</Text>
          </Paragraph>
        </SectionPiece>
      </AmendedText>
    </Section>
    <Section type="amending">
      <Label>4</Label>
      <Text>Section 100 of the Act is amended by adding the following after subsection (4):</Text>
      <AmendedText>
        <Subsection change="ins">
          <MarginalNote>Unlawful use of replacement workers</MarginalNote>
          <Label>(5)</Label>
          <Text>Every person who contravenes or fails to comply with subsection 94(2.1) is guilty of an offence and liable, on summary conviction, to a fine not exceeding one hundred thousand dollars for each day or part of a day during which the offence continues.</Text>
        </Subsection>
      </AmendedText>
    </Section>
  </Body>
</Bill>