<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>


<Bill bill-origin="commons" bill-type="private-public" xml:lang="en" date-time="2013-02-19 12:18:14"><Identification><BillNumber>C-267</BillNumber><Parliament><Session>2</Session><Number>43</Number><RegnalYear><Year-s>69-70</Year-s><Monarch>Elizabeth II</Monarch></RegnalYear><Year-s>2020-2021</Year-s></Parliament><LongTitle>An Act to amend the Criminal Code (increasing the period of parole ineligibility)</LongTitle><ShortTitle status="unofficial" /><RunningHead>An Act to amend the Criminal Code (increasing the period of parole ineligibility)</RunningHead><BillHistory><Stages stage="first-reading-house"><Date><YYYY>2021</YYYY><MM>2</MM><DD>17</DD></Date></Stages></BillHistory><BillSponsor><Emphasis style="smallcaps">Mr. Duncan</Emphasis></BillSponsor><BillRefNumber date-time="2013-02-19">432092</BillRefNumber></Identification><Introduction><Summary><TitleText>SUMMARY</TitleText><Provision><Text>This enactment amends the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Criminal Code</XRefExternal> to provide that a person convicted of the abduction, sexual assault and murder of the same victim in respect of the same event or series of events is to be sentenced to imprisonment for life without eligibility for parole until the person has served a sentence of between twenty-five and forty years as determined by the presiding judge after considering the recommendation, if any, of the jury.</Text></Provision></Summary><Enacts><Provision><Text>Her Majesty, by and with the advice and consent <Keep>of the</Keep> Senate and House of Commons of Canada, <Keep>enacts</Keep> as follows:</Text></Provision></Enacts></Introduction><Body><Heading level="1"><TitleText>Short Title</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Short title</MarginalNote><Label>1</Label><Text>This Act may be cited as the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Respecting Families of Murdered and Brutalized Persons Act</XRefExternal>.</Text></Section><Heading level="1" type="amending"><MarginalNote><HistoricalNote>R.S., c. C-46</HistoricalNote></MarginalNote><TitleText>Criminal Code</TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><Label>2</Label><Text>Section 745 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Criminal Code</XRefExternal> is amended by adding the following after paragraph (a):</Text><AmendedText><SectionPiece><Paragraph change="ins"><Label>(a.1)</Label><Text>in respect of a person who has been convicted, in respect of the same victim and the same event or series of events, of an offence under section 279, 280, 281, 282 or 283, an offence under section 151 to 153.1, 271, 272 or 273, and murder, that the person be sentenced to imprisonment for life without eligibility for parole until the person has served at least twenty-five years of the sentence or any greater number of years, not being more than forty years, that has been substituted for that number of years under section 745.52;</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>3</Label><Text>The Act is amended by adding the following after section 745.21:</Text><AmendedText><Section change="ins"><MarginalNote>Recommendation by jury</MarginalNote><Label>745.22</Label><Text>When a jury finds an accused guilty, in respect of the same victim and the same event or series of events, of an offence under section 279, 280, 281, 282 or 283, an offence under section 151 to 153.1, 271, 272 or 273 and murder, the judge presiding at the trial shall, before discharging the jury, put to them the following question:<PageBreak /></Text><Provision pointsize="8" first-line-indent="1" subsequent-line-indent="0"><Text>You have found the accused guilty of (state offences). The law requires that I now pronounce a sentence of imprisonment for life against the accused. Do you wish to make any recommendation with respect to the number of years that the accused must serve before becoming eligible for release on parole? You are not required to make any recommendation, but if you do, I will consider it when I am determining whether I should substitute for the twenty-five year period, which the law would otherwise require the accused to serve before becoming eligible to be considered for release on parole, a number of years that is more than twenty-five but not more than forty.</Text></Provision></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>4</Label><Text>The Act is amended by adding the following after section 745.51:</Text><AmendedText><Section change="ins"><MarginalNote>Ineligibility for parole</MarginalNote><Label>745.52</Label><Text>At the time of the sentencing under section 745 of an offender who is convicted, in respect of the same victim and the same event or series of events, of an offence under section 279, 280, 281, 282 or 283, an offence under section 151 to 153.1, 271, 272 or 273 and murder, the judge who presided at the trial of the offender or, if that judge is unable to do so, any judge of the same court may, having regard to the character of the offender, the nature of the offences and the circumstances surrounding their commission, and to the recommendation, if any, made under section 745.22, by order, substitute for twenty-five years a number of years of imprisonment (being more than twenty-five but not more than forty) without eligibility for parole, as the judge deems fit in the circumstances.</Text></Section></AmendedText></Section></Body></Bill>