<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><Bill bill-origin="commons" bill-type="private-public" xml:lang="en" date-time="2021-02-22 07:46:25"><Identification><BillNumber>C-276</BillNumber><Parliament><Session>2</Session><Number>43</Number><RegnalYear><Year-s>69-70</Year-s><Monarch>Elizabeth II</Monarch></RegnalYear><Year-s>2020-2021</Year-s></Parliament><LongTitle>An Act to designate the month of March as Hellenic Heritage Month</LongTitle><ShortTitle status="unofficial" /><RunningHead>Hellenic Heritage Month Act</RunningHead><BillHistory><Stages stage="first-reading-house"><Date><YYYY>2021</YYYY><MM>3</MM><DD>22</DD></Date></Stages></BillHistory><BillSponsor><Emphasis style="smallcaps">Ms. Koutrakis</Emphasis></BillSponsor><BillRefNumber date-time="2021-02-22">432076</BillRefNumber></Identification><Introduction><Summary><TitleText>SUMMARY</TitleText><Provision><Text>This enactment designates the month of March as “Hellenic Heritage Month”.</Text></Provision></Summary><Preamble><Provision><MarginalNote>Preamble</MarginalNote><Text>Whereas over 270,000 Canadians claim Greek descent, and numerous Greek communities exist across the country;</Text></Provision><Provision><Text>Whereas Greek Canadians have made meaningful contributions to the political, economic and social fabric of Canada;</Text></Provision><Provision><Text>Whereas the origins of Canadian democracy can be traced back to the ancient Greek city-state of Athens;</Text></Provision><Provision><Text>Whereas the month of March is culturally significant for the Greek community, as it was the month during which Greece became independent from the Ottoman Empire, and the year 2021 marks the bicentennial of Greek independence from this rule;</Text></Provision><Provision><Text>And whereas the celebration nation-wide of Hellenic Heritage Month would continue to encourage Greek Canadians to promote their traditions and culture and share them with the rest of Canada;  </Text></Provision><Provision language-align="yes"><Text>Now, therefore, Her Majesty, by and with the advice and consent of the Senate and House of Commons of Canada, enacts as follows:</Text></Provision></Preamble></Introduction><Body><Heading level="1"><TitleText>Short Title</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Short title</MarginalNote><Label>1</Label><Text>This Act may be cited as the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Hellenic Heritage Month Act</XRefExternal>.<PageBreak /></Text></Section><Heading level="1"><TitleText>Hellenic Heritage Month </TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Designation</MarginalNote><Label>2</Label><Text>Throughout Canada, in each and every year, the month of March is to be known as “Hellenic Heritage Month”. </Text></Section></Body></Bill>