<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><Bill bill-origin="commons" bill-type="private-public" xml:lang="en" date-time="2020-03-27 10:39:08"><Identification><BillNumber>C-289</BillNumber><Parliament><Session>2</Session><Number>43</Number><RegnalYear><Year-s>69-70</Year-s><Monarch>Elizabeth II</Monarch></RegnalYear><Year-s>2020-2021</Year-s></Parliament><LongTitle>An Act to amend the Criminal Code (sentencing)</LongTitle><ShortTitle status="unofficial" /><RunningHead>An Act to amend the Criminal Code (sentencing)</RunningHead><BillHistory><Stages stage="first-reading-house"><Date><YYYY>2021</YYYY><MM>4</MM><DD>20</DD></Date></Stages></BillHistory><BillSponsor><Emphasis style="smallcaps">Mr. Calkins</Emphasis></BillSponsor><BillRefNumber date-time="2020-03-27">432033</BillRefNumber></Identification><Introduction><Summary><TitleText>SUMMARY</TitleText><Provision><Text>This enactment amends the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Criminal Code</XRefExternal> to add, as an aggravating circumstance for sentencing purposes, evidence that an offence was directed at property or persons that were vulnerable because of their remoteness from emergency services and, for the purposes of some offences, the fact that a person carried, used or threatened to use a weapon or an imitation of a weapon.</Text></Provision><Provision><Text>It also requires that a court, when exercising its discretion to grant credit for time spent in custody in determining the sentence to be imposed on a person convicted of an offence, consider the reasons for detaining the person in pre-sentence custody.</Text></Provision></Summary><Enacts><Provision><Text>Her Majesty, by and with the advice and consent <Keep>of the</Keep> Senate and House of Commons of Canada, <Keep>enacts</Keep> as follows:</Text></Provision></Enacts></Introduction><Body><Heading level="1"><MarginalNote><HistoricalNote>R.S., c. C-46</HistoricalNote></MarginalNote><TitleText>Criminal Code</TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><Label>1</Label><Text>Section 348.1 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Criminal Code</XRefExternal> is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><Section><MarginalNote>Aggravating circumstance</MarginalNote><Label>348.1</Label><Text>If a person is convicted of an offence under section 98 or 98.1, subsection 279(2) or section 343, 346 or 348, the court imposing the sentence on the person shall consider as an aggravating circumstance the fact that the <Ins><DefinitionRef>place</DefinitionRef>, within the meaning of paragraph 348(3)(a) or (b)</Ins>, was occupied at the time of the commission of the offence and that the person, in committing the offence, knew that or was reckless as to whether the <Ins>place</Ins> was occupied and</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>used violence or threats of violence to a person or property; or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph change="ins"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>carried, used or threatened to use a weapon or an imitation of a weapon.</Text></Paragraph></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>2</Label><Text>Paragraph 718.2(a) of the Act is amended by adding the following after subparagraph (i):</Text><AmendedText><SectionPiece><Subparagraph change="ins"><Label>(i.1)</Label><Text>evidence that the offence was directed at property or persons that were vulnerable because of their remoteness from emergency medical or police services,</Text></Subparagraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>3</Label><Text>Section 719 of the Act is amended by adding the following after subsection (3): </Text><AmendedText><Subsection change="ins"><MarginalNote>Considerations</MarginalNote><Label>(3.01)</Label><Text>In exercising its discretion under subsection (3), a court shall take into account the fact that the person was detained in custody for the reason stated in the record referred to in subsection 515(9.1).</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Section></Body></Bill>