<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><Bill bill-type="private-public" bill-origin="commons" xml:lang="en" date-time="2018-01-23 11:47:56"><Identification><BillNumber>C-284</BillNumber><Parliament><Session>2</Session><Number>43</Number><RegnalYear><Year-s>69-70</Year-s><Monarch>Elizabeth II</Monarch></RegnalYear><Year-s>2020-2021</Year-s></Parliament><LongTitle>An Act to amend the Department of Industry Act (financial assistance)</LongTitle><ShortTitle status="unofficial" /><RunningHead>An Act to amend the Department of Industry Act (financial assistance)</RunningHead><BillHistory><Stages stage="first-reading-house"><Date><YYYY>2021</YYYY><MM>4</MM><DD>13</DD></Date></Stages></BillHistory><BillSponsor><Emphasis style="smallcaps">Ms. McLeod</Emphasis></BillSponsor><BillRefNumber date-time="2018-01-23">432014</BillRefNumber></Identification><Introduction><Summary><TitleText>SUMMARY</TitleText><Provision><Text>This enactment amends the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Department of Industry Act</XRefExternal> in order to require the Minister of Industry to publish certain information concerning the financial assistance provided either under section 14 of the Act or by any economic development or opportunities agency for which the Minister has responsibility.</Text></Provision></Summary><Enacts><Provision><Text>Her Majesty, by and with the advice and consent <Keep>of the</Keep> Senate and House of Commons of Canada, <Keep>enacts</Keep> as follows:</Text></Provision></Enacts></Introduction><Body><Heading level="1" type="amending"><MarginalNote><HistoricalNote>1995, c. 1</HistoricalNote></MarginalNote><TitleText>Department of Industry Act</TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><Label>1</Label><Text>The <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Department of Industry Act</XRefExternal> is amended by adding the following after section 14:</Text><AmendedText><Section change="ins"><MarginalNote>Publication — financial assistance</MarginalNote><Label>14.1</Label><Text>Within 90 days after the end of each fiscal year in which loans or grants and contributions were made or loan insurance or credit insurance was provided, either under section 14 or by any economic development or opportunities agency for which the Minister has responsibility, the Minister shall publish the following information on the Department of Industry's website:</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>a statement of all loans or grants and contributions of $100,000 or more made, and loan insurance or credit insurance provided during that fiscal year;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>the circumstances of and terms and conditions for repayment of the loans made, including the repayment method and schedule, and the repayment status; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(c)</Label><Text>in the event that stock options or other financial or similar instruments were obtained as a condition under which loans or grants and contributions were made, or loan insurance or credit insurance provided, the details of these options, including the number of options acquired, exercised, assigned or sold, and the terms and conditions attached to the options.</Text></Paragraph></Section></AmendedText></Section><Heading level="1" type="amending"><TitleText>Coming into Force</TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote>Coming into force</MarginalNote><Label>2</Label><Text>This Act comes into force 90 days after the day on which it receives royal assent.</Text></Section></Body></Bill>