<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><Bill bill-origin="commons" bill-type="private-public" xml:lang="en" date-time="2016-02-17 10:26:21"><Identification><BillNumber>C-283</BillNumber><Parliament><Session>2</Session><Number>43</Number><RegnalYear><Year-s>69-70</Year-s><Monarch>Elizabeth II</Monarch></RegnalYear><Year-s>2020-2021</Year-s></Parliament><LongTitle>An Act to establish National Food Waste Awareness Day and to provide for the development of a national strategy to reduce food waste in Canada</LongTitle><ShortTitle status="unofficial" /><RunningHead>Fight Against Food Waste Act</RunningHead><BillHistory><Stages stage="first-reading-house"><Date><YYYY>2021</YYYY><MM>4</MM><DD>13</DD></Date></Stages></BillHistory><BillSponsor><Emphasis style="smallcaps">Ms. Blaney</Emphasis></BillSponsor><BillRefNumber date-time="2016-02-17">432029</BillRefNumber></Identification><Introduction><Summary><TitleText>SUMMARY</TitleText><Provision first-line-indent="0" subsequent-line-indent="0"><Text>This enactment designates the 16th day of October in each year as “National Food Waste Awareness Day” and provides for the development and implementation of a national strategy to reduce food waste in Canada. </Text></Provision></Summary><Preamble><Provision first-line-indent="0" subsequent-line-indent="0"><MarginalNote>Preamble</MarginalNote><Text>Whereas Canadians annually send tens of billions of dollars
in food to the landfill or compost heap;</Text></Provision><Provision first-line-indent="0" subsequent-line-indent="0"><Text>Whereas millions of tonnes of foodstuffs are
wasted in Canada each year;</Text></Provision><Provision first-line-indent="0" subsequent-line-indent="0"><Text>Whereas food waste occurs primarily among manufacturers
of processed foods, retailers and consumers;</Text></Provision><Provision first-line-indent="0" subsequent-line-indent="0"><Text>And whereas over 1,100,000 Canadians, nearly 35% of them
young people and children, visited food banks each
month in 2018;</Text></Provision><Provision first-line-indent="0" subsequent-line-indent="0" language-align="yes"><Text>Now, therefore, Her Majesty, by and with the advice and consent of the Senate and House of Commons of Canada, <Keep>enacts</Keep> as follows:</Text></Provision></Preamble></Introduction><Body><Heading level="1"><TitleText>Short Title</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Short title</MarginalNote><Label>1</Label><Text>This Act may be cited as the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Fight Against Food Waste Act</XRefExternal>.</Text></Section><Heading level="1"><TitleText>National Day</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>National Food Waste Awareness Day</MarginalNote><Label>2</Label><Text>Throughout Canada, in each year, the 16th day of October is to be known as “National Food Waste Awareness Day”.</Text></Section><Heading level="1"><TitleText>National Strategy</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Development and implementation</MarginalNote><Label>3</Label><Text>The Minister of Agriculture and Agri-Food, in consultation with representatives of the provincial and territorial governments responsible for agriculture and agri-food and stakeholders in the agriculture and agri-food industry, must develop and implement a national strategy to reduce food waste in Canada that includes measures to</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>raise public awareness of food waste through a national campaign;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>put in place the tools needed to allow manufacturers
of processed foods, retailers and consumers to reduce food waste;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(c)</Label><Text>facilitate the donation, by the private sector, of food products that are blemished but safe for consumption to community organizations and food banks;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(d)</Label><Text>study various ways of reducing the environmental impact of the production of unused food resources; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(e)</Label><Text>establish food waste reduction targets.</Text></Paragraph></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Report to Parliament</MarginalNote><Label>4</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The Minister of Agriculture and Agri-Food must prepare a report setting out the national strategy and cause the report to be tabled in each House of Parliament in the year following the day on which this Act comes into force.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Publication of report</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The Minister must post the report on the website of the Department of Agriculture and Agri-Food within 10 days after the day on which the report is tabled in Parliament.</Text></Subsection></Section><Heading level="1"><TitleText>Review and Report</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Review and report</MarginalNote><Label>5</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Within five years after the day on which the report referred to in section 5 is tabled and every five years after that, the Minister of Agriculture and Agri-Food must prepare a report on the effectiveness of the national strategy, setting out the Minister's conclusions and recommendations and cause the report to be tabled in each House of Parliament on any of the first 15 days on which that House is sitting after the report is completed.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Publication of report</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The Minister must post the report on the website of the Department of Agriculture and Agri-Food within 10 days after the day on which the report is tabled in Parliament.</Text></Subsection></Section></Body></Bill>