<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><Bill bill-origin="commons" bill-type="private-public" xml:lang="en" date-time="2021-04-21 16:53:32"><Identification><BillNumber>C-297</BillNumber><Parliament><Session>2</Session><Number>43</Number><RegnalYear><Year-s>69-70</Year-s><Monarch>Elizabeth II</Monarch></RegnalYear><Year-s>2020-2021</Year-s></Parliament><LongTitle>An Act to amend the Fisheries Act  (selective fishing programs)</LongTitle><ShortTitle status="unofficial" /><RunningHead>An Act to amend the Fisheries Act  (selective fishing programs)</RunningHead><BillHistory><Stages stage="first-reading-house"><Date><YYYY>2021</YYYY><MM>5</MM><DD>26</DD></Date></Stages></BillHistory><BillSponsor><Emphasis style="smallcaps">Mr. Strahl</Emphasis></BillSponsor><BillRefNumber date-time="2021-04-21">432112</BillRefNumber></Identification><Introduction><Summary><TitleText>SUMMARY</TitleText><Provision><Text>This enactment amends the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Fisheries Act</XRefExternal> to authorize the Minister of Fisheries and Oceans to establish selective fishing programs to allow for the conservation of any species of fish that is at risk of overexploitation and to promote the fishing of species of which there are healthy stocks.</Text></Provision></Summary><Enacts><Provision><Text>Her Majesty, by and with the advice and consent <Keep>of the</Keep> Senate and House of Commons of Canada, <Keep>enacts</Keep> as follows:</Text></Provision></Enacts></Introduction><Body><Heading level="1"><MarginalNote><HistoricalNote>R.S., c. F-14</HistoricalNote></MarginalNote><TitleText>Fisheries Act</TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><Label>1</Label><Text>The <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Fisheries Act</XRefExternal> is amended by adding the following after section 6.2:</Text><AmendedText><Section change="ins"><MarginalNote>Selective fishing programs</MarginalNote><Label>6.21</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The Minister may, as part of a measure implemented under subsection 6.1(1) or a plan developed under subsection 6.2(1), establish a selective fishing program in any area that the Minister specifies to allow for the conservation of a species of fish and to promote the fishing of species of which there are healthy stocks. </Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Implementation</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The Minister may impose any obligation that the Minister considers to be necessary for the implementation of a selective fishing program, including restricting, for the purpose of preventing the unintended catching of the affected species of fish, the use of any type of fishing gear or equipment or fishing vessel in the specified area, requiring the return to the water unharmed of any fish that was caught unintentionally and requiring the marking of hatchery fish.</Text></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>2</Label><Text>Subsection 43(1) of the Act is amended by adding the following after paragraph (c):</Text><AmendedText><SectionPiece><Paragraph change="ins"><Label>(c.1)</Label><Text>for the purposes of section 6.21, respecting the marking of hatchery fish;</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Section></Body></Bill>