<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><Bill bill-origin="commons" bill-type="private-public" xml:lang="en" date-time="2021-05-07 14:29:00"><Identification><BillNumber>C-306</BillNumber><Parliament><Session>2</Session><Number>43</Number><RegnalYear><Year-s>69-70</Year-s><Monarch>Elizabeth II</Monarch></RegnalYear><Year-s>2020-2021</Year-s></Parliament><LongTitle>An Act respecting the development of a national perinatal mental health strategy</LongTitle><ShortTitle status="unofficial" /><RunningHead>National Perinatal Mental Health Strategy Act</RunningHead><BillHistory><Stages stage="first-reading-house"><Date><YYYY>2021</YYYY><MM>6</MM><DD>3</DD></Date></Stages></BillHistory><BillSponsor><Emphasis style="smallcaps">Mr. Davies</Emphasis></BillSponsor><BillRefNumber date-time="2021-05-07">432066</BillRefNumber></Identification><Introduction><Summary><TitleText>SUMMARY</TitleText><Provision><Text>This enactment requires the Minister of Health to develop a national strategy to support perinatal mental health across Canada. It also provides for reporting requirements in relation to the strategy. </Text></Provision></Summary><Preamble><Provision><MarginalNote>Preamble</MarginalNote><Text>Whereas perinatal mental health problems are a significant public health issue both in Canada and globally;</Text></Provision><Provision><Text>Whereas early detection and effective treatment of perinatal mental health disorders are critical for the health and well-being of parents and the emotional, cognitive and physical development of children;</Text></Provision><Provision><Text>Whereas stigma, poor awareness, resource inadequacies and service fragmentation represent barriers to accessing perinatal mental health screening and services across Canada;</Text></Provision><Provision><Text>Whereas perinatal mental health is affected by socio-economic status, with research showing higher rates of post-partum depression and depressive symptoms among mothers from marginalized populations;</Text></Provision><Provision><Text>And whereas only one-third of mothers in Canada who reported feelings consistent with either post-partum depression or an anxiety disorder also reported receiving treatment since the birth of their child;</Text></Provision><Provision language-align="yes"><Text>Now, therefore, Her Majesty, by and with the advice and consent of the Senate and House of Commons of Canada, enacts as follows:</Text></Provision></Preamble></Introduction><Body><Heading level="1"><TitleText>Short Title</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Short title</MarginalNote><Label>1</Label><Text>This Act may be cited as the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">National Perinatal Mental Health Strategy Act</XRefExternal>.</Text></Section><Heading level="1"><TitleText>Interpretation</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Definitions</MarginalNote><Label>2</Label><Text>The following definitions apply in this Act.</Text><Definition><Text><DefinedTermEn>Indigenous governing body</DefinedTermEn> means a council, government or other entity that is authorized to act on behalf of an Indigenous group, community or people that holds rights recognized and affirmed by section 35 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Constitution Act, 1982</XRefExternal>. (<DefinedTermFr>corps dirigeant autochtone</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Definition><Definition><Text><DefinedTermEn>Minister </DefinedTermEn> means the Minister of Health. (<DefinedTermFr>ministre</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Definition></Section><Heading level="1"><TitleText>National Perinatal Mental Health Strategy</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Development</MarginalNote><Label>3</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The Minister must develop a national strategy to support perinatal mental health in Canada.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Consultation</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>In developing the strategy, the Minister must consult with representatives of provincial governments, Indigenous governing bodies and other relevant stakeholders including perinatal health care providers, perinatal mental health care specialists and researchers, representatives of advocacy organizations and individuals with lived experience.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Content</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>The strategy must include measures to</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>provide universal access to perinatal mental health screening during pregnancy and the postpartum period;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>ensure timely access to specialist perinatal mental health care services and treatments during pregnancy and the postpartum period;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(c)</Label><Text>expand the availability of specialist perinatal mental health community care;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(d)</Label><Text>increase public and professional awareness of the frequency, impact and treatment of perinatal mental health disorders;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(e)</Label><Text>improve training for health care professionals with respect to perinatal mental health;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(f)</Label><Text>ensure access to culturally relevant perinatal mental health care services and treatment options;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(g)</Label><Text>ensure access to gender-affirming and inclusive perinatal mental health care services and treatment options;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(h)</Label><Text>support the provision of trauma-informed care in the perinatal period;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(i)</Label><Text>address the social determinants of perinatal mental health;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(j)</Label><Text>reduce barriers to accessing perinatal mental health services;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(k)</Label><Text>combat stigma with respect to perinatal mental health; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(l)</Label><Text>promote research on perinatal mental health in Canada. </Text></Paragraph></Subsection></Section><Heading level="1"><TitleText>Reports to Parliament</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Tabling of national strategy</MarginalNote><Label>4</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Within one year after the day on which this Act comes into force, the Minister must prepare a report setting out the national strategy and cause it to be tabled in each House of Parliament on any of the first 15 days on which that House is sitting after it is completed.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Publication</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The Minister must publish the report on the website of the Department of Health within 10 days after it has been tabled in both Houses of Parliament.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Report</MarginalNote><Label>5</Label><Text>Within two years after the report referred to in section 4 has been tabled in both Houses of Parliament, and every five years after that, the Minister must, in consultation with the parties referred to in subsection 3(2), prepare a report on the effectiveness of the national strategy that sets out the Minister’s conclusions and recommendations, and cause the report to be tabled in each House of Parliament on any of the first 15 days on which that House is sitting after it is completed.</Text></Section></Body></Bill>