<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><Bill bill-origin="commons" bill-type="private-public" xml:lang="en" date-time="2021-04-29 11:00:02"><Identification><BillNumber>C-302</BillNumber><Parliament><Session>2</Session><Number>43</Number><RegnalYear><Year-s>69-70</Year-s><Monarch>Elizabeth II</Monarch></RegnalYear><Year-s>2020-2021</Year-s></Parliament><LongTitle>An Act to amend the Criminal Code (pornographic material)</LongTitle><ShortTitle status="unofficial" /><RunningHead>An Act to amend the Criminal Code (pornographic material)</RunningHead><BillHistory><Stages stage="first-reading-house"><Date><YYYY>2021</YYYY><MM>5</MM><DD>27</DD></Date></Stages></BillHistory><BillSponsor><Emphasis style="smallcaps">Mr. Viersen</Emphasis></BillSponsor><BillRefNumber date-time="2021-04-29">432004</BillRefNumber></Identification><Introduction><Summary><TitleText>SUMMARY</TitleText><Provision><Text>This enactment amends the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Criminal Code</XRefExternal> to prohibit a person from making pornographic material for commercial purposes without having first ascertained that each person whose image is depicted in the material is 18 years of age or older and has given their express consent to their image being depicted. It also prohibits a person from distributing or advertising pornographic material for commercial purposes without having first ascertained that each person whose image is depicted in the material was 18 years of age or older at the time the material was made and gave their express consent to their image being depicted.</Text></Provision></Summary><Enacts><Provision><Text>Her Majesty, by and with the advice and consent <Keep>of the</Keep> Senate and House of Commons of Canada, <Keep>enacts</Keep> as follows:</Text></Provision></Enacts></Introduction><Body><Heading level="1"><TitleText>Short Title</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Short title</MarginalNote><Label>1</Label><Text>This Act may be cited as the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Stopping Internet Sexual Exploitation Act</XRefExternal>.</Text></Section><Heading level="1"><MarginalNote><HistoricalNote>R.S., c. C-46</HistoricalNote></MarginalNote><TitleText>Criminal Code</TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><Label>2</Label><Text>The <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Criminal Code</XRefExternal> is amended by adding the following after section 172.1:</Text><AmendedText change="ins"><Heading level="1"><TitleText>Making and Distributing Pornographic Material</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Definition of <DefinitionRef>pornographic material</DefinitionRef></MarginalNote><Label>172.11</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>In this section and sections 172.12 and 172.13, <DefinedTermEn>pornographic material</DefinedTermEn> means a photographic, film, video or other visual representation, whether or not it was made by electronic or mechanical means, </Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>that shows a person who is engaged in or is depicted as engaged in explicit sexual activity; or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>the dominant characteristic of which is the depiction, for a sexual purpose, of a sexual organ or the anal region of a person.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Offence — making pornographic material</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Every person commits an offence who, for commercial purposes, makes pornographic material without having first ascertained that each person whose image is <Keep svc="1">depicted</Keep> in the material is 18 years of age or older and has given their express consent to their image being depicted.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Offence — distributing pornographic material</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>Every person commits an offence who, for commercial purposes, distributes or advertises pornographic material without having first obtained from the maker of the material written confirmation that each person whose image is depicted in the material was 18 years of age or older at the time the material was made, that they gave their express consent to their image being depicted in the material and that they have not subsequently withdrawn that consent in writing.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Punishment — making pornographic material</MarginalNote><Label>(4)</Label><Text>Every person who contravenes subsection (2) is guilty of an offence punishable on summary conviction and is liable</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>in the case of an individual, </Text><Subparagraph><Label>(i)</Label><Text>for a first offence, to a fine of not more than $1,000,</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph><Label>(ii)</Label><Text>for a second offence, to a fine of not more than $5,000, and</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph><Label>(iii)</Label><Text>for each subsequent offence, to a fine of not more than $10,000 or to imprisonment for a term of not more than six months, or to both; and</Text></Subparagraph></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>in the case of a person other than an individual,</Text><Subparagraph><Label>(i)</Label><Text>for a first offence, to a fine of not more than $10,000,</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph><Label>(ii)</Label><Text>for a second offence, to a fine of not more than $50,000, and</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph><Label>(iii)</Label><Text>for each subsequent offence, to a fine of not more than $100,000.</Text></Subparagraph></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Punishment — distributing or advertising pornographic material</MarginalNote><Label>(5)</Label><Text>Every person who contravenes subsection (3) is guilty of an offence punishable on summary conviction and is liable</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>in the case of an individual,</Text><Subparagraph><Label>(i)</Label><Text>for a first offence, to a fine of not more than $5,000, </Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph><Label>(ii)</Label><Text>for a second offence, to a fine of not more than $10,000, and</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph><Label>(iii)</Label><Text>for each subsequent offence, to a fine of not more than $20,000 or to imprisonment for a term of not more than six months, or to both; and</Text></Subparagraph></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>in the case of a person other than an individual, </Text><Subparagraph><Label>(i)</Label><Text>for a first offence, to a fine of not more than $20,000,</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph><Label>(ii)</Label><Text>for a second offence, to a fine of not more than $100,000, and</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph><Label>(iii)</Label><Text>for each subsequent offence, to a fine of not more than $200,000.</Text></Subparagraph></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>No defence — age verification</MarginalNote><Label>(6)</Label><Text>It is not a defence to a charge under subsection (2) that the accused believed that a person whose image is depicted in the pornographic material was 18 years of age or older unless the accused establishes that </Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>they attempted to verify the person’s age by asking for and examining a piece of identification issued by a federal or provincial authority or a foreign government — or any other documentation prescribed by regulation — containing the person’s photograph, date of birth and signature; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>they believed on reasonable grounds that the documentation was authentic.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Definition of <DefinitionRef>consent</DefinitionRef></MarginalNote><Label>(7)</Label><Text>In this section and in section 172.13, <DefinedTermEn>consent</DefinedTermEn> means the voluntary agreement, in writing, of the person whose image is depicted in the pornographic material to their image being so depicted. </Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Aggravating factors</MarginalNote><Label>(8)</Label><Text>If a person is convicted of an offence under subsection (2) or (3), the court that imposes the sentence shall consider as aggravating factors</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>the fact that the person whose image is depicted in the pornographic material was under 18 years of age at the time the material was made or did not consent to the sexual activity that is depicted in the material; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>the fact that the pornographic material is obscene within the meaning of subsection 163(8) or promotes hatred against an <DefinitionRef>identifiable group</DefinitionRef> as defined by subsection 318(4). </Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Defence of public good</MarginalNote><Label>(9)</Label><Text>No person shall be convicted of an offence under subsection (2) or (3) if the act that is alleged to constitute the offence serves the public good and does not extend beyond what serves the public good.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Question of law, motives</MarginalNote><Label>(10)</Label><Text>For the purposes of subsection (9),</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>it is a question of law whether an act serves the public good and whether there is evidence that the act alleged goes beyond what serves the public good, but it is a question of fact whether the act does or does not extend beyond what serves the public good; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>the motives of an accused are irrelevant. </Text></Paragraph></Subsection></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Order — maker or distributor of pornographic material</MarginalNote><Label>172.12</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>When an offender is convicted, or is discharged on the conditions prescribed in a probation order under section 730, of an offence referred to in subsection 172.11(2) or (3), the court that sentences or discharges the offender, in addition to any other punishment that may be imposed for that offence or any other condition prescribed in the order of discharge, may make, subject to the conditions or exemptions that the court directs, an order </Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>prohibiting the offender from using the Internet or other digital network, unless the offender does so in accordance with conditions set by the court;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>requiring the offender to ensure that the pornographic material in relation to which the offence was committed is no longer stored on or made available through the offender’s <DefinitionRef>computer system</DefinitionRef> as defined in subsection 342.1(2); or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(c)</Label><Text>requiring the offender to remove or cause to be removed the material in relation to which the offence was committed from the Internet or other digital network.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Duration</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>An order made under subsection (1) may be in force for any period that the court considers appropriate, including any period to which the offender is sentenced to imprisonment.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Court may vary order</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>A court that makes an order under subsection (1) or, if the court is for any reason unable to act, another court of equivalent jurisdiction in the same province may, on application of the offender or the prosecutor, require the offender to appear before it at any time and, after hearing the parties, that court may vary the conditions prescribed in the order if, in the opinion of the court, the variation is desirable because of changed circumstances after the conditions were prescribed.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Offence</MarginalNote><Label>(4)</Label><Text>Every person who is bound by an order and who does not comply with the order is guilty of</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>an indictable offence and is liable to imprisonment for a term of not more than two years; or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>an offence punishable on summary conviction.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Regulations</MarginalNote><Label>172.13</Label><Text>The Governor in Council may, for the purposes of subsections 172.11(2) and (3), make regulations</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>prescribing the documentation that may be used to verify the age of a person and their consent to their image being depicted; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>respecting any records to be kept by makers of pornographic material, as well as by any person who distributes or advertises such material, and the period of time for which the records are to be kept.</Text></Paragraph></Section></AmendedText></Section></Body></Bill>