<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><Bill bill-origin="commons" bill-type="private-public" xml:lang="en" date-time="2021-06-16 14:34:31"><Identification><BillNumber>C-323</BillNumber><Parliament><Session>2</Session><Number>43</Number><RegnalYear><Year-s>69-70</Year-s><Monarch>Elizabeth II</Monarch></RegnalYear><Year-s>2020-2021</Year-s></Parliament><LongTitle>An Act to establish a national strategy on brain injuries</LongTitle><ShortTitle status="unofficial" /><RunningHead>National Strategy on Brain Injuries Act</RunningHead><BillHistory><Stages stage="first-reading-house"><Date><YYYY>2021</YYYY><MM>6</MM><DD>23</DD></Date></Stages></BillHistory><BillSponsor><Emphasis style="smallcaps">Mr. MacGregor</Emphasis></BillSponsor><BillRefNumber date-time="2021-06-16">432140</BillRefNumber></Identification><Introduction><Summary><TitleText>SUMMARY</TitleText><Provision><Text>This enactment provides for the development of a national strategy to support and improve the prevention and treatment of brain injuries.</Text></Provision></Summary><Enacts><Provision><Text>Her Majesty, by and with the advice and consent <Keep>of the</Keep> Senate and House of Commons of Canada, <Keep>enacts</Keep> as follows:</Text></Provision></Enacts></Introduction><Body><Heading level="1"><TitleText>Short Title</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Short title</MarginalNote><Label>1</Label><Text>This Act may be cited as the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">National Strategy on Brain Injuries Act</XRefExternal>.</Text></Section><Heading level="1"><TitleText>National Strategy</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Development</MarginalNote><Label>2</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The Minister of Health must, in consultation with the representatives of the provincial governments responsible for health and with Indigenous groups and other relevant stakeholders,
develop a national strategy to support and improve brain injury prevention and treatment.
</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Content</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The strategy must include measures designed to achieve the following objectives:</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>promote the implementation of preventive measures to reduce the risk of brain injuries;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>identify the training, education and guidance needs of health care and other professionals related to the prevention and treatment of brain injuries;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(c)</Label><Text>promote research and improve data collection on brain injury treatment;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(d)</Label><Text>promote information and knowledge sharing in relation to brain injury prevention and treatment;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(e)</Label><Text>create national guidelines on the prevention, diagnosis and management of brain injuries, including recommended standards of care that reflect best methodological, medical and psychosocial practices;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(f)</Label><Text>encourage the use of consulting psychologists to create a support system for people who are suffering from the effects of a brain injury, especially in educational institutions, sports organizations and workplaces; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(g)</Label><Text>develop and maintain a government website to provide current facts, research and best practices related to the prevention, diagnosis and management of brain injuries, as well as other relevant resources.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection></Section><Heading level="1"><TitleText>Reports to Parliament</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Tabling of strategy</MarginalNote><Label>3</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Within one year after the day on which this Act comes into force, the Minister of Health must prepare a report setting out the strategy and cause the report to be tabled before each House of Parliament on any of the first 15 days on which that House is sitting after the report is completed.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Publication</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The Minister must publish the report on the website of the Department of Health within 10 days after the day on which the report is tabled in both Houses of Parliament.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Report</MarginalNote><Label>4</Label><Text>Within five years after the report referred to in <Keep>section 3</Keep> has been tabled in both Houses of Parliament, the Minister of Health must, in consultation with the parties referred to in subsection 2(1), evaluate the effectiveness of the strategy and the situation with respect to brain injury prevention and treatment, prepare a report setting out conclusions and recommendations regarding the strategy, and cause the report to be tabled in each House of Parliament on any of the first 15 days on which that House is sitting after it is completed.</Text></Section></Body></Bill>