<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!--Arbortext, Inc., 1988-2010, v.4002--><Bill bill-origin="commons" bill-type="govt-public" xml:lang="en"><Identification><BillNumber>C-35</BillNumber><Parliament><Session>2</Session><Number>43</Number><RegnalYear><Year-s>69-70</Year-s><Monarch>Elizabeth II</Monarch></RegnalYear><Year-s>2020-2021</Year-s></Parliament><LongTitle>An Act to reduce poverty and to support the financial security of persons with disabilities by establishing the Canada disability benefit and making a consequential amendment to the Income Tax Act</LongTitle><ShortTitle status="official">Canada Disability Benefit Act</ShortTitle><RunningHead>Canada Disability Benefit Act</RunningHead><BillHistory><Stages stage="first-reading-house"><Date><YYYY>2021</YYYY><MM>6</MM><DD>22</DD></Date></Stages></BillHistory><BillSponsor>MINISTER OF EMPLOYMENT, WORKFORCE DEVELOPMENT AND DISABILITY INCLUSION<LineBreak /><?xm-replace_text LineBreak?> </BillSponsor><BillRefNumber date-time="2021-6-21">91007</BillRefNumber></Identification><Introduction><Recommendation><TitleText>RECOMMENDATION</TitleText><Provision format-ref="section"><Text>His Excellency the Administrator of the Government of Canada recommends to the House of Commons the appropriation of public revenue under the circumstances, in the manner and for the purposes set out in a measure entitled “<Emphasis style="italic">An Act to reduce poverty and to support the financial security of persons with disabilities by establishing the Canada disability benefit and making a consequential amendment to the Income Tax Act</Emphasis>”.</Text></Provision></Recommendation><Summary><TitleText>SUMMARY</TitleText><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>This enactment establishes the Canada disability benefit to reduce poverty and to support the financial security of working-age persons with disabilities. It sets out general provisions for the administration of the benefit and authorizes the Governor in Council to implement most of the benefit’s design elements through regulations. It also makes a consequential amendment to the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Income Tax Act</XRefExternal>.</Text></Provision></Summary><TableOfProvisions label-column-width="2.5"><Heading level="1"><TitleText>TABLE OF PROVISIONS</TitleText></Heading><Heading level="1"><TitleText>An Act to reduce poverty and to support the financial security of persons with disabilities by establishing the Canada disability benefit and making a consequential amendment to the Income Tax Act</TitleText></Heading><Label> </Label><Text>Preamble</Text><Heading level="1"><TitleText>Short Title</TitleText></Heading><Label><Emphasis style="bold">1</Emphasis></Label><Text><XRefExternal reference-type="act">Canada Disability Benefit Act</XRefExternal></Text><Heading level="1"><TitleText>Definition</TitleText></Heading><Label><Emphasis style="bold">2</Emphasis></Label><Text>Definition of <Emphasis style="italic">Minister</Emphasis></Text><Heading level="1"><TitleText>Purposes of Act</TitleText></Heading><Label><Emphasis style="bold">3</Emphasis></Label><Text>Purposes</Text><Heading level="1"><TitleText>Canada Disability Benefit</TitleText></Heading><Label><Emphasis style="bold">4</Emphasis></Label><Text>Eligibility</Text><Label><Emphasis style="bold">5</Emphasis></Label><Text>Payment of benefit</Text><Heading level="1"><TitleText>General</TitleText></Heading><Label><Emphasis style="bold">6</Emphasis></Label><Text>Obligation to provide information</Text><Label><Emphasis style="bold">7</Emphasis></Label><Text>Social Insurance Number</Text><Label><Emphasis style="bold">8</Emphasis></Label><Text>Agreements</Text><Label><Emphasis style="bold">9</Emphasis></Label><Text>Payments cannot be charged, etc.</Text><Label><Emphasis style="bold">10</Emphasis></Label><Text>Consolidated Revenue Fund</Text><Heading level="1"><TitleText>Regulations</TitleText></Heading><Label><Emphasis style="bold">11</Emphasis></Label><Text>Regulations</Text><Heading level="1"><TitleText>Parliamentary Review</TitleText></Heading><Label><Emphasis style="bold">12</Emphasis></Label><Text>Parliamentary review</Text><Heading level="1"><TitleText>Consequential Amendment to the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Income Tax Act</XRefExternal></TitleText></Heading><Label><Emphasis style="bold">13</Emphasis></Label><Text /><Heading level="1"><TitleText>Coming into Force</TitleText></Heading><Label><Emphasis style="bold">14</Emphasis></Label><Text>Order in council</Text></TableOfProvisions><Preamble><Provision language-align="no" list-item="no"><MarginalNote>Preamble</MarginalNote><Text>Whereas working-age persons with disabilities are more likely to live in poverty than working-age persons without disabilities, because of economic and social exclusion;</Text></Provision><Provision language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text>Whereas persons with disabilities often face barriers to employment, including work disincentives such as the loss of income and other benefits as a result of becoming employed;</Text></Provision><Provision language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text>Whereas the Government of Canada is committed to the economic and social inclusion of persons with disabilities, as evidenced by its introduction of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Accessible Canada Act</XRefExternal>;</Text></Provision><Provision language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text>Whereas the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Canadian Charter of Rights and Freedoms</XRefExternal> guarantees persons with disabilities the right to the equal protection and equal benefit of the law without discrimination;</Text></Provision><Provision language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text>Whereas reducing poverty contributes to the progressive realization of Canada’s international obligations under the United Nations Convention on the Rights of Persons with Disabilities;</Text></Provision><Provision language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text>Whereas Canada aspires to be a world leader in the eradication of poverty, and Parliament, with a view to this objective, enacted the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Poverty Reduction Act</XRefExternal>;</Text></Provision><Provision language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text>Whereas progress made by Canada in reducing poverty for persons with disabilities and others contributes to meeting the Sustainable Development Goals of the United Nations;</Text></Provision><Provision language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text>Whereas the Government of Canada seeks to build on its successes in addressing poverty through providing benefits for seniors and for families with children;</Text></Provision><Provision language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text>Whereas, in the spirit of “Nothing Without Us”, the Government of Canada recognizes the importance, in developing support measures for persons with disabilities, of engaging with the disability community, in accordance with the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Accessible Canada Act</XRefExternal>, which specifies that “persons with disabilities must be involved in the development and design of laws, policies, programs, services and structures”;</Text></Provision><Provision language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text>And whereas Parliament recognizes the leading role that the provinces and territories play in providing supports and services to persons with disabilities and the importance of engaging with them in developing income supports and other support services;</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>Now therefore, Her Majesty, by and with the advice and consent of the Senate and House of Commons of Canada, enacts as follows:</Text></Provision></Preamble></Introduction><Body><Heading level="1"><TitleText>Short Title</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Short title</MarginalNote><Label>1</Label><Text>This Act may be cited as the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Canada Disability Benefit Act</XRefExternal>.</Text></Section><Heading level="1"><TitleText>Definition</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Definition of <DefinedTermEn>Minister</DefinedTermEn></MarginalNote><Label>2</Label><Text>In this Act, <DefinedTermEn>Minister</DefinedTermEn> means the Minister of Employment and Social Development.</Text></Section><Heading level="1"><TitleText>Purposes of Act</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Purposes</MarginalNote><Label>3</Label><Text>The purposes of this Act are to reduce poverty and to support the financial security of working-age persons with disabilities.</Text></Section><Heading level="1"><TitleText>Canada Disability Benefit</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Eligibility</MarginalNote><Label>4</Label><Text>A person is eligible for a Canada disability benefit if they meet the eligibility criteria set out in the regulations.</Text></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Payment of benefit</MarginalNote><Label>5</Label><Text>The Minister must, in accordance with the regulations, pay a Canada disability benefit to a person who is eligible for the benefit, applies or has an application made on their behalf, in accordance with the regulations, and meets any other conditions set out in the regulations.</Text></Section><Heading level="1"><TitleText>General</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Obligation to provide information</MarginalNote><Label>6</Label><Text>An applicant or the representative of an applicant who is incapable of managing their own affairs must provide the Minister with any information that the Minister may require in respect of the application.</Text></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Social Insurance Number</MarginalNote><Label>7</Label><Text>The Minister is authorized to collect and use, for the purposes of the administration and enforcement of this Act, the Social Insurance Number of an applicant.</Text></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Agreements</MarginalNote><Label>8</Label><Text>In order to carry out the purposes of this Act, the Minister may enter into agreements with any department or agency of the Government of Canada and may, with the approval of the Governor in Council, enter into agreements with any department or agency of a province.</Text></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Payments cannot be charged, etc.</MarginalNote><Label>9</Label><Text>A benefit under this Act</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>is not subject to the operation of any law relating to bankruptcy or insolvency;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>cannot be assigned, charged, attached or given as security;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(c)</Label><Text>cannot be retained by way of deduction, set-off or compensation under any Act of Parliament other than this Act; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(d)</Label><Text>is garnishable moneys for the purposes of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Family Orders and Agreements Enforcement Assistance Act</XRefExternal>.</Text></Paragraph></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Consolidated Revenue Fund</MarginalNote><Label>10</Label><Text>All benefits payable under this Act are to be paid out of the Consolidated Revenue Fund.</Text></Section><Heading level="1"><TitleText>Regulations</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Regulations</MarginalNote><Label>11</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The Governor in Council may make regulations</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>respecting the eligibility criteria for a Canada disability benefit;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>respecting conditions that are to be met in order to receive or to continue to receive a benefit;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(c)</Label><Text>respecting the amount of a benefit or the method for determining the amount;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(d)</Label><Text>respecting the manner in which a benefit is to be indexed to inflation;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(e)</Label><Text>respecting payment periods and the amount to be paid each period;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(f)</Label><Text>respecting applications for a benefit;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(g)</Label><Text>respecting the amendment or rescission of decisions made by the Minister;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(h)</Label><Text>respecting reviews or reconsiderations of decisions made under this Act;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(i)</Label><Text>respecting appeals;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(j)</Label><Text>respecting the circumstances in which retroactive payments may be made to persons who do not apply in the time specified in the regulations but are otherwise eligible;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(k)</Label><Text>respecting applications made on behalf of persons who are incapable of managing their own affairs, payments to those persons and reviews, reconsiderations or appeals commenced on their behalf;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(l)</Label><Text>respecting the circumstances in which the Minister may deem an applicant or beneficiary to be dead and may determine their date of death if the applicant or beneficiary has disappeared under circumstances that, in the opinion of the Minister, raise beyond a reasonable doubt a presumption that the applicant or beneficiary is dead;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(m)</Label><Text>respecting the application of this Act when an applicant or beneficiary dies;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(n)</Label><Text>authorizing the Minister to correct administrative errors;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(o)</Label><Text>respecting the identification of debts due to Her Majesty in right of Canada;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(p)</Label><Text>respecting the recovery of overpayments and debts due to Her Majesty in right of Canada, including limitation or prescription periods;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(q)</Label><Text>establishing offences punishable on summary conviction for the commission of any of the following acts and setting fines or terms of imprisonment or both for such offences:</Text><Subparagraph><Label>(i)</Label><Text>knowingly using false identity information or another person’s identity information for the purpose of obtaining a benefit for themselves,</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph><Label>(ii)</Label><Text>counselling a person to apply for a benefit with intent to steal all or a substantial part of it,</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph><Label>(iii)</Label><Text>knowingly making false or misleading representations in relation to an application;</Text></Subparagraph></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(r)</Label><Text>establishing a system of administrative monetary penalties applicable to the commission of either or both of the following acts and setting the amounts of those penalties:</Text><Subparagraph><Label>(i)</Label><Text>knowingly making false or misleading representations in relation to an application,</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph><Label>(ii)</Label><Text>making an application for, and receiving, a benefit while knowingly not being eligible to receive it;</Text></Subparagraph></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(s)</Label><Text>adapting section 44.2 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Old Age Security Act</XRefExternal> for the purpose of applying that section as adapted to the verification of compliance or the prevention of non-compliance with this Act and to the use of copies as evidence;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(t)</Label><Text>authorizing the Minister, for any purpose related to verifying compliance or preventing non-compliance with this Act, to require an applicant, a beneficiary or the representative of an applicant or beneficiary who is incapable of managing their own affairs, to be at a suitable place — or to be available by audioconference or videoconference or in any other suitable manner — at a suitable time in order to provide any information or any document that the Minister may require in respect of the application; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(u)</Label><Text>generally, for carrying out the purposes and provisions of this Act.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Distinguishing — classes</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Regulations made under subsection (1) may distinguish among different classes of applicants and beneficiaries.</Text></Subsection></Section><Heading level="1"><TitleText>Parliamentary Review</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Parliamentary review</MarginalNote><Label>12</Label><Text>As soon as feasible after the third anniversary of the day on which this section comes into force and after each subsequent fifth anniversary, a review of this Act and of its administration and operation is to be undertaken by a committee of the Senate, of the House of Commons or of both Houses of Parliament that may be designated or established for that purpose.</Text></Section><Heading level="1"><MarginalNote><HistoricalNote>R.S., c. 1 (5th Supp.)</HistoricalNote></MarginalNote><TitleText>Consequential Amendment to the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Income Tax Act</XRefExternal></TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><Label>13</Label><Text>Paragraph 241(4)(d) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Income Tax Act</XRefExternal> is amended by adding the following after subparagraph (vii.5):</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><SectionPiece><Subparagraph><Label>(vii.51)</Label><Text>to an official solely for the purposes of the administration and enforcement of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Canada Disability Benefit Act</XRefExternal> or the evaluation or formulation of policy for that Act,</Text></Subparagraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Section><Heading level="1"><TitleText>Coming into Force</TitleText></Heading><Section type="transitional"><MarginalNote>Order in council</MarginalNote><Label>14</Label><Text>This Act comes into force on a day to be fixed by order of the Governor in Council.</Text></Section></Body></Bill>