<!--Arbortext, Inc., 1988-2010, v.4002--><Bill bill-origin="commons" bill-type="govt-public" xml:lang="en"><Identification><BillNumber>C-6</BillNumber><Parliament><Session>2</Session><Number>43</Number><RegnalYear><Year-s>69</Year-s><Monarch>Elizabeth II</Monarch></RegnalYear><Year-s>2020</Year-s></Parliament><LongTitle>An Act to amend the Criminal Code (conversion therapy)</LongTitle><ShortTitle status="unofficial">An Act to amend the Criminal Code (conversion therapy)</ShortTitle><RunningHead>An Act to amend the Criminal Code (conversion therapy)</RunningHead><BillHistory><Stages stage="report-house"><Date><YYYY>2020</YYYY><MM>12</MM><DD>11</DD></Date><StageText>Reprinted as amended by the Standing Committee on Justice and Human Rights as a working copy for the use of the House of Commons at Report Stage and as reported to the House on December 11, 2020</StageText></Stages></BillHistory><BillSponsor>MINISTER OF JUSTICE</BillSponsor><BillRefNumber date-time="2020-09-23">90942</BillRefNumber></Identification><Introduction><Summary><TitleText>SUMMARY</TitleText><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>This enactment amends the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Criminal Code</XRefExternal> to, among other things, create the following offences:</Text><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>causing a person to undergo conversion therapy without the person’s consent;</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>causing a child to undergo conversion therapy;</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>(c)</Label><Text>doing anything for the purpose of removing a child from Canada with the intention that the child undergo conversion therapy outside Canada;</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>(d)</Label><Text>promoting or advertising an offer to provide conversion therapy; and</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>(e)</Label><Text>receiving a financial or other material benefit from the provision of conversion therapy.</Text></Provision></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>It also amends the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Criminal Code</XRefExternal> to authorize courts to order that advertisements for conversion therapy be disposed of or deleted.</Text></Provision></Summary><Preamble><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><MarginalNote>Preamble</MarginalNote><Text>Whereas conversion therapy causes harm to the persons, and in particular the children, who are subjected to it;</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text>Whereas conversion therapy causes harm to society because, among other things, it is based on and propagates myths and stereotypes about sexual orientation, gender identity and <Ins>gender expression</Ins>, including the myth that a person’s sexual orientation,
gender identity and <Ins>gender expression</Ins> ought to be changed;</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text>And whereas, in light of those harms, it is important to discourage and denounce the provision of conversion therapy in order to protect the human dignity and equality of all Canadians;</Text></Provision></Preamble><Enacts><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>Now, therefore, Her Majesty, by and with the advice and consent <Keep>of the</Keep> Senate and House of Commons of Canada, <Keep>enacts</Keep> as follows:</Text></Provision></Enacts></Introduction><Body><Heading level="1"><MarginalNote><HistoricalNote>R.S., c. C-46</HistoricalNote></MarginalNote><TitleText><XRefExternal reference-type="act">Criminal Code</XRefExternal></TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><Label>1</Label><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Subsection 164(1) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Criminal Code</XRefExternal> is amended by striking out “or” at the end of paragraph (d), by adding “or” at the end of paragraph (e) and by adding the following after paragraph (e):</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(f)</Label><Text>the representation, written material or recording, copies of which are kept in premises within the jurisdiction of the court, is an advertisement for conversion therapy.</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><MarginalNote><HistoricalNote>2018, c. 29, s. 12(2)</HistoricalNote></MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Subsections 164(3) to (5) of the Act are replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Subsection><MarginalNote>Owner and maker may appear</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>The owner and the maker of the matter seized under subsection (1), and alleged to be obscene, child pornography, a voyeuristic recording, an intimate image, an advertisement of sexual services or an advertisement for conversion therapy, may appear and be represented in the proceedings to oppose the making of an order for the forfeiture of the matter.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Order of forfeiture</MarginalNote><Label>(4)</Label><Text>If the court is satisfied, on a balance of probabilities, that the publication, representation, written material or recording referred to in subsection (1) is obscene, child pornography, a voyeuristic recording, an intimate image, an advertisement of sexual services or an advertisement for conversion therapy, it may make an order declaring the matter forfeited to Her Majesty in right of the province in which the proceedings take place, for disposal as the Attorney General may direct.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Disposal of matter</MarginalNote><Label>(5)</Label><Text>If the court is not satisfied that the publication, representation, written material or recording referred to in subsection (1) is obscene, child pornography, a voyeuristic recording, an intimate image, an advertisement of sexual services or an advertisement for conversion therapy, it shall order that the matter be restored to the person from whom it was seized without delay after the time for final appeal has expired.</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><MarginalNote><HistoricalNote>2014, c. 25, s. 46(4)</HistoricalNote></MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>Subsection 164(7) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Subsection><MarginalNote>Consent</MarginalNote><Label>(7)</Label><Text>If an order is made under this section by a judge in a province with respect to one or more copies of a publication, a representation, written material or a recording, no proceedings shall be instituted or continued in that province under section 162, 162.1, 163, 163.1, 286.4 or 320.104 with respect to those or other copies of the same publication, representation, written material or recording without the consent of the Attorney General.</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(4)</Label><Text>Subsection 164(8) of the Act is amended by adding the following in alphabetical order:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><SectionPiece><Definition><Text><DefinedTermEn>advertisement for conversion therapy</DefinedTermEn> means any material — including a photographic, film, video, audio or other recording, made by any means, a visual representation or any written material — that is used to advertise an offer to provide conversion therapy contrary to section 320.104; (<DefinedTermFr>publicité de thérapie de conversion</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Definition></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection></Section><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote><HistoricalNote>2014, c. 25, s. 46(5)</HistoricalNote></MarginalNote><Label>2</Label><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The portion of subsection 164.1(1) of the Act before paragraph (a) is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Section><MarginalNote>Warrant of seizure</MarginalNote><Label>164.1</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>If a judge is satisfied by information on oath that there are reasonable grounds to believe that there is material  —  namely, <DefinitionRef>child pornography</DefinitionRef> as defined in section 163.1, a voyeuristic recording, an intimate image, an advertisement of sexual services or an advertisement for conversion therapy, or <DefinitionRef>computer data</DefinitionRef> as defined in subsection 342.1(2) that makes child pornography, a voyeuristic recording, an intimate image, an advertisement of sexual services or an advertisement for conversion therapy available  — that is stored on and made available through a <DefinitionRef>computer system</DefinitionRef> as defined in subsection 342.1(2) that is within the jurisdiction of the court, the judge may order the custodian of the computer system to</Text></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><MarginalNote><HistoricalNote>2014, c. 25, s. 46(6)</HistoricalNote></MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Subsection 164.1(5) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Subsection><MarginalNote>Order</MarginalNote><Label>(5)</Label><Text>If the court is satisfied, on a balance of probabilities, that the material is<DefinitionRef> child pornography</DefinitionRef> as defined in section 163.1, a voyeuristic recording, an intimate image, an advertisement of sexual services or an advertisement for conversion therapy, or <DefinitionRef>computer data</DefinitionRef> as defined in subsection 342.1(2) that makes child pornography, the voyeuristic recording, the intimate image, the advertisement of sexual services or the advertisement for conversion therapy available, it may order the custodian of the computer system to delete the material.</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><MarginalNote><HistoricalNote>2014, c. 25, s. 46(7)</HistoricalNote></MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>Subsection 164.1(7) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Subsection><MarginalNote>Return of material</MarginalNote><Label>(7)</Label><Text>If the court is not satisfied that the material is <DefinitionRef>child pornography</DefinitionRef> as defined in section 163.1, a voyeuristic recording, an intimate image, an advertisement of sexual services or an advertisement for conversion therapy, or <DefinitionRef>computer data</DefinitionRef> as defined in subsection 342.1(2) that makes child pornography, the voyeuristic recording, the intimate image, the advertisement of sexual services or the advertisement for conversion therapy available, the court shall order that the electronic copy be returned to the custodian of the computer system and terminate the order under paragraph (1)(b).</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Subsection></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>3</Label><Text>Paragraph (a) of the definition<DefinitionRef> offence</DefinitionRef> in section 183 of the Act is amended by</Text><Paragraph type="amending"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>adding the following after subparagraph (xlvi):</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><SectionPiece><Subparagraph><Label>(xlvi.1)</Label><Text>section 273.3 (removal of child from Canada),</Text></Subparagraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>adding the following after subparagraph (liii):</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><SectionPiece><Subparagraph><Label>(liii.1)</Label><Text>section 320.102 (forced conversion therapy),</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph><Label>(liii.2)</Label><Text>section 320.103 (causing child to undergo conversion therapy),</Text></Subparagraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Paragraph></Section><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote><HistoricalNote>2019, c. 25, s. 98</HistoricalNote></MarginalNote><Label>4</Label><Text>Paragraph 273.3(1)(c) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(c)</Label><Text>under the age of 18 years, with the intention that an act be committed outside Canada that if it were committed in Canada would be an offence against section 155, subsection 160(2) or section 170, 171, 267, 268, 269, 271, 272, 273 or 320.103 in respect of that person; or</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>5</Label><Text>The Act is amended by adding the following after section 320.1:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Heading level="2"><TitleText>Conversion Therapy</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Definition of <DefinedTermEn>conversion therapy</DefinedTermEn></MarginalNote><Label>320.101</Label><Text>In sections 320.102 to 320.106, <DefinedTermEn>conversion therapy</DefinedTermEn> means a practice, treatment or service designed to change a person’s sexual orientation to heterosexual, <Ins>to change a person’s</Ins> gender identity or
<Ins>gender expression</Ins> to cisgender or to repress or reduce non-heterosexual attraction or sexual behaviour
<Ins>or non-cisgender gender expression</Ins>. For greater certainty, this definition does not include a practice, treatment or service that relates to <Ins>the exploration and development of an integrated personal
identity without favouring any particular sexual orientation, gender identity or gender expression</Ins>.</Text></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Forced conversion therapy</MarginalNote><Label>320.102</Label><Text>Everyone who knowingly causes a person to undergo conversion therapy <Ins>without</Ins> the person’s <Ins>consent</Ins> is</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>guilty of an indictable offence and liable to imprisonment for a term of not more than five years; or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>guilty of an offence punishable on summary conviction.</Text></Paragraph></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Causing child to undergo conversion therapy</MarginalNote><Label>320.103</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Everyone who knowingly causes a person who is under the age of 18 years to undergo conversion therapy is</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>guilty of an indictable offence and liable to imprisonment for a term of not more than five years; or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>guilty of an offence punishable on summary conviction.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Mistake of age</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>It is not a defence to a charge under subsection (1) that the accused believed that the person was 18 years of age or older, unless the accused took reasonable steps to ascertain the person’s age.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Advertising conversion therapy</MarginalNote><Label>320.104</Label><Text>Everyone who knowingly <Ins>promotes or</Ins> advertises an offer to provide conversion therapy is</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>guilty of an indictable offence and liable to imprisonment for a term of not more than two years; or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>guilty of an offence punishable on summary conviction.</Text></Paragraph></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Material benefit from conversion therapy</MarginalNote><Label>320.105</Label><Text>Everyone who receives a financial or other material benefit, knowing that it is obtained or derived directly or indirectly from the provision of conversion therapy, is</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>guilty of an indictable offence and liable to imprisonment for a term of not more than two years; or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>guilty of an offence punishable on summary conviction.</Text></Paragraph></Section></AmendedText></Section><Heading level="1"><TitleText>Coming into Force</TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote>30th day after royal assent</MarginalNote><Label>6</Label><Text>This Act comes into force on the 30th day after the day on which it receives royal assent.</Text></Section></Body></Bill>