<?xml-stylesheet href='BillExchange.css' type='text/css'?><Bill bill-origin="senate" bill-type="private-public" xml:lang="en" date-time="2014-06-16 10:03:18"><Identification><BillNumber>S-201</BillNumber><Parliament><Session>2</Session><Number>43</Number><RegnalYear><Year-s>69</Year-s><Monarch>Elizabeth II</Monarch></RegnalYear><Year-s>2020</Year-s></Parliament><LongTitle>An Act to amend the Constitution Act, 1867 and the Parliament of Canada Act (Speaker of the Senate)</LongTitle><ShortTitle status="unofficial" /><RunningHead>An Act to amend the Constitution Act, 1867 and the Parliament of Canada Act (Speaker of the Senate)</RunningHead><BillHistory><Stages stage="first-reading-senate"><Date><YYYY>2020</YYYY><MM>9</MM><DD>30</DD></Date></Stages></BillHistory><BillSponsor>Senator Mercer</BillSponsor><BillRefNumber date-time="2004-10-05">4320321</BillRefNumber></Identification><Introduction><Summary><TitleText>SUMMARY</TitleText><Provision><Text>This enactment amends the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Constitution Act, 1867</XRefExternal> to provide for the election of the Speaker and the Deputy Speaker of the Senate and their participation in votes.</Text></Provision><Provision language-align="yes"><Text>It also makes related amendments to the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Parliament of Canada Act</XRefExternal>.</Text></Provision></Summary><Enacts><Provision language-align="yes"><Text>Her Majesty, by and with the advice and consent of the Senate and House of Commons of Canada, enacts as follows:</Text></Provision></Enacts></Introduction><Body><Heading level="1" type="amending"><MarginalNote><HistoricalNote>30-31 Vict., c. 3 (U.K.)</HistoricalNote></MarginalNote><TitleText><XRefExternal reference-type="act">Constitution Act, 1867</XRefExternal></TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><Label>1</Label><Text>Section 34 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Constitution Act, 1867</XRefExternal> is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText change="ins"><Section><MarginalNote>Election of Speaker and Deputy Speaker of Senate</MarginalNote><Label>34.</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The Senate, on its first assembling after a <Keep>General</Keep> Election, shall proceed with all practicable speed to elect, by secret ballot, one senator to be Speaker and another to be Deputy Speaker.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Vacancy in office of Speaker or Deputy Speaker</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>If a vacancy occurs in the office of Speaker or Deputy Speaker by death, resignation or otherwise, the Senate shall proceed with all practicable speed to elect another senator to be Speaker or Deputy Speaker, as the case may be.</Text></Subsection></Section></AmendedText><ExplanatoryNote><TitleText><XRefExternal reference-type="act">Constitution Act, 1867</XRefExternal></TitleText><Label><Emphasis style="italic">Clause 1</Emphasis>:</Label><ExplanatoryText>Existing text of section 34:</ExplanatoryText><ExistingText><Section><Label>34.</Label><Text>The Governor General may from Time to Time, by Instrument under the Great Seal of Canada, appoint a Senator to be Speaker of the Senate, and may remove him and appoint another in his Stead.</Text></Section></ExistingText></ExplanatoryNote></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>2</Label><Text>Section 36 of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><Section><MarginalNote>Voting in Senate</MarginalNote><Label>36.</Label><Text>Questions arising in the Senate shall be decided by a majority of voices <Ins>other than that of the senator presiding</Ins>, and when the voices are equal<Ins>, but not otherwise, the senator presiding shall have a vote</Ins>.</Text></Section></AmendedText><ExplanatoryNote><Label><Emphasis style="italic">Clause 2</Emphasis>:</Label><ExplanatoryText>Existing text of section 36:</ExplanatoryText><ExistingText><Section><Label>36.</Label><Text>Questions arising in the Senate shall be decided by a Majority of Voices, and the Speaker shall in all Cases have a Vote, and when the Voices are equal the Decision shall be deemed to be in the Negative.</Text></Section></ExistingText></ExplanatoryNote></Section><Heading level="1" type="amending"><MarginalNote><HistoricalNote>R.S., c. P-1</HistoricalNote></MarginalNote><TitleText><XRefExternal reference-type="act">Parliament of Canada Act</XRefExternal></TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><Label>3</Label><Text>The heading before section 17 and sections 17 to 19 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Parliament of Canada Act</XRefExternal> are replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><Heading level="2"><TitleText><Ins>Speaker and Deputy Speaker of the Senate</Ins></TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Speaker leaving the chair</MarginalNote><Label>17</Label><Text><Ins>If</Ins> the Speaker of the Senate finds it necessary to leave the chair during any part of <Ins>a sitting</Ins> of the Senate on any day, the Speaker may call on <Ins>the Deputy Speaker</Ins> to take the chair and preside as Speaker during the remainder of that day unless the Speaker resumes the chair before the close of the <Ins>sitting</Ins> for that day.</Text></Section><Section change="ins"><MarginalNote>Deputy Speaker leaving the chair</MarginalNote><Label>17.1</Label><Text>If the Deputy Speaker finds it necessary to leave the chair during any part of a sitting on that day, the Deputy Speaker may call on any senator to take the chair and preside as Speaker during the remainder of that day unless the Speaker or Deputy Speaker resumes the chair before the close of the sitting for that day.</Text></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Unavoidable absence</MarginalNote><Label>18</Label><Text>Whenever the Senate is informed of the unavoidable absence of <Ins>both</Ins> the Speaker <Ins>and the Deputy Speaker</Ins> by the Clerk at the table, the Senate may choose any senator to preside as Speaker during <Ins>their</Ins> absence and that senator has and shall execute all the powers, privileges and duties of Speaker until the Speaker <Ins>or the Deputy Speaker</Ins> resumes the chair.</Text></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Validity of acts</MarginalNote><Label>19</Label><Text>Every act done by <Ins>the Deputy Speaker or</Ins> any senator acting under section <Ins>17.1</Ins> or 18 has the same effect and validity as if the act had been done by the Speaker.</Text></Section></AmendedText><ExplanatoryNote><TitleText><XRefExternal reference-type="act">Parliament of Canada Act</XRefExternal></TitleText><Label><Emphasis style="italic">Clause 3</Emphasis>:</Label><ExplanatoryText>Existing text of the heading and sections 17 and 18:</ExplanatoryText><ExistingText><Heading level="2"><TitleText>Deputy Speaker</TitleText></Heading><Section><Label>17</Label><Text>Whenever the Speaker of the Senate, from illness or other cause, finds it necessary to leave the chair during any part of the sittings of the Senate on any day, the Speaker may call on any senator to take the chair and preside as Speaker during the remainder of that day unless the Speaker resumes the chair before the close of the sittings for that day.</Text></Section><Section><Label>18</Label><Text>Whenever the Senate is informed of the unavoidable absence of the Speaker thereof by the Clerk at the table, the Senate may choose any senator to preside as Speaker during such absence and that senator thereupon has and shall execute all the powers, privileges and duties of Speaker until the Speaker resumes the chair or another Speaker is appointed by the Governor General.</Text></Section><Section><Label>19</Label><Text>Every act done by any senator acting pursuant to section 17 or 18 has the same effect and validity as if the act had been done by the Speaker.</Text></Section></ExistingText></ExplanatoryNote></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>4</Label><Text>Paragraph 62.1(1)(b) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>the member of the Senate occupying the position of <Ins>Deputy</Ins> Speaker of the Senate, $20,600;</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText><ExplanatoryNote><Label><Emphasis style="italic">Clause 4</Emphasis>:</Label><ExplanatoryText>Existing text of relevant portions of section 62.1:</ExplanatoryText><ExistingText><Section><Label>62.1</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Despite section 60, for the fiscal year commencing on April 1, 2004 there shall be paid to the following members of the Senate and the House of Commons the following annual salaries:
</Text><Paragraph><Label>. . .</Label><Text /></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>the member of the Senate occupying the recognized position of Speaker <Language xml:lang="la">pro tempore</Language> of the Senate, $20,600;</Text></Paragraph></Subsection></Section></ExistingText></ExplanatoryNote></Section><Heading level="1"><TitleText>Coming into Force</TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote>Dissolution of 43rd Parliament</MarginalNote><Label>5</Label><Text>This Act comes into force on the dissolution of the 43rd Parliament.</Text></Section></Body></Bill>