<Bill bill-origin="senate" bill-type="private-public" xml:lang="en" date-time="2020-01-22 15:52:37"><Identification><BillNumber>S-202</BillNumber><Parliament><Session>2</Session><Number>43</Number><RegnalYear><Year-s>69</Year-s><Monarch>Elizabeth II</Monarch></RegnalYear><Year-s>2020</Year-s></Parliament><LongTitle>An Act to amend the Assisted Human Reproduction Act</LongTitle><ShortTitle status="unofficial" /><RunningHead>An Act to amend the Assisted Human Reproduction Act</RunningHead><BillHistory><Stages stage="first-reading-senate"><Date><YYYY>2020</YYYY><MM>9</MM><DD>30</DD></Date></Stages></BillHistory><BillSponsor>Senator Moncion</BillSponsor><BillRefNumber date-time="">4321921</BillRefNumber></Identification><Introduction><Summary><TitleText>SUMMARY</TitleText><Provision><Text>This enactment amends the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Assisted Human Reproduction Act</XRefExternal> to decriminalize payment for sperm or ovum donation and for surrogacy in certain circumstances.</Text></Provision><Provision><Text>The enactment also amends the Act to allow for the purchase of other human reproductive material.</Text></Provision></Summary><Enacts><Provision><Text>Her Majesty, by and with the advice and consent of the Senate and House of Commons of Canada, <Keep>enacts</Keep> as follows:</Text></Provision></Enacts></Introduction><Body><Heading level="1"><MarginalNote><HistoricalNote>2004, c. 2</HistoricalNote></MarginalNote><TitleText>Assisted Human Reproduction Act</TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><Label>1</Label><Text>Section 2 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Assisted Human Reproduction Act</XRefExternal> is amended by adding “and” at the end of paragraph (e) and by repealing paragraph (f).</Text><ExplanatoryNote><TitleText><XRefExternal reference-type="act">Assisted Human Reproduction Act</XRefExternal></TitleText><Label><Emphasis style="italic">Clause 1</Emphasis>:</Label><ExplanatoryText>Existing text of relevant portions of section 2:</ExplanatoryText><ExistingText><Section><Label>2</Label><Text>The Parliament of Canada recognizes and declares that</Text><Paragraph><Label>. . . </Label><Text /></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(e)</Label><Text>persons who seek to undergo assisted reproduction procedures must not be discriminated against, including on the basis of their sexual orientation or marital status;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(f)</Label><Text>trade in the reproductive capabilities of women and men and the exploitation of children, women and men for commercial ends raise health and ethical concerns that justify their prohibition; and</Text></Paragraph></Section></ExistingText></ExplanatoryNote></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>2</Label><Text>Section 6 of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><Section><MarginalNote>Surrogate mother — requirements</MarginalNote><Label>6</Label><Text>No person shall counsel or induce a female person to become a surrogate mother, or perform any medical procedure to assist a female person to become a surrogate mother, knowing or having reason to believe that she is</Text><Paragraph><Label><Ins>(a)</Ins></Label><Text>under 21 years of age;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph change="ins"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>incapable of consenting to becoming a surrogate mother; or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph change="ins"><Label>(c)</Label><Text>being coerced by a third party to become a surrogate mother.</Text></Paragraph></Section></AmendedText><ExplanatoryNote><Label><Emphasis style="italic">Clause 2</Emphasis>:</Label><ExplanatoryText>Existing text of section 6:</ExplanatoryText><ExistingText><Section><Label>6</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>No person shall pay consideration to a female person to be a surrogate mother, offer to pay such consideration or advertise that it will be paid.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><Label>(2)</Label><Text>No person shall accept consideration for arranging for the services of a surrogate mother, offer to make such an arrangement for consideration or advertise the arranging of such services.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><Label>(3)</Label><Text>No person shall pay consideration to another person to arrange for the services of a surrogate mother, offer to pay such consideration or advertise the payment of it.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><Label>(4)</Label><Text>No person shall counsel or induce a female person to become a surrogate mother, or perform any medical procedure to assist a female person to become a surrogate mother, knowing or having reason to believe that the female person is under 21 years of age.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><Label>(5)</Label><Text>This section does not affect the validity under provincial law of any agreement under which a person agrees to be a surrogate mother.</Text></Subsection></Section></ExistingText></ExplanatoryNote></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>3</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Subsection 7(1) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText change="ins"><Section><MarginalNote>Sperm or ovum donation — requirements</MarginalNote><Label>7</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>No person shall, except for a purpose permitted under section 9, counsel or induce a person to donate their sperm or ova, or perform any medical procedure to assist a person to donate their sperm or ova, knowing or having reason to believe that the person is </Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>under 18 years of age;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>incapable of consenting to the donation; or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(c)</Label><Text>being coerced by a third party to donate.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection></Section></AmendedText><ExplanatoryNote><Label><Emphasis style="italic">Clause 3</Emphasis>:</Label><ExplanatoryText>Existing text of relevant portions of section 7:</ExplanatoryText><ExistingText><Section><Label>7</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>No person shall purchase, offer to purchase or advertise for the purchase of sperm or ova from a donor or a person acting on behalf of a donor.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><Label>. . . </Label><Text /></Subsection><Subsection><Label>(3)</Label><Text>No person shall purchase, offer to purchase or advertise for the purchase of a human cell or gene from a donor or a person acting on behalf of a donor, with the intention of using the gene or cell to create a human being or of making it available for that purpose.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><Label>. . . </Label><Text /></Subsection></Section></ExistingText></ExplanatoryNote></Subsection><Subsection><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Subsection 7(3) of the Act is repealed.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>4</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Subsection 12(1) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText change="ins"><Section><MarginalNote>Reimbursement of expenditures</MarginalNote><Label>12</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>No person shall, except in accordance with the regulations, reimburse any person for an expenditure <Keep>incurred</Keep> in the maintenance or transport of an <Emphasis style="italic">in vitro</Emphasis> embryo.</Text></Subsection></Section></AmendedText><ExplanatoryNote><Label><Emphasis style="italic">Clause 4</Emphasis>:</Label><ExplanatoryText>Existing text of subsection 12(1):</ExplanatoryText><ExistingText><Section><Label>12</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>No person shall, except in accordance with the regulations,</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>reimburse a donor for an expenditure incurred in the course of donating sperm or an ovum;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>reimburse any person for an expenditure incurred in the maintenance or transport of an in vitro embryo; or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(c)</Label><Text>reimburse a surrogate mother for an expenditure incurred by her in relation to her surrogacy.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection></Section></ExistingText></ExplanatoryNote></Subsection><Subsection><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Subsection 12(3) of the Act is repealed.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>5</Label><Text>Paragraph 65(1)‍(e.‍1) of the Act is repealed.</Text><ExplanatoryNote><Label><Emphasis style="italic">Clause 5</Emphasis>:</Label><ExplanatoryText>Existing text of relevant portions of subsection 65(1):</ExplanatoryText><ExistingText><Section><Label>65</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The Governor in Council may make regulations for carrying into effect the purposes and provisions of this Act and, in particular, may make regulations</Text><Paragraph><Label>. . . </Label><Text /></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(e.1)</Label><Text>for the purposes of subsection 12(3), respecting the reimbursement of a loss of income;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>. . . </Label><Text /></Paragraph></Subsection></Section></ExistingText></ExplanatoryNote></Section><Heading level="1"><TitleText>Coming into Force</TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote>180 days after royal assent</MarginalNote><Label>6</Label><Text>This Act comes into force 180 days after the day on which it receives royal assent.</Text></Section></Body></Bill>