<Bill bill-origin="senate" bill-type="private-public" xml:lang="en" date-time="2020-04-07 09:37:39"><Identification><BillNumber>S-210</BillNumber><Parliament><Session>2</Session><Number>43</Number><RegnalYear><Year-s>69</Year-s><Monarch>Elizabeth II</Monarch></RegnalYear><Year-s>2020</Year-s></Parliament><LongTitle>An Act to establish the Office of the Commissioner for Children and Youth in Canada</LongTitle><ShortTitle status="unofficial">Commissioner for Children and Youth in Canada Act</ShortTitle><RunningHead>Commissioner for Children and Youth in Canada Act</RunningHead><BillHistory><Stages stage="first-reading-senate"><Date><YYYY>2020</YYYY><MM>9</MM><DD>30</DD></Date></Stages></BillHistory><BillSponsor>Senator Moodie</BillSponsor><BillRefNumber date-time="">4321919</BillRefNumber></Identification><Introduction><Summary><TitleText>SUMMARY</TitleText><Provision><Text>This enactment provides for the establishment of the Office of the Commissioner for Children and Youth in Canada. It also makes consequential amendments to other Acts.</Text></Provision></Summary><TableOfProvisions><Heading level="1"><TitleText>TABLE OF PROVISIONS</TitleText></Heading><Heading level="1"><TitleText>An Act to establish the Office of the Commissioner for Children and Youth in Canada</TitleText></Heading><Text>Preamble</Text><Heading level="1"><TitleText>Short Title</TitleText></Heading><Label><Emphasis style="bold">1</Emphasis></Label><Text><Emphasis style="italic">Commissioner for Children and Youth in Canada Act</Emphasis></Text><Heading level="1"><TitleText>Interpretation</TitleText></Heading><Label><Emphasis style="bold">2</Emphasis></Label><Text>Definitions</Text><Heading level="1"><TitleText>Designation of Minister</TitleText></Heading><Label><Emphasis style="bold">3</Emphasis></Label><Text>Order in council</Text><Heading level="1"><TitleText>Purpose</TitleText></Heading><Label><Emphasis style="bold">4</Emphasis></Label><Text>Purpose</Text><Heading level="1"><TitleText>Commissioner for Children and Youth in Canada</TitleText></Heading><Label><Emphasis style="bold">5</Emphasis></Label><Text>Appointment</Text><Label><Emphasis style="bold">6</Emphasis></Label><Text>Status</Text><Label><Emphasis style="bold">7</Emphasis></Label><Text>Tenure</Text><Label><Emphasis style="bold">8</Emphasis></Label><Text>Interim appointment</Text><Label><Emphasis style="bold">9</Emphasis></Label><Text>Duties</Text><Label><Emphasis style="bold">10</Emphasis></Label><Text>Salary and expenses</Text><Label><Emphasis style="bold">11</Emphasis></Label><Text>Mandate</Text><Label><Emphasis style="bold">12</Emphasis></Label><Text>Advice</Text><Label><Emphasis style="bold">13</Emphasis></Label><Text>Collaboration</Text><Heading level="1"><TitleText>Assistant Commissioner</TitleText></Heading><Label><Emphasis style="bold">14</Emphasis></Label><Text>Appointment</Text><Label><Emphasis style="bold">15</Emphasis></Label><Text>Duties generally</Text><Label><Emphasis style="bold">16</Emphasis></Label><Text>Focus</Text><Heading level="1"><TitleText>Inquiries</TitleText></Heading><Label><Emphasis style="bold">17</Emphasis></Label><Text>Inquiries</Text><Label><Emphasis style="bold">18</Emphasis></Label><Text>Access to information</Text><Label><Emphasis style="bold">19</Emphasis></Label><Text>Report</Text><Heading level="1"><TitleText>Reports</TitleText></Heading><Label><Emphasis style="bold">20</Emphasis></Label><Text>Annual report</Text><Heading level="1"><TitleText>Office of the Commissioner for Children and Youth in Canada</TitleText></Heading><Label><Emphasis style="bold">21</Emphasis></Label><Text>Establishment</Text><Label><Emphasis style="bold">22</Emphasis></Label><Text>Chief executive officer</Text><Label><Emphasis style="bold">23</Emphasis></Label><Text>Contracts, etc.</Text><Label><Emphasis style="bold">24</Emphasis></Label><Text>Employees</Text><Heading level="1"><TitleText>General Provisions</TitleText></Heading><Label><Emphasis style="bold">25</Emphasis></Label><Text>Security requirements</Text><Label><Emphasis style="bold">26</Emphasis></Label><Text>Confidentiality</Text><Label><Emphasis style="bold">27</Emphasis></Label><Text>No summons</Text><Heading level="1"><TitleText>Offences</TitleText></Heading><Label><Emphasis style="bold">28</Emphasis></Label><Text>Obstruction</Text><Heading level="1"><TitleText>Review</TitleText></Heading><Label><Emphasis style="bold">29</Emphasis></Label><Text>Review of Act</Text><Heading level="1" type="amending"><TitleText><Emphasis style="bold">Consequential Amendments</Emphasis></TitleText></Heading><Label><Emphasis style="bold">30</Emphasis></Label><Text><Emphasis style="bold"><XRefExternal reference-type="act">Access to Information Act</XRefExternal></Emphasis></Text><Label><Emphasis style="bold">32</Emphasis></Label><Text><Emphasis style="bold"><XRefExternal reference-type="act">Financial Administration Act</XRefExternal></Emphasis></Text><Label><Emphasis style="bold">34</Emphasis></Label><Text><Emphasis style="bold"><XRefExternal reference-type="act">Privacy Act</XRefExternal></Emphasis></Text><Label><Emphasis style="bold">35</Emphasis></Label><Text><Emphasis style="bold"><XRefExternal reference-type="act">Official Languages Act</XRefExternal></Emphasis></Text><Label><Emphasis style="bold">36</Emphasis></Label><Text><Emphasis style="bold"><XRefExternal reference-type="act">Public Sector Compensation Act</XRefExternal></Emphasis></Text><Label><Emphasis style="bold">37</Emphasis></Label><Text><Emphasis style="bold"><XRefExternal reference-type="act">Public Servants Disclosure Protection Act</XRefExternal></Emphasis></Text><Heading level="1" type="amending"><TitleText><Emphasis style="bold">Coming into Force</Emphasis></TitleText></Heading><Label><Emphasis style="bold">38</Emphasis></Label><Text><Emphasis style="bold">Order in Council</Emphasis></Text></TableOfProvisions><Preamble><Provision pointsize="10" topmarginspacing="-6" language-align="yes"><MarginalNote>Preamble</MarginalNote><Text>Whereas the true measure of a country is the attention it devotes to its children and youth, including to their well-being, health, security, material situation, education and socialization, and the consideration it gives to their sense of being loved, valued and included in their family and society;</Text></Provision><Provision><Text>Whereas children and youth in Canada have no independent voice to represent their rights and interests in Parliament, limited opportunity to participate in political processes and no recourse to effective complaint mechanisms when their rights are violated;</Text></Provision><Provision><Text>Whereas Canada, by ratifying the United Nations Convention on the Rights of the Child on December 13, 1991, recognizes</Text></Provision><Provision first-line-indent="1" subsequent-line-indent="1" language-align="no"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>the right of every child to a standard of living adequate for their physical, mental, spiritual, moral and social development,</Text></Provision><Provision first-line-indent="1" subsequent-line-indent="1" language-align="no"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>the right of every child to have their best interests given primary consideration in all actions concerning them,</Text></Provision><Provision first-line-indent="1" subsequent-line-indent="1" language-align="no"><Label>(c)</Label><Text>the right of every child who is capable of forming their own views to express those views freely in all matters affecting them and the right to have those views given due weight in accordance with the child芒聙聶s age and maturity,</Text></Provision><Provision first-line-indent="1" subsequent-line-indent="1" language-align="no"><Label>(d)</Label><Text>the right of every child who is a member of an ethnic, religious or linguistic minority or who is First Nations, Inuit or Metis to, in community with other members of his or her group, enjoy his or her own culture, profess and practise his or her own religion, or use his or her own language and the importance of traditions and cultural values for the protection and harmonious development of every child; and</Text></Provision><Provision first-line-indent="1" subsequent-line-indent="1" language-align="no"><Label>(e)</Label><Text>its obligation to undertake all appropriate legislative, administrative, and other measures for the implementation of the rights recognized in the Convention;</Text></Provision><Provision language-align="no"><Text>Whereas children and youth under federal jurisdiction 芒聙聰 such as First Nations, Inuit and M脙漏tis children and youth 芒聙聰 do not benefit from provincial and territorial human rights protections;</Text></Provision><Provision><Text>Whereas, on November 10, 2010, Canada announced its support for the principles set out in the United Nations Declaration on the Rights of Indigenous Peoples, and on May 10, 2016, Canada undertook to promote and protect the rights of First Nations, Inuit and M脙漏tis peoples by reaffirming that it fully supports the Declaration without qualification;</Text></Provision><Provision><Text>Whereas, in particular, Canada芒聙聶s obligations include promoting and protecting the rights of First Nations, Inuit and M脙漏tis children and youth 芒聙聰 as well as respecting the sovereignty of First Nations, Inuit and M脙漏tis peoples 芒聙聰 in accordance with the United Nations Declaration on the Rights of Indigenous Peoples and the recommendations of the Truth and Reconciliation Commission of Canada as part of Canada芒聙聶s nation-to-nation relationship with First Nations, Inuit and M脙漏tis peoples;</Text></Provision><Provision><Text>Whereas Call for Justice 12.9 from the Inquiry on Missing and Murdered Indigenous Women and Girls calls for a child and youth advocate in every province, as well as a federal counterpart;</Text></Provision><Provision><Text>Whereas Canada recognizes its obligation to consult with and work in cooperation and partnership with First Nations, Inuit and M脙漏tis peoples to address matters concerning First Nations, Inuit and M脙漏tis children and youth to support their identity, dignity and well-being;</Text></Provision><Provision><Text>Whereas Canada has obligations in respect of</Text></Provision><Provision first-line-indent="1" subsequent-line-indent="1" language-align="no"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>addressing issues of concern to First Nations, Inuit and M脙漏tis peoples 芒聙聰 including First Nations, Inuit and M脙漏tis children and youth 芒聙聰 such as protection from loss of languages, land, resources and well-being,</Text></Provision><Provision first-line-indent="1" subsequent-line-indent="1" language-align="no"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>acknowledging and rectifying historical practices that separated generations of children from their families and culture, and</Text></Provision><Provision first-line-indent="1" subsequent-line-indent="1" language-align="no"><Label>(c)</Label><Text>consulting with First Nations, Inuit and M脙漏tis peoples on their own laws and practices for protecting and supporting children and youth;</Text></Provision><Provision><Text>Whereas Canada has an obligation to ensure the well-being and rights of children and youth who are racialized, have disabilities or identify as <Keep svc="1">gender-diverse</Keep> people or people with diverse sexual orientation;</Text></Provision><Provision language-align="no"><Text>And whereas it is important for Canada to address inequities experienced by all vulnerable populations, especially children and youth consistent with the rights and freedoms afforded to all persons under the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Canadian Charter of Rights and Freedoms</XRefExternal>;</Text></Provision></Preamble><Enacts><Provision language-align="yes"><Text>Now, therefore, Her Majesty, by and with the advice and consent of the Senate and House of Commons of Canada, enacts as follows:</Text></Provision></Enacts></Introduction><Body><Heading level="1"><TitleText>Short Title</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Short title</MarginalNote><Label>1</Label><Text>This Act may be cited as the <Emphasis style="italic">Commissioner for Children and Youth in Canada Act</Emphasis>.</Text></Section><Heading level="1"><TitleText>Interpretation</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Definitions</MarginalNote><Label>2</Label><Text>The definitions in this section apply in this Act.</Text><Definition><Text><DefinedTermEn>children and youth</DefinedTermEn> means persons who are under the age of 18 years. (<DefinedTermFr>enfant</DefinedTermFr> ou <DefinedTermFr>jeune</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Definition><Definition><Text><DefinedTermEn>Commissioner</DefinedTermEn> means the Commissioner for Children and Youth in Canada appointed under section 5. (<DefinedTermFr>commissaire</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Definition><Definition><Text><DefinedTermEn>Convention</DefinedTermEn> means the Convention on the Rights of the Child adopted on November 20, 1989, by the General Assembly of the United Nations and ratified by Canada on December 13, 1991, including its Optional Protocols, as ratified by Canada and amended from time to time. (<DefinedTermFr>Convention</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Definition><Definition><Text><DefinedTermEn> governing body</DefinedTermEn> means a council, government or other entity that is authorized to act on behalf of a community or people. (<DefinedTermFr>corps dirigeant</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Definition><Definition><Text><DefinedTermEn>government institution</DefinedTermEn> means</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>a department named in Schedule I to the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Financial Administration Act</XRefExternal>, including the minister responsible for that department and any person acting on behalf of that minister; or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>a division or branch of the federal public administration set out in column I of Schedule I.1 to the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Financial Administration Act</XRefExternal>, a corporation named in Schedule II to that Act, a parent Crown corporation as defined in subsection 83(1) of that Act or the Canadian Forces. (<DefinedTermFr>institution f脙漏d脙漏rale</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Paragraph></Definition><Definition><Text><DefinedTermEn>Minister</DefinedTermEn> means the Minister designated under section 3. (<DefinedTermFr>ministre</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Definition><Definition><Text><DefinedTermEn>statutory instrument</DefinedTermEn> means any rule, order, regulation, ordinance, direction, form, tariff of costs or fees, letters patent, commission, warrant, proclamation, bylaw, resolution or other instrument issued, made or established</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>in the execution of a power conferred by or under an Act of Parliament, by or under which that instrument is expressly authorized to be issued, made or established other than by the conferring on any person or body of powers or functions in relation to a matter to which that instrument relates; or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>by or under the authority of the Governor in Council, other than in the execution of a power conferred by or under an Act of Parliament. (<DefinedTermFr>texte r脙漏glementaire</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Paragraph></Definition><Definition><Text><DefinedTermEn>Office</DefinedTermEn> means the Office of the Commissioner for Children and Youth in Canada established by section 21. (<DefinedTermFr>Bureau</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Definition></Section><Heading level="1"><TitleText>Designation of Minister</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Order in council</MarginalNote><Label>3</Label><Text>The Governor in Council may, by order, designate any federal minister to be the Minister referred to in this Act.</Text></Section><Heading level="1"><TitleText>Purpose</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Purpose</MarginalNote><Label>4</Label><Text>The purpose of this Act is to establish an independent Commissioner for Children and Youth in Canada to promote, monitor and report on the implementation of Canada芒聙聶s obligations under the Convention and to advance the rights of children and youth in Canada, giving primary consideration to the best interests of the child in all actions concerning children.</Text></Section><Heading level="1"><TitleText>Commissioner for Children and Youth in Canada</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Appointment</MarginalNote><Label>5</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>On a recommendation made by the Minister under subsection (2), the Governor in Council must, by commission under the Great Seal, appoint a Commissioner for Children and Youth in Canada after</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>consultation with the leader or facilitator of every recognized party or recognized parliamentary group in the Senate and the leader of every recognized party in the House of Commons; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>approval of the appointment by resolution of the Senate and House of Commons.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Recommendation</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Before making the recommendation referred to in subsection (1), the Minister must</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>advertise the vacancy or prospective vacancy across Canada in a manner sufficient to enable qualified individuals to apply for appointment;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>consult with organizations or persons that, in the opinion of the Minister, have a particular interest in the work of the Commissioner, including representatives from First Nations, Inuit or M脙漏tis governing bodies and organizations representing First Nations, Inuit and M脙漏tis children and youth; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(c)</Label><Text>ensure that the person recommended for appointment is of good character, has proven experience in and a commitment to promoting the rights of children and youth and is qualified in accordance with any criteria established by the Minister.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Status</MarginalNote><Label>6</Label><Text>The Commissioner is deemed to be</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>a person employed in the public service for the purposes of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Public Service Superannuation Act</XRefExternal>;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>an employee for the purposes of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Government Employees Compensation Act</XRefExternal>; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(c)</Label><Text>employed in the federal public administration for the purposes of any regulations made under section 9 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Aeronautics Act</XRefExternal>.</Text></Paragraph></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Tenure</MarginalNote><Label>7</Label><Text>The Commissioner holds office during good behaviour for a non-renewable term of seven years but may be removed for cause by the Governor in Council at any time on address of the Senate and House of Commons.</Text></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Interim appointment</MarginalNote><Label>8</Label><Text>In the event of the absence or incapacity of the Commissioner, or if that office is vacant, the Governor in Council may appoint any suitable person to hold that office in the interim for a term not exceeding six months.</Text></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Duties</MarginalNote><Label>9</Label><Text>The Commissioner must engage exclusively in the duties of the office of Commissioner under this or any other Act of Parliament and must not hold any other office or engage in any other employment for remuneration.</Text></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Salary and expenses</MarginalNote><Label>10</Label><Text>The Commissioner is to be paid the salary and expenses set by the Governor in Council and is entitled to be paid for any travel and living expenses incurred in the performance of their duties while absent from their ordinary place of work.</Text></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Mandate</MarginalNote><Label>11</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The mandate of the Commissioner is</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>to advocate at the national level in Canada for the promotion and protection of the rights, well-being and views of children and youth, particularly those who belong to a vulnerable group;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>to collaborate with First Nations, Inuit or M脙漏tis children and youth and governing bodies to include First Nations, Inuit and M脙漏tis views and values in the Commissioner芒聙聶s advocacy for First Nations, Inuit and M脙漏tis children and youth;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(c)</Label><Text>to foster public understanding and recognition of the Convention, the role and activities of the Commissioner and the rights and well-being of children and youth in Canada;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(d)</Label><Text>to monitor the development and application of legislation, statutory instruments and government policies and practices affecting children and youth;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(e)</Label><Text>to promote, monitor and report on the effective implementation of Canada芒聙聶s obligations under the Convention that fall within the legislative authority of Parliament, particularly as they relate to</Text><Subparagraph><Label>(i)</Label><Text>non-discrimination in ensuring the rights set forth in the Convention,</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph><Label>(ii)</Label><Text>the best interests of the child as a primary consideration in all actions concerning them,</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph><Label>(iii)</Label><Text>every child芒聙聶s right to life, survival and development, and</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph><Label>(iv)</Label><Text>the right of every child who is capable of forming their own views to express those views freely in all matters affecting them and the right to have those views given due weight in accordance with their age and maturity;</Text></Subparagraph></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(f)</Label><Text>to review proposed and enacted federal legislation and statutory instruments in order to assess their impact on the rights of children and youth, including consistency with the Convention;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(g)</Label><Text>to monitor and report on the implementation of the Convention by government institutions, including in respect of policies, services and programs affecting children and youth and their rights;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(h)</Label><Text>to consider any recommendations, suggestions and requests concerning the rights of children and youth that the Commissioner receives from any source;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(i)</Label><Text>to assist in the development and implementation, in cooperation with First Nations, Inuit or M脙漏tis children and youth and governing bodies, of programs adapted to the rights, well-being, traditions and needs of First Nations, Inuit and M脙漏tis children and youth;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(j)</Label><Text>to collaborate and cooperate with authorities across Canada that promote, advocate for or serve children and youth in order to foster common policies and practices and to avoid conflicts in the handling of matters in cases of shared jurisdiction;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(k)</Label><Text>to encourage, through the use of media, social networks and other methods, the participation of children and youth, according to their age and maturity, in all aspects of Canadian society and in the activities of the Office and Commissioner;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(l)</Label><Text>to consult with children and youth and representatives of children and youth groups, as well as service providers and others, in respect of issues that may have an impact on the lives of children and youth;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(m)</Label><Text>to promote accessible and effective complaint mechanisms for children and youth and to monitor their use;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(n)</Label><Text>to facilitate access to justice for children and youth and to effective remedies for breaches of their rights, and to seek intervener or amicus curiae status as the Commissioner considers appropriate;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(o)</Label><Text>to promote First Nations, Inuit and M脙漏tis manners of collaboration, advocacy and dispute resolution in relation to First Nations, Inuit and M脙漏tis children and youth, with a view to ensuring that all actions regarding their rights are considered in the context of the collective and individual rights of First Nations, Inuit and M脙漏tis children and youth;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(p)</Label><Text>to encourage the right of First Nations, Inuit and M脙漏tis children and youth to maintain cultural connections, including connections with extended families, lands and waters, traditional languages, songs, stories and all forms of artistic expression as markers of their identity; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(q)</Label><Text>to encourage the implementation of First Nations, Inuit and M脙漏tis law and legal processes in all matters concerning advocacy for First Nations, Inuit and M脙漏tis children and youth in accordance with the rights of the child, including implementing specific First Nations, Inuit and M脙漏tis preferences for protocol, forum, spiritual practice and community involvement.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Mandate 芒聙聰 consideration</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>In carrying out their mandate, the Commissioner is to take into account the multiple and intersecting forms of marginalization and discrimination that persons face, in order to consider the diverse needs of Canadian children.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Advice</MarginalNote><Label>12</Label><Text>The Commissioner may provide advice to any Minister of the Crown, on the Commissioner芒聙聶s own initiative or at the request of the Minister.</Text></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Collaboration</MarginalNote><Label>13</Label><Text>The Minister of Foreign Affairs must consult the Commissioner before finalizing Canada芒聙聶s reports to the United Nations Committee on the Rights of the Child on the implementation of the Convention.</Text></Section><Heading level="1"><TitleText>Assistant Commissioner</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Appointment</MarginalNote><Label>14</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The Governor in Council may, on the recommendation of the Commissioner, appoint one or more Assistant Commissioners for Children and Youth in Canada.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Tenure of office and removal of Assistant Commissioner</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Subject to this section, an Assistant Commissioner holds office during good behaviour for a term not exceeding five years.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Further terms</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>An Assistant Commissioner, on the expiry of a first or any subsequent term of office, is eligible to be reappointed for a further term not exceeding five years.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Duties generally</MarginalNote><Label>15</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>An Assistant Commissioner shall engage exclusively in any duties or functions of the Office under this Act that are delegated by the Commissioner to that Assistant Commissioner and shall not hold any other office under Her Majesty for reward or engage in any other employment for reward.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Salary and expenses</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>An Assistant Commissioner is entitled to be paid a salary to be fixed by the Governor in Council and any travel and living expenses incurred in the performance of duties under this Act or any other Act of Parliament and that the Commissioner considers reasonable.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Benefits</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>An Assistant Commissioner is deemed to be</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>a person employed in the public service for the purposes of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Public Service Superannuation Act</XRefExternal>;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>an employee for the purposes of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Government Employees Compensation Act</XRefExternal>; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(c)</Label><Text>employed in the federal public administration for the purposes of any regulations made under section 9 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Aeronautics Act</XRefExternal>.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection></Section><Section><MarginalNote> Focus</MarginalNote><Label>16</Label><Text>In making a recommendation under subsection 14(1) or delegating duties or functions under subsection 15(1), the Commissioner must consider appointing an Assistant Commissioner for the purpose of ensuring focus on <Keep svc="1">matters</Keep> related, in particular, to First Nations, Inuit and M脙漏tis children and youth.</Text></Section><Heading level="1"><TitleText>Inquiries</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Inquiries</MarginalNote><Label>17</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The Commissioner may, on the Commissioner芒聙聶s own initiative or on request from any Minister of the Crown, a committee of the Senate or House of Commons or a member of the public, conduct an inquiry into any matter related to the Commissioner芒聙聶s mandate, including a systemic inquiry into any matter under federal jurisdiction that affects the rights of children and youth.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Declined inquires</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The Commissioner may decline a request for an inquiry for any reason, including that</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>the Commissioner is of the view that the request is frivolous or vexatious; or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>the matter is not related to the Commissioner芒聙聶s mandate.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Abandonment or set-aside</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>The Commissioner may abandon or set aside any inquiry as the Commissioner considers appropriate.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Powers</MarginalNote><Label>(4)</Label><Text>The Commissioner has all the powers of a commissioner appointed under Part II of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Inquiries Act</XRefExternal> for the purpose of carrying out an inquiry and may make a copy of any document examined in the course of an inquiry.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Powers 芒聙聰 places of detention or residence</MarginalNote><Label>(5)</Label><Text>The Commissioner may, upon reasonable notice and subject to any personal safety and security considerations or restrictions,</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>enter any place of detention or residence for children and youth under control or operation of the Government of Canada; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>have direct access, in conditions of privacy, to the children and youth detained in a place described in paragraph (a).</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Return of documents or things</MarginalNote><Label>(6)</Label><Text>The Commissioner must return any document or thing to the person who was required to produce it within 10 days after a request for its return is made to the Commissioner, but nothing precludes the Commissioner from again requiring its production.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Access to information</MarginalNote><Label>18</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The Commissioner is entitled to free access, at all convenient times, to all records under the control of a government institution that relate to the fulfilment of the Commissioner芒聙聶s responsibilities, and the Commissioner is also entitled to require and receive from government institutions and their employees any information, reports and explanations that the Commissioner considers necessary for that purpose.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Exception</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Subsection (1) does not apply in respect of any information that is a confidence of the Queen芒聙聶s Privy Council for Canada as defined in subsection 39(2) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Canada Evidence Act</XRefExternal>.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Report</MarginalNote><Label>19</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>At the conclusion of an inquiry under section 17, the Commissioner must prepare a report containing a summary of the matter under inquiry and setting out any conclusions and recommendations.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Copy of report</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>A copy of the report must be provided to the person, Minister, committee of the Senate or House of Commons or other entity that requests it and must be posted on the Office website.</Text></Subsection></Section><Heading level="1"><TitleText>Reports</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Annual report</MarginalNote><Label>20</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The Commissioner must, within three months after the end of each calendar year, prepare a report for the year that sets out</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>the Commissioner芒聙聶s assessment of</Text><Subparagraph><Label>(i)</Label><Text>the implementation of the Convention by the Government of Canada during that year, and</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph><Label>(ii)</Label><Text>the effectiveness of initiatives taken by the Government of Canada during that year to improve the rights and well-being of children and youth;</Text></Subparagraph></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>the Commissioner芒聙聶s recommendations to improve the Government of Canada芒聙聶s implementation of the Convention and the effectiveness of its initiatives for children and youth, including any measures to monitor and respond to initiatives regarding First Nations, Inuit and M脙漏tis children and youth; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(c)</Label><Text>the activities of the Office and the Commissioner.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Special reports</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The Commissioner may, at any time, prepare a special report on any matter within the Commissioner芒聙聶s mandate if, in the Commissioner芒聙聶s opinion, the matter is of such urgency or importance that a report should not be deferred until the time provided for submission of the next annual report made under subsection (1).</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Tabling of report</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>The Commissioner must submit the annual report and any special report to the Speakers of the Senate and the House of Commons, and the Speakers must lay any such reports before their respective Houses on any of the first 15 days on which that House is sitting after the Speaker receives the report.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Publication</MarginalNote><Label>(4)</Label><Text>The Commissioner must post the annual report or any special report on the Office website within 10 days after the day on which it is tabled in both Houses.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Response</MarginalNote><Label>(5)</Label><Text>The Minister must, within 90 days after an annual or special report is submitted to Parliament, submit a comprehensive written response to the report that addresses</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>the finding of any violations of the rights of children and youth; or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>any impact assessment on the rights of children and youth that is contained in the report.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Tabling of response</MarginalNote><Label>(6)</Label><Text>The Minister shall cause a copy of a response prepared under subsection (5) to be tabled in each House of Parliament on any of the first five days on which that House sits following completion of the response.</Text></Section><Heading level="1"><TitleText>Office of the Commissioner for Children and Youth in Canada</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Establishment</MarginalNote><Label>21</Label><Text>The Office of the Commissioner for Children and Youth in Canada is hereby established, to assist in fulfilling the mandate of the Commissioner.</Text></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Chief executive officer</MarginalNote><Label>22</Label><Text>The Commissioner is the chief executive officer of the Office and has the control and management of the Office and all matters connected with it.</Text></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Contracts, etc.</MarginalNote><Label>23</Label><Text>The Commissioner may enter into contracts, memoranda of understanding or other arrangements, including contracts to engage the services of legal counsel or other persons having professional, technical or specialized knowledge, to advise or assist the Commissioner or the Office.</Text></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Employees</MarginalNote><Label>24</Label><Text>The employees of the Office are to be appointed in accordance with the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Public Service Employment Act</XRefExternal>.</Text></Section><Heading level="1"><TitleText>General Provisions</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Security requirements</MarginalNote><Label>25</Label><Text>If the Commissioner, or any person acting on behalf of or under the direction of the Commissioner, receives or obtains information relating to any inquiry or investigation under this or any other Act of Parliament, the Commissioner or the person must, with respect to access to and use of that information, satisfy any security requirements applicable to, and take any oath of secrecy required to be taken by, persons who normally have access to and use of that information.</Text></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Confidentiality</MarginalNote><Label>26</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Subject to subsections (2) to (4), the Commissioner, and every person acting on behalf of or under the direction of the Commissioner, may not disclose any information that comes to their knowledge in the performance of their duties and functions under this Act.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Disclosure authorized</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The Commissioner may disclose, and may authorize any person acting on behalf of or under the direction of the Commissioner to disclose, information</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>that, in the opinion of the Commissioner, is necessary to carry out an inquiry under this Act or establish the grounds for findings and recommendations contained in any report under the Act;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>that is subject to a request for disclosure from a committee of the Senate or the House of Commons;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(c)</Label><Text>in the course of</Text><Subparagraph><Label>(i)</Label><Text>a prosecution for an offence under this Act or under section 131 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Criminal Code</XRefExternal> (perjury) in respect of a statement made under this Act, or</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph><Label>(ii)</Label><Text>an appeal or subsequent action related to a matter referred to in subparagraph (i).</Text></Subparagraph></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Disclosure of offence authorized</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>The Commissioner may disclose to the Attorney General of Canada or of a province information relating to the commission of an offence under a law of Canada or a province if, in the Commissioner芒聙聶s opinion, there is evidence of such an offence.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Disclosure 芒聙聰 harm</MarginalNote><Label>(4)</Label><Text>The Commissioner may disclose any information in the Commissioner芒聙聶s possession to any law enforcement agency or agent or to any child protection or welfare agency if the Commissioner believes there is a risk of imminent harm to a child or young person.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section><MarginalNote>No summons</MarginalNote><Label>27</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The Commissioner, and any person acting on behalf of or under the direction of the Commissioner, is not a competent or compellable witness in respect of any matter coming to the knowledge of the Commissioner or that person as a result of performing any duties or functions under this Act in any proceedings other than</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>a prosecution for an offence under this Act; or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>a prosecution for an offence under section 131 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Criminal Code</XRefExternal> (perjury) in respect of a statement made under this Act or an appeal or subsequent action related to that prosecution.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Protection of Commissioner</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>No criminal or civil proceedings lie against the Commissioner, or against any person acting on behalf of or under the direction of the Commissioner, for anything done, reported, said or omitted in good faith in the course of the exercise or performance or purported exercise or performance of any power, duty or function of the Commissioner under this Act.</Text></Subsection></Section><Heading level="1"><TitleText>Offences</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Obstruction</MarginalNote><Label>28</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>No person may obstruct the Commissioner or any person acting on behalf of or under the direction of the Commissioner in the performance of the Commissioner芒聙聶s duties and functions under this Act.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Reprisal</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>No person may take or threaten to take any reprisal action against a person because that person requested an inquiry under this Act, participated in an inquiry under this Act or otherwise aided the Commissioner in the exercise of the Commissioner芒聙聶s duties and functions under this Act.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Offences and punishment</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>Every person who contravenes subsection (1) or (2) is guilty of an offence and liable on summary conviction to a fine of $10,000.</Text></Subsection></Section><Heading level="1"><TitleText>Review</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Review of Act</MarginalNote><Label>29</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Within five years after the day on which this section comes into force, the Minister must conduct a review of this Act and make available to the public a written report respecting that review.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Subsequent reviews</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>A subsequent review must be conducted within five years after the day on which the report on a previous review was made available to the public, and the Minister must make a written report respecting each subsequent review available to the public.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Duty to inform public</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>The Minister must inform the public of the date on which a review is to begin.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Review to include consultation with children and youth</MarginalNote><Label>(4)</Label><Text>Every review conducted must include consultations with children and youth and an evaluation of the extent to which their rights, well-being and views have been considered under this Act.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Review to include consultations and address First Nations, Inuit and M脙漏tis issues</MarginalNote><Label>(5)</Label><Text>Every review must be conducted in collaboration with First Nations, Inuit or M脙漏tis children and youth and governing bodies and must include an evaluation of the progress that has been made under this Act in addressing the systemic disadvantage experienced by First Nations, Inuit and M脙漏tis children and youth.</Text></Subsection></Section><Heading level="1"><TitleText>Consequential Amendments</TitleText></Heading><Heading level="2"><MarginalNote><HistoricalNote>R.S., c. A-1</HistoricalNote></MarginalNote><TitleText><XRefExternal reference-type="act">Access to Information Act</XRefExternal></TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><Label>30</Label><Text>Subsection 16.1(1) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Access to Information Act</XRefExternal> is amended by adding the following after paragraph (b):</Text><AmendedText change="ins"><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(b.1)</Label><Text>the Commissioner for Children and Youth in Canada;</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText><ExplanatoryNote><TitleText><XRefExternal reference-type="act">Access to Information Act</XRefExternal></TitleText><Label><Emphasis style="italic">Clause 30</Emphasis>:</Label><ExplanatoryText>Text of relevant portion of subsection 16.1(1) :</ExplanatoryText><ExistingText><Section><Label>16.1</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The following heads of government institutions shall refuse to disclose any record requested under this Part that contains information that was obtained or created by them or on their behalf in the course of an investigation, examination or audit conducted by them or under their authority:</Text></Subsection></Section></ExistingText></ExplanatoryNote></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>31</Label><Text>Schedule I to the Act is amended by adding the following in alphabetical order under the heading 芒聙聹OTHER GOVERNMENT
INSTITUTIONS芒聙聺:
</Text><AmendedText change="ins"><BilingualGroup><BilingualItemEn>Office of the Commissioner for Children and Youth in Canada</BilingualItemEn><BilingualItemFr>Bureau du commissaire 脙聽 l芒聙聶enfance et 脙聽 la jeunesse du Canada</BilingualItemFr></BilingualGroup></AmendedText><ExplanatoryNote><Label><Emphasis style="italic">Clause 31</Emphasis>:</Label><ExplanatoryText>New.</ExplanatoryText></ExplanatoryNote></Section><Heading level="2"><MarginalNote><HistoricalNote>R.S., c. F-11</HistoricalNote></MarginalNote><TitleText><XRefExternal reference-type="act">Financial Administration Act</XRefExternal></TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><Label>32</Label><Text>Schedule I.1 to the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Financial Administration Act</XRefExternal> is amended by adding the following in alphabetical order in column I:</Text><AmendedText change="ins"><BilingualGroup><BilingualItemEn>Office of the Commissioner for Children and Youth in Canada</BilingualItemEn><BilingualItemFr>Bureau du commissaire 脙聽 l芒聙聶enfance et 脙聽 la jeunesse du Canada</BilingualItemFr></BilingualGroup></AmendedText><ContinuedSectionSubsection><Text>and a corresponding reference in column II to 芒聙聹Minister of Justice芒聙聺.</Text></ContinuedSectionSubsection><ExplanatoryNote><TitleText><XRefExternal reference-type="act">Financial Administration Act</XRefExternal></TitleText><Label><Emphasis style="italic">Clause 32</Emphasis>:</Label><ExplanatoryText>New.</ExplanatoryText></ExplanatoryNote></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>33</Label><Text>Schedule IV to the Act is amended by adding the following in alphabetical order:</Text><AmendedText change="ins"><BilingualGroup><BilingualItemEn>Office of the Commissioner for Children and Youth in Canada</BilingualItemEn><BilingualItemFr>Bureau du commissaire 脙聽 l芒聙聶enfance et 脙聽 la jeunesse du Canada</BilingualItemFr></BilingualGroup></AmendedText><ExplanatoryNote><Label><Emphasis style="italic">Clause 33</Emphasis>:</Label><ExplanatoryText>New.</ExplanatoryText></ExplanatoryNote></Section><Heading level="2"><MarginalNote><HistoricalNote>R.S., c. P-21</HistoricalNote></MarginalNote><TitleText><XRefExternal reference-type="act">Privacy Act</XRefExternal></TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><Label>34</Label><Text>The schedule to the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Privacy Act</XRefExternal> is amended by adding the following in alphabetical order under the heading 芒聙聹OTHER GOVERNMENT INSTITUTIONS芒聙聺:</Text><AmendedText change="ins"><BilingualGroup><BilingualItemEn>Office of the Commissioner for Children and Youth in Canada</BilingualItemEn><BilingualItemFr>Bureau du commissaire 脙聽 l芒聙聶enfance et 脙聽 la jeunesse du Canada</BilingualItemFr></BilingualGroup></AmendedText><ExplanatoryNote><TitleText><XRefExternal reference-type="act">Privacy Act</XRefExternal></TitleText><Label><Emphasis style="italic">Clause 34</Emphasis>:</Label><ExplanatoryText>New.</ExplanatoryText></ExplanatoryNote></Section><Heading level="2"><MarginalNote><HistoricalNote>R.S., c. 31 (4th Supp.)</HistoricalNote></MarginalNote><TitleText><XRefExternal reference-type="act">Official Languages Act</XRefExternal></TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><Label>35</Label><Text>Subsection 24(3) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Official Languages Act</XRefExternal> is amended by striking out 芒聙聹and芒聙聺 at the end of paragraph (e), by adding 芒聙聹and芒聙聺 at the end of paragraph (f) and by adding the following after paragraph (f): </Text><AmendedText><SectionPiece><Paragraph change="ins"><Label>(g)</Label><Text>the Office of the Commissioner for Children and Youth in Canada.</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText><ExplanatoryNote><TitleText><XRefExternal reference-type="act">Official Languages Act</XRefExternal></TitleText><Label><Emphasis style="italic">Clause 35</Emphasis>:</Label><ExplanatoryText>Existing text of relevant portions of subsection 24(3):</ExplanatoryText><ExistingText><Subsection><Label>(3)</Label><Text>Without restricting the generality of subsection (2), the duty set out in that subsection applies in respect of</Text><Paragraph><Label>. . .</Label><Text /></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(e)</Label><Text>the Office of the Privacy Commissioner; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(f)</Label><Text>the Office of the Commissioner of Lobbying.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection></ExistingText></ExplanatoryNote></Section><Heading level="2"><MarginalNote><HistoricalNote>1991, c. 30</HistoricalNote></MarginalNote><TitleText><XRefExternal reference-type="act">Public Sector Compensation Act</XRefExternal></TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><Label>36</Label><Text>Schedule I to the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Public Sector Compensation Act</XRefExternal> is amended by adding the following in alphabetical order under the heading 芒聙聹Other Portions of the Public Service芒聙聺:</Text><AmendedText change="ins"><BilingualGroup><BilingualItemEn>Office of the Commissioner for Children and Youth in Canada</BilingualItemEn><BilingualItemFr>Bureau du commissaire 脙聽 l芒聙聶enfance et 脙聽 la jeunesse du Canada</BilingualItemFr></BilingualGroup></AmendedText><ExplanatoryNote><TitleText><XRefExternal reference-type="act">Public Sector Compensation Act</XRefExternal></TitleText><Label><Emphasis style="italic">Clause 36</Emphasis>:</Label><ExplanatoryText>New.</ExplanatoryText></ExplanatoryNote></Section><Heading level="2"><MarginalNote><HistoricalNote>2005, c. 46 </HistoricalNote></MarginalNote><TitleText><XRefExternal reference-type="act">Public Servants Disclosure Protection Act</XRefExternal></TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><Label>37</Label><Text>Schedule 2 to the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Public Servants Disclosure Protection Act</XRefExternal> is amended by
adding the following in alphabetical order:
</Text><AmendedText change="ins"><BilingualGroup><BilingualItemEn>Office of the Commissioner for Children and Youth in Canada</BilingualItemEn><BilingualItemFr>Bureau du commissaire 脙聽 l芒聙聶enfance et 脙聽 la jeunesse du Canada</BilingualItemFr></BilingualGroup></AmendedText><ExplanatoryNote><TitleText><XRefExternal reference-type="act">Public Servants Disclosure Protection Act</XRefExternal></TitleText><Label><Emphasis style="italic">Clause 37</Emphasis>:</Label><ExplanatoryText>New.</ExplanatoryText></ExplanatoryNote></Section><Heading level="1"><TitleText>Coming into Force</TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote>Order in council</MarginalNote><Label>38</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Subject to subsection (2), this Act comes into force on a day to be fixed by order of the Governor in Council.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Royal recommendation</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>No order may be made under subsection (1) unless the appropriation of moneys for the purposes of this Act has been recommended by the Governor General and such moneys have been appropriated by Parliament.</Text></Subsection></Section></Body></Bill>