<Bill bill-origin="senate" bill-type="private-public" xml:lang="en" date-time="2020-12-01 11:32:55"><Identification><BillNumber>S-221</BillNumber><Parliament><Session>2</Session><Number>43</Number><RegnalYear><Year-s>69</Year-s><Monarch>Elizabeth II</Monarch></RegnalYear><Year-s>2020</Year-s></Parliament><LongTitle>An Act to amend the Criminal Code (mischief related to memorials to first responders)</LongTitle><ShortTitle status="unofficial" /><RunningHead>An Act to amend the Criminal Code (mischief related to memorials to first responders)</RunningHead><BillHistory><Stages stage="first-reading-senate"><Date><YYYY>2020</YYYY><MM>12</MM><DD>8</DD></Date></Stages></BillHistory><BillSponsor>Senator Housakos</BillSponsor><BillRefNumber date-time="">4322021</BillRefNumber></Identification><Introduction><Summary><TitleText>SUMMARY</TitleText><Provision language-align="yes"><Text>This enactment amends the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Criminal Code</XRefExternal> to provide for the offence of committing mischief in relation to a monument or similar structure that honours first responders.</Text></Provision></Summary><Preamble><Provision pointsize="10" topmarginspacing="-6" language-align="yes"><MarginalNote>Preamble</MarginalNote><Text>Whereas first responders regularly put their own lives and physical, emotional and mental well-being at risk in order to save the lives of others;</Text></Provision><Provision><Text>Whereas, for their selfless heroism, first responders are honoured and commemorated with various memorials, statues, cenotaphs and other structures throughout Canada;</Text></Provision><Provision><Text>Whereas vandalism against these memorials, statues, cenotaphs and other structures dishonours the memory of these first responders and their service to the community;</Text></Provision><Provision><Text>And whereas significant penalties should be imposed against any person convicted of mischief against a memorial, statue, cenotaph or other structure honouring first responders;</Text></Provision></Preamble><Enacts><Provision language-align="yes" hyphenation="no"><Text>Now, therefore, Her Majesty, by and with the advice and consent of the Senate and House of Commons of Canada, enacts as follows:</Text></Provision></Enacts></Introduction><Body><Heading level="1"><MarginalNote><HistoricalNote>R.S., c. C-46</HistoricalNote></MarginalNote><TitleText><XRefExternal reference-type="act">Criminal Code</XRefExternal></TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><Label>1</Label><Text>Section 430 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Criminal Code</XRefExternal> is amended by adding the following after subsection (4.11):</Text><AmendedText change="ins"><Subsection><MarginalNote>Mischief related to memorials to first responders</MarginalNote><Label>(4.12)</Label><Text>Everyone who commits mischief in relation to property that is a building or structure or part of a building or structure that primarily serves as a monument to honour first responders — including a statue or monument — or an object associated with honouring or remembering those persons if that object is located in or on the grounds of such a building or structure, or a cemetery is guilty of an indictable offence or an offence punishable on summary conviction and is liable,</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>whether the offence is prosecuted by indictment or punishable on summary conviction, to the following minimum punishment:</Text><Subparagraph><Label>(i)</Label><Text>for a first offence, to a fine of not less than $1,000,</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph><Label>(ii)</Label><Text>for a second offence, to imprisonment for not less than 14 days, and</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph><Label>(iii)</Label><Text>for each subsequent offence, to imprisonment for not less than 30 days;</Text></Subparagraph></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>if the offence is prosecuted by indictment, to imprisonment for a term not exceeding 10 years; or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(c)</Label><Text>if the offence is punishable on summary conviction, to imprisonment for a term not exceeding 18 months.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Definition of <DefinedTermEn>first responders</DefinedTermEn></MarginalNote><Label>(4.13)</Label><Text>In subsection (4.12), <DefinedTermEn>first responders</DefinedTermEn> means any persons who provide emergency services, including police officers, firefighters and paramedics, and includes members of the Canadian Forces who provide those services.</Text></Subsection></AmendedText><ExplanatoryNote><TitleText><XRefExternal reference-type="act">Criminal Code</XRefExternal></TitleText><Label><Emphasis style="italic">Clause 1</Emphasis>:</Label><ExplanatoryText>New.</ExplanatoryText></ExplanatoryNote></Section></Body></Bill>