<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!--Arbortext, Inc., 1988-2010, v.4002--><Bill bill-origin="commons" bill-type="govt-public" xml:lang="en"><!--Authoring to Exchange Transform created with transform.acl--><Identification><BillNumber>C-14</BillNumber><Parliament><Session>1</Session><Number>45</Number><RegnalYear><Year-s>3-4</Year-s><Monarch>Charles III</Monarch></RegnalYear><Year-s>2025-2026</Year-s></Parliament><LongTitle>An Act to amend the Criminal Code, the Youth Criminal Justice Act and the National Defence Act (bail and sentencing)</LongTitle><ShortTitle status="unofficial">Bail and Sentencing Reform Act</ShortTitle><RunningHead>Bail and Sentencing Reform Act</RunningHead><BillHistory><Stages stage="report-house"><Date><YYYY>2026</YYYY><MM>2</MM><DD>9</DD></Date><StageText>Reprinted as amended by the Standing Committee on Justice and Human Rights as a working copy for the use of the House of Commons at Report Stage and as reported to the House on February 9, 2026</StageText></Stages></BillHistory><BillSponsor>MINISTER OF JUSTICE</BillSponsor><BillRefNumber date-time="2025-10-23">91245</BillRefNumber></Identification><Introduction><Recommendation><TitleText>RECOMMENDATION</TitleText><Provision format-ref="section"><Text>Her Excellency the Governor General recommends to the House of Commons the appropriation of public revenue under the circumstances, in the manner and for the purposes set out in a measure entitled “<Emphasis style="italic">An Act to amend the Criminal Code, the Youth Criminal Justice Act and the National Defence Act (bail and sentencing)</Emphasis>”.</Text></Provision></Recommendation><Summary><TitleText>SUMMARY</TitleText><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>This enactment amends the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Criminal Code</XRefExternal> to, among other things,</Text><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>provide direction to peace officers, justices and judges when they apply the principle of restraint;</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>(a.1)</Label><Text>provide that  a person must not be named as surety if the person was convicted
of an indictable offence within ten years prior to a release order;</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>require a justice, before making a release order or a detention order in respect of an accused, to consider whether the accused is charged with an offence in the commission of which random and unprovoked violence was used or attempted;</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>(c)</Label><Text>require a justice to impose a condition prohibiting the possession of a firearm or other weapon, and to consider imposing other conditions, when making a release order in respect of an accused charged with the offence of extortion or any offence involving a criminal organization;</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>(d)</Label><Text>require a justice to consider imposing certain conditions when making a release order in respect of an accused charged with an offence of motor vehicle theft or with the offence of breaking and entering a dwelling-house;</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>(e)</Label><Text>create a reverse onus provision for any accused charged with the offence of motor vehicle theft involving violence, motor vehicle theft for a criminal organization, extortion involving violence, breaking and entering a dwelling-house, certain offences related to trafficking in persons or human smuggling, certain offences in the commission of which violence was allegedly used and that would constitute the accused's third or subsequent such indictable offence or certain offences in which an accused is alleged to have choked, suffocated or strangled a complainant;</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>(f)</Label><Text>expand the reverse onus provision to any person charged with a serious offence involving violence and the use of a weapon who has been previously convicted, within 10 years, of a serious offence involving violence and the use of a weapon;</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>(g)</Label><Text>add the number or gravity of any outstanding charges against an accused as circumstances that a justice is to consider in assessing whether the detention of the accused is necessary to maintain confidence in the administration of justice;</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>(h)</Label><Text>expand the circumstances in which the release documents that an accused is subject to may be cancelled, provide for circumstances in which they can be cancelled and allow for the review, by the court of appeal, of decisions to cancel such documents;</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>(i)</Label><Text>create a reverse onus provision for any person who has been found guilty of certain offences if the prosecutor applies to vacate that person’s interim release order;</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>(j)</Label><Text>create new aggravating factors to address repeat violent offending, offences against first responders, retail theft and theft, mischief to property offences and assaults against public transit employees;</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>(k)</Label><Text>add new consecutive sentence provisions for repeat violent offences, motor vehicle theft offences and breaking and entering offences, and extortion and arson offences;</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>(l)</Label><Text>require courts to give primary consideration to denunciation and deterrence of repeat motor vehicle theft offences, repeat breaking and entering offences and organized crime offences;</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>(m)</Label><Text>restrict the possibility of imposing conditional sentence orders for sexual assault, and offences of a sexual nature or committed for a sexual purpose that involves a victim under 18 years of age;</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>(n)</Label><Text>restore the availability of driving prohibitions for the offences of manslaughter and criminal negligence causing bodily harm or death; and</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>(o)</Label><Text>improve the administration of justice as it relates to sentencing by increasing the penalty for contempt, enhancing the fine enforcement regime and expanding the availability of remote appearances in the mental disorder regime.</Text></Provision></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent 0-0" list-item="no" language-align="yes"><Text>It also amends the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Department of Justice Act</XRefExternal> to provide that the Minister must prepare an annual report on the state of judicial interim release in Canada.</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>It also amends the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Youth Criminal Justice Act</XRefExternal> to, among other things,</Text><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>clarify the definition of “violent offence” to mean, among other things, an offence in the commission of which a young person causes bodily harm or involving the use or trafficking of a firearm;</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>provide that the time a young person is unlawfully at large does not count towards time served for a youth custody and supervision order;</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>(c)</Label><Text>enable police officers to publish identifying information about a young person in urgent situations where there is an imminent danger to public safety;</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>(d)</Label><Text>clarify the process for the detention and release of young persons who are remanded for an alleged breach of a condition of their youth custody sentence while awaiting a review by the youth justice court;</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>(e)</Label><Text>set out a period of access for records of extrajudicial measures, other than extrajudicial sanctions, and clarify the rules for records of investigations kept by police that did not result in a charge or extrajudicial measures; and</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>(f)</Label><Text>make several technical sentencing amendments.</Text></Provision></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>It also amends the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">National Defence Act</XRefExternal> to, among other things,</Text><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>improve the administration of military justice as it relates to sentencing by increasing the penalty for contempt;</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>require courts martial to give primary consideration to denunciation and deterrence of offences involving criminal organizations; and</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>(c)</Label><Text>create new aggravating circumstances to address repeat violent offending, offences against first responders, stealing for commercial purposes and certain property offences.</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>Finally, the enactment also includes transitional provisions and coordinating amendments.</Text></Provision></Provision></Summary><Enacts><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>His Majesty, by and with the advice and consent of the Senate and House of Commons of Canada, enacts as follows:</Text></Provision></Enacts></Introduction><Body><Heading level="1"><TitleText>Short Title</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Short title</MarginalNote><Label>1</Label><Text>This Act may be cited as the <XRefExternal reference-level="federal" reference-type="act">Bail and Sentencing Reform Act</XRefExternal>.</Text></Section><Heading level="1"><MarginalNote><HistoricalNote>R.S., c. C-46</HistoricalNote></MarginalNote><TitleText><XRefExternal reference-type="act">Criminal Code</XRefExternal></TitleText></Heading><Heading level="2"><TitleText>Amendments to the Act</TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><Label>2</Label><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Paragraph (c) of the definition <DefinitionRef>superior court of criminal jurisdiction</DefinitionRef> in section 2 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Criminal Code</XRefExternal> is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(c)</Label><Text>in the Provinces of Nova Scotia, British Columbia, Prince Edward Island and Newfoundland and Labrador, the Court of Appeal or the Supreme Court,</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Paragraph (e) of the definition <DefinitionRef>superior court of criminal jurisdiction</DefinitionRef> in section 2 of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(e)</Label><Text>in Yukon and the Northwest Territories, the Supreme Court, and</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>3</Label><Text>The definition <DefinitionRef>superior court</DefinitionRef> in subsection 84(1) of the Act is amended by adding “and” at the end of paragraph (c) and by replacing paragraphs (d) and (e) with the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(d)</Label><Text>in Nova Scotia, British Columbia, Prince Edward Island, Newfoundland and Labrador and a territory, the Supreme Court; (<DefinedTermFr>cour supérieure</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>4</Label><Text>Paragraph 145(5)(b) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>is bound to comply with an order under subsection 515(12), 516.1(1) or 522(2.1) and who fails, without lawful excuse, to comply with that order.</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>5</Label><Text>Paragraphs (c) and (d) of the definition <DefinitionRef>court</DefinitionRef> in subsection 164(8) of the Act are replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(d)</Label><Text>in the Provinces of Nova Scotia, British Columbia, Prince Edward Island and Newfoundland and Labrador, in Yukon and in the Northwest Territories, the Supreme Court, and</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>6</Label><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Paragraph 188(4)(c) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(c)</Label><Text>in the Provinces of Nova Scotia, British Columbia, Prince Edward Island and Newfoundland and Labrador, in Yukon and in the Northwest Territories, the Chief Justice of the Supreme Court;</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Paragraph 188(4)(e) of the Act is repealed.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section change="ins" type="amending"><Label>6.1</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Subsection 269.01(1) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><Section><MarginalNote>Aggravating circumstance — assault against a public transit employee</MarginalNote><Label>269.01</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>When a court imposes a sentence for an offence referred to in paragraph 264.1(1)(a) or any of sections 266 to 269, it shall consider as an aggravating circumstance the fact that the victim of the offence was, at the time of the commission of the offence, a public transit employee engaged in the performance of his or her duty.</Text></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The definition <DefinedTermEn>public transit operator</DefinedTermEn> in subsection 269.01(2) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><SectionPiece><Definition><Text><DefinedTermEn>public transit employee</DefinedTermEn> means an individual who works for, or is contracted to work for, an organization that provides passenger transportation services to the public. (<DefinedTermFr>employé des services de transport en commun</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Definition></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>7</Label><Text>Paragraphs (c) and (d) of the definition <DefinedTermEn>court</DefinedTermEn> in subsection 320(8) of the Act are replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(d)</Label><Text>in the Provinces of Nova Scotia, British Columbia, Prince Edward Island and Newfoundland and Labrador, in Yukon and in the Northwest Territories, the Supreme Court, and</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>8</Label><Text>Subsection 320.24(4) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Subsection><MarginalNote>Discretionary order of prohibition — other offences</MarginalNote><Label>(4)</Label><Text>If an offender is found guilty of an offence under section 220, 221, 236 or 320.13, subsection 320.14(2) or (3) or 320.15(2) or (3) or any of sections 320.16 to 320.18, the court that sentences the offender may, in addition to any other punishment that may be imposed for that offence, make an order prohibiting the offender from operating the type of conveyance in question during a period to be determined in accordance with subsection (5).</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>9</Label><Text>The Act is amended by adding the following after section 333.1:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Section><MarginalNote>Sentences to be served consecutively — breaking and entering</MarginalNote><Label>333.11</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>A sentence imposed on a person for an offence under subsection 333.1(3) or (4) shall be served consecutively to any other sentence imposed on the person for an offence under section 348 arising out of the same event or series of events.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Sentences to be served consecutively — other offences</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>A sentence imposed on a person for a second or subsequent offence under subsection 333.1(3) or (4) shall be served consecutively to any other sentence imposed on the person for an offence arising out of the same event or series of events.</Text></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>10</Label><Text>The Act is amended by adding the following after section 334:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Section><MarginalNote>Aggravating circumstance — stolen property</MarginalNote><Label>334.1</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Without limiting the generality of section 718.2, when a court imposes a sentence for an offence referred to in section 322, 343, 348, 351 or 354, it shall consider as an aggravating circumstance the fact that the offence was committed with intent to sell or barter the stolen property or to fraudulently return it to a retail merchant.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Aggravating circumstance — <DefinedTermEn>essential infrastructure</DefinedTermEn></MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Without limiting the generality of section 718.2, when a court imposes a sentence for an offence referred to in section 322, 343 or 430, it shall consider as an aggravating circumstance the fact that the offence interfered with the access to or functioning of an <DefinitionRef>essential infrastructure</DefinitionRef>, as defined in subsection 52.1(2), or caused it to be unsafe or unfit for use.</Text></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>11</Label><Text>The Act is amended by adding the following after section 346:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Section><MarginalNote>Sentences to be served consecutively</MarginalNote><Label>346.1</Label><Text>A sentence imposed on a person for an offence under section 346 shall be served consecutively to any other sentence imposed on the person for an offence under any of sections 433 to 436 arising out of the same event or series of events.</Text></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending" change="ins"><Label>11.1</Label><Text>Paragraph 485.2(7)(c) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(c)</Label><Text>set out a summary of subsection 145(3), section 512.1 and subsections 524(4) and (6.2).</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>12</Label><Text>The heading before section 493 of the French version of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no" xml:lang="fr"><Heading level="2"><TitleText>Définitions et interprétation</TitleText></Heading></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>13</Label><Text>The Act is amended by adding the following after section 493:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Section><MarginalNote>Clarification — indictable offence</MarginalNote><Label>493.01</Label><Text>For greater certainty, a reference to an indictable offence includes an offence that may be punishable on summary conviction if it is also an offence that may be prosecuted by indictment, unless the prosecutor has elected to proceed by way of summary conviction.</Text></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>14</Label><Text>The Act is amended by adding the following after section 493.1:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Section><MarginalNote>Clarification</MarginalNote><Label>493.11</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>For greater certainty, section 493.1 does not require the accused to be released.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Application</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>For the purposes of section 493.1,</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>a peace officer shall not release the accused if the peace officer believes on reasonable grounds that it is necessary in the public interest for the accused to be detained in custody under subsection 498(1.1), including for the safety and security of any victim of or witness to the offence;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>a peace officer shall, if they release the accused, impose the least onerous conditions that are appropriate in the circumstances, namely, those that are necessary to address the risks posed by the accused as they relate to the purposes referred to in subsection 501(3), including the safety and security of any victim of or witness to the offence;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(c)</Label><Text>a justice or judge, as the case may be, shall not give primary consideration to the release of the accused at the earliest reasonable opportunity if the accused is one to whom subsection 515(6), 522(2), 523(2.1) or <Ins>524(4)</Ins>  applies;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(d)</Label><Text>a justice or judge shall, if they release the accused, impose the least onerous conditions that are appropriate in the circumstances, namely, those that are necessary to address the risks posed by the accused as they relate to the grounds referred to in subsection 515(10), including the protection or safety of the public; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(e)</Label><Text>a justice or judge shall not order that the accused be released if the detention of the accused is justified under subsection 515(10), including for the protection or safety of the public.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>15</Label><Text>Section 495.1 of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Section><MarginalNote>Arrest without warrant — application of section 524</MarginalNote><Label>495.1</Label><Text>Despite any other provision in this Act, if a peace officer has reasonable grounds to believe that an accused has contravened or is about to contravene a summons, appearance notice, undertaking or release order that was issued or given to the accused or entered into by the accused, or has committed an offence while being subject to a summons, appearance notice, undertaking or release order, the peace officer may arrest the accused without a warrant for the purpose of taking them before a judge or justice to be dealt with under section 524.</Text></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending" change="ins"><Label>15.1</Label><Text>Subsection 500(2) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><Subsection><MarginalNote>Summary of consequences — failure to appear</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>An appearance notice shall set out a summary of subsections 145(3) and (6), section 512.2 and subsections 524(4) and (6.2) and the possible consequences of a failure to appear at a judicial referral hearing under section 523.1.</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Section><Section change="ins" type="amending"><Label>15.2</Label><Text>Paragraph 501(1)(c) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(c)</Label><Text>a summary of subsections 145(4) and (6), sections 512 and 512.2 and subsections 524(4) and (6.2).</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>16</Label><Text>Subsection 502(2) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Subsection><MarginalNote>Replacement or variation without consent</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The accused or the prosecutor may, in the absence of consent between them,</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>apply to a justice for a release order referred to in section 515 to replace an undertaking given by the accused under paragraph 498(1)(c), 499(b) or 503(1.1)(b) with the order; or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>apply to a justice to vary the undertaking in respect of which the accused has been released under section 498, 499 or 503, in which case the undertaking so varied is deemed to be an undertaking given under section 498, 499 or 503, as the case may be.</Text></Paragraph><ContinuedSectionSubsection><Text>If the prosecutor makes the application, the prosecutor must provide three days’ notice to the accused.</Text></ContinuedSectionSubsection></Subsection></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>17</Label><Text>The portion of subsection 503(1) of the Act before paragraph (a) is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Section><MarginalNote>Taking before justice</MarginalNote><Label>503</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Subject to the other provisions of this section, a peace officer who arrests a person with or without warrant and who has not released the person under any other provision under this Part or under section 705.1 shall, in accordance with the following paragraphs, cause the person to be taken before a justice to be dealt with according to law:</Text></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>18</Label><Text>Subsection 507(1) of the Act is amended by striking out “and” at the end of paragraph (a) and by adding the following after paragraph (a):</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(a.1)</Label><Text>if a hearing is held, hold it <Language xml:lang="la">in camera</Language>; and</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>19</Label><Text>Paragraph 507.1(3)(a) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>has heard and considered, <Language xml:lang="la">ex parte</Language> and <Language xml:lang="la">in camera</Language>, the allegations of the informant and the evidence of witnesses;</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>20</Label><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Subsection 508(1) of the Act is amended by adding the following after paragraph (a):</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(a.1)</Label><Text>if a hearing is held, hold it <Language xml:lang="la">in camera</Language>;</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Paragraph 508(1)(b) of the Act is amended by striking out “or” at the end of subparagraph (i), by striking out “and” at the end of subparagraph (ii), by adding “or” at the end of subparagraph (ii) and by adding the following after subparagraph (ii):</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><SectionPiece><Subparagraph><Label>(iii)</Label><Text>in the case of the undertaking, amend it to correct the time and place set out in the condition requiring the accused to attend court; and</Text></Subparagraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection></Section><Section type="amending" change="ins"><Label>20.1</Label><Text>Subsection 509(4) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><Subsection><MarginalNote>Summary of certain provisions</MarginalNote><Label>(4)</Label><Text>The summons must set out a summary of subsection 145(3), section 512.1 and subsections 524(4) and (6.2).</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>21</Label><Text>Section 511 of the Act is amended by adding the following after subsection (2):</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Subsection><MarginalNote>Warrant — cancellation</MarginalNote><Label>(2.1)</Label><Text>Despite subsection (2), a judge or justice having jurisdiction in the territorial division in which the warrant was issued may cancel the warrant on application by the prosecutor, with or without the appearance of the accused, if the judge or justice is satisfied that it is in the interests of justice to do so.</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>22</Label><Text>Section 512.3 of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Section><MarginalNote>Warrant to appear under section 524</MarginalNote><Label>512.3</Label><Text>If a justice is satisfied that there are reasonable grounds to believe that an accused has contravened or is about to contravene any summons, appearance notice, undertaking or release order that was issued or given to the accused or entered into by the accused or has committed an offence while being subject to any summons, appearance notice, undertaking or release order, the justice may issue a warrant for the purpose of taking the accused before a justice under section 524.</Text></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>23</Label><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Section 515 of the Act is amended by adding the following after subsection (2.03):</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Subsection><MarginalNote>Non-application</MarginalNote><Label>(2.04)</Label><Text>Subsection (2.01) does not apply to an accused to whom subsection (6) applies.</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending" change="ins"><Label>(1.1)</Label><Text>Section 515 of the Act is amended by adding the following after subsection (2.1):</Text><AmendedText><Subsection><MarginalNote>Prohibition — surety convicted of indictable offence</MarginalNote><Label>(2.11)</Label><Text>Despite subsection (2.1), a judge, justice or court shall not name a person as surety if the person was convicted of an indictable offence within ten years before the day on which the release order is made.</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Subsection 515(3) of the Act is amended by striking out “or” at the end of paragraph (a) and by adding the following after that paragraph (a):</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no" xml:lang="en"><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(a.1)</Label><Text>whether the accused is charged with an offence in the commission of which random and unprovoked violence was used or attempted; or</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(3)</Label><Text>Subsection 515(4.1) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Subsection><MarginalNote>Condition prohibiting possession of firearms, etc.</MarginalNote><Label>(4.1)</Label><Text>When the justice makes an order under subsection (2) in respect of an accused who is charged with any of the following offences, the justice shall add to the order a condition prohibiting the accused from possessing a firearm, cross-bow, prohibited weapon, restricted weapon, prohibited device, firearm part, ammunition, prohibited ammunition or explosive substance, or all those things, until the accused is dealt with according to law unless the justice considers that such a condition is not required in the interests of the safety of the accused or the safety and security of a victim of the offence or of any other person:</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>an offence in the commission of which violence against a person was used, threatened or attempted;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>a terrorism offence;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(c)</Label><Text>an offence that is alleged to have been committed for the benefit of, at the direction of or in association with a criminal organization;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(d)</Label><Text>an offence under section 264 (criminal harassment);</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(e)</Label><Text>an offence under section 346 (extortion);</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(f)</Label><Text>an offence under section 423.1 (intimidation of a justice system participant);</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(g)</Label><Text>an offence under subsection 423.2(1) (intimidation — health services);</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(h)</Label><Text>an offence relating to the contravention of any of sections 9 to 14 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Cannabis Act</XRefExternal>;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(i)</Label><Text>an offence relating to the contravention of any of sections 5 to 7 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Controlled Drugs and Substances Act</XRefExternal>;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(j)</Label><Text>an offence that involves, or the subject-matter of which is, a firearm, a cross-bow, a prohibited weapon, a restricted weapon, a prohibited device, a firearm part, ammunition, prohibited ammunition or an explosive substance;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(k)</Label><Text>an offence under subsection 20(1), 20.1(1), 20.2(1), 20.3(1) or 20.4(1) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Foreign Interference and Security of Information Act</XRefExternal>, or an offence under subsection 21(1) or 22(1) or section 23 of that Act that is committed in relation to an offence under subsection 20(1), 20.1(1), 20.2(1), 20.3(1) or 20.4(1) of that Act.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(4)</Label><Text>Subsection 515(4.3) of the Act is amended by adding the following after paragraph (a):</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(a.1)</Label><Text>an offence that is alleged to have been committed for the benefit of, at the direction of or in association with a criminal organization;</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(5)</Label><Text>Paragraph 515(4.3)(b) of the Act is amended by replacing “264” with “264, 346”.</Text></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(6)</Label><Text>Section 515 of the Act is amended by adding the following after subsection (4.3):</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Subsection><MarginalNote>Additional conditions</MarginalNote><Label>(4.4)</Label><Text>Before making an order under subsection (2) in respect of an accused who is charged with an offence described in subsection 333.1(1), (3) or (4) or paragraph 348(1)(d), the justice shall consider whether it is desirable, in the interests of the safety and security of any person, particularly a victim of or witness to the offence or a justice system participant, to include as a condition of the order that the accused</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>abstain from going to any place or entering any geographic area specified in the order, except in accordance with any specified conditions that the justice considers necessary;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>abstain from having in their possession any instrument specified in the order that is suitable for the purpose of breaking into any place or motor vehicle; or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(c)</Label><Text>return to and remain at their place of residence at the times specified in the order.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(7)</Label><Text>The portion of subsection 515(6) of the Act before paragraph (a) is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Subsection><MarginalNote>Order of detention</MarginalNote><Label>(6)</Label><Text>Unless the accused, having been given a reasonable opportunity to do so, shows cause why the accused’s detention in custody is not justified by clearly demonstrating that their proposed release plan addresses the risks posed by the accused as they relate to the grounds referred to in subsection (10), the justice shall order, despite any provision of this section, that the accused be detained in custody until the accused is dealt with according to law, if the accused is charged</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(8)</Label><Text>Subparagraph 515(6)(a)(iv) of the English version of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no" xml:lang="en"><SectionPiece><Subparagraph><Label>(iv)</Label><Text>that is an offence under subsection 16(1) or (2), 17(1), 19(1), 20(1), 20.1(1), 20.3(1), 20.4(1) or 22(1) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Foreign Interference and Security of Information Act</XRefExternal>,</Text></Subparagraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(9)</Label><Text>Paragraph 515(6)(a) of the Act is amended by striking out “or” at the end of subparagraph (vii) and by adding the following after subparagraph (viii):</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><SectionPiece><Subparagraph><Label>(ix)</Label><Text>that is an offence under any of sections 266 to 268 and 271 to 273 in the commission of which the accused is alleged to have choked, suffocated or strangled the complainant,</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph><Label>(x)</Label><Text>that is an offence under section 279.01 or 279.011,</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph><Label>(xi)</Label><Text>that is an offence under subsection 333.1(3) or (4),</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph><Label>(xii)</Label><Text>that is an offence under subsection 346 in the commission of which violence was allegedly used, threatened or attempted against any person,</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph change="ins"><Label>(xii.1)</Label><Text>that is an offence in the commission of which violence was allegedly used and that would constitute the accused’s third or subsequent indictable offence in the commission of which violence was used,</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph><Label>(xiii)</Label><Text>that is an offence under paragraph 348(1)(d), or</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph><Label>(xiv)</Label><Text>that is an offence under section 117 or 118 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Immigration and Refugee Protection Act</XRefExternal>;</Text></Subparagraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(10)</Label><Text>Paragraph 515(6)(b.2) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(b.2)</Label><Text>with an offence in the commission of which violence was allegedly used, threatened or attempted against a person with the use of a weapon, and the accused has been previously convicted, within 10 years of the day on which they were charged for that offence, of another offence in the commission of which violence was also used, threatened or attempted against any person with the use of a weapon, if the maximum term of imprisonment for each of those offences is 10 years or more;</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(11)</Label><Text>Paragraph 515(10)(c) of the Act is amended by striking out “and” at the end of subparagraph (iii), by adding “and” at the end of subparagraph (iv) and by adding the following after subparagraph (iv):</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><SectionPiece><Subparagraph><Label>(v)</Label><Text>the number or gravity of any outstanding charges against the accused that arise out of separate events.</Text></Subparagraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>24</Label><Text>Section 516 of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Section><MarginalNote>Adjournment of proceedings</MarginalNote><Label>516</Label><Text>A justice may, before or at any time during the course of any proceedings under section 515, on application by the prosecutor or the accused, adjourn the proceedings and remand the accused to custody in prison by warrant in Form 19, but no adjournment shall be for more than three clear days except with the consent of the accused.</Text></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Remand in custody — non-communication order</MarginalNote><Label>516.1</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>A justice who remands an accused to custody under subsection 503(3) or 515(11) or section 516 may order that the accused abstain from communicating, directly or indirectly, with any victim, witness or other person identified in the order, except in accordance with any conditions specified in the order that the justice considers necessary.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Duration of order</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>An order made under subsection (1) remains in force,</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>until it is varied or revoked;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>until an order in respect of the accused is made under section 515;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(c)</Label><Text>until the accused is acquitted of the offence, if applicable; or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(d)</Label><Text>until the time the accused is sentenced, if applicable.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>25</Label><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Subsection 520(1) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Section><MarginalNote>Review of order</MarginalNote><Label>520</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>If a judge or justice makes an order under subsection 515(2), (5), (6), (7) or (12) or vacates, varies or makes any order under paragraph 523(2)(b), the accused may, at any time before the trial of the charge, apply to a judge for a review of the order.</Text></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Paragraph 520(7)(e) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(e)</Label><Text>if the accused shows cause, allow the application, vacate or vary the order previously made by the justice and make any other order provided for in section 515 that the judge considers is warranted.</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(3)</Label><Text>Subsection 520(8) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Subsection><MarginalNote>Limitation of further applications</MarginalNote><Label>(8)</Label><Text>If an application under this section or section 521 or 525 has been heard, a further or other application under this section or section 521 shall not be made with respect to that same accused, except with leave of a judge, before the expiry of 30 days from the date of the decision of the judge who heard the previous application.</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Subsection></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>26</Label><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Subsection 521(1) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Section><MarginalNote>Review of order</MarginalNote><Label>521</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>If a judge or justice makes an order under subsection 515(1), (2), (7) or (12) or vacates, varies or makes any order under paragraph 523(2)(b), the prosecutor may, at any time before the trial of the charge, apply to a judge for a review of the order.</Text></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Paragraph 521(8)(e) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(e)</Label><Text>if the prosecutor shows cause, allow the application, vacate or vary the order previously made by the justice and make any other order provided for in section 515 that the judge considers to be warranted.</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(3)</Label><Text>Subsection 521(9) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Subsection><MarginalNote>Limitation of further applications</MarginalNote><Label>(9)</Label><Text>If an application under this section or section 520 or 525 has been heard, a further or other application under this section or section 520 shall not be made with respect to the same accused, except with leave of a judge, before the expiry of 30 days from the date of the decision of the judge who heard the previous application.</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Subsection></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>27</Label><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Subsection 522(2) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Subsection><MarginalNote>Idem</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Where an accused is charged with an offence listed in section 469, a judge of or a judge presiding in a superior court of criminal jurisdiction for the province in which the accused is charged shall order that the accused be detained in custody unless the accused, having been given a reasonable opportunity to do so, shows cause why their detention in custody is not justified within the meaning of subsection 515(10) by clearly demonstrating that their proposed release plan addresses the risks posed by the accused as they relate to the grounds referred to in that subsection.</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Section 522 of the Act is amended by adding the following after subsection (3):</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Subsection><MarginalNote>Non-application</MarginalNote><Label>(3.1)</Label><Text>For the purposes of subsection (3), subsection 515(2.01) does not apply to an accused referred to in subsection (2).</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Subsection></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>28</Label><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Subsection 523(1) of the Act replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Section><MarginalNote>Period for which appearance notice, etc., continues in force</MarginalNote><Label>523</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Subject to subsection (2), if an accused, in respect of an offence with which they are charged, has not been taken into custody or has been released from custody under any provision of this Part, the appearance notice, summons, undertaking or release order issued to, given or entered into by the accused continues in force, subject to its terms, and applies in respect of any new information charging the same offence or an included offence that was received after the appearance notice, summons, undertaking or release order was issued, given or entered into,</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>if the accused is, at their trial, determined to be guilty of an offence listed in section 469, until their trial is completed;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>if the accused is, at their trial, determined to be guilty of an offence other than an offence listed in section 469, until a <DefinitionRef>sentence</DefinitionRef> within the meaning of section 673 is imposed on the accused; or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(c)</Label><Text>in any other case, until their trial is completed.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Paragraph 523(2)(a) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>the court, judge or justice before which or whom an accused who is charged with an offence listed in section 469 is being tried, at any time until the accused’s trial is completed,</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(a.1)</Label><Text>the court, judge or justice before which or whom an accused who is charged with an offence other than an offence listed in section 469 is being tried, at any time until a <DefinitionRef>sentence</DefinitionRef> within the meaning of section 673 is imposed on the accused,</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(3)</Label><Text>Paragraph 523(2)(c) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(c)</Label><Text>with the consent of the prosecutor and the accused or, if the accused or the prosecutor applies to vacate or vary an order that would otherwise apply under subsection (1.1), without such consent,</Text><Subparagraph><Label>(i)</Label><Text>the court, judge or justice before which or whom an accused is to be tried, at any time,</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph><Label>(ii)</Label><Text>if the accused is charged with an offence listed in section 469, a judge of or a judge presiding in a superior court of criminal jurisdiction for the province, at any time until the accused’s trial is completed, or</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph><Label>(iii)</Label><Text>if the accused is charged with an offence other than an offence listed in section 469, the justice by whom an order was made under this Part or any other justice, at any time until a <DefinitionRef>sentence</DefinitionRef> within the meaning of section 673 is imposed on the accused,</Text></Subparagraph><ContinuedParagraph><Text>may, on cause being shown, vacate or vary any order previously made under this Part for the interim release or detention of the accused and make any other order provided for in this Part for the detention or release of the accused that the court, judge or justice considers to be warranted.</Text></ContinuedParagraph></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(4)</Label><Text>Section 523 of the Act is amended by adding the following after subsection (2):</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Subsection><MarginalNote>Order of detention until sentencing — onus</MarginalNote><Label>(2.1)</Label><Text>Despite subsection (2), if the prosecutor brings an application to vacate an order for the interim release of the accused after the accused is, at their trial, determined to be guilty of an offence other than an offence listed in section 469 and before a <DefinitionRef>sentence</DefinitionRef> within the meaning of section 673 is imposed on the accused, the court, judge or justice shall order that the accused be detained in custody unless the accused, having been given a reasonable opportunity to do so, shows cause why their detention in custody is not justified under subsection 515(10) by clearly demonstrating that their proposed release plan addresses the risks posed by the accused as they relate to the grounds referred to in that subsection.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Application — subsection (2)</MarginalNote><Label>(2.2)</Label><Text>For the purposes of subsection (2), if an accused is charged with an offence listed in section 469 but is, at their trial, determined to be guilty of an offence other than an offence listed in section 469, the accused is deemed to have been charged with an offence other than an offence listed in section 469.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Non-application</MarginalNote><Label>(2.3)</Label><Text>For the purposes of subsection (2), subsection 515(2.01) does not apply to an accused referred to in subsection (2.1).</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Subsection></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>29</Label><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Paragraph 524(2)(b) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>the accused has been arrested for having committed an offence while being subject to a summons, appearance notice, undertaking or release order and the prosecutor seeks to have it cancelled under this section.</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Paragraph 524(3)(b) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>there are reasonable grounds to believe that the accused has committed an offence while being subject to the summons, appearance notice, undertaking or release order.</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(3)</Label><Text><Ins>Subsection</Ins> 524(4) of the Act <Ins>is</Ins> replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Subsection change="ins"><MarginalNote>Detention — onus on accused</MarginalNote><Label>(4)</Label><Text>If the judge or justice cancels the summons, appearance notice, undertaking or release order, the judge or justice shall, in the following circumstances, order that the accused be detained in custody unless the accused, having been given a reasonable opportunity to do so, shows cause why their detention in custody is not justified under subsection 515(10) by clearly demonstrating that their proposed release plan addresses the risks posed by the accused as they relate to the grounds referred to in that subsection:</Text><Paragraph change="ins"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>the judge or justice found under paragraph (3)(a) that the accused has contravened or had been about to contravene the summons, appearance notice, undertaking or release order;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph change="ins"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>the judge or justice found under paragraph (3)(b) that there are reasonable grounds to believe that the accused has committed an indictable offence while being subject to the summons, appearance notice, undertaking or release order; or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph change="ins"><Label>(c)</Label><Text>any of the outstanding charges against the accused include charges for an offence referred to in subsection 515(6) or 522(2).</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection type="amending" change="ins"><Label>(4)</Label><Text>Section 524 of the Act is amended by adding the following after subsection (5):</Text><AmendedText><Subsection><MarginalNote>Non-application</MarginalNote><Label>(5.1)</Label><Text>For the purposes of subsection (5), subsection 515(2.01) does not apply to an accused referred to in subsection (4).</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending" change="ins"><Label>(5)</Label><Text>Section 524 of the Act is amended by adding the following after subsection (6):</Text><AmendedText><Subsection><MarginalNote>Release order — onus on prosecutor</MarginalNote><Label>(6.1)</Label><Text>If the judge or justice cancels the summons, appearance notice, undertaking or release order in respect of an accused to whom subsection (4) does not apply, the judge or justice shall, unless the prosecutor shows cause why the detention of the accused is justified, make a release order referred to in subsection 515.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Detention order</MarginalNote><Label>(6.2)</Label><Text>If the judge or justice does not make a release order under subsection (6.1), they shall make a detention order referred to in section 515.</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending" change="ins"><Label>(6)</Label><Text>Subsections 524(9) and (10) of the Act are replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><Subsection><MarginalNote>Review — order by judge</MarginalNote><Label>(9)</Label><Text>An order made under subsection (4), (5), (6.1) or (6.2) respecting an accused referred to in paragraph (1)(a) is not subject to review except as provided in section 680.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Review — order of justice</MarginalNote><Label>(10)</Label><Text>An order made under subsection (4), (5), (6.1) or (6.2) respecting an accused other than the accused referred to in paragraph (1)(a), is subject to review under sections 520 and 521 as if the order were made under section 515.</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Subsection></AmendedText></Subsection></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>30</Label><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Section 525 of the Act is amended by adding the following after subsection (4):</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Subsection><MarginalNote>Clarification</MarginalNote><Label>(4.1)</Label><Text>For greater certainty, if in conducting the hearing referred to in subsection (1) the judge conducts a proceeding under section 515, they shall order the release or detention of the accused on cause being shown in accordance with that section.</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Section 525 of the Act is amended by adding the following after subsection (5):</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Subsection><MarginalNote>Detention order</MarginalNote><Label>(5.1)</Label><Text>If the judge does not make a release order under subsection (5), the judge shall make an order that the accused continue to be detained. The order is deemed to be a detention order made under section 515.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Clarification — further hearing</MarginalNote><Label>(5.2)</Label><Text>For greater certainty, after an order is made under subsection (5.1), no further hearing under this section shall be held unless required by the judge under paragraph (4)(b).</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Subsection></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>31</Label><Text>The portion of subsection 527(5) of the English version of the Act before paragraph (a) is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Subsection><MarginalNote>Detention in other cases</MarginalNote><Label>(5)</Label><Text>If the appearance of a prisoner is required for the purposes of subsection (1), the judge or provincial court judge shall give appropriate directions in the order with respect to the manner in which the prisoner is</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>32</Label><Text>Paragraph (h.1) of the definition <DefinitionRef>judge</DefinitionRef> in section 552 of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(h.1)</Label><Text>in the Province of Newfoundland and Labrador, a judge of the Supreme Court,</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>33</Label><Text>Subparagraph 561(1)(b)(ii) of the French version of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no" xml:lang="fr"><SectionPiece><Subparagraph><Label>(ii)</Label><Text>tout mode de procès avec le consentement écrit du poursuivant.</Text></Subparagraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>34</Label><Text>Subsection 672.5(13) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Subsection><MarginalNote>Remote appearance</MarginalNote><Label>(13)</Label><Text>If the accused so agrees, the court or the chairperson of the Review Board may permit the accused to appear by videoconference for any part of the hearing.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Remote appearance — compelling circumstances</MarginalNote><Label>(13.01)</Label><Text>Despite subsection (13), the court or Review Board may order their appearance by audioconference or videoconference if the court or Review Board determines that compelling circumstances exist to do so.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Audioconference only</MarginalNote><Label>(13.02)</Label><Text>The court or Review Board may allow the accused to appear by audioconference only if it is satisfied that</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>videoconferencing is not readily available; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>the appearance by audioconference would permit the court or Review Board to conduct the proceedings effectively despite not seeing the accused.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Factors</MarginalNote><Label>(13.03)</Label><Text>When deciding whether to make an order under subsection (13.01), the court or Review Board must take into account the following factors:</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>the accused’s right to a review of their disposition;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>the location and personal circumstances of the accused, including any potential adverse effects of an audioconference or videoconference on the accused’s mental condition;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(c)</Label><Text>the suitability of the available technology and the location from where the parties will participate in the hearing;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(d)</Label><Text>the accused’s opportunity to communicate privately with legal counsel, if they are represented, or to have access to legal advice during the hearing;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(e)</Label><Text>the subject matter and the anticipated complexity of the hearing; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(f)</Label><Text>any other factor that the court or Review Board considers relevant.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Written reasons</MarginalNote><Label>(13.04)</Label><Text>If the court or Review Board decides to make the order, it must provide reasons in writing.</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending" change="ins"><Label>34.1</Label><Text>The portion of subsection 680(1) of the Act before paragraph (a) is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><Section><MarginalNote>Review by court of appeal</MarginalNote><Label>680</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>A decision made by a judge under section 522, a decision made under subsections 524(3) to (5), (6.1) or (6.2) with respect to an accused referred to in paragraph 524(1)(a) or a decision made by a judge of the court of appeal under section 320.25 or 679 may, on the direction of the chief justice or acting chief justice of the court of appeal, be reviewed by that court and that court may, if it does not confirm the decision,</Text></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>35</Label><Text>Section 705 of the Act is amended by adding the following after subsection (3):</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Subsection><MarginalNote>Witness — warrant endorsement</MarginalNote><Label>(4)</Label><Text>A court, judge, justice or provincial court judge that issues a warrant under this section may, by making an endorsement on the warrant in Form 29.1, authorize the release of the person referred to in the warrant, on an undertaking with conditions.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Conditions — undertaking</MarginalNote><Label>(5)</Label><Text>The court, judge, justice or provincial court judge that endorses the warrant must include any conditions of the undertaking that the court, judge, justice or provincial court judge considers necessary to ensure that the person will appear and give evidence in the proceeding.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Apply to vary undertaking</MarginalNote><Label>(6)</Label><Text>The person referred to in subsections (1) or (2) may apply to the court, judge, justice or provincial court judge to vary the undertaking in respect of which they have been released.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Deeming</MarginalNote><Label>(7)</Label><Text>An undertaking that is varied under subsection (6) is deemed to be an undertaking given under section 705.1.</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>36</Label><Text>The Act is amended by adding the following after section 705:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Section><MarginalNote>Release — undertaking</MarginalNote><Label>705.1</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>If a person has been arrested by a peace officer under a warrant issued under subsection 705(1) or (2) and the warrant has been endorsed under subsection 705(4), a peace officer may release the person if they give an undertaking in Form 10.1.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Information required</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The undertaking must set out</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>the name, date of birth and contact information of the person; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>information about the proceeding in which the person was served a subpoena or bound by a recognizance, to attend to give evidence.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Mandatory conditions</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>The undertaking must include a condition that the person attend court at the time and place stated in the undertaking and to attend afterwards as required by the court.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Other conditions</MarginalNote><Label>(4)</Label><Text>The undertaking must include any condition that is imposed by the court, judge, justice or provincial court judge under subsection 705(5) and set out in the endorsement made in Form 29.1.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Signature — witness</MarginalNote><Label>(5)</Label><Text>The person referred to in subsection 705(1) or (2) shall be requested to sign in duplicate their undertaking and, whether or not they comply with that request, one of the duplicates shall be given to them.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Lack of signature — refusal or failure</MarginalNote><Label>(6)</Label><Text>If the person fails or refuses to sign, the lack of the person’s signature does not invalidate the undertaking.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Conditions in effect</MarginalNote><Label>(7)</Label><Text>The conditions with respect to the undertaking remain in effect until they are cancelled or changed or until the person appears and remains in attendance at the proceeding as required by the mandatory condition.</Text></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>37</Label><Text>Subsection 708(2) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Subsection><MarginalNote>Punishment</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>A court, judge, justice or provincial court judge may deal summarily with a person who is guilty of contempt of court under this section and that person is liable to a fine not exceeding $5,000 or to imprisonment for a term not exceeding two years less a day, or to both, and may be ordered to pay the costs that are incident to the service of any process under this Part and to that person’s detention, if any.</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>38</Label><Text>The Act is amended by adding the following after section 718.04:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Section><MarginalNote>Objectives — offence of motor vehicle theft when violence used</MarginalNote><Label>718.05</Label><Text>If a court imposes a sentence for a second or subsequent offence under subsection 333.1(3), it shall give primary consideration to the objectives of denunciation and deterrence of the conduct that forms the basis of the offence.</Text></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Objectives — offence of breaking and entering</MarginalNote><Label>718.06</Label><Text>If a court imposes a sentence for a second or subsequent offence under section 348, it shall give primary consideration to the objectives of denunciation and deterrence of the conduct that forms the basis of the offence.</Text></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Objectives — offence for the benefit of a criminal organization</MarginalNote><Label>718.07</Label><Text>If a court imposes a sentence for an offence that is committed for the benefit of, at the direction of or in association with a criminal organization, it shall give primary consideration to the objectives of denunciation and deterrence of the conduct that forms the basis of the offence.</Text></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>39</Label><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Subparagraph 718.2(a)(iii.2) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><SectionPiece><Subparagraph><Label>(iii.2)</Label><Text>evidence that the offence was committed against a person who, in the performance of their duties and functions, was providing health services, including personal care services, or was providing services as a first responder,</Text></Subparagraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Paragraph 718.2(a) of the Act is amended by striking out “and” at the end of subparagraph (vi), by adding “and” at the end of subparagraph (vii) and by adding the following after subparagraph (vii):</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><SectionPiece><Subparagraph><Label>(viii)</Label><Text>evidence that the offence was committed with the use of violence, threats or attempts of violence against another person and that the offender has been convicted, within the previous five years, of one or more such offences,</Text></Subparagraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>40</Label><Text>Paragraph 718.3(4)(b) of the Act is amended by striking out “or” at the end of subparagraph (ii), by adding “or” at the end of subparagraph (iii) and by adding the following after subparagraph (iii):</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><SectionPiece><Subparagraph><Label>(iv)</Label><Text>one of the offences was committed with the use of violence, threats or attempts of violence against another person and the accused has been convicted, within the previous five years, of one or more such offences.</Text></Subparagraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>41</Label><Text>Section 734.5 of the Act is amended by striking out “or” at the end of paragraph (a), by adding “or” at the end of paragraph (b) and by adding the following after paragraph (b):</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(c)</Label><Text>where the proceeds of the fine belong to His Majesty in right of Canada by virtue of subsection 734.4(2), the person responsible, by or under an Act of the legislature of a province, for issuing, renewing or suspending a licence, permit or other similar instrument in relation to the offender may refuse to issue or renew or may suspend the licence, permit or other instrument until the fine is paid in full, proof of which lies on the offender.</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>42</Label><Text>The Act is amended by adding the following after section 734.5:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Section><MarginalNote>Compensation agreements</MarginalNote><Label>734.51</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The Attorney General of Canada may enter into an agreement with the government of a province or with any provincial, municipal or local authority</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>respecting the sharing with that province or authority of the amounts in respect of fines that are collected in respect of the prosecution of offences commenced under this Act or any other Act of Parliament, for the purpose of providing for compensation by Canada to that province or authority, in whole or in part, for the administration and enforcement of this Act or any other Act of Parliament; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>despite subsections 17(1) and (4) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Financial Administration Act</XRefExternal>, authorizing the government of the province or the authority to withhold amounts, in accordance with the terms and conditions of the agreement, from the fines referred to in paragraph (a) to be remitted to the Receiver General and deposited in the Consolidated Revenue Fund.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Appropriation by Parliament</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>All or a portion of the amount of fines referred to in paragraph (1)(a) that are to be shared under an agreement are deemed to be appropriated by Parliament for that purpose.</Text></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>43</Label><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Paragraph 742.1(c) of the Act is amended by striking out “or” at the end of subparagraph (ii) and by adding the following after subparagraph (ii):</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><SectionPiece><Subparagraph><Label>(ii.1)</Label><Text>section 272 (sexual assault with a weapon, threats to a third party or causing bodily harm),</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph><Label>(ii.2)</Label><Text>section 273 (aggravated sexual assault), or</Text></Subparagraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Section 742.1 of the Act is amended by striking out “and” at the end of subparagraph (c)(iii) and by adding the following after paragraph (c):</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(c.1)</Label><Text>the offence is not an offence, prosecuted by way of indictment, under any of the following provisions:</Text><Subparagraph><Label>(i)</Label><Text>section 153.1 (sexual exploitation of person with disability), or</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph><Label>(ii)</Label><Text>section 271 (sexual assault);</Text></Subparagraph></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(c.2)</Label><Text>the offence is not an offence, prosecuted by way of indictment, of a sexual nature, or committed for a sexual purpose, that involves a victim under 18 years of age; and</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>44</Label><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Paragraph 745.6(3)(c) of the Act is repealed.</Text></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Paragraph 745.6(3)(e) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(e)</Label><Text>in relation to the Provinces of Nova Scotia, British Columbia, Prince Edward Island and Newfoundland and Labrador, the Chief Justice of the Supreme Court; and</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>45</Label><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Paragraph 812(1)(c) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(c)</Label><Text>in the Provinces of Nova Scotia, British Columbia, Prince Edward Island and Newfoundland and Labrador, the Supreme Court;</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Paragraph 812(1)(g) of the Act is repealed.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>46</Label><Text>The reference to “The Trial Division of the Supreme Court” in column II of the schedule to Part XXV of the Act, opposite “Newfoundland and Labrador” in column I, is replaced by a reference to “The Supreme Court”.</Text></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>47</Label><Text>The paragraph of Form 6 of Part XXVIII of the Act that begins with “If you do not comply” and ends with “(Subsection 524(4) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Criminal Code</XRefExternal>).” is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Provision format-ref="indent-1-0" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text>If you do not comply with this summons or are charged with committing an offence after it has been issued to you, this summons may be cancelled and, as a result, you may be detained in custody (<Ins>subsections</Ins> 524(4) <Ins>and (6.2)</Ins> of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Criminal Code</XRefExternal>).</Text></Provision></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>48</Label><Text>The paragraph of Form 6.2 of Part XXVIII of the Act that begins with “If you are on interim release” and ends with “(section 524 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Criminal Code</XRefExternal>).” is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text>If you are on interim release and do not comply with this summons or are charged with committing an offence after it has been issued to you, any summons, appearance notice, undertaking or release order to which you are subject may be cancelled and, as a result, you may be detained in custody (section 524 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Criminal Code</XRefExternal>).</Text></Provision></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>49</Label><Text><Ins>Paragraphs (d) and</Ins> (e) of Form 8 of Part XXVIII of the Act <Ins>are</Ins> replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Provision change="ins" format-ref="indent-1-1" list-item="no"><Label>□</Label><Text>(d) the accused has contravened or was about to contravene a (summons <Emphasis style="italic">or</Emphasis> appearance notice <Emphasis style="italic">or</Emphasis> undertaking <Emphasis style="italic">or</Emphasis> release order) and it was cancelled, and the detention of the accused in custody is justified [515(10), 523.1(3), 524(3), (4) and (6.2)];</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>□</Label><Text>(e) there are reasonable grounds to believe that the accused has committed an offence after having become subject to the (summons <Emphasis style="italic">or</Emphasis> appearance notice <Emphasis style="italic">or</Emphasis> undertaking <Emphasis style="italic">or</Emphasis> release order) and the detention of the accused in custody is justified [515(10), 524(3), (4) and <Ins>(6.2)</Ins>];</Text></Provision></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>50</Label><Text>The paragraph of section 6 of Form 9 of Part XXVIII of the Act that begins with “If you do not comply” and ends with “(subsection 524(4) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Criminal Code</XRefExternal>).” is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text>If you do not comply with this appearance notice or are charged with committing an offence after you have been released, this appearance notice may be cancelled and, as a result, you may be detained in custody (<Ins>subsections</Ins> 524(4) <Ins>and (6.2)</Ins> of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Criminal Code</XRefExternal>).</Text></Provision></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>51</Label><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Section 7 of Form 10 of Part XXVIII of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Provision format-ref="indent-1-0" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>7</Label><Text><Emphasis style="underline">Variation and Replacement</Emphasis></Text><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text>The conditions of this undertaking may be varied with the written consent of the prosecutor and yourself. In addition, you or the prosecutor may apply to a justice of the peace to replace this undertaking with a release order under section 515 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Criminal Code</XRefExternal>. Finally, you or the prosecutor may apply to a justice of the peace to vary this undertaking.</Text></Provision></Provision></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The paragraph of section 9 of Form 10 of Part XXVIII of the Act that begins with “If you do not comply” and ends with “(subsection 524(4) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Criminal Code</XRefExternal>).” is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text>If you do not comply with this undertaking or are charged with committing an offence after you have been released, this undertaking may be cancelled and, as a result, you may be detained in custody (<Ins>subsections</Ins> 524(4) <Ins>and (6.2)</Ins> of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Criminal Code</XRefExternal>).</Text></Provision></AmendedText></Subsection></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>52</Label><Text>Part XXVIII of the Act is amended by adding the following after Form 10:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Schedule bilingual="no" spanlanguages="no"><ScheduleFormHeading><Label>FORM 10.1</Label><OriginatingRef>(Subsection 705(4))</OriginatingRef><TitleText>Undertaking — Witness</TitleText></ScheduleFormHeading><FormGroup><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>Canada,</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text>Province of <Leader leader="dot" length="4pc" />,</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text>(<Emphasis style="italic">territorial division</Emphasis>).</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>1</Label><Text><Emphasis style="underline">Identification</Emphasis></Text><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text>Surname: <Leader leader="dot" length="4pc" /> Given name(s): <Leader leader="dot" length="4pc" /></Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text>Date of Birth: <Leader leader="dot" length="4pc" /></Text></Provision></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>2</Label><Text><Emphasis style="underline">Contact Information</Emphasis></Text><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text><Leader leader="dot" length="4pc" /></Text></Provision></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>3</Label><Text><Emphasis style="underline">Proceeding in which you were served a subpoena or bound by a recognizance, to attend to give evidence</Emphasis></Text><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text>Whereas A.B. has been charged that (<Emphasis style="italic">state offence as in the information</Emphasis>), and it has been made to appear that you are likely to give material evidence and/or bring with you anything in your possession or under your control that relates to the said charge.</Text></Provision></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>4</Label><Text><Emphasis style="underline">Mandatory Condition</Emphasis></Text><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text>You must attend court as indicated below, and afterwards as required by the court:</Text><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text>Date: <Leader leader="dot" length="4pc" /></Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text>Time: <Leader leader="dot" length="4pc" /></Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text>Court number: <Leader leader="dot" length="4pc" /></Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text>Court address: <Leader leader="dot" length="4pc" /></Text></Provision></Provision></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>5</Label><Text><Emphasis style="underline">Conditions determined by the court, judge, justice or provincial court judge</Emphasis></Text><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text>You must also comply with the following conditions (<Emphasis style="italic">reproduce the conditions determined by the court, justice or provincial court judge as set out in Form 29.1</Emphasis>):</Text></Provision></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>6</Label><Text><Emphasis style="underline">Conditions in effect</Emphasis></Text><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text>The mandatory condition and the conditions determined by the court, judge, justice or provincial court judge on this undertaking remain in effect until they are cancelled or changed or until you appear and remain in attendance at the proceeding as required by the mandatory condition (section 763 of the <XRefExternal reference-level="federal" reference-type="act">Criminal Code</XRefExternal>).</Text></Provision></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>7</Label><Text><Emphasis style="underline">Variation</Emphasis></Text><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text>The conditions of this undertaking may be varied by application to the court, judge, justice or provincial court judge.</Text></Provision></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>8</Label><Text><Emphasis style="underline">Consequence for non-compliance</Emphasis></Text><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text>You are warned that, unless you have a lawful excuse, you commit an offence under section 145 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Criminal Code</XRefExternal> if you fail to follow any of the conditions set out in this undertaking, including</Text><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>if you fail to attend court as required; or</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>if you fail to comply with the conditions determined by the court, judge, justice or provincial court judge.</Text></Provision></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text>If you commit an offence under section 145 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Criminal Code</XRefExternal>, a warrant for your arrest may be issued (section 512 or 512.2 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Criminal Code</XRefExternal>) and you may be liable to a fine or to imprisonment, or to both.</Text></Provision></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>9</Label><Text><Emphasis style="underline">Signatures</Emphasis></Text><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text>WITNESS:</Text><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text>I understand the contents of this undertaking and agree to comply with the mandatory condition and the conditions determined by the court, judge, justice or provincial court judge.</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text>I understand that I do not have to accept the conditions and that, if I do not accept the conditions, I will be brought before a court, judge, provincial court judge or justice under sections 705 and 706 of the <XRefExternal reference-level="federal" reference-type="act">Criminal Code</XRefExternal>.</Text></Provision></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text>Signed on (<Emphasis style="italic">date</Emphasis>)<Leader leader="dot" length="6pc" />, at (<Emphasis style="italic">place</Emphasis>)<Leader leader="dot" length="5pc" />.</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text><Leader leader="dot" length="10pc" /></Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text>(<Emphasis style="italic">Signature of witness</Emphasis>)</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text>PEACE OFFICER:</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text>Signed on (<Emphasis style="italic">date</Emphasis>)<Leader leader="dot" length="6pc" />, at (<Emphasis style="italic">place</Emphasis>) <Leader leader="dot" length="5pc" /></Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text><Leader leader="dot" length="10pc" /></Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text>(<Emphasis style="italic">Signature of peace officer</Emphasis>)<Leader leader="dot" length="10pc" /></Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text><Leader leader="dot" length="10pc" /></Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text>(<Emphasis style="italic">Name of the peace officer</Emphasis>)</Text></Provision></Provision></FormGroup></Schedule></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>53</Label><Text>The paragraph of item 8 of Form 11 of Part XXVIII of the Act that begins with “If you do not comply” and ends with “(subsection 524(4) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Criminal Code</XRefExternal>).” is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text>If you do not comply with this release order or are charged with committing an offence after you have been released, this release order may be cancelled and, as a result, you may be detained in custody (<Ins>subsections</Ins> 524(4) <Ins>and (6.2)</Ins> of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Criminal Code</XRefExternal>).</Text></Provision></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>54</Label><Text>Form 12 of Part XXVIII of the Act is amended by adding the following after section 7:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Provision format-ref="indent-1-0" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>7.1</Label><Text><Emphasis style="underline">Financial Information</Emphasis></Text><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text>Annual Income ...................</Text></Provision><Provision language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text>Assests (nature and value) ...................</Text></Provision><Provision language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text>Other ...................</Text></Provision></Provision></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>55</Label><Text>Part XXVIII of the Act is amended by adding the following after Form 29:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Schedule bilingual="no" spanlanguages="no"><ScheduleFormHeading><Label>FORM 29.1</Label><OriginatingRef>(Subsection 705(4))</OriginatingRef><TitleText>Endorsement of Witness — Warrant</TitleText></ScheduleFormHeading><FormGroup><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>Canada,</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text>Province of <Leader leader="dot" length="4pc" />,</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text>(<Emphasis style="italic">territorial division</Emphasis>).</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text>Whereas this warrant is issued under subsection 705(1) or (2) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Criminal Code</XRefExternal> in respect of a witness who has been served with a subpoena to give evidence in a proceeding or who has been bound by a recognizance to attend and give evidence in a proceeding, I authorize the release of that person under subsections 705(4) and (5) of that Act.</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text>This endorsement is subject to the following conditions: (<Emphasis style="italic">specify conditions</Emphasis>).</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text>Dated (<Emphasis style="italic">date</Emphasis>)<Leader leader="dot" length="6pc" />, at (<Emphasis style="italic">place</Emphasis>) <Leader leader="dot" length="5pc" /></Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="centered" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text>(<Emphasis style="italic">Signature of judge, justice or provincial court judge</Emphasis>)<Leader leader="dot" length="10pc" /></Text></Provision></FormGroup></Schedule></AmendedText></Section><Heading level="2"><TitleText>Transitional Provisions</TitleText></Heading><Section type="transitional"><MarginalNote>Words and expressions</MarginalNote><Label>56</Label><Text>Unless the context requires otherwise, words and expressions used in sections <XRefInternal>57</XRefInternal> and <XRefInternal>58</XRefInternal> have the same meaning as in the <XRefExternal reference-level="federal" reference-type="act">Criminal Code</XRefExternal>.</Text></Section><Section type="transitional"><MarginalNote>Outstanding fines</MarginalNote><Label>57</Label><Text>The provisions of the <XRefExternal reference-level="federal" reference-type="act">Criminal Code</XRefExternal>, as enacted by sections <XRefInternal>41</XRefInternal> and <XRefInternal>42</XRefInternal>, apply to the proceeds of a fine that is unpaid on the day on which those sections come into force.</Text></Section><Section type="transitional"><MarginalNote>Clarification — certain offences</MarginalNote><Label>58</Label><Subsection type="transitional"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>For greater certainty, the provisions of the <XRefExternal reference-level="federal" reference-type="act">Criminal Code</XRefExternal>, as enacted by sections <XRefInternal>8</XRefInternal>, 9, 11, <XRefInternal>37</XRefInternal>, <XRefInternal><Ins>40</Ins></XRefInternal> and <XRefInternal>43</XRefInternal>, apply only with respect to an offence that is committed on or after the day on which those sections come into force.</Text></Subsection><Subsection type="transitional"><MarginalNote>Clarification — Parts XVI and XXVIII</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>For greater certainty, the amendments to Parts XVI and XXVIII of the <XRefExternal reference-level="federal" reference-type="act">Criminal Code</XRefExternal> made by this Act apply with respect to any matter or proceeding under that Part XVI that is ongoing on the day on which section <XRefInternal>12</XRefInternal> comes into force.</Text></Subsection><Subsection type="transitional"><MarginalNote>Clarification — Application</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>For greater certainty, the provisions of the <XRefExternal reference-level="federal" reference-type="act">Criminal Code</XRefExternal>, as enacted by sections <XRefInternal>10</XRefInternal>, <XRefInternal>34</XRefInternal> to <XRefInternal>36</XRefInternal>, <XRefInternal>38</XRefInternal> and <XRefInternal><Ins>39</Ins></XRefInternal>, also apply with respect to any matter or proceeding that is ongoing on the day on which those sections come into force.</Text></Subsection></Section><Heading level="1" change="ins"><MarginalNote><HistoricalNote>R.S., c. J-2</HistoricalNote></MarginalNote><TitleText>Department of Justice Act</TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending" change="ins"><Label>58.1</Label><Text>The <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Department of Justice Act</XRefExternal> is amended by adding the following after section 4.2:</Text><AmendedText><Section><MarginalNote>Annual report — judicial interim release</MarginalNote><Label>4.3</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Every year, the Minister shall prepare a report on the state of judicial interim release in Canada and cause it to be tabled in each House of Parliament on any of the first 15 sitting days of that House after January 1.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Contents</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The report must include the following:</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>data on judicial interim release outcomes, including in respect of compliance with release conditions, recidivism by accused at large on release orders and incidents requiring public attention;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>an analysis of the effectiveness of release conditions; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(c)</Label><Text>data on the accessibility of judicial interim release and disparities between different groups.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Section><Heading level="1"><MarginalNote><HistoricalNote>2002, c. 1</HistoricalNote></MarginalNote><TitleText><XRefExternal reference-type="act">Youth Criminal Justice Act</XRefExternal></TitleText></Heading><Heading level="2"><TitleText>Amendments to the Act</TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><Label>59</Label><Subsection><Label>(<Ins>1</Ins>)</Label><Text>Paragraph (a) of the definition <DefinitionRef>violent offence</DefinitionRef> in subsection 2(1) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Youth Criminal Justice Act</XRefExternal> is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>an offence in the commission of which a young person causes bodily harm;</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending" change="ins"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The definition <DefinedTermEn>violent offence</DefinedTermEn> in subsection 2(1) of the Act is amended by striking out “or” at the end of paragraph (b), by adding “or” at the end of paragraph (c) and by adding the following after paragraph (c):</Text><AmendedText><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(d)</Label><Text>an offence committed by a young person involving the use or trafficking of a firearm. (<DefinedTermFr>infraction avec violence</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>60</Label><Text>Section 9 of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Section><MarginalNote>Evidence of measures is inadmissible</MarginalNote><Label>9</Label><Text>Evidence that a young person has received a warning, caution or referral mentioned in section 6, 7 or 8 or that a police officer has taken no further action in respect of an offence, and evidence of the offence, is inadmissible for the purpose of proving prior offending behaviour in any proceedings before a court in respect of the young person.</Text></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>61</Label><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Subsection 17(1) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Section><MarginalNote>Youth justice court may make rules</MarginalNote><Label>17</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The youth justice court for a province may, for the purpose of regulating proceedings within its jurisdiction, establish rules of court not inconsistent with this Act or any other Act of Parliament or with any regulations made under section 155.</Text></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Subsection 17(3) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Subsection><MarginalNote>Publication of rules</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>Rules of court that are made under the authority of this section must be published or otherwise made available to the public.</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Subsection></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>62</Label><Text>The portion of subsection 29(1) of the Act before paragraph (a) is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Section><MarginalNote>Release order with conditions</MarginalNote><Label>29</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>A youth justice court judge or a justice may impose a condition set out in subsections 515(4) to (4.4) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Criminal Code</XRefExternal> in respect of a release order only if they are satisfied that</Text></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>63</Label><Text>Paragraph 42(13)(b) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>is found guilty of more than one offence for each of which a sentence referred to in any of those paragraphs is imposed.</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>64</Label><Text>The Act is amended by adding the following after section 49:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Section><MarginalNote>Reasons — credit for time in detention</MarginalNote><Label>49.1</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The youth justice court shall give reasons for any credit granted for the time spent in detention by the young person as a result of the offence and shall cause those reasons to be stated in the record of the case.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Record of proceedings</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The youth justice court shall cause to be stated in the record of the case and on the warrant of committal the offence, the amount of time spent in detention, the term of the custody and supervision order that would have been imposed before any credit was granted, the amount of time credited, if any, and the sentence imposed.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Validity not affected</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>Failure to comply with subsection (1) or (2) does not affect the validity of the sentence imposed by the court.</Text></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>65</Label><Text>Subsection 56(5) of the Act is amended by striking out “or” at the end of paragraph (a), by adding “or” at the end of paragraph (b) and by adding the following after paragraph (b):</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(c)</Label><Text>if a young person is subject to a deferred custody and supervision order, at the end of the period set out in that order.</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>66</Label><Text>Subsection 57(1) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Section><MarginalNote>Transfer of youth sentence</MarginalNote><Label>57</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>When a youth sentence has been imposed under any of paragraphs 42(2)(c) to (i), (k), (l) or (s) in respect of a young person and the young person or a parent with whom the young person resides is or becomes a resident of a territorial division outside the jurisdiction of the youth justice court that imposed the youth sentence, whether in the same or in another province, a youth justice court judge in the territorial division in which the youth sentence was imposed may, on the application of the Attorney General or on the application of the young person or the young person’s parent, with the consent of the Attorney General, transfer to a youth justice court in another territorial division the youth sentence and any portion of the record of the case that is appropriate. All subsequent proceedings relating to the case shall then be carried out and enforced by that court.</Text></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>67</Label><Text>Subsection 58(1) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Section><MarginalNote>Interprovincial arrangements</MarginalNote><Label>58</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>When a youth sentence has been imposed under any of paragraphs 42(2)(c) and (k) to (s) in respect of a young person, the youth sentence in one province may be dealt with in any other province in accordance with any agreement that may have been made between those provinces.</Text></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>68</Label><Text>The Act is amended by adding the following after section 108:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Section><MarginalNote>Applicable provisions — detention and release</MarginalNote><Label>108.1</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>If the case of a young person is referred to the youth justice court under section 108 for a review under section 103 or 109 and the young person is remanded to custody under section 102 or 106, sections 28 to 31 apply, with any necessary modifications, to an application for their release from custody until the completion of the review by the youth justice court.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Reference</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>For the purposes of subsection (1), any reference in section 29 to a young person charged with a serious offence is to be read as a reference to a young person who has breached or is about to breach a condition referred to in section 102 or 106, as the case may be.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Continuation of sentence</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>Despite the suspension of their conditional supervision and subject to section 107, the young person continues to serve their sentence until the review is completed by the youth justice court.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Conditions continue to apply</MarginalNote><Label>(4)</Label><Text>During the suspension of their conditional supervision, any conditions imposed to which the young person is subject continues to apply, in addition to any conditions that may be imposed on them, in respect of a release order, until the completion of the review by the youth justice court.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Notice to Attorney General</MarginalNote><Label>(5)</Label><Text>The provincial director shall, without delay, give notice to the Attorney General of an application in respect of the release from custody of a young person referred to in subsection (1).</Text></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>69</Label><Text>The Act is amended by adding the following after section 109:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Section><MarginalNote>Time not counted</MarginalNote><Label>109.1</Label><Text>The time spent by a young person who is unlawfully at large while subject to a youth sentence does not count as part of any term of a custody and supervision order.</Text></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>70</Label><Text>Section 110 of the Act is amended by adding the following after subsection (4):</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Subsection><MarginalNote>Publication — urgent situation</MarginalNote><Label>(4.1)</Label><Text>A police officer may publish information that identifies a young person without a court order referred to in subsection (4) if the police officer has reasonable grounds to believe that</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>the young person has committed or is likely to commit an indictable offence; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>the urgency of the situation is such that the immediate publication is necessary for <Ins>all of</Ins> the following reasons:</Text><Subparagraph><Label>(i)</Label><Text>the young person is an imminent danger to the public and the publication could aid in the prevention of serious bodily harm or death,</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph><Label>(ii)</Label><Text>the publication is necessary to assist in apprehending the young person, and</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph><Label>(iii)</Label><Text>the court order could not, with reasonable diligence, be obtained.</Text></Subparagraph></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Publication — more than 24 hours</MarginalNote><Label>(4.2)</Label><Text>The court order must be obtained if the publication is required for more than 24 hours after it has been made.</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>71</Label><Text>Section 115 of the Act is amended by adding the following after subsection (1.1):</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Subsection><MarginalNote>For greater certainty</MarginalNote><Label>(1.2)</Label><Text>For greater certainty, the police force may keep a record of an investigation in respect of an offence alleged to have been committed by a young person even if the investigation did not result in a charge or extrajudicial measures were not used to deal with that young person.</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>72</Label><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Subsection 119(2) of the Act is amended by adding the following after paragraph (a):</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(a.1)</Label><Text>if an extrajudicial measure, other than an extrajudicial sanction, is used to deal with the young person, the period ending two years from the day on which the decision to use the extrajudicial measure is made;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(a.2)</Label><Text>if the young person is the subject of an investigation referred to in subsection 115(1.2), two years from the day on which the young person ceases to be the subject of the investigation;</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Section 119 of the Act is amended by adding the following after subsection (4):</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Subsection><MarginalNote>Records — certain investigations</MarginalNote><Label>(4.1)</Label><Text>Access to a record kept in respect of an investigation referred to in subsection 115(1.2) is to be given only to the following persons for the following purposes:</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>a peace officer or the Attorney General, in order to make a decision under this Act in respect of the young person to whom the investigation relates; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>a peace officer, for the purpose of investigating an offence.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Evidence of investigation — inadmissible</MarginalNote><Label>(4.2)</Label><Text>Evidence that forms a part of a police investigation referred to in subsection 115(1.2) in respect of a young person is inadmissible for the purpose of proving prior offending behaviour in any proceedings before a court in respect of the young person.</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Subsection></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>73</Label><Text>Section 124 of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Section><MarginalNote>Access to record by young person</MarginalNote><Label>124</Label><Text>Despite any other provision of this Act, a young person to whom a record relates and their counsel may have access to the record at any time.</Text></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>74</Label><Text>Section 156 of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Section><MarginalNote>Agreements with provinces</MarginalNote><Label>156</Label><Text>The Minister of Justice may enter into an agreement with the government of any province providing for payments by Canada to the province in respect of costs incurred by the province or a municipality in the province for care of and services provided to young persons dealt with under this Act.</Text></Section></AmendedText></Section><Heading level="2"><TitleText>Transitional Provisions</TitleText></Heading><Section type="transitional"><MarginalNote>Definition of <DefinedTermEn>Act</DefinedTermEn></MarginalNote><Label>75</Label><Subsection type="transitional"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>In this section and sections <XRefInternal>76</XRefInternal> to <XRefInternal>78</XRefInternal>, <DefinedTermEn>Act</DefinedTermEn> means the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Youth Criminal Justice Act</XRefExternal>.</Text></Subsection><Subsection type="transitional"><MarginalNote>Words and expressions</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Unless the context requires otherwise, words and expressions used in sections <XRefInternal>76</XRefInternal> to <XRefInternal>78</XRefInternal> have the same meaning as in the Act.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section type="transitional"><MarginalNote>Pending requests — records relating to extrajudicial measures</MarginalNote><Label>76</Label><Subsection type="transitional"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Paragraph 119(2)(a.1) of the Act, as enacted by subsection <XRefInternal>72</XRefInternal>(1), applies in respect of requests for access to records relating to extrajudicial measures, other than extrajudicial sanctions, that have been made before the day on which that subsection <XRefInternal>72</XRefInternal>(1) comes into force but for which access was not yet given before that day.</Text></Subsection><Subsection type="transitional"><MarginalNote>For greater certainty — records relating to extrajudicial measures</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>For greater certainty, paragraph 119(2)(a.1) of the Act, as enacted by subsection <XRefInternal>72</XRefInternal>(1), applies in respect of records relating to extrajudicial measures, other than extrajudicial sanctions, that were created before the day on which that subsection <XRefInternal>72</XRefInternal>(1) comes into force and in respect of which a request for access is made on or after the day on which subsection <XRefInternal>72</XRefInternal>(1) comes into force.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section type="transitional"><MarginalNote>Pending request — records relating to investigations</MarginalNote><Label>77</Label><Subsection type="transitional"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Paragraph 119(2)(a.2) and subsections 119(4.1) and (4.2) of the Act, as enacted by subsections <XRefInternal>72</XRefInternal>(1) and (2), apply in respect of requests for access to records relating to an investigation referred to in subsection 115(1.2) of the Act, as enacted by section <XRefInternal>71</XRefInternal>, that have been made before the day on which those subsections <XRefInternal>72</XRefInternal>(1) and (2) come into force but for which access was not yet given before that day.</Text></Subsection><Subsection type="transitional"><MarginalNote>For greater certainty — records relating to investigations</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>For greater certainty, paragraph 119(2)(a.2) and subsections 119(4.1) and (4.2) of the Act, as enacted by subsections <XRefInternal>72</XRefInternal>(1) and (2), apply in respect of records relating to an investigation referred to in subsection 115(1.2) of the Act, as enacted by section <XRefInternal>71</XRefInternal>, that were created before the day on which those subsections <XRefInternal>72</XRefInternal>(1) and (2) come into force and in respect of which a request for access is made on or after the day on which subsections <XRefInternal>72</XRefInternal>(1) and (2) come into force.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section type="transitional"><MarginalNote>Clarification — certain offences</MarginalNote><Label>78</Label><Subsection type="transitional"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>For greater certainty, the provisions of the Act, as enacted by sections <XRefInternal>59</XRefInternal>, <XRefInternal>63</XRefInternal> to <XRefInternal>67</XRefInternal> and <XRefInternal>69</XRefInternal>, apply only with respect to an offence that is committed on or after the day on which those sections come into force.</Text></Subsection><Subsection type="transitional"><MarginalNote>Clarification — application</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>For greater certainty, the provisions of the Act, as enacted by sections <XRefInternal>60</XRefInternal> to <XRefInternal>62</XRefInternal>, <XRefInternal>68</XRefInternal>, <XRefInternal>70</XRefInternal>, <XRefInternal>71</XRefInternal>, <XRefInternal>73</XRefInternal> and <XRefInternal>74</XRefInternal>, also apply with respect to any matter or proceeding that is ongoing on the day on which those sections come into force.</Text></Subsection></Section><Heading level="1"><MarginalNote><HistoricalNote>R.S., c. N-5</HistoricalNote></MarginalNote><TitleText><XRefExternal reference-type="act">National Defence Act</XRefExternal></TitleText></Heading><Heading level="2"><TitleText>Amendments to the Act</TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><Label>79</Label><Text>Paragraph 203.3(a) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">National Defence Act</XRefExternal> is amended by adding the following after subparagraph (iv):</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><SectionPiece><Subparagraph><Label>(iv.1)</Label><Text>the offence was committed against a person who, in the performance of their duties and functions, was providing services as a first responder,</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph><Label>(iv.2)</Label><Text>the offence was committed with the use of violence, threats or attempts of violence against another person and the offender has been convicted, within the previous five years, of one or more such offences,</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph><Label>(iv.3)</Label><Text>in the case of an offence under section 114 or 115, it was committed with intent to sell or barter the stolen property or to fraudulently return it to a retail merchant,</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph><Label>(iv.4)</Label><Text>in the case of an offence under any of sections 113 to 116, the offence interfered with the access to or functioning of an <DefinitionRef>essential infrastructure</DefinitionRef>, as defined in subsection 52.1(2) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Criminal Code</XRefExternal>, or caused it to be unsafe or unfit for use,</Text></Subparagraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>80</Label><Text>The Act is amended by adding the following after section 203.4:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Section><MarginalNote>Objectives — offence for the benefit of a criminal organization</MarginalNote><Label>203.41</Label><Text>When a court martial imposes a sentence for an offence that is committed for the benefit of, at the direction of, or in association with, a criminal organization, the court martial shall give primary consideration to the objectives of denunciation and deterrence of the conduct that forms the basis of the offence.</Text></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>81</Label><Text>The portion of section 302 of the Act before paragraph (a) is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Section><MarginalNote>Offences of contempt</MarginalNote><Label>302</Label><Text>Every person is guilty of an offence and liable, on summary conviction, to a fine of not more than $5,000 or to imprisonment for less than two years, or to both, if the person</Text></Section></AmendedText></Section><Heading level="2" change="ins"><TitleText>Review of Act</TitleText></Heading><Section change="ins" type="amending"><MarginalNote>Review by committee</MarginalNote><Label>81.1</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>As soon as possible after the fifth anniversary of the day on which this Act receives royal assent, the provisions enacted by this Act are to be referred to the committee of the Senate, of the House of Commons or of both Houses of Parliament that may be designated or established for the purpose of reviewing the provisions.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Report</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The committee to which the provisions are referred is to review them and submit a report to the House or Houses of Parliament of which it is a committee, including a statement setting out any changes to the provisions that the committee recommends.</Text></Subsection></Section><Heading level="2" change="ins"><TitleText>Transitional Provisions</TitleText></Heading><Section type="transitional"><MarginalNote>Clarification — application
</MarginalNote><Label>82</Label><Subsection><Label>(<Ins>1</Ins>)</Label><Text>For greater certainty, the provisions of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">National Defence Act</XRefExternal>, as enacted by sections 79 <Ins>and 80, also</Ins> apply with respect to <Ins>any matter or proceeding</Ins> that is <Ins>ongoing</Ins> on the day on which those sections come into force.</Text></Subsection><Subsection change="ins"><MarginalNote>Clarification — certain offences</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>For greater certainty, section 302 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">National Defence Act</XRefExternal>, as enacted by section 81, applies only with respect to an offence that is committed on or after the day on which that section 81 comes into force.</Text></Subsection></Section><Heading level="1"><TitleText>Coordinating Amendments</TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote>Bill C-9</MarginalNote><Label>83</Label><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Subsections (2) to (6) apply if Bill C-9, introduced in the 1st session of the 45th Parliament and entitled the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Combatting Hate Act</XRefExternal> (in this section referred to as the “other Act”), receives royal assent.</Text></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>If subsection 9(1) of the other Act comes into force before subsection <XRefInternal>23</XRefInternal>(3) of this Act, then that subsection <XRefInternal>23</XRefInternal>(3) is amended by replacing the paragraphs 515(4.1)(h) to (k) that it enacts with the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(h)</Label><Text>an offence under subsection 423.3(1) (intimidation — building used for religious worship, etc.);</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(i)</Label><Text>an offence relating to the contravention of any of sections 9 to 14 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Cannabis Act</XRefExternal>;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(j)</Label><Text>an offence relating to the contravention of any of sections 5 to 7 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Controlled Drugs and Substances Act</XRefExternal>;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(k)</Label><Text>an offence that involves, or the subject-matter of which is, a firearm, a cross-bow, a prohibited weapon, a restricted weapon, a prohibited device, a firearm part, ammunition, prohibited ammunition or an explosive substance;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(l)</Label><Text>an offence under subsection 20(1), 20.1(1), 20.2(1), 20.3(1) or 20.4(1) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Foreign Interference and Security of Information Act</XRefExternal>, or an offence under subsection 21(1) or 22(1) or section 23 of that Act that is committed in relation to an offence under subsection 20(1), 20.1(1), 20.2(1), 20.3(1) or 20.4(1) of that Act.</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(3)</Label><Text>If subsection <XRefInternal>23</XRefInternal>(3) of this Act comes into force before subsection 9(1) of the other Act, then that subsection 9(1) is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Section type="amending"><Label>9</Label><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Subsection 515(4.1) of the Act is amended by adding the following after paragraph (g):</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(g.1)</Label><Text>an offence under subsection 423.3(1) (intimidation — building used for religious worship, etc.);</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(4)</Label><Text>If subsection 9(1) of the other Act and subsection <XRefInternal>23</XRefInternal>(3) of this Act come into force on the same day, then that subsection 9(1) is deemed to have come into force before that subsection <XRefInternal>23</XRefInternal>(3) and subsection (2) applies as a consequence.</Text></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(5)</Label><Text>If subsection <XRefInternal>23</XRefInternal>(5) of this Act comes into force before subsection 9(2) of the other Act, then that subsection 9(2) is amended by replacing the paragraph 515(4.3)(b) that it enacts with the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>an offence described in section 264, 346 or 423.1 or subsection 423.2(1) or 423.3(1);</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(6)</Label><Text>If subsection 9(2) of the other Act and subsection <XRefInternal>23</XRefInternal>(5) of this Act come into force on the same day, then that subsection 9(2) is deemed to have come into force before that subsection <XRefInternal>23</XRefInternal>(5).</Text></Subsection></Section><Heading level="1"><TitleText>Coming into Force</TitleText></Heading><Section type="CIF"><MarginalNote>30th day after royal assent</MarginalNote><Label>84</Label><Text>Sections <XRefInternal>2</XRefInternal> to <XRefInternal>55</XRefInternal>, <XRefInternal>59</XRefInternal> to <XRefInternal>74</XRefInternal> and <XRefInternal>79</XRefInternal> to <XRefInternal>81</XRefInternal> come into force on the 30th day after the day on which this Act receives royal assent.</Text></Section></Body></Bill>