<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><Bill bill-origin="commons" bill-type="private-public" xml:lang="en" date-time="2022-03-11 13:25:48"><Identification><BillNumber>C-206</BillNumber><Parliament><Session>1</Session><Number>45</Number><RegnalYear><Year-s>3</Year-s><Monarch>Charles III</Monarch></RegnalYear><Year-s>2025</Year-s></Parliament><LongTitle>An Act to establish a national strategy on brain injuries</LongTitle><ShortTitle status="unofficial" /><RunningHead>National Strategy on Brain Injuries Act</RunningHead><BillHistory><Stages stage="first-reading-house"><Date><YYYY>2025</YYYY><MM>6</MM><DD>10</DD></Date></Stages></BillHistory><BillSponsor><Emphasis style="smallcaps">Mr. Johns</Emphasis></BillSponsor><BillRefNumber date-time="2022-03-11">451012</BillRefNumber></Identification><Introduction><Summary><TitleText>SUMMARY</TitleText><Provision><Text>This enactment provides for the development of a national strategy to support and improve brain injury awareness, prevention and treatment as well as the rehabilitation and recovery of persons living with a brain injury.</Text></Provision></Summary><Enacts><Provision><Text>His Majesty, by and with the advice and consent <Keep>of the</Keep> Senate and House of Commons of Canada, <Keep>enacts</Keep> as follows:</Text></Provision></Enacts></Introduction><Body><Heading level="1"><TitleText>Short Title</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Short title</MarginalNote><Label>1</Label><Text>This Act may be cited as the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">National Strategy on Brain Injuries Act</XRefExternal>.</Text></Section><Heading level="1"><TitleText>National Strategy</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Development</MarginalNote><Label>2</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The Minister of Health must, in consultation with representatives of the provincial governments responsible for health, Indigenous groups and relevant stakeholders, develop a national strategy to support and improve brain injury awareness, prevention and treatment as well as the rehabilitation and recovery of persons living with a brain injury.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Content</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The strategy must include measures designed to</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>promote the implementation of preventive measures to reduce the risk of brain injuries;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>assist in identifying the training, education and guidance needs of health care and other professionals related to brain injury prevention and treatment and the rehabilitation and recovery of persons living with a brain injury;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(c)</Label><Text>promote research and improve data collection on the incidence and treatment of brain injuries and on the rehabilitation and recovery of persons living with a brain injury;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(d)</Label><Text>promote information and knowledge sharing with respect to brain injury prevention, diagnosis and treatment and the rehabilitation and recovery of persons living with a brain injury;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(e)</Label><Text>create national guidelines on the prevention, diagnosis and management of brain injuries in all communities, including recommended standards of care that reflect best methodological, medical and psychosocial practices;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(f)</Label><Text>promote awareness and education with particular emphasis on improving public understanding and protecting the rights of persons living with a brain injury;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(g)</Label><Text>foster collaboration with and provide financial support to national, provincial and local brain injury associations and brain injury service providers to develop and provide enhanced and integrated mental health resources for persons living with a brain injury and for their families;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(h)</Label><Text>encourage consultation with mental health professionals, particularly in educational institutions, sports organizations and workplaces, to provide persons who are suffering from the effects of a brain injury, including mental health and addiction problems, with a support system within the community;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(i)</Label><Text>identify challenges resulting from brain injury, such as mental health problems, addiction, housing and homelessness issues and criminality, including intimate partner violence, and work to develop solutions in collaboration with stakeholders;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(j)</Label><Text>develop, publish and maintain online resources providing current facts, research and best practices related to brain injuries; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(k)</Label><Text>establish a task force to include policy makers, stakeholders, community agencies, brain injury associations and Indigenous groups, as well as persons who have experienced a brain injury and their families, to make recommendations in relation to the national strategy.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection></Section><Heading level="1"><TitleText>Reports to Parliament</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Tabling of strategy</MarginalNote><Label>3</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Within 18 months after the day on which this Act comes into force, the Minister of Health must prepare a report setting out the strategy and cause the report to be tabled before each House of Parliament on any of the first 15 days on which that House is sitting after the report is completed.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Publication</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The Minister must publish the report on the website of the Department of Health within 10 days after the day on which the report is tabled in both Houses of Parliament.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Report</MarginalNote><Label>4</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Within five years after the day on which the report referred to in section 3 has been tabled in both Houses of Parliament, the Minister of Health must, in consultation with the parties referred to in subsection 2(1), evaluate the effectiveness of the strategy and the situation with respect to brain injury awareness, prevention and treatment, and to the rehabilitation and recovery of persons living with a brain injury, and prepare a report setting out conclusions and recommendations regarding the strategy.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Tabling of report</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The Minister must cause the report to be tabled before each House of Parliament on any of the first 15 days on which that House is sitting after it is completed.</Text></Subsection></Section></Body></Bill>