<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><Bill bill-origin="commons" bill-type="private-public" xml:lang="en" date-time="2022-11-22 11:14:29"><Identification><BillNumber>C-208</BillNumber><Parliament><Session>1</Session><Number>45</Number><RegnalYear><Year-s>3</Year-s><Monarch>Charles III</Monarch></RegnalYear><Year-s>2025</Year-s></Parliament><LongTitle>An Act to recognize a national livestock brand as a symbol of Canada and of western and frontier heritage </LongTitle><ShortTitle status="unofficial" /><RunningHead>National Livestock Brand of Canada Act</RunningHead><BillHistory><Stages stage="first-reading-house"><Date><YYYY>2025</YYYY><MM>6</MM><DD>11</DD></Date></Stages></BillHistory><BillSponsor><Emphasis style="smallcaps">Mr. Bonk</Emphasis></BillSponsor><BillRefNumber date-time="2022-11-22">451040</BillRefNumber></Identification><Introduction><Summary><TitleText>SUMMARY</TitleText><Provision><Text>This enactment recognizes and declares a livestock brand as the national livestock brand of Canada.</Text></Provision></Summary><Preamble><Provision><MarginalNote>Preamble</MarginalNote><Text>Whereas livestock brands have been a proud part of Canada’s western and frontier heritage since before Confederation;</Text></Provision><Provision><Text>Whereas these brands not only serve to identify livestock, but are also heraldic symbols for livestock owners;</Text></Provision><Provision><Text>Whereas the rich history of livestock brands in western Canada is one that is shared with Indigenous peoples;</Text></Provision><Provision><Text>Whereas the recognition of western and frontier heritage, pioneer culture, farming, ranching and agriculture, as well as other aspects of our nation’s history, can promote national unity;</Text></Provision><Provision><Text>And whereas Parliament recognizes the importance of including an element of western and frontier culture in the official national symbols of Canada;</Text></Provision></Preamble><Enacts><Provision><Text>Now, therefore, His Majesty, by and with the advice and consent of the Senate and House of Commons of Canada, enacts as follows:</Text></Provision></Enacts></Introduction><Body><Heading level="1"><TitleText>Short Title</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Short title</MarginalNote><Label>1</Label><Text>This Act may be cited as the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">National Livestock Brand of Canada Act</XRefExternal>.</Text></Section><Heading level="1"><TitleText>National Livestock Brand</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>National livestock brand</MarginalNote><Label>2</Label><Text>The livestock brand illustrated in the schedule is hereby recognized and declared to be the national livestock brand of Canada.</Text></Section></Body><Schedule bilingual="yes"><ScheduleFormHeading><Label>SCHEDULE / ANNEXE</Label><OriginatingRef>(Section 2 / article 2)</OriginatingRef><TitleText>National Livestock Brand — Marque de bétail nationale</TitleText></ScheduleFormHeading><ImageGroup spanlanguages="yes"><AlternateText /><Image source="PMB Brand.tif" /></ImageGroup></Schedule></Bill>