<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><Bill bill-origin="commons" bill-type="private-public" xml:lang="en" date-time="2025-08-11 11:10:17"><Identification><BillNumber>C-222</BillNumber><Parliament><Session>1</Session><Number>45</Number><RegnalYear><Year-s>3-4</Year-s><Monarch>Charles III</Monarch></RegnalYear><Year-s>2025</Year-s></Parliament><LongTitle>An Act to amend the Employment Insurance Act and the Canada Labour Code (death of a child)</LongTitle><ShortTitle status="unofficial" /><RunningHead>Relieving Grieving Parents of an Administrative Burden Act (Evan's Law)</RunningHead><BillHistory><Stages stage="first-reading-house"><Date><YYYY>2025</YYYY><MM>9</MM><DD>18</DD></Date></Stages></BillHistory><BillSponsor><Emphasis style="smallcaps">Mr. Beech</Emphasis></BillSponsor><BillRefNumber date-time="2025-08-11">451105</BillRefNumber></Identification><Introduction><Summary><TitleText>SUMMARY</TitleText><Provision><Text>This enactment amends the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Employment Insurance Act</XRefExternal> to provide that a person to whom employment insurance benefits are payable to care for a newborn child or a child placed with them for the purpose of adoption remains eligible to receive those benefits even if the child dies during the benefit period. It also amends the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Canada Labour Code</XRefExternal> to provide that an employee who is entitled to maternity leave or to parental leave to care for a newborn child or a child who is in their care for the purpose of adoption remains entitled to the maternity leave or the parental leave even if the child dies during the period for which leave has been granted.</Text></Provision></Summary><Enacts><Provision><Text>His Majesty, by and with the advice and consent <Keep>of the</Keep> Senate and House of Commons of Canada, <Keep>enacts</Keep> as follows:</Text></Provision></Enacts></Introduction><Body><Heading level="1"><TitleText>Short Title</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Short title</MarginalNote><Label>1</Label><Text>This Act may be cited as the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Relieving Grieving Parents of an Administrative Burden Act (Evan's Law)</XRefExternal>.</Text></Section><Heading level="1"><MarginalNote><HistoricalNote>1996, c. 23</HistoricalNote></MarginalNote><TitleText>Employment Insurance Act</TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><Label>2</Label><Text>Section 23 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Employment Insurance Act</XRefExternal> is amended by adding the following after subsection (2):</Text><AmendedText change="ins"><Subsection><MarginalNote>Benefits still payable — death of child</MarginalNote><Label>(2.1)</Label><Text>For the purposes of subsection (1), paragraphs 12(3)(b) and (4)(b) and subsection 12(4.01), if the child or children referred to in that subsection (1) die during the period referred to in subsection (2), the claimant is deemed to care for the child or children until that period expires.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>No report or new claim required</MarginalNote><Label>(2.2)</Label><Text>Despite any other provision of this Act, the claimant referred to in subsection (2.1) is not required to make a new claim for benefits or file a report to prove their eligibility to receive or continue to receive benefits.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Exception</MarginalNote><Label>(2.3)</Label><Text>Subsection (2.1) does not apply if the child or children die as the result of the commission of an offence and the claimant is convicted of the offence.</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>3</Label><Text>Section 152.05 of the Act is amended by adding the following after subsection (2):</Text><AmendedText change="ins"><Subsection><MarginalNote>Benefits still payable — death of child</MarginalNote><Label>(2.1)</Label><Text>For the purposes of subsection (1), paragraphs 152.14(1)(b) and (2)(b) and subsection 152.14(4), if the child or children referred to in that subsection (1) die during the period referred to in subsection (2), the self-employed person is deemed to care for the child or children until that period expires.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>No report or new claim required</MarginalNote><Label>(2.2)</Label><Text>Despite any other provision of this Act, the self-employed person referred to in subsection (2.1) is not required to make a new claim for benefits or file a report to prove their eligibility to receive or continue to receive benefits.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Exception</MarginalNote><Label>(2.3)</Label><Text>Subsection (2.1) does not apply if the child or children die as the result of the commission of an offence and the self-employed person is convicted of the offence.</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Section><Heading level="1"><MarginalNote><HistoricalNote>R.S., c. L-2</HistoricalNote></MarginalNote><TitleText>Canada Labour Code</TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><Label>4</Label><Text>Section 206 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Canada Labour Code</XRefExternal> is amended by adding the following after subsection (3):</Text><AmendedText change="ins"><Subsection><MarginalNote>Death of child</MarginalNote><Label>(4)</Label><Text>If a newborn child of an employee who is on a leave of absence from employment under this section dies during the period following the actual date of confinement that is provided for under subsection (1), the employee remains entitled to the period of leave she would have taken under this section had that child not died.</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>5</Label><Text>Section 206.1 of the Act is amended by adding the following after subsection (2):</Text><AmendedText change="ins"><Subsection><MarginalNote>Death of child</MarginalNote><Label>(2.01)</Label><Text>For the purposes of subsection (1), if the child dies during the period referred to in subsection (2), the employee is deemed to care for that child until that period expires.</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Section></Body></Bill>