<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><Bill bill-origin="commons" bill-type="private-public" xml:lang="en" date-time="2016-02-01 10:03:05"><Identification><BillNumber>C-234</BillNumber><Parliament><Session>1</Session><Number>45</Number><RegnalYear><Year-s>3-4</Year-s><Monarch>Charles III</Monarch></RegnalYear><Year-s>2025-2026</Year-s></Parliament><LongTitle>An Act respecting the establishment and award of a Living Donor Recognition Medal</LongTitle><ShortTitle status="unofficial" /><RunningHead>Living Donor Recognition Medal Act</RunningHead><BillHistory><Stages stage="report-house"><Date><YYYY>2026</YYYY><MM>3</MM><DD>25</DD></Date><StageText>Reprinted as amended by the Standing Committee on Health as a working copy for the use of the House of Commons at Report Stage and as reported to the House on March 25, 2026</StageText></Stages></BillHistory><BillSponsor><Emphasis style="smallcaps">Mr. Aboultaif</Emphasis></BillSponsor><BillRefNumber date-time="2016-02-01">451051</BillRefNumber></Identification><Introduction><Summary><TitleText>SUMMARY</TitleText><Provision first-line-indent="0" subsequent-line-indent="0"><Text>This enactment establishes a medal to be awarded to admissible persons who have donated one of their organs during their lifetime without profiting from their donation.</Text></Provision></Summary><Preamble><Provision><MarginalNote>Preamble</MarginalNote><Text>Whereas thousands of Canadians are currently awaiting life-saving organ transplants, and the generosity of living donors makes these organ transplants possible through the gift of life;</Text></Provision><Provision><Text>Whereas living organ donors demonstrate extraordinary compassion, courage and commitment to the well-being of others, often at personal risk and with no expectation of reward;</Text></Provision><Provision><Text>Whereas these acts of altruism not only save lives but also reduce the burden on the health care system and inspire communities across Canada by embodying the highest values of citizenship and humanity;</Text></Provision><Provision><Text>And whereas Parliament wishes to institute a Living Donor Recognition Medal to recognize and honour the altruistic and life-saving act of living organ donation;</Text></Provision></Preamble><Enacts><Provision language-align="yes"><Text>Now, therefore, His Majesty, by and with the advice and consent of the Senate and House of Commons of Canada, enacts as follows:</Text></Provision></Enacts></Introduction><Body><Heading level="1"><TitleText>Short Title</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Short title</MarginalNote><Label>1</Label><Text>This Act may be cited as the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Living Donor Recognition Medal Act</XRefExternal>.</Text></Section><Heading level="1"><TitleText>Interpretation</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Definitions

</MarginalNote><Label>2</Label><Text>The following definitions apply in this Act.</Text><Definition><Text><DefinedTermEn>Medal</DefinedTermEn> means the Living Donor Recognition Medal established under section 4.‍ (<DefinedTermFr>médaille</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Definition><Definition><Text><DefinedTermEn>Minister</DefinedTermEn> means the member of the King’s Privy Council for Canada designated under section 3. (<DefinedTermFr>ministre</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Definition><Definition><Text><DefinedTermEn>organ</DefinedTermEn> <Ins>means</Ins> any form of human tissue, <Ins>including blood and bone marrow</Ins>. (<DefinedTermFr>organe</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Definition></Section><Heading level="1"><TitleText>Designation</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Minister</MarginalNote><Label>3</Label><Text>The Governor in Council may, by order, designate a member of the King’s Privy Council for Canada as the Minister for the purpose of this Act.</Text></Section><Heading level="1"><TitleText>Medal</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Establishment</MarginalNote><Label>4</Label><Text>A medal to be called the Living Donor Recognition Medal is established.</Text></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Design of Medal</MarginalNote><Label>5</Label><Text>The Governor in Council may determine the design of the Medal and its associated ribbon.</Text></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Award of Medal</MarginalNote><Label>6</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The Governor <Ins>General</Ins> may award the Medal to <Ins>a person</Ins> who has donated one <Ins>of their</Ins> organs <Ins>without profiting from the donation and is eligible for the Medal under the regulations</Ins>.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Single award</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The Medal is not to be awarded more than once to the same person.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><Label>(3)</Label><Text>[<Emphasis style="italic">Deleted</Emphasis>]</Text></Subsection></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Awards ceremony</MarginalNote><Label>7</Label><Text>In order to recognize and promote living organ donation, the Medal is to be presented to the recipient, whenever possible, in a public ceremony <Ins>and</Ins> by a representative of the Crown, <Ins>a territorial commissioner</Ins>, a Senator, a member of <Ins>the House of Commons</Ins> or <Ins>a representative of an entity prescribed by regulation or of an entity of a prescribed class of entities. A public servant designated by the Office of the Governor General’s Secretary determines whether the ceremony is public and the choice of presenter</Ins>.</Text></Section><Section change="ins"><MarginalNote>Post-nominal letters</MarginalNote><Label>7.1</Label><Text>A recipient of the Medal is entitled to use the post-nominal letters “L.D.M.”.</Text></Section><Heading level="1"><TitleText>Regulations</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Regulations</MarginalNote><Label>8</Label><Text>The Governor in Council may make regulations</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>respecting the <Ins>eligibility criteria for</Ins> the Medal;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>prescribing <Ins>entities</Ins> or classes of <Ins>entities that are responsible for assessing</Ins> eligibility for the Medal <Ins>or assisting with that assessment</Ins>; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph change="ins"><Label>(c)</Label><Text>prescribing entities or classes of entities for the purposes of section 7.</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(d)</Label><Text>[<Emphasis style="italic">Deleted</Emphasis>]</Text></Paragraph></Section><Heading level="1"><TitleText>Prerogative</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Prerogative not affected</MarginalNote><Label>9</Label><Text>Nothing in this Act limits the right of the Governor General to exercise all powers and authorities of His Majesty in respect of the Medal.</Text></Section><Heading level="1"><TitleText>Report to Parliament</TitleText></Heading><Section><Label>10</Label><Text>[<Emphasis style="italic">Deleted</Emphasis>]</Text></Section><Heading level="1"><TitleText>Implementation</TitleText></Heading><Section><Label>11</Label><Text>[<Emphasis style="italic">Deleted</Emphasis>]</Text></Section></Body></Bill>