<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><Bill bill-origin="commons" bill-type="private-public" xml:lang="en" date-time="2025-06-27 11:11:57"><Identification><BillNumber>C-230</BillNumber><Parliament><Session>1</Session><Number>45</Number><RegnalYear><Year-s>3-4</Year-s><Monarch>Charles III</Monarch></RegnalYear><Year-s>2025-2026</Year-s></Parliament><LongTitle>An Act to amend the Financial Administration Act and to make consequential amendments to other Acts (debt forgiveness registry)</LongTitle><ShortTitle status="unofficial" /><RunningHead>An Act to amend the Financial Administration Act and to make consequential amendments to other Acts (debt forgiveness registry)</RunningHead><BillHistory><Stages stage="report-house"><Date><YYYY>2026</YYYY><MM>4</MM><DD>13</DD></Date><StageText>Reprinted as amended by the Standing Committee on Public Accounts as a working copy for the use of the House of Commons at Report Stage and as reported to the House on April 13, 2026</StageText></Stages></BillHistory><BillSponsor><Emphasis style="smallcaps">Mr. Chambers</Emphasis></BillSponsor><BillRefNumber date-time="2025-06-27">451037</BillRefNumber></Identification><Introduction><Summary><TitleText>SUMMARY</TitleText><Provision><Text>This enactment amends the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Financial Administration Act</XRefExternal> to require that the President of the Treasury Board establish and maintain a public registry of large debts and obligations owed by certain entities to His Majesty, as well as claims by His Majesty against such entities, that have been remitted, forgiven, written off or waived. It also makes consequential amendments to other Acts.</Text></Provision></Summary><Enacts><Provision><Text>His Majesty, by and with the advice and consent <Keep>of the</Keep> Senate and House of Commons of Canada, <Keep>enacts</Keep> as follows:</Text></Provision></Enacts></Introduction><Body><Heading level="1"><MarginalNote><HistoricalNote>R.S., c. F-11</HistoricalNote></MarginalNote><TitleText>Financial Administration Act</TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><Label>1</Label><Text>The <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Financial Administration Act</XRefExternal> is amended by adding the following after section 25:</Text><AmendedText><Section><MarginalNote>Public registry</MarginalNote><Label>25.1</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The President of the Treasury Board must establish and maintain a public registry in the form of an online, searchable database containing information <Ins>relating to</Ins> any debt or obligation owed by a corporation, trust company or partnership to His Majesty — and <Ins>to</Ins> any claim by His Majesty against a corporation, trust company or partnership — <Ins>that was</Ins>, in whole or in part, <Ins>remitted</Ins>, forgiven, written off or waived, under this or any other Act of Parliament, <Ins>in an amount of $2,000,000</Ins> or more.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Contents of registry</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The registry must include the following information in relation to each debt, obligation or claim:</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>the name, as well as any business name, of the corporation, trust company or partnership;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>the amount that was <Ins>remitted</Ins>, forgiven, written off or waived;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph change="ins"><Label>(c)</Label><Text>an indication of whether the debt, obligation or claim was remitted, forgiven, written off or waived;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(d)</Label><Text><Ins>the fiscal year in</Ins> which the debt, obligation or claim was <Ins>remitted, forgiven, written off or waived</Ins>;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph change="ins"><Label>(e)</Label><Text>the Act of Parliament or agreement, arrangement, contract or other instrument or act under which the debt, obligation or claim arose;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph change="ins"><Label>(f)</Label><Text>the Act of Parliament under which the debt, obligation or claim was remitted, forgiven, written off or waived; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Ins>g</Ins>)</Label><Text>any other information that the President of the Treasury Board <Ins>considers appropriate</Ins>.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection change="ins"><MarginalNote>Exception</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>Despite subsection (2), the President of the Treasury Board may exclude from the registry any information that, in their opinion, would be inappropriate to make publicly accessible for reasons related to the protection of confidential, personal or sensitive information.</Text></Subsection><Subsection change="ins"><MarginalNote>Reasons for exclusion</MarginalNote><Label>(3.1)</Label><Text>If any information is excluded from the registry under subsection (3), the President of the Treasury Board must identify in the registry whether the information was excluded for reasons relating to the protection of confidential information, personal information or sensitive information.</Text></Subsection><Subsection change="ins"><MarginalNote>Establishment of registry</MarginalNote><Label>(4)</Label><Text>The registry must be established within 18 months after the day on which this section comes into force and, on the day that it is established, must include information relating to each debt, obligation or claim referred to in subsection (1) that was remitted, forgiven, written off or waived — after the day on which this section comes into force — during the fiscal year to which the Public Accounts most recently tabled in the House of Commons relate.</Text></Subsection><Subsection change="ins"><MarginalNote>Maintenance of registry</MarginalNote><Label>(5)</Label><Text>Within 90 days after the day on which the Public Accounts are tabled in the House of Commons, the President of the Treasury Board must update the registry to include information relating to each debt, obligation or claim referred to in subsection (1) that was remitted, forgiven, written off or waived during the fiscal year to which the tabled Public Accounts relate.</Text></Subsection><Subsection change="ins"><MarginalNote>For greater certainty</MarginalNote><Label>(6)</Label><Text>For greater certainty, for the purposes of this section, a debt or obligation owed to a Crown corporation is not a debt or obligation owed to His Majesty and a claim by a Crown corporation is not a claim by His Majesty.</Text></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Section><Heading level="1"><TitleText>Consequential Amendments</TitleText></Heading><Heading level="2"><MarginalNote><HistoricalNote>R.S., c. 1 (5th Supp.)</HistoricalNote></MarginalNote><TitleText>Income Tax Act</TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><Label>2</Label><Text>Paragraph 241(4)(f) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Income Tax Act</XRefExternal> is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(f)</Label><Text>provide taxpayer information solely for the purposes of sections 23 to 25.1 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Financial Administration Act</XRefExternal>;</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Section><Heading level="2"><MarginalNote><HistoricalNote>R.S., c. E-15</HistoricalNote></MarginalNote><TitleText>Excise Tax Act</TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><Label>3</Label><Text>Paragraph 295(5)(e) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Excise Tax Act</XRefExternal> is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(e)</Label><Text>provide confidential information solely for the purposes of sections 23 to 25.1 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Financial Administration Act</XRefExternal>;</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Section><Heading level="2"><MarginalNote><HistoricalNote>2002, c. 22</HistoricalNote></MarginalNote><TitleText>Excise Act, 2001</TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><Label>4</Label><Text>Paragraph 211(6)(f) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Excise Act, 2001</XRefExternal> is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(f)</Label><Text>provide confidential information solely for the purposes of sections 23 to 25.1 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Financial Administration Act</XRefExternal>;</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Section><Heading level="2"><MarginalNote><HistoricalNote>2006, c. 13</HistoricalNote></MarginalNote><TitleText>Softwood Lumber Products Export Charge Act, 2006</TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><Label>5</Label><Text>Paragraph 84(6)(f) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Softwood Lumber Products Export Charge Act, 2006</XRefExternal> is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(f)</Label><Text>provide confidential information solely for the purposes of sections 23 to 25.1 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Financial Administration Act</XRefExternal>;</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Section><Heading level="2"><MarginalNote><HistoricalNote>2024, c. 15, s. 96</HistoricalNote></MarginalNote><TitleText>Digital Services Tax Act</TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><Label>6</Label><Text>Paragraph 108(6)(f) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Digital Services Tax Act</XRefExternal> is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(f)</Label><Text>provide confidential information solely for the purposes of sections 23 to 25.1 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Financial Administration Act</XRefExternal>;</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Section><Heading level="2"><MarginalNote><HistoricalNote>2024, c. 17, s. 81</HistoricalNote></MarginalNote><TitleText>Global Minimum Tax Act</TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><Label>7</Label><Text>Paragraph 123(6)(f) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Global Minimum Tax Act</XRefExternal> is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(f)</Label><Text>provide confidential information solely for the purposes of sections 23 to 25.1 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Financial Administration Act</XRefExternal>;</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Section><Heading level="1" change="ins"><TitleText>Coordinating Amendments</TitleText></Heading><Section change="ins" type="amending"><MarginalNote>Bill C-15</MarginalNote><Label>8</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Subsections (2) and (3) apply if Bill C-15, introduced in the 1st session of the 45th Parliament and entitled <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Budget 2025 Implementation Act, No. 1</XRefExternal> (in this section referred to as the “other Act”), receives royal assent.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><Label>(2)</Label><Text>If subsection 126(2) of the other Act comes into force before section 6 of this Act, then that section 6 is deemed never to have come into force and is repealed.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><Label>(3)</Label><Text>If subsection 126(2) of the other Act comes into force on the same day as section 6 of this Act, then that section 6 is deemed never to have come into force and is repealed.</Text></Subsection></Section></Body></Bill>