<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><Bill bill-origin="commons" bill-type="private-public" xml:lang="en" date-time="2023-05-25 10:55:51"><Identification><BillNumber>C-243</BillNumber><Parliament><Session>1</Session><Number>45</Number><RegnalYear><Year-s>3-4</Year-s><Monarch>Charles III</Monarch></RegnalYear><Year-s>2025</Year-s></Parliament><LongTitle>An Act to amend the Corrections and Conditional Release Act (parole review)</LongTitle><ShortTitle status="unofficial" /><RunningHead>An Act to amend the Corrections and Conditional Release Act (parole review)</RunningHead><BillHistory><Stages stage="first-reading-house"><Date><YYYY>2025</YYYY><MM>9</MM><DD>22</DD></Date></Stages></BillHistory><BillSponsor><Emphasis style="smallcaps">Mr. Diotte</Emphasis></BillSponsor><BillRefNumber date-time="2023-05-25">451107</BillRefNumber></Identification><Introduction><Summary><TitleText>SUMMARY</TitleText><Provision><Text>This enactment amends the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Corrections and Conditional Release Act</XRefExternal> to provide that, in the case of an offender who is serving a sentence for first degree murder or second degree murder, parole is reviewed in accordance with the statutory time frames — not on application by the offender — once the Board has decided not to grant day or full parole to the offender or to cancel or terminate the offender’s parole.</Text></Provision></Summary><Enacts><Provision><Text>His Majesty, by and with the advice and consent <Keep>of the</Keep> Senate and House of Commons of Canada, <Keep>enacts</Keep> as follows:</Text></Provision></Enacts></Introduction><Body><Heading level="1"><MarginalNote><HistoricalNote>1992, c. 20</HistoricalNote></MarginalNote><TitleText>Corrections and Conditional Release Act</TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><Label>1</Label><Text>Section 122 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Corrections and Conditional Release Act</XRefExternal> is amended by adding the following after subsection (4):</Text><AmendedText change="ins"><Subsection><MarginalNote>No application — murder</MarginalNote><Label>(4.1)</Label><Text>Despite subsection (4), in the case of an offender who is serving a sentence for first degree murder or second degree murder within the meaning of section 231 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Criminal Code</XRefExternal>, no further application for day parole may be made if, following a review, the Board does not grant day parole or cancels or terminates parole.</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>2</Label><Text>Section 123 of the Act is amended by adding the following after subsection (6):</Text><AmendedText change="ins"><Subsection><MarginalNote>No application — murder</MarginalNote><Label>(6.1)</Label><Text>Despite subsection (6), in the case of an offender who is serving a sentence for first degree murder or second degree murder within the meaning of section 231 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Criminal Code</XRefExternal>, no further application for full parole may be made if, following a review, the Board does not grant full parole or cancels or terminates parole.</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Section></Body></Bill>