<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><Bill bill-origin="commons" bill-type="private-public" xml:lang="en" date-time="2025-09-25 14:13:15"><Identification><BillNumber>C-248</BillNumber><Parliament><Session>1</Session><Number>45</Number><RegnalYear><Year-s>3-4</Year-s><Monarch>Charles III</Monarch></RegnalYear><Year-s>2025</Year-s></Parliament><LongTitle>An Act respecting the holding of a pan-Canadian conference on time change</LongTitle><ShortTitle status="unofficial">Time Change Act</ShortTitle><RunningHead>Time Change Act</RunningHead><BillHistory><Stages stage="first-reading-house"><Date><YYYY>2025</YYYY><MM>10</MM><DD>6</DD></Date></Stages></BillHistory><BillSponsor><Emphasis style="smallcaps">Mrs. Lalonde</Emphasis></BillSponsor><BillRefNumber date-time="2025-09-25">451034</BillRefNumber></Identification><Introduction><Summary><TitleText>SUMMARY </TitleText><Provision><Text>This enactment provides that a pan-Canadian conference on time change must be held with representatives of the provincial governments, Indigenous governing bodies and other relevant stakeholders, and that a report on the conference must be published online.</Text></Provision></Summary><Enacts><Provision><Text>His Majesty, by and with the advice and consent <Keep>of the</Keep> Senate and House of Commons of Canada, <Keep>enacts</Keep> as follows:</Text></Provision></Enacts></Introduction><Body><Heading level="1"><TitleText>Short Title</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Short title </MarginalNote><Label>1</Label><Text>This Act may be cited as the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Time Change Act</XRefExternal>.</Text></Section><Heading level="1"><TitleText>Interpretation</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Definitions</MarginalNote><Label>2</Label><Text>The following definitions apply in this Act.</Text><Definition><Text><DefinedTermEn>Indigenous governing body</DefinedTermEn> means a council, government or other entity that is authorized to act on behalf of an Indigenous group, community or people that holds rights recognized and affirmed by section 35 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Constitution Act, 1982</XRefExternal>. (<DefinedTermFr>corps dirigeant autochtone</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Definition><Definition><Text><DefinedTermEn>Minister</DefinedTermEn> means the Minister designated under section 3. (<DefinedTermFr>ministre</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Definition></Section><Heading level="1"><TitleText>Designation of Minister</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Order</MarginalNote><Label>3</Label><Text>The Governor in Council may, by order, designate a member of the King’s Privy Council for Canada as the Minister for the purposes of this Act.</Text></Section><Heading level="1"><TitleText>Pan-Canadian Conference  </TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Conference </MarginalNote><Label>4</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Within a year after the day on which this Act comes into force, the Minister must hold a pan-Canadian conference on time change to promote cooperation on the matter between the federal and provincial governments.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Agenda </MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The conference topics must include the following:</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>the main issues respecting time change, including economic issues; </Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>the scientific studies on the effects of time change on health, safety and productivity; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(c)</Label><Text>the possibility of adopting a more uniform approach across Canada.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Participants </MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>The Minister must invite to the conference</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>representatives of the provincial governments responsible for matters related to time change;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>Indigenous governing bodies; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(c)</Label><Text>any other relevant stakeholders, including health scientists and representatives from municipal governments and from the public safety, agriculture, education, early childhood care and eldercare sectors.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Report </MarginalNote><Label>5</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Within six months after the day on which the conference referred to in section 4 is held, the Minister must prepare a report on the conference and publish it on the departmental website.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Content </MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The report must set out the information and recommendations resulting from the discussions held at the conference.</Text></Subsection></Section></Body></Bill>