<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><Bill bill-origin="commons" bill-type="private-public" xml:lang="en" date-time="2025-09-10 13:38:12"><Identification><BillNumber>C-246</BillNumber><Parliament><Session>1</Session><Number>45</Number><RegnalYear><Year-s>3-4</Year-s><Monarch>Charles III</Monarch></RegnalYear><Year-s>2025</Year-s></Parliament><LongTitle>An Act to amend the Criminal Code (consecutive sentences for sexual offences)</LongTitle><ShortTitle status="unofficial" /><RunningHead>An Act to amend the Criminal Code (consecutive sentences for sexual offences)</RunningHead><BillHistory><Stages stage="first-reading-house"><Date><YYYY>2025</YYYY><MM>9</MM><DD>23</DD></Date></Stages></BillHistory><BillSponsor><Emphasis style="smallcaps">Mrs. Thomas</Emphasis></BillSponsor><BillRefNumber date-time="2025-09-10">451090</BillRefNumber></Identification><Introduction><Summary><TitleText>SUMMARY</TitleText><Provision><Text>This enactment amends the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Criminal Code</XRefExternal> to require that sentences for sexual offences be served consecutively. </Text></Provision></Summary><Preamble><Provision><MarginalNote>Preamble </MarginalNote><Text>Whereas Parliament recognizes that sexual offences inflict profound and lasting harm on victims, their families and communities, and that such offences often involve a pattern of repeated conduct that must be addressed firmly and consistently in sentencing;</Text></Provision><Provision><Text>Whereas Parliament considers it essential, in the interests of public safety and the protection of vulnerable persons, that sentences for multiple sexual offences reflect the gravity of each offence and the distinct harm caused to each victim;</Text></Provision><Provision><Text>And whereas Parliament wishes to ensure that sentencing practices denounce sexual violence, deter its commission and promote confidence in the administration of justice, while respecting the principle of proportionality;</Text></Provision></Preamble><Enacts><Provision><Text>Now, therefore, His Majesty, by and with the advice and consent <Keep>of the</Keep> Senate and House of Commons of Canada, <Keep>enacts</Keep> as follows:</Text></Provision></Enacts></Introduction><Body><Heading level="1"><MarginalNote><HistoricalNote>R.S., c. C-46</HistoricalNote></MarginalNote><TitleText>Criminal Code</TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><Label>1</Label><Text>Subsection 718.3(7) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Criminal Code</XRefExternal> is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><Subsection><MarginalNote>Cumulative punishments — sexual offences</MarginalNote><Label>(7)</Label><Text>When a court sentences an accused for a sexual offence, the court shall direct that the sentence of imprisonment it imposes for that sexual offence be served consecutively to </Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>any other sentence of imprisonment for a sexual offence that the court imposes on the accused at the same time; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>any other sentence of imprisonment for a sexual offence to which the accused is subject at the time of sentencing.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection></AmendedText></Section></Body></Bill>