<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!--Arbortext, Inc., 1988-2010, v.4002--><Bill bill-origin="commons" bill-type="govt-public" xml:lang="en"><!--Authoring to Exchange Transform created with transform.acl--><Identification><BillNumber>C-25</BillNumber><Parliament><Session>1</Session><Number>45</Number><RegnalYear><Year-s>3-4</Year-s><Monarch>Charles III</Monarch></RegnalYear><Year-s>2025-2026</Year-s></Parliament><LongTitle>An Act to amend the Canada Elections Act and to enact An Act to change the names of certain electoral districts, 2026</LongTitle><ShortTitle status="official">Strong and Free Elections Act</ShortTitle><RunningHead>Strong and Free Elections Act</RunningHead><BillHistory><Stages stage="first-reading-house"><Date><YYYY>2026</YYYY><MM>3</MM><DD>26</DD></Date></Stages></BillHistory><BillSponsor>MINISTER OF TRANSPORT AND LEADER OF THE GOVERNMENT IN THE HOUSE OF COMMONS</BillSponsor><BillRefNumber date-time="2026-03-25">91251</BillRefNumber></Identification><Introduction><Recommendation><TitleText>RECOMMENDATION</TitleText><Provision format-ref="section"><Text>Her Excellency the Governor General recommends to the House of Commons the appropriation of public revenue under the circumstances, in the manner and for the purposes set out in a measure entitled “<Emphasis style="italic">An Act to amend the Canada Elections Act and to enact An Act to change the names of certain electoral districts, 2026</Emphasis>”.</Text></Provision></Recommendation><Summary><TitleText>SUMMARY</TitleText><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>This enactment amends the <XRefExternal reference-level="federal" reference-type="act">Canada Elections Act</XRefExternal> to, among other things,</Text><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>establish new prohibitions and modify existing prohibitions, including in relation to foreign influence in the electoral process, accepting or offering a bribe, unauthorized use of a computer, making or publishing false or misleading information respecting elections and the candidate nomination process;</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>establish new prohibitions in relation to voting in a nomination contest or leadership contest;</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>(c)</Label><Text>prohibit the acceptance or use of certain contributions by political entities and third parties, including from anonymous sources;</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>(d)</Label><Text>provide for new requirements relating to political parties’ policies for the protection of personal information; and</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>(e)</Label><Text>expand the scope of certain provisions relating to the administration and enforcement of that Act, including by increasing the maximum administrative monetary penalties that may be imposed for certain violations and by granting the Commissioner of Canada Elections certain powers in respect of any conspiracy or attempt to commit, or being an accessory after the fact or counselling in relation to, a contravention of that Act.</Text></Provision></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>The enactment also enacts a statute to change the name of certain electoral districts as a result of proposals by the members of the House of Commons who represent those electoral districts.</Text></Provision></Summary><Enacts><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>His Majesty, by and with the advice and consent of the Senate and House of Commons of Canada, enacts as follows:</Text></Provision></Enacts></Introduction><Body><Heading level="1"><TitleText>Short Title</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Short title</MarginalNote><Label>1</Label><Text>This Act may be cited as the <XRefExternal reference-level="federal" reference-type="act">Strong and Free Elections Act</XRefExternal>.</Text></Section><Heading level="1"><Label>PART 1</Label><MarginalNote><HistoricalNote>2000, c. 9</HistoricalNote></MarginalNote><TitleText><XRefExternal reference-level="federal" reference-type="act">Canada Elections Act</XRefExternal></TitleText></Heading><Heading level="2"><TitleText>Amendments to the Act</TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><Label>2</Label><Text>Section 25 of the <XRefExternal reference-level="federal" reference-type="act">Canada Elections Act</XRefExternal> is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Section><MarginalNote>List in <XRefExternal reference-type="canada-gazette">Canada Gazette</XRefExternal></MarginalNote><Label>25</Label><Text>Between the 1st and 20th days of January in each year, the Chief Electoral Officer shall publish a list in the <XRefExternal reference-type="canada-gazette">Canada Gazette</XRefExternal> of the name, <Ins>municipality, or its equivalent, and province of residence</Ins> and occupation of the returning officer for each electoral district in Canada.</Text></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>3</Label><Text>Section 71 of the Act is amended by adding the following after subsection (2):</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Subsection change="ins"><MarginalNote>Contravention of section 92.3</MarginalNote><Label>(2.1)</Label><Text>A nomination is not to be refused on the ground that an elector who signed the prospective candidate’s nomination paper contravened section 92.3.</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>4</Label><Text>The Act is amended by adding the following after section 92:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Section change="ins"><MarginalNote>Conveying false or misleading information — nomination paper</MarginalNote><Label>92.1</Label><Text>No person or entity shall convey or cause to be conveyed false or misleading information to be included in a nomination paper.</Text></Section><Section change="ins"><MarginalNote>Filing nomination paper — false or misleading information</MarginalNote><Label>92.2</Label><Text>No person who files a nomination paper under section 67 shall include false or misleading information in the nomination paper.</Text></Section><Section change="ins"><MarginalNote>Signing multiple nomination papers</MarginalNote><Label>92.3</Label><Text>No person shall sign, for a given election, as an elector referred to in paragraph 66(1)(e) or (f), the nomination paper of more than one prospective candidate.</Text></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>5</Label><Text>Subsection 93(1.1) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Subsection><MarginalNote>Preliminary lists to parties</MarginalNote><Label>(1.1)</Label><Text>The Chief Electoral Officer shall make available in electronic form or in formats that include electronic form, to each registered party or eligible party that requests them, the preliminary lists of electors for an electoral district in respect of which a writ has been issued <Ins>if the party</Ins></Text><Paragraph change="ins"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>was represented in the House of Commons on the day before the day on which the writ was issued;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph change="ins"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>endorsed a candidate in one of the last two elections in that electoral district; or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph change="ins"><Label>(c)</Label><Text>endorsed candidates in at least two thirds of all electoral districts in the last general election.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection change="ins"><MarginalNote><XRefExternal reference-type="act">Electoral Boundaries Readjustment Act</XRefExternal></MarginalNote><Label>(1.2)</Label><Text>For the purposes of paragraph (1.1)(b), if the boundaries of an electoral district are revised or a new electoral district is established as a result of a representation order referred to in section 25 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Electoral Boundaries Readjustment Act</XRefExternal>, a candidate who, in one of those last two elections, was endorsed in an electoral district that coincides with all or part of the revised electoral district or new electoral district is considered to have been endorsed in the revised or new electoral district.</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>6</Label><Text>The heading of Part 11.1 of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Heading level="1"><TitleText>Prohibitions in Relation to Voting <Ins>at an Election</Ins></TitleText></Heading></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>7</Label><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Paragraph 281.7(1)(f) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(f)</Label><Text>alter, deface or destroy a ballot, <Ins>a special ballot</Ins>, the initials of the election officer that are signed on a ballot or the number of the polling division or advance polling district that is marked on a ballot;</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Paragraph 281.7(1)(i) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(i)</Label><Text>destroy, take, open or otherwise interfere with a ballot box, <Ins>inner or outer envelope</Ins> or book or packet of ballots or special ballots otherwise than as provided by this Act or by instructions of the Chief Electoral Officer.</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>8</Label><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The portion of subsection 282.4(1) of the Act before paragraph (a) is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Section><MarginalNote>Undue influence by foreigners</MarginalNote><Label>282.4</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>No person or entity referred to in any of paragraphs (a) to <Ins>(d)</Ins> shall unduly influence an elector to vote or refrain from voting, or to vote or refrain from voting for a particular candidate, <Ins>potential candidate</Ins>, registered party or <Ins>eligible party</Ins>, at <Ins>an</Ins> election:</Text></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Paragraph 282.4(1)(b) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>a corporation or entity incorporated, formed or otherwise organized outside Canada <Ins>if it</Ins> does not carry on business in Canada or <Ins>one of the primary activities that it carries on</Ins> in Canada <Ins>consists of doing anything</Ins> to influence electors to vote or refrain from voting, or to vote or refrain from voting for a particular candidate, <Ins>potential candidate</Ins>, registered party or <Ins>eligible party</Ins>, at <Ins>an</Ins> election;</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(3)</Label><Text>Subsection 282.4(1) of the Act is amended by adding “or” at the end of paragraph (c) and by replacing paragraphs (d) and (e) with the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><SectionPiece><Paragraph change="ins"><Label>(d)</Label><Text>a <DefinitionRef>foreign economic entity</DefinitionRef>, a <DefinitionRef>foreign entity</DefinitionRef>, a <DefinitionRef>foreign power</DefinitionRef> or a <DefinitionRef>foreign state</DefinitionRef>, as those expressions are defined in subsection 2(1) of the <XRefExternal reference-level="federal" reference-type="act">Foreign Interference and Security of Information Act</XRefExternal>.</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(4)</Label><Text>The portion of subsection 282.4(2) of the Act before paragraph (b) is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Subsection><MarginalNote>Meaning of unduly influencing</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>For the purposes of subsection (1), a person or entity unduly influences an elector to vote or refrain from voting, or to vote or refrain from voting for a particular candidate, <Ins>potential candidate</Ins>, registered party or <Ins>eligible party</Ins>, at an election if</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>they knowingly incur any expense to directly promote or oppose a candidate, <Ins>potential candidate</Ins>, registered party or <Ins>eligible party</Ins> or the leader of a registered party <Ins>or eligible party; or</Ins></Text></Paragraph></Subsection></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(5)</Label><Text>The portion of subsection 282.4(3) of the Act before paragraph (a) is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Subsection><MarginalNote>Exceptions</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>For greater certainty, subsection (1) does not apply if the only thing done by the person or entity to influence the elector to vote or refrain from voting, or to vote or refrain from voting for the particular candidate, <Ins>potential candidate</Ins>, registered party or <Ins>eligible party</Ins>, consists of</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(6)</Label><Text>Paragraph 282.4(3)(b) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>a statement by them that encourages the elector to vote or refrain from voting for any candidate, <Ins>potential candidate</Ins>, registered party or <Ins>eligible party</Ins> in the election; or</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(7)</Label><Text>Subsection 282.4(5) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Subsection><MarginalNote>Selling advertising space</MarginalNote><Label>(5)</Label><Text>No person or entity shall sell any advertising space to a person or entity to whom subsection (1) applies for the purpose of enabling that person or entity to transmit an election advertising message or <Ins>partisan advertising message</Ins> or to cause an election advertising message or <Ins>partisan advertising message</Ins> to be transmitted.</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Subsection></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>9</Label><Text>Section 282.7 of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Section><MarginalNote>Offering bribe</MarginalNote><Label>282.7</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>No person shall, directly or indirectly, offer a bribe to influence an elector to vote or refrain from voting, or to vote or refrain from voting for a particular candidate, <Ins>potential candidate</Ins>, registered party or <Ins>eligible party</Ins>, at <Ins>an</Ins> election.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Accepting bribe</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>No person shall accept or agree to accept a bribe that is offered to them to vote or refrain from voting, or to vote or refrain from voting for a particular candidate, <Ins>potential candidate</Ins>, registered party or <Ins>eligible party</Ins>, at <Ins>an</Ins> election.</Text></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>10</Label><Text>Subsection 330(1) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Section><MarginalNote>Prohibition — use of broadcasting station outside Canada</MarginalNote><Label>330</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>No person shall, with intent to influence persons to vote or refrain from voting, or to vote or refrain from voting for a particular candidate, <Ins>potential candidate, nomination contestant, leadership contestant</Ins>, registered party or <Ins>eligible party</Ins>, at an election, <Ins>nomination contest or leadership contest</Ins>, use a broadcasting station outside Canada, or aid, abet, counsel or procure the use of a broadcasting station outside Canada, for the broadcasting of any matter having reference to an election, <Ins>nomination contest or leadership contest</Ins>.</Text></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>11</Label><Text>The portion of paragraph (a) of the definition <DefinedTermEn>third party</DefinedTermEn> in section 349 of the Act before subparagraph (i) is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>in <Ins>Divisions</Ins> 0.1 <Ins>and 0.2</Ins>, a person or a group other than</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>12</Label><Text>The heading of Division 0.1 of Part 17 of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Heading level="2"><TitleText>Prohibitions <Ins>in Relation to</Ins> Foreign <Ins>Property, Services and</Ins> Funds</TitleText></Heading></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>13</Label><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The portion of the definition <DefinitionRef>advertising</DefinitionRef> in subsection 349.01(1) of the Act before paragraph (a) is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><SectionPiece><Definition><Text><DefinedTermEn>advertising</DefinedTermEn> means the transmission to the public by any means of an advertising message that promotes or opposes a registered party or eligible party or the election of a potential candidate, nomination contestant, <Ins>leadership contestant</Ins>, candidate or leader of a registered party or eligible party, otherwise than by taking a position on an issue with which any such party or person is associated. For greater certainty, it does not include</Text></Definition></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The definition <DefinitionRef>advertising</DefinitionRef> in subsection 349.01(1) of the Act is amended by striking out “or” at the end of paragraph (e), by adding “or” at the end of paragraph (f) and by adding the following after paragraph (f):</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><SectionPiece><Definition><Paragraph change="ins"><Label>(g)</Label><Text>the making of telephone calls to persons only to encourage them to vote at a nomination contest or leadership contest. (<DefinedTermFr>publicité</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Paragraph></Definition></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(3)</Label><Text>Paragraph (b) of the definition <DefinedTermEn>foreign entity</DefinedTermEn> in subsection 349.01(1) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>a corporation or entity incorporated, formed or otherwise organized outside Canada <Ins>if it</Ins> does not carry on business in Canada or <Ins>one of the primary activities that it carries</Ins> on in Canada consists of doing anything to influence electors to vote or refrain from voting, or to vote or refrain from voting for a particular candidate, <Ins>potential candidate</Ins>, registered party or <Ins>eligible party</Ins>, at an election;</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(4)</Label><Text>The definition <DefinedTermEn>foreign entity</DefinedTermEn> in subsection 349.01(1) of the Act is amended by adding “or” at the end of paragraph (c) and by replacing paragraphs (d) and (e) with the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><SectionPiece><Paragraph change="ins"><Label>(d)</Label><Text>a <DefinitionRef>foreign economic entity</DefinitionRef>, a <DefinitionRef>foreign entity</DefinitionRef>, a <DefinitionRef>foreign power</DefinitionRef> or a <DefinitionRef>foreign state</DefinitionRef>, as those expressions are defined in subsection 2(1) of the <XRefExternal reference-level="federal" reference-type="act">Foreign Interference and Security of Information Act</XRefExternal>.</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(5)</Label><Text>The portion of paragraph 349.01(2)(b) of the Act before subparagraph (i) is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>in relation to the election of a potential candidate, nomination contestant, <Ins>leadership contestant</Ins>, candidate or leader of a registered party or eligible party,</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(6)</Label><Text>Subparagraph 349.01(2)(b)(i) of the French version of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no" xml:lang="fr"><SectionPiece><Subparagraph><Label>(i)</Label><Text>nommer le candidat potentiel, le candidat à l’investiture, <Ins>le candidat à la direction,</Ins> le candidat ou le chef de parti,</Text></Subparagraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>14</Label><Text>Section 349.02 of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Section change="ins"><MarginalNote>Definition of <DefinitionRef>partisan activity</DefinitionRef></MarginalNote><Label>349.011</Label><Text>For the purposes of this Division, the definition <DefinitionRef>partisan activity</DefinitionRef> in section 349 also includes an activity that promotes or opposes a leadership contestant.</Text></Section><Section change="ins"><MarginalNote>Prohibition — provision of property, services or funds</MarginalNote><Label>349.012</Label><Text>No foreign entity shall provide property or services or transfer funds to a third party for a partisan activity, for advertising, including election advertising and partisan advertising, or for an election survey.</Text></Section><Section change="ins"><MarginalNote>Prohibition — circumventing prohibition under section 349.012</MarginalNote><Label>349.013</Label><Text>No foreign entity shall</Text><Paragraph change="ins"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>circumvent or attempt to circumvent the prohibition under section 349.012; or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph change="ins"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>act in collusion with another person or entity for that purpose.</Text></Paragraph></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Prohibition — use of foreign property, services or funds</MarginalNote><Label>349.02</Label><Text>No third party shall use <Ins>property, services or</Ins> funds for a partisan activity, for advertising, <Ins>including</Ins> election advertising <Ins>and partisan advertising</Ins>, or for an election survey if the source of the <Ins>property, services or</Ins> funds is a foreign entity.</Text></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>15</Label><Text>The Act is amended by adding the following after section 349.03:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Heading change="ins" level="2"><Label>DIVISION 0.2</Label><TitleText>Prohibition on Accepting Certain Contributions</TitleText></Heading><Section change="ins"><MarginalNote>Prohibition — cryptoasset, money order or payment product</MarginalNote><Label>349.04</Label><Text>No third party shall accept a contribution made for partisan activity, partisan advertising, election advertising or election survey purposes that is in the form of</Text><Paragraph change="ins"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>a cryptoasset, namely a digital asset protected by cryptographic measures;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph change="ins"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>a money order; or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph change="ins"><Label>(c)</Label><Text>a prepaid payment product, namely a physical or electronic product that is or can be loaded with funds and that can be used to make withdrawals or purchase goods or services.</Text></Paragraph></Section><Section change="ins"><MarginalNote>Return of cryptoasset, money order or payment product</MarginalNote><Label>349.05</Label><Text>If a third party receives a contribution referred to in section 349.04, the third party shall, within 30 days after becoming aware of the receipt of the contribution, take one of the following measures:</Text><Paragraph change="ins"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>return the contribution unused to the contributor;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph change="ins"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>if it is not possible to return the contribution, destroy it unused;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph change="ins"><Label>(c)</Label><Text>if it is not possible to return or destroy the contribution, convert it into money and pay the amount of it to the Chief Electoral Officer, who shall forward that amount to the Receiver General.</Text></Paragraph></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>16</Label><Text>Subparagraph 349.4(2)(b)(i) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><SectionPiece><Subparagraph><Label>(i)</Label><Text>it does not carry on business in Canada or <Ins>one of the primary activities that it carries</Ins> on in Canada during a pre-election period consists of doing anything to influence electors during that period to vote or refrain from voting, or to vote or refrain from voting for a particular candidate, <Ins>potential candidate</Ins>, registered party or <Ins>eligible party</Ins>, at the following election, and</Text></Subparagraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>17</Label><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Section 349.91 of the Act is amended by adding the following after subsection (2):</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Subsection change="ins"><MarginalNote>List of Canadian contributors</MarginalNote><Label>(2.1)</Label><Text>If subsection 349.95(1) applies to the third party, the interim third-party expenses return shall include the following for each Canadian individual whose contributions of a total amount of more than $200 were used to pay for the regulated expenses under that subsection:</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>their name and address;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>the amount of each contribution;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(c)</Label><Text>a list of the property or services that was contributed; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(d)</Label><Text>the date each contribution was made.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Paragraphs 349.91(4)(a) to (c) of the Act are replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>the amount of contributions for partisan activity, partisan advertising, election advertising or election survey purposes that were received during the period referred to in paragraph (1)(a);</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>for each contributor who made contributions of a total amount of more than $200 for partisan activity, partisan advertising, election advertising or election survey purposes during the period referred to in paragraph (1)(a), their name and address and the amount and date of each contribution; and</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(3)</Label><Text>Subsection 349.91(7) of the Act is repealed.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>18</Label><Text>The portion of section 349.94 of the Act before paragraph (a) is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Section><MarginalNote>Prohibition — use of anonymous contributions</MarginalNote><Label>349.94</Label><Text>No third party shall use a contribution for the purpose of any of the following if the third party does not know the name and address of the contributor:</Text></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>19</Label><Text>The Act is amended by adding the following after section 349.94:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Section change="ins"><MarginalNote>Limitation on expenses</MarginalNote><Label>349.95</Label><Subsection change="ins"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>A third party shall use only contributions from Canadian individuals to pay for regulated expenses and shall use, as regulated expenses, only property or services that are contributions from Canadian individuals.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Own funds</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>However, if the total amount of contributions received, from all sources and for any purpose, by the third party during the previous year is equal to or less than 10% of its revenue for that year, the third party may use its own funds, namely funds that are not contributions made to it, to pay for regulated expenses and may use, as regulated expenses, property or services that it has provided. In that case, the third party shall include a statement, prepared in accordance with generally accepted accounting principles, of its revenues and expenses for that year in the third-party expenses return referred to in section 359.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Excluded amounts</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>For the purposes of subsection (2), grants and contributions received from the Government of Canada or of a province or from a municipality are not included in determining the third party’s revenue for the previous year.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Previous year — choice of third party</MarginalNote><Label>(4)</Label><Text>For the purposes of subsections (2) and (3), the third party may choose as their previous year either</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>the calendar year that precedes the calendar year in which a pre-election period occurs, or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>the fiscal year that precedes the fiscal year in which a pre-election period occurs.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Non-application</MarginalNote><Label>(5)</Label><Text>This section does not apply in respect of a third party who is an individual or a third party that is not required to register under subsection 349.6(1).</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Definitions</MarginalNote><Label>(6)</Label><Text>The following definitions apply in this section.</Text><Definition><Text><DefinedTermEn>Canadian individual</DefinedTermEn> means an individual who is a Canadian citizen or a <DefinitionRef>permanent resident</DefinitionRef> as defined in subsection 2(1) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Immigration and Refugee Protection Act</XRefExternal>. (<DefinedTermFr>particulier canadien</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Definition><Definition><Text><DefinedTermEn>regulated expenses</DefinedTermEn> means any of the following expenses:</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>partisan activity expenses in relation to partisan activities that are carried out during a pre-election period;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>partisan advertising expenses in relation to partisan advertising messages that are transmitted during that period; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(c)</Label><Text>election survey expenses in relation to election surveys that are conducted during that period. (<DefinedTermFr>dépenses réglementées</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Paragraph></Definition></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>20</Label><Text>Subparagraph 351.1(2)(b)(i) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><SectionPiece><Subparagraph><Label>(i)</Label><Text>it does not carry on business in Canada or <Ins>one of the</Ins> primary <Ins>activities that it carries on</Ins> in Canada during an election period <Ins>consists of doing anything</Ins> to influence electors during that period to vote or refrain from voting, or to vote or refrain from voting for a particular candidate, <Ins>potential candidate</Ins>, registered party or <Ins>eligible party</Ins>, at the election, and</Text></Subparagraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>21</Label><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Section 357.01 of the Act is amended by adding the following after subsection (2):</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Subsection change="ins"><MarginalNote>List of Canadian contributors</MarginalNote><Label>(2.1)</Label><Text>If subsection 349.95(1) or 358(1) applies to the third party, the interim third-party expenses return shall include the following for each Canadian individual whose contributions of a total amount of more than $200 were used to pay for the regulated expenses under that subsection:</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>their name and address;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>the amount of each contribution;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(c)</Label><Text>a list of the property or services that was contributed; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(d)</Label><Text>the date each contribution was made.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Paragraphs 357.01(4)(a) to (c) of the Act are replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>the amount of contributions for partisan activity, partisan advertising, election advertising or election survey purposes that were received during the period referred to in paragraph (1)(b);</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>for each contributor who made contributions of a total amount of more than $200 for partisan activity, partisan advertising, election advertising or election survey purposes during the period referred to in paragraph (1)(b), their name and address and the amount and date of each contribution; and</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(3)</Label><Text>Subsection 357.01(7) of the Act is repealed.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>22</Label><Text>The portion of section 357.1 of the Act before paragraph (a) is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Section><MarginalNote>Prohibition — use of anonymous contributions</MarginalNote><Label>357.1</Label><Text>No third party shall use a contribution for the purpose of any of the following if the third party does not know the name and address of the contributor:</Text></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>23</Label><Text>The Act is amended by adding the following after section 357.1:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Section change="ins"><MarginalNote>Limitation on expenses</MarginalNote><Label>358</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>A third party shall use only contributions from Canadian individuals to pay for regulated expenses and shall use, as regulated expenses, only property or services that are contributions from Canadian individuals.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Own funds</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>However, if the total amount of contributions received, from all sources and for any purpose, by the third party during the previous year is equal to or less than 10% of its revenue for that year, the third party may use its own funds, namely funds that are not contributions made to it, to pay for regulated expenses and may use, as regulated expenses, property or services that it has provided. In that case, the third party shall include a statement, prepared in accordance with generally accepted accounting principles, of its revenues and expenses for that year in the third-party expenses return referred to in section 359.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Excluded amounts</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>For the purposes of subsection (2), grants and contributions received from the Government of Canada or of a province or from a municipality are not included in determining the third party’s revenue for the previous year.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Previous year — choice of third party</MarginalNote><Label>(4)</Label><Text>For the purposes of subsections (2) and (3), the third party may choose as their previous year either</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>the calendar year that precedes the calendar year in which an election period occurs, or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>the fiscal year that precedes the fiscal year in which an election period occurs.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Non-application</MarginalNote><Label>(5)</Label><Text>This section does not apply in respect of a third party who is an individual or a third party that is not required to register under subsection 353(1).</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Definitions</MarginalNote><Label>(6)</Label><Text>The following definitions apply in this section.</Text><Definition><Text><DefinedTermEn>Canadian individual</DefinedTermEn> means an individual who is a Canadian citizen or a <DefinitionRef>permanent resident</DefinitionRef> as defined in subsection 2(1) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Immigration and Refugee Protection Act</XRefExternal>. (<DefinedTermFr>particulier canadien</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Definition><Definition><Text><DefinedTermEn>regulated expenses</DefinedTermEn> means any of the following expenses:</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>partisan activity expenses in relation to partisan activities that are carried out during an election period;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>election advertising expenses in relation to election advertising messages that are transmitted during that period; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(c)</Label><Text>election survey expenses in relation to election surveys that are conducted during that period. (<DefinedTermFr>dépenses réglementées</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Paragraph></Definition></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>24</Label><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Section 359 of the Act is amended by adding the following after subsection (3):</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Subsection change="ins"><MarginalNote>Measures taken</MarginalNote><Label>(3.1)</Label><Text>If section 349.05 applies to the third party, the third-party expenses return shall set out the measures that the third party has taken in accordance with that section.</Text></Subsection><Subsection change="ins"><MarginalNote>Statement of revenues and expenses</MarginalNote><Label>(3.2)</Label><Text>If subsection 349.95(2) or 358(2) applies to the third party, the third-party expenses return shall include the statement of its revenues and expenses referred to in that subsection.</Text></Subsection><Subsection change="ins"><MarginalNote>List of Canadian contributors</MarginalNote><Label>(3.3)</Label><Text>If subsection 349.95(1) or 358(1) applies to the third party, the third-party expenses return shall include the following for each Canadian individual whose contributions of a total amount of more than $200 were used to pay for the regulated expenses under that subsection:</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>their name and address;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>the amount of each contribution;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(c)</Label><Text>a list of the property or services that was contributed; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(d)</Label><Text>the date each contribution was made.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Paragraphs 359(4)(a) to (b.1) of the Act are replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>the amount of contributions for partisan activity, partisan advertising, election advertising or election survey purposes that were received during the period beginning on the day after polling day at the general election previous to the polling day referred to in subsection (1) and ending on the polling day referred to in that subsection;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>for each contributor who made contributions of a total amount of more than $200 for partisan activity, partisan advertising, election advertising or election survey purposes during the period referred to in paragraph (a), their name and address and the amount and date of each contribution; and</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(3)</Label><Text>Subsection 359(6) of the Act is repealed.</Text></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(4)</Label><Text>Subsection 359(7) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Subsection><MarginalNote>Names to be provided</MarginalNote><Label>(7)</Label><Text>If the third party is unable to identify which contributions were received during the period referred to in paragraph (4)(a) for partisan activity, partisan advertising, election advertising or election survey purposes, the third-party expenses return shall include the names and addresses of every contributor who contributed a total of more than $200 to it during that period.</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Subsection></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>25</Label><Text>The Act is amended by adding the following after section 362:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Heading change="ins" level="1"><Label>PART 17.1</Label><TitleText>Prohibitions in Relation to Voting at a Nomination Contest or Leadership Contest</TitleText></Heading><Section change="ins"><MarginalNote>Application</MarginalNote><Label>362.1</Label><Text>The provisions of this Part apply inside and outside Canada.</Text></Section><Section change="ins"><MarginalNote>Undue influence by foreigners</MarginalNote><Label>362.2</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>No person or entity referred to in any of paragraphs (a) to (d) shall unduly influence another person to vote or refrain from voting, or to vote or refrain from voting for a particular nomination contestant or leadership contestant, at a nomination contest or leadership contest:</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>an individual who is not a Canadian citizen or a <DefinitionRef>permanent resident</DefinitionRef> as defined in subsection 2(1) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Immigration and Refugee Protection Act</XRefExternal> and who does not reside in Canada;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>a corporation or entity incorporated, formed or otherwise organized outside Canada if it does not carry on business in Canada or one of the primary activities that it carries on in Canada consists of doing anything to influence persons to vote or refrain from voting, or to vote or refrain from voting for a particular nomination contestant or leadership contestant, at a nomination contest or leadership contest;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(c)</Label><Text>a trade union that does not hold bargaining rights for employees in Canada; or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph change="ins"><Label>(d)</Label><Text>a <DefinitionRef>foreign economic entity</DefinitionRef>, a <DefinitionRef>foreign entity</DefinitionRef>, a <DefinitionRef>foreign power</DefinitionRef> or a <DefinitionRef>foreign state</DefinitionRef>, as those expressions are defined in subsection 2(1) of the <XRefExternal reference-level="federal" reference-type="act">Foreign Interference and Security of Information Act</XRefExternal>.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Meaning of unduly influencing</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>For the purposes of subsection (1), a person or entity unduly influences another person to vote or refrain from voting, or to vote or refrain from voting for a particular nomination contestant or leadership contestant, at a nomination contest or leadership contest if</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>the person or entity knowingly incurs any expense to directly promote or oppose a nomination contestant or leadership contestant in the nomination contest or leadership contest; or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>one of the things done by the person or entity to influence the other person is an offence under an Act of Parliament or a regulation made under any such Act, or under an Act of the legislature of a province or a regulation made under any such Act.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Exceptions</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>For greater certainty, subsection (1) does not apply if the only thing done by the person or entity to influence the other person to vote or refrain from voting, or to vote or refrain from voting for a nomination contestant or leadership contestant, at a nomination contest or leadership contest, consists of</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>an expression of the person or entity’s opinion about the outcome or desired outcome of the contest;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>a statement by the person or entity that encourages the other person to vote or refrain from voting for any nomination contestant or leadership contestant in the nomination contest or leadership contest; or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(c)</Label><Text>the transmission to the public through broadcasting, or through electronic or print media, of an editorial, a debate, a speech, an interview, a column, a letter, a commentary or news, regardless of the expense incurred in doing so, if no contravention of subsection 330(1) is involved in the transmission.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Collusion</MarginalNote><Label>(4)</Label><Text>No person or entity shall act in collusion with a person or entity to whom subsection (1) applies for the purpose of contravening that subsection.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Selling advertising space</MarginalNote><Label>(5)</Label><Text>No person or entity shall sell any advertising space to a person or entity to whom subsection (1) applies for the purpose of enabling that person or entity to transmit a message to influence another person to vote or refrain from voting, or to vote or refrain from voting for a particular nomination contestant or leadership contestant, at a nomination contest or leadership contest or to cause such a message to be transmitted.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section change="ins"><MarginalNote>Offering bribe</MarginalNote><Label>362.3</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>No person shall, directly or indirectly, offer a bribe to influence another person to vote or refrain from voting, or to vote or refrain from voting for a particular nomination contestant or leadership contestant, at a nomination contest or leadership contest.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Accepting bribe</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>No person shall accept or agree to accept a bribe that is offered to them to vote or refrain from voting, or to vote or refrain from voting for a particular nomination contestant or leadership contestant, at a nomination contest or leadership contest.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section change="ins"><MarginalNote>Intimidation, etc.</MarginalNote><Label>362.4</Label><Text>No person shall</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>by intimidation or duress, compel or attempt to compel another person to vote or refrain from voting, or to vote or refrain from voting for a particular nomination contestant or leadership contestant, at a nomination contest or leadership contest; or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>by any pretence or contrivance, influence or attempt to influence another person to vote or refrain from voting, or to vote or refrain from voting for a particular nomination contestant or leadership contestant, at a nomination contest or leadership contest.</Text></Paragraph></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>26</Label><Text>The Act is amended by adding the following after section 372:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Section change="ins"><MarginalNote>Prohibition — cryptoasset, money order or payment product</MarginalNote><Label>372.1</Label><Text>No chief agent of a registered party, financial agent of a registered association, official agent of a candidate or financial agent of a nomination contestant or leadership contestant shall accept a contribution that is in the form of</Text><Paragraph change="ins"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>a cryptoasset, namely a digital asset protected by cryptographic measures;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph change="ins"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>a money order; or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph change="ins"><Label>(c)</Label><Text>a prepaid payment product, namely a physical or electronic product that is or can be loaded with funds and that can be used to make withdrawals or purchase goods or services.</Text></Paragraph></Section><Section change="ins"><MarginalNote>Return of cryptoasset, money order or payment product</MarginalNote><Label>372.2</Label><Text>If a person or entity referred to in section 372.1 receives a contribution referred to in that section, the chief agent of the registered party, the financial agent of the registered association, the official agent of the candidate or the financial agent of the nomination contestant or leadership contestant shall, within 30 days after becoming aware of the receipt of the contribution, take one of the following measures:</Text><Paragraph change="ins"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>return the contribution unused to the contributor;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph change="ins"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>if it is not possible to return the contribution, destroy it unused;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph change="ins"><Label>(c)</Label><Text>if it is not possible to return or destroy the contribution, convert it into money and pay the amount of it to the Chief Electoral Officer, who shall forward that amount to the Receiver General.</Text></Paragraph></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>27</Label><Text>Subsection 378(1) of the Act is amended by striking out “and” at the end of paragraph (c), by adding “and” at the end of paragraph (d) and by adding the following after paragraph (d):</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><SectionPiece><Paragraph change="ins"><Label>(e)</Label><Text>expenses related to security.</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>28</Label><Text>Section 384.2 of the Act and the heading before it are replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Heading level="3"><TitleText>Reports</TitleText></Heading></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>29</Label><Text>Subsection 384.3(13) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Subsection><MarginalNote>Publication of reports</MarginalNote><Label>(13)</Label><Text>The Chief Electoral Officer shall publish reports provided under subsections (1), (6) and (8), and any corrected or revised versions of those reports, as soon as feasible after receiving them, in the manner that he or she considers appropriate. <Ins>The reports that are published must limit the information on the location referred to in paragraph (2)(a) to the municipality, or its equivalent, and the province in which the event took place</Ins>.</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>30</Label><Text>Section 384.4 of the Act and the heading before it are repealed.</Text></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>31</Label><Text>Paragraph 385(2)(k) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(k)</Label><Text>the party’s policy for the protection of personal information; and</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>32</Label><Text>Section 387 of the Act is amended by striking out “and” at the end of paragraph (b), by adding “and” at the end of paragraph (c) and by adding the following after paragraph (c):</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><SectionPiece><Paragraph change="ins"><Label>(d)</Label><Text>the Chief Electoral Officer is satisfied that the party’s policy for the protection of personal information meets the requirements set out in subsection 446.6(1).</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>33</Label><Text>Subsection 405(1) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Section><MarginalNote>Changes in information</MarginalNote><Label>405</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Within 30 days after the day on which there is a change in the information in respect of a registered party or an eligible party in the registry of political parties, the party shall report the change to the Chief Electoral Officer in writing. The report shall be certified by the <Ins>party’s</Ins> leader <Ins>or chief agent</Ins>.</Text></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>34</Label><Text>Paragraph 406(1)(a) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>a statement certified by its leader <Ins>or chief agent</Ins> confirming the validity of the information concerning the party in the registry of political parties; or</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>35</Label><Text>Section 432 of the Act is amended by adding the following after subsection (2):</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Subsection change="ins"><MarginalNote>Measures taken</MarginalNote><Label>(2.1)</Label><Text>If section 372.2 applies to the registered party, the financial transactions return shall set out the measures that the chief agent of the registered party has taken in accordance with that section.</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>36</Label><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Section 446.6 of the Act is amended by striking out “and” at the end of paragraph (d), by adding “and” at the end of paragraph (e) and by adding the following after paragraph (e):</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><SectionPiece><Paragraph change="ins"><Label>(f)</Label><Text>require the party to protect the personal information that is under its control through physical, organizational and technological security safeguards with a level of protection proportionate to the sensitivity of the personal information;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph change="ins"><Label>(g)</Label><Text>require the party to take appropriate steps in the case of the loss of, unauthorized access to or unauthorized disclosure of personal information that is under its control as a result of a breach of its security safeguards, including by, as soon as feasible, informing the individual whose personal information has been lost, accessed or disclosed if it is reasonable in the circumstances to believe the breach creates a real risk of significant harm to the individual;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph change="ins"><Label>(h)</Label><Text>require the party to ensure, by contract or otherwise, that any person or entity to which it transfers personal information provides a level of protection of the personal information equivalent to that which the party is required to provide under the policy;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph change="ins"><Label>(i)</Label><Text>require the privacy officer or their delegate to attend at least one meeting per calendar year relating to the protection of personal information held by the Chief Electoral Officer; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph change="ins"><Label>(j)</Label><Text>prohibit the party, as well as any person or entity acting on the party’s behalf, including the party’s candidates, electoral district associations, officers, agents, employees, volunteers and representatives, from</Text><Subparagraph change="ins"><Label>(i)</Label><Text>providing false or misleading information to individuals about the purposes for which the party collects personal information,</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph change="ins"><Label>(ii)</Label><Text>selling personal information under the party’s control, or</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph change="ins"><Label>(iii)</Label><Text>disclosing personal information under the party’s control to the public for the purpose of causing harm.</Text></Subparagraph></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Section 446.6 of the Act is renumbered as subsection 446.6(1) and is amended by adding the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Subsection change="ins"><MarginalNote>Real risk of significant harm — factors</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>For the purposes of paragraph (1)(g), the factors that are relevant to determining whether a breach of security safeguards creates a real risk of significant harm to an individual include</Text><Paragraph change="ins"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>the sensitivity of the personal information involved in the breach; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph change="ins"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>the probability that the personal information has been, is being or will be misused.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection change="ins"><MarginalNote>Definition of <DefinitionRef>significant harm</DefinitionRef></MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>For the purposes of this section, <DefinedTermEn>significant harm</DefinedTermEn> includes bodily harm, humiliation, damage to reputation or relationships, loss of employment, business or professional opportunities, financial loss, identity theft, negative effects on the credit record and damage to or loss of property.</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Subsection></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>37</Label><Text>Section 475.4 of the Act is amended by adding the following after subsection (2):</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Subsection change="ins"><MarginalNote>Measures taken</MarginalNote><Label>(2.1)</Label><Text>If section 372.2 applies to the registered association, the financial transactions return shall set out the measures that the financial agent of the registered association has taken in accordance with that section.</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>38</Label><Text>Section 476.75 of the Act is amended by adding the following after subsection (2):</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Subsection change="ins"><MarginalNote>Measures taken</MarginalNote><Label>(2.1)</Label><Text>If section 372.2 applies to the nomination contestant, the nomination campaign return shall set out the measures that the financial agent of the nomination contestant has taken in accordance with that section.</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>39</Label><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The portion of section 477.2 of the English version of the Act before paragraph (a) is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Section><MarginalNote>Official agent — ineligibility</MarginalNote><Label>477.2</Label><Text>The following persons are ineligible to be an official agent <Ins>for a candidate</Ins>:</Text></Section></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Section 477.2 of the Act is amended by adding the following after paragraph (b):</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><SectionPiece><Paragraph change="ins"><Label>(b.1)</Label><Text>the official agent of any other candidate in the same electoral district;</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>40</Label><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Subparagraph 477.59(2)(a.4)(ii) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><SectionPiece><Subparagraph><Label>(ii)</Label><Text>an indication of which of those expenses are expenses referred to in <Ins>any of</Ins> paragraphs 378(1)(c) <Ins>to (e)</Ins>, and</Text></Subparagraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Section 477.59 of the Act is amended by adding the following after subsection (2):</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Subsection change="ins"><MarginalNote>Measures taken</MarginalNote><Label>(2.1)</Label><Text>If section 372.2 applies to the candidate, the electoral campaign return shall set out the measures that the official agent of the candidate has taken in accordance with that section.</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Subsection></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>41</Label><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Paragraph 477.73(3)(c) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(c)</Label><Text>60% of the candidate’s paid personal expenses, as set out in their electoral campaign return, other than childcare expenses or expenses referred to in <Ins>any of</Ins> paragraphs 378(1)(c) <Ins>to (e)</Ins>,</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Subsection 477.73(3) of the Act is amended by striking out “and” at the end of paragraph (e), by adding “and” at the end of paragraph (f) and by adding the following after paragraph (f):</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><SectionPiece><Paragraph change="ins"><Label>(g)</Label><Text>65% — to a maximum of $3,250 — of the candidate’s paid expenses referred to in paragraph 378(1)(e).</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>42</Label><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Paragraph 477.74(2)(c) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(c)</Label><Text>60% of the candidate’s paid personal expenses, as set out in their electoral campaign return, other than childcare expenses and expenses referred to in <Ins>any of</Ins> paragraphs 378(1)(c) <Ins>to (e)</Ins>,</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Subsection 477.74(2) of the Act is amended by striking out “and” at the end of paragraph (e), by adding “and” at the end of paragraph (f) and by adding the following after paragraph (f):</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><SectionPiece><Paragraph change="ins"><Label>(g)</Label><Text>65% — to a maximum of $3,250 — of the candidate’s paid expenses referred to in paragraph 378(1)(e).</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>43</Label><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Paragraph 477.741(a) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>60% of the candidate’s personal expenses, as set out in their electoral campaign return, other than childcare expenses and expenses referred to <Ins>in any of paragraphs</Ins> 378(1)(c) <Ins>to (e)</Ins>, that were paid other than from the bank account referred to in subsection 477.46(1),</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Section 477.741 of the Act is amended by adding “and” at the end of paragraph (b) and by adding the following after paragraph (b):</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><SectionPiece><Paragraph change="ins"><Label>(c)</Label><Text>65% of the total of the candidate’s expenses referred to in paragraph 378(1)(e) — to a maximum of $3,2500 — as set out in their electoral campaign return, that were paid other than from the bank account referred to in subsection 477.46(1).</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>44</Label><Text>Subsection 477.94(3) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Subsection><MarginalNote>Exception</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>Subsection (2) does not prohibit the Commissioner from inspecting the statements referred to in that subsection, and any of those statements may be provided to the Director of Public Prosecutions and produced by the Director for the purpose of a prosecution for an offence under this Act <Ins>or for a conspiracy to commit, an attempt to commit, being an accessory after the fact in relation to, or any counselling in relation to, an offence under this Act</Ins>.</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>45</Label><Text>Section 478.8 of the Act is amended by adding the following after subsection (2):</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Subsection change="ins"><MarginalNote>Measures taken</MarginalNote><Label>(2.1)</Label><Text>If section 372.2 applies to the leadership contestant, the leadership campaign return shall set out the measures that the financial agent of the leadership contestant has taken in accordance with that section.</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>46</Label><Text>The Act is amended by adding the following before section 480:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Section change="ins"><MarginalNote>Application</MarginalNote><Label>479.1</Label><Text>Sections 480 to 482.1 apply inside and outside Canada.</Text></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>47</Label><Text>Subsection 480(1) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Section><MarginalNote>Obstruction, etc., of electoral process</MarginalNote><Label>480</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Every person is guilty of an offence who, with the intention of delaying or obstructing the electoral process, contravenes this Act, otherwise than by committing an offence under subsection (2) or <Ins>any of</Ins> sections 480.1 <Ins>to</Ins> 482.1 or contravening a provision referred to in any of sections 484 to 499.</Text></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>48</Label><Text>Section 480.1 of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Section><MarginalNote>Impersonation</MarginalNote><Label>480.1</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Every person is guilty of an offence who, with intent to mislead,</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>falsely represents themselves to be <Ins>any of the persons referred to in paragraph (2)</Ins>;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>causes anyone to falsely represent themselves to be <Ins>any of those persons</Ins>;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph change="ins"><Label>(c)</Label><Text>creates or causes to be created an image that is likely to be mistaken for an image of any of those persons;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph change="ins"><Label>(d)</Label><Text>creates or causes to be created an imitation of the voice of any of those persons that is likely to be mistaken for the voice of the persons or an audio recording that falsely represents anything said by any of those persons;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph change="ins"><Label>(e)</Label><Text>distributes, transmits or publishes an image referred to in paragraph (c) or imitation or audio recording referred to in paragraph (d).</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Persons</MarginalNote><Label><Ins>(2)</Ins></Label><Text><Ins>For the purposes of paragraphs (1)(a) to (e), the persons are the following:</Ins></Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>the Chief Electoral Officer, a member of the Chief Electoral Officer’s staff or a person who is authorized to act on the Chief Electoral Officer’s behalf;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>an election officer or a person who is authorized to act on an election officer’s behalf;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(c)</Label><Text>a person who is authorized to act on behalf of the Office of the Chief Electoral Officer, <Ins>including the Commissioner</Ins>;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(d)</Label><Text>a leader of a registered party or eligible party;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(e)</Label><Text>a person who is authorized to act on behalf of a registered party or registered association;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label><Ins>(f)</Ins></Label><Text>a candidate or a person who is authorized to act on a candidate’s behalf;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph change="ins"><Label>(g)</Label><Text>a potential candidate;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph change="ins"><Label>(h)</Label><Text>a prospective candidate;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph change="ins"><Label>(i)</Label><Text>a nomination contestant; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph change="ins"><Label>(j)</Label><Text>a leadership contestant.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Exception</MarginalNote><Label><Ins>(3)</Ins></Label><Text>A person does not commit an offence under subsection (1) if they establish that the <Ins>image, imitation or</Ins> representation was manifestly for the purpose of parody or satire.</Text></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>49</Label><Text>Subsections 481(1) and (2) of the Act are replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Section><MarginalNote>Misleading publications</MarginalNote><Label>481</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Every person or entity is guilty of an offence that distributes, transmits or publishes any material that purports to be made, distributed, transmitted or published by or under the authority of the Chief Electoral Officer, <Ins>the Commissioner</Ins> or a returning officer, political party, <Ins>nomination contestant</Ins>, candidate, <Ins>potential candidate</Ins>, prospective candidate or <Ins>leadership contestant</Ins>, if</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>the person or entity was not authorized by the Chief Electoral Officer, <Ins>the Commissioner</Ins> or that returning officer, political party, <Ins>nomination contestant</Ins>, candidate, <Ins>potential candidate</Ins>, prospective candidate or <Ins>leadership contestant</Ins> to distribute, transmit or publish it; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>the person or entity distributes, transmits or publishes it with the intent of misleading the public into believing that it was made, distributed, transmitted or published by or under the authority of the Chief Electoral Officer, <Ins>the Commissioner</Ins> or that returning officer, political party, <Ins>nomination contestant</Ins>, candidate, <Ins>potential candidate</Ins>, prospective candidate or <Ins>leadership contestant</Ins>.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Factors</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>In determining whether a person or entity has committed an offence under subsection (1), the court may consider whether the material included the use of</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>a name, logo, social media account identifier, username or domain name that is distinctive and commonly associated with the Chief Electoral Officer, <Ins>the Commissioner</Ins>, a returning officer or the political party, <Ins>nomination contestant</Ins>, candidate, <Ins>potential candidate</Ins>, prospective candidate or <Ins>leadership contestant</Ins>, as the case may be; or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>the name, voice, image or signature of the Chief Electoral Officer, <Ins>the Commissioner</Ins>, a returning officer or the <Ins>nomination contestant</Ins>, candidate, <Ins>potential candidate</Ins>, prospective candidate or <Ins>leadership contestant</Ins> or of a public figure who is associated with the political party.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>50</Label><Text>The portion of subsection 482(1) of the Act before paragraph (a) is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Section><MarginalNote>Unauthorized use of computer</MarginalNote><Label>482</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Every person or entity is guilty of an offence that, fraudulently and with the intention of affecting the results <Ins>or disrupting the conduct</Ins> of an election, <Ins>nomination contest or leadership contest</Ins>,</Text></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>51</Label><Text>The Act is amended by adding the following after section 482:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Section change="ins"><MarginalNote>False statements</MarginalNote><Label>482.01</Label><Text>Every person or entity is guilty of an offence that makes or publishes, with the intention of affecting the results or disrupting the conduct of an election, a statement that they know is false or misleading in respect of</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>who may vote in an election, including who is qualified as an elector or may register as an elector;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>the process by which an individual may register to vote;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(c)</Label><Text>where, when or the manner in which an individual may vote in an election, including at an advance poll or by special ballot;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(d)</Label><Text>whom an individual may vote for at an election;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(e)</Label><Text>the process by which an individual becomes a candidate;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(f)</Label><Text>the process by which votes at an election are counted or the results are validated; or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(g)</Label><Text>the preliminary, validated or official results of an election.</Text></Paragraph></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>52</Label><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Subsection 486(3) of the Act is amended by striking out “or” at the end of paragraph (c) and by adding the following after paragraph (d):</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><SectionPiece><Paragraph change="ins"><Label>(e)</Label><Text>knowingly contravenes section 92.1 (conveying false or misleading information — nomination paper); or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph change="ins"><Label>(f)</Label><Text>knowingly contravenes section 92.2 (filing nomination paper — false or misleading information).</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Subsection 486(4) of the Act is amended by striking out “or” at the end of paragraph (a), by adding “or” at the end of paragraph (b) and by adding the following after paragraph (b):</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><SectionPiece><Paragraph change="ins"><Label>(c)</Label><Text>knowingly contravenes section 92.1 (conveying false or misleading information — nomination paper).</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>53</Label><Text>The heading before section 491.1 of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Heading level="3"><TitleText>Offences under Part 11.1 (Prohibitions in relation to Voting <Ins>at an Election</Ins>)</TitleText></Heading></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>54</Label><Text>The heading “Offences under Division 0.1 of Part 17 (Prohibition on Use of Foreign Funds by Third Parties)” before section 495.21 of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Heading level="4"><TitleText>Offences under Division 0.1 of Part 17 (Prohibition <Ins>in Relation to</Ins> Foreign <Ins>Property, Services and</Ins> Funds)</TitleText></Heading></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>55</Label><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Section 495.21 of the Act is amended by adding the following before subsection (1):</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Section change="ins"><MarginalNote>Strict liability offences — summary conviction</MarginalNote><Label>495.21</Label><Subsection><Label>(0.1)</Label><Text>Every foreign entity is guilty of an offence who</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>contravenes section 349.012 (making a prohibited contribution); or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>contravenes paragraph 349.013(a) (circumventing prohibition) or 349.013(b) (colluding to circumvent prohibition).</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection change="ins"><MarginalNote>Offences requiring intent — dual procedure</MarginalNote><Label>(0.2)</Label><Text>Every foreign entity is guilty of an offence who</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>knowingly contravenes section 349.012 (making a prohibited contribution); or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>knowingly contravenes paragraph 349.013(a) (circumventing prohibition) or 349.013(b) (colluding to circumvent prohibition).</Text></Paragraph></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Subsection 495.21(2) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Subsection><MarginalNote>Offences requiring intent — dual procedure</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Every third party is guilty of an offence who</Text><Paragraph change="ins"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>knowingly contravenes section 349.02 (use of foreign contributions); or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph change="ins"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>knowingly contravenes paragraph 349.03(a) (circumventing prohibition) or 349.03(b) (colluding to circumvent prohibition).</Text></Paragraph></Subsection></AmendedText></Subsection></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>56</Label><Text>The Act is amended by adding the following after section 495.21:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Heading change="ins" level="4"><TitleText>Offences under Division 0.2 of Part 17 (Prohibition on Accepting Certain Contributions)</TitleText></Heading><Section change="ins"><MarginalNote>Strict liability offences — summary conviction</MarginalNote><Label>495.22</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Every third party is guilty of an offence who contravenes</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>section 349.04 (accepting a contribution that is in the form of a cryptoasset, money order or payment product); or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>section 349.05 (failure to return a contribution that is in the form of a cryptoasset, money order or payment product).</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Offences requiring intent — dual procedure</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Every third party who knowingly contravenes section 349.05 (failure to return a contribution that is in the form of a cryptoasset, money order or payment product) is guilty of an offence.</Text></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>57</Label><Text>Subsection 495.3(1) of the Act is amended by striking out “or” at the end of paragraph (g), by adding “or” at the end of paragraph (h) and by adding the following after paragraph (h):</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><SectionPiece><Paragraph change="ins"><Label>(i)</Label><Text>subsection 349.95(1) (limitation on expenses).</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>58</Label><Text>Subsection 496(1) of the Act is amended by striking out “or” at the end of paragraph (d.2), by adding “or” at the end of paragraph (e) and by adding the following after paragraph (e):</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><SectionPiece><Paragraph change="ins"><Label>(f)</Label><Text>subsection 358(1) (limitation on expenses).</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>59</Label><Text>The Act is amended by adding the following after section 496.1:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Heading change="ins" level="3"><TitleText>Offences under Part 17.1 (Prohibitions in Relation to Voting at a Nomination Contest or Leadership Contest)</TitleText></Heading><Section change="ins"><MarginalNote>Offences requiring intent — dual procedure</MarginalNote><Label>496.2</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Every person is guilty of an offence who</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>contravenes subsection 362.2(1) (undue influence by foreigners);</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>knowingly contravenes subsection 362.2(4) (collusion);</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(c)</Label><Text>knowingly contravenes subsection 362.2(5) (selling advertising space);</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(d)</Label><Text>knowingly contravenes subsection 362.3(1) (offering bribe);</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(e)</Label><Text>knowingly contravenes subsection 362.3(2) (accepting bribe); or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(f)</Label><Text>knowingly contravenes paragraph 362.4(a) or (b) (intimidation, etc.).</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Offences requiring intent — dual procedure</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Every entity is guilty of an offence that</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>contravenes subsection 362.2(1) (undue influence by foreigners);</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>knowingly contravenes subsection 362.2(4) (collusion); or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(c)</Label><Text>knowingly contravenes subsection 362.2(5) (selling advertising space).</Text></Paragraph></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>60</Label><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Subsection 497(1) of the Act is amended by adding the following after paragraph (h):</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><SectionPiece><Paragraph change="ins"><Label>(h.1)</Label><Text>being a registered party, registered association, nomination contestant, candidate, or leadership contestant, contravenes section 372.1 (accepting a contribution that is in the form of a cryptoasset, money order or payment product);</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph change="ins"><Label>(h.2)</Label><Text>being the chief agent of a registered party, the financial agent of a registered association, the official agent of a candidate, or the financial agent of a nomination contestant or leadership contestant, contravenes section 372.2 (failure to return a contribution that is in the form of a cryptoasset, money order or payment product);</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Subsection 497(2) of the Act is amended by adding the following after paragraph (m):</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><SectionPiece><Paragraph change="ins"><Label>(m.1)</Label><Text>being the chief agent of a registered party, the financial agent of a registered association, the official agent of a candidate, or the financial agent of a nomination contestant or leadership contestant, knowingly contravenes section 372.2 (failure to return a contribution that is in the form of a cryptoasset, money order or payment product);</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>61</Label><Text>Paragraphs 497.01(a) to (k) of the Act are repealed.</Text></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>62</Label><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Subsection 500(1) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Section><MarginalNote>Punishment — strict liability offences</MarginalNote><Label>500</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Every person who is guilty of an offence under any of subsections 484(1), 489(1), 491(1), 492(1), 495(1), 495.1(1), 495.2(1), 495.21<Ins>(0.1) and</Ins> (1), <Ins>495.22(1)</Ins>, 495.3(1), 496(1), 496.1(1), 497(1), 497.1(1), 497.2(1), 497.3(1), 497.4(1), 497.5(1), 498(1) and 499(1) is liable on summary conviction to a fine of not more than $2,000 or to imprisonment for a term of not more than three months, or to both.</Text></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The portion of subsection 500(5) of the Act before paragraph (a) is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Subsection><MarginalNote>Punishment — offences requiring intent (dual procedure)</MarginalNote><Label>(5)</Label><Text>Every person who is guilty of an offence under any of subsections 480(1) and (2), 480.1(1), 481(1) and 482(1), <Ins>sections 482.01 and</Ins> 482.1, subsections 484(3), 485(2), 486(3) and (4), 487(2), 488(2) and 489(3), section 490, subsection 491(3), section 491.2, subsection 492(2), section 494, subsections 495(5), 495.1(2), 495.2(2), 495.21<Ins>(0.2) and</Ins> (2), <Ins>495.22(2)</Ins>, 495.3(2), 496(2) <Ins>and</Ins> 496.1(2), <Ins>section 496.2 and subsections</Ins> 497(2), 497.1(3), 497.2(3), 497.3(2), 497.4(2), 497.5(2), 498(2) and 499(2) is liable</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(3)</Label><Text>Subsection 500(5.1) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Subsection><MarginalNote>Additional punishment — third parties</MarginalNote><Label>(5.1)</Label><Text>Every third party that is guilty of an offence under subsection 495.21(1) or (2) is, in addition to the punishment provided under subsection (1) or (5), liable to a fine of up to five times the amount of the funds, or five times the <Ins>commercial value of the property or services, involved in the commission of the offence</Ins>.</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Subsection></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>63</Label><Text>Subsection 502(2) of the Act is amended by adding the following after paragraph (h):</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><SectionPiece><Paragraph change="ins"><Label>(h.001)</Label><Text>being a nomination contestant or a leadership contestant, contravenes subsection 362.3(1) (offering bribe);</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>64</Label><Text>Section 508 of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Section><MarginalNote>Evidence</MarginalNote><Label>508</Label><Text>In a prosecution for an offence under this Act <Ins>or for a conspiracy to commit, an attempt to commit, being an accessory after the fact in relation to, or any counselling in relation to, an offence under this Act</Ins>, the written statement of the returning officer is, in the absence of evidence to the contrary, sufficient evidence of the holding of the election and of any person named in the certificate having been a candidate.</Text></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>65</Label><Text>Section 508.1 of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Section><MarginalNote>Violation</MarginalNote><Label>508.1</Label><Text>Every person or entity commits a violation and is liable to an administrative monetary penalty in an amount established in accordance with the provisions of this Act <Ins>if the person or entity</Ins></Text><Paragraph><Label><Ins>(a)</Ins></Label><Text>contravenes section <Ins>43.1, any of paragraphs 56(a) to (d), subsection 66(4), section 81, 81.1, 92.1, 92.2 or 92.3, subsection 136(4) or 166(1), section</Ins> 281.3, 281.4, 281.5 or <Ins>281.8</Ins> or a provision of any of Parts 16, 17 and 18;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph change="ins"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>conspires with any person or entity to contravene, or attempts to contravene, a provision referred to in paragraph (a);</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph change="ins"><Label>(c)</Label><Text>counsels any person or entity to contravene a provision referred to in paragraph (a), in the case where the provision is not contravened;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph change="ins"><Label>(d)</Label><Text>is an accessory after the fact to the contravention of a provision referred to in paragraph (a); or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label><Ins>(e)</Ins></Label><Text>fails to comply with a requirement of the Chief Electoral Officer under any of Parts <Ins>16, 17 and 18</Ins>, a provision of a compliance agreement, a provision of an undertaking that has been accepted by the Commissioner <Ins>or a requirement of the Commissioner or the Commissioner’s authorized representative under section 510.002</Ins>.</Text></Paragraph></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>66</Label><Text>Section 508.3 of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Section><MarginalNote>How act or omission may be proceeded with</MarginalNote><Label>508.3</Label><Text>If an act or omission may be proceeded with as a violation or as an offence, proceeding in one manner precludes proceeding in the other.</Text></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>67</Label><Text>Section 508.5 of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Section><MarginalNote>Maximum amount of penalty</MarginalNote><Label>508.5</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Subject to <Ins>subsections</Ins> (2) <Ins>to (6)</Ins>, the maximum administrative monetary penalty for a violation is $<Ins>25,000</Ins>, in the case of an individual, and $<Ins>100,000</Ins>, in the case of a corporation or an entity.</Text></Subsection><Subsection change="ins"><MarginalNote>Maximum — sections 349.012, 349.013, 349.02 and 349.03</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The maximum administrative monetary penalty for a violation arising from the contravention of section 349.012, 349.013, 349.02 or 349.03 is an amount equal to twice the amount of the funds, or twice the commercial value of the property or services, involved in the contravention of that section, plus</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>$25,000, in the case of an individual; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>$100,000, in the case of a corporation or an entity.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Maximum — sections 349.04, 349.05, 363, 367, 372.1 and 372.2</MarginalNote><Label><Ins>(3)</Ins></Label><Text>The maximum administrative monetary penalty for a violation arising from the contravention of section <Ins>349.04, 349.05</Ins>, 363, 367, <Ins>372.1</Ins> or <Ins>372.2</Ins> is an amount equal to twice the amount that was contributed — <Ins>accepted or not returned, not destroyed, or not converted and paid, as the case may be</Ins> — in contravention of that section, plus</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>$<Ins>25,000</Ins>, in the case of an individual; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>$<Ins>100,000</Ins>, in the case of a corporation or an entity.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection change="ins"><MarginalNote>Maximum — subsections 349.4(1) and 351.1(1)</MarginalNote><Label>(4)</Label><Text>The maximum administrative monetary penalty for a violation arising from the contravention of subsection 349.4(1) or 351.1(1) is an amount equal to twice the amount of the expense incurred by the third party in contravention of that subsection, plus</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>$25,000, in the case of an individual; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>$100,000, in the case of a corporation or an entity.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection change="ins"><MarginalNote>Maximum — subsections 349.95(1) and 358(1)</MarginalNote><Label>(5)</Label><Text>The maximum administrative monetary penalty for a violation arising from the contravention of subsection 349.95(1) or 358(1) is an amount equal to twice the amount of the contribution that was used in contravention of that subsection, plus</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>$<Ins>25,000</Ins>, in the case of an individual; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>$<Ins>100,000</Ins>, in the case of a corporation or an entity.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection change="ins"><MarginalNote>Maximum — section 368</MarginalNote><Label>(6)</Label><Text>The maximum administrative monetary penalty for a violation arising from the contravention of any of subsections 368(1) to (4) is an amount equal to twice the amount at issue in the contravention of that subsection, plus</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>$25,000, in the case of an individual; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>$100,000, in the case of a corporation or an entity.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>68</Label><Text>Subsection 508.6(1) of the Act is amended by adding the following after paragraph (b):</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><SectionPiece><Paragraph change="ins"><Label>(b.1)</Label><Text>whether the violation was committed by, at the direction of or in association with a <DefinitionRef>foreign entity</DefinitionRef>, as defined in subsection 349.01(1);</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>69</Label><Text>Section 509.22 of the Act is renumbered as subsection 509.22(1) and is amended by adding the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Subsection change="ins"><MarginalNote>Clarification</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>For greater certainty, the Commissioner may, in the exercise or performance of the Commissioner’s powers, duties and functions under this Part, enter into memoranda of understanding or other arrangements with a department or body that is listed in a schedule to the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Financial Administration Act</XRefExternal> and has technical or specialized knowledge on matters of national security or any other matters related to those powers, duties and functions.</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>70</Label><Text>The Act is amended by adding the following after section 510.001:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Section change="ins"><MarginalNote>Investigative powers — violations</MarginalNote><Label>510.002</Label><Text>In conducting an investigation to determine whether a violation referred to in section 508.1 has been committed, the Commissioner or the Commissioner’s authorized representative may</Text><Paragraph change="ins"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>in the same manner and to the same extent as a superior court of record,</Text><Subparagraph change="ins"><Label>(i)</Label><Text>summon and enforce the attendance of persons before the Commissioner or the representative and require them to give oral or written evidence on oath, and</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph change="ins"><Label>(ii)</Label><Text>require persons to preserve or produce any documents or other things that the Commissioner or representative considers relevant for the investigation; and</Text></Subparagraph></Paragraph><Paragraph change="ins"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>administer oaths.</Text></Paragraph></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>71</Label><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The portion of subsection 510.01(1) of the Act before paragraph (b) is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Section><MarginalNote>Order requiring testimony, etc.</MarginalNote><Label>510.01</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>If, on application of the Commissioner or <Ins>the Commissioner’s</Ins> authorized representative, a judge is satisfied by information on oath that there are reasonable grounds to believe that this Act has been contravened or is about to be contravened — <Ins>or that there is or is about to be a conspiracy or attempt to contravene this Act or that a person or entity is or is about to be an accessory after the fact, or has counselled or is about to counsel, in relation to such a contravention</Ins> — and that an individual has or is likely to have information that will provide evidence of the contravention <Ins>or conduct in question</Ins>, a judge may order the individual to</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>attend as specified in the order and be examined on oath by the Commissioner or the authorized representative on any matter that is relevant to the contravention <Ins>or conduct</Ins> before an individual, in sections 510.02 to 510.04 referred to as a “presiding officer”, designated in the order;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph change="ins"><Label>(a.1)</Label><Text>preserve any records or other things specified in the order;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph change="ins"><Label>(a.2)</Label><Text>produce to the Commissioner or the authorized representative, within a time and at a place specified in the order, a record — or a copy of a record certified by affidavit to be a true copy — or any other thing specified in the order; or</Text></Paragraph></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Subsection 510.01(3) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Subsection><MarginalNote>Restriction</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>No order may be made under subsection (1) against <Ins>the</Ins> individual <Ins>whose conduct is being investigated</Ins>.</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Subsection></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>72</Label><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Subsection 510.1(1) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Section><MarginalNote>Confidentiality</MarginalNote><Label>510.1</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Subject to <Ins>subsections</Ins> (2) <Ins>and (4)</Ins>, neither the Commissioner nor any person acting under <Ins>the Commissioner’s</Ins> direction shall disclose any information relating to an investigation that comes to their knowledge in the exercise of their powers or the performance of their duties and functions under this Act, including information that reveals or from which may be inferred the name of the complainant, if any, the person whose conduct is being investigated or any witness.</Text></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Paragraph 510.1(2)(d) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(d)</Label><Text>information that is required to be disclosed in the course of a prosecution for an offence under this Act <Ins>or for a conspiracy to commit, an attempt to commit, being an accessory after the fact in relation to, or any counselling in relation to, an offence under this Act</Ins>;</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(3)</Label><Text>Section 510.1 of the Act is amended by adding the following after subsection (3):</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Subsection change="ins"><MarginalNote>Information relating to investigations</MarginalNote><Label>(4)</Label><Text>The Commissioner may disclose — or may authorize any person acting under the Commissioner’s direction to disclose — any information relating to an investigation that comes to their knowledge in the exercise of their powers or the performance of their duties and functions under this Act to the government of a foreign state, an international organization of states, an international organization established by the government of states or an institution of such a government or organization if</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>the disclosure may, in the Commissioner’s opinion, be relevant to an investigation conducted by the Commissioner or to an investigation or proceeding in respect of a contravention of the laws of a foreign state that address conduct that is substantially similar to conduct prohibited under this Act; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>the information is disclosed in accordance with a memorandum of understanding or other arrangement that the Commissioner enters into with the government, organization or institution.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection change="ins"><MarginalNote>Contents of memorandum or arrangement</MarginalNote><Label>(5)</Label><Text>The memorandum of understanding or other arrangement shall</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>restrict the use of the information to the purpose for which it was originally disclosed; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>stipulate that the information be treated in a confidential manner and not be further disclosed without the express consent of the Commissioner or the person authorized by the Commissioner to disclose the information.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection></AmendedText></Subsection></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>73</Label><Text>Section 511 of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Section><MarginalNote>Commissioner may institute prosecution</MarginalNote><Label>511</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>If the Commissioner believes on reasonable grounds that an offence under this Act has been committed — <Ins>or that there has been a conspiracy to commit or an attempt to commit an offence under this Act or that a person or entity has been an accessory after the fact, or has counselled, in relation to an offence under this Act</Ins> — the Commissioner may institute a prosecution or cause one to be instituted.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Information</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text><Ins>The</Ins> prosecution is instituted by the laying of an information in writing and under oath before a <DefinitionRef>justice</DefinitionRef>, as defined in section 2 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Criminal Code</XRefExternal>.</Text></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>74</Label><Text>Subsection 512(1) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Section><MarginalNote>Director’s consent required</MarginalNote><Label>512</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>No prosecution for an offence under this Act — <Ins>or for a conspiracy to commit, an attempt to commit, being an accessory after the fact in relation to, or any counselling in relation to, an offence under this Act</Ins> — may be instituted by a person, other than the Commissioner or a person acting under <Ins>the Commissioner’s</Ins> direction, without the prior written consent of the Director of Public Prosecutions provided after consultation with the Commissioner.</Text></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>75</Label><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Subsection 514(1) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Section><MarginalNote>Limitation period</MarginalNote><Label>514</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Proceedings in respect of an offence under a provision set out in subsection 500(1) — <Ins>or in respect of a conspiracy to commit, an attempt to commit, being an accessory after the fact in relation to, or any counselling in relation to, such an offence</Ins> — may be commenced at any time within, but not later than, six years after the day on which the subject matter of the proceedings arose.</Text></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Subsection 514(3) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Subsection><MarginalNote>No limitation period</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>Proceedings in respect of an offence under a provision set out in any of subsections 500(2) to (5) — <Ins>or in respect of a conspiracy to commit, an attempt to commit, being an accessory after the fact in relation to, or any counselling in relation to, such an offence</Ins> — may be commenced at any time.</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Subsection></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>76</Label><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Subsection 516(1) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Section><MarginalNote>Application for injunction</MarginalNote><Label>516</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>If the Commissioner has reasonable grounds to believe that a person <Ins>or entity</Ins> has committed, is about to commit or is likely to commit an act or omission that is contrary to this Act — <Ins>or an act or omission that constitutes a conspiracy or attempt to contravene this Act or that constitutes being an accessory after the fact or counselling in relation to a contravention of this Act</Ins> — the Commissioner may, during an election period, after taking into account the nature and seriousness of the act or omission, the need to ensure fairness of the electoral process and the public interest, apply to a competent court described in subsection 525(1) for an injunction described in subsection (2).</Text></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The portion of subsection 516(2) of the Act before paragraph (a) is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Subsection><MarginalNote>Injunction</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>If the court, on application by the Commissioner under subsection (1), is satisfied that there are reasonable grounds to believe that a person <Ins>or entity</Ins> has committed, is about to commit or is likely to commit an act or omission <Ins>referred to in that subsection</Ins> and that the nature and seriousness of the act or omission, the need to ensure fairness of the electoral process and the public interest justify the issuing of an injunction, the court may issue an injunction ordering any person <Ins>or entity</Ins> named in the application to do one or both of the following:</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(3)</Label><Text>Subsection 516(3) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Subsection><MarginalNote>Notice</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>No injunction may be issued under subsection (2) unless at least 48 hours notice is given to each person <Ins>or entity</Ins> named in the application or the urgency of the situation is such that service of notice would not be in the public interest.</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Subsection></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>77</Label><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Subsection 517(1) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Section><MarginalNote>Power to enter into compliance agreement</MarginalNote><Label>517</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Subject to subsection (7), the Commissioner may enter into a compliance agreement, aimed at ensuring compliance with this Act, with a person or entity (in this section and sections 518 to 521 called the “contracting party”) if the Commissioner believes on reasonable grounds that the person or entity has committed, is about to commit or is likely to commit an act or omission that could constitute an offence under this Act <Ins>or that could constitute a conspiracy or attempt to commit, or being an accessory after the fact or counselling in relation to, an offence under this Act.</Ins></Text></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Subsection 517(4) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Subsection><MarginalNote>Admission of responsibility</MarginalNote><Label>(4)</Label><Text>A compliance agreement may include a statement by the contracting party in which it admits responsibility for the act or omission <Ins>in question</Ins>.</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Subsection></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>78</Label><Text>Paragraph 521.11(1)(b) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>identifies the provision of this Act, the requirement or the provision of the compliance agreement or undertaking <Ins>to which the violation relates</Ins>;</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>79</Label><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Paragraph 521.13(3)(a) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>identifies the provision of this Act, the requirement or the provision of the compliance agreement or undertaking <Ins>to which the violation relates</Ins>;</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Paragraph 521.13(3)(b) of the English version of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>identifies the act or omission to which the <Ins>violation</Ins> relates; and</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>80</Label><Text>Paragraphs 521.14(a) and (b) of the Act are replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>request a review by the Commissioner with respect to the alleged violation or the penalty, or both, if the amount of the penalty is</Text><Subparagraph><Label>(i)</Label><Text>$<Ins>8,500</Ins> or less, in the case of an individual, or</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph><Label>(ii)</Label><Text>$<Ins>30,000</Ins> or less, in the case of a corporation or an entity; or</Text></Subparagraph></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>request a review by the Chief Electoral Officer with respect to the alleged violation or the penalty, or both, if the amount of the penalty is</Text><Subparagraph><Label>(i)</Label><Text>more than $<Ins>8,500</Ins>, in the case of an individual, or</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph><Label>(ii)</Label><Text>more than $<Ins>30,000</Ins>, in the case of a corporation or an entity.</Text></Subparagraph></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>81</Label><Text>Section 521.24 of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Section><MarginalNote>Common law principles</MarginalNote><Label>521.24</Label><Text>Every rule and principle of the common law that renders any circumstance a justification or excuse in relation to a charge for any offence applies in respect of a violation to the extent that it is not inconsistent with this Act.</Text></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>82</Label><Text>Section 521.27 of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Section><MarginalNote>Parties to violation</MarginalNote><Label>521.27</Label><Subsection change="ins"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>A person or entity is a party to a violation committed by another person or entity and is liable for the violation if it</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>does or omits to do anything for the purpose of aiding that other person or entity to commit the violation;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>abets that other person or entity in committing the violation; or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(c)</Label><Text>counsels that other person or entity to commit the violation.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Violation by officers, etc.</MarginalNote><Label><Ins>(2)</Ins></Label><Text>If <Ins>a corporation or</Ins> an entity commits a violation, any of <Ins>its</Ins> directors, officers or agents or mandataries who directed, authorized, assented to, acquiesced in or participated in the commission of the violation is a party to and liable for the violation.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Application</MarginalNote><Label><Ins>(3)</Ins></Label><Text><Ins>Subsections (1) and (2) apply</Ins> whether or not the <Ins>person or</Ins> entity that actually committed the violation is proceeded against under this Act.</Text></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>83</Label><Text>Subsection 540(4.1) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Subsection><MarginalNote>Exception</MarginalNote><Label>(4.1)</Label><Text>The Chief Electoral Officer may also disclose any of the documents referred to in subsection (3) to the Commissioner for the purposes of the exercise or performance of the Commissioner’s powers, duties and functions under this Act and the Commissioner may, in turn, disclose any of those documents to the Director of Public Prosecutions, who may produce them for the purpose of a prosecution — or possible prosecution — by the Director for an offence under this Act <Ins>or for a conspiracy or attempt to commit, or being an accessory after the fact or counselling in relation to, an offence under this Act</Ins>.</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Section><Heading level="2"><TitleText>Interpretation</TitleText></Heading><Section type="transitional"><MarginalNote>Definition of <DefinitionRef>Act</DefinitionRef></MarginalNote><Label>84</Label><Subsection type="transitional"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>In this section and sections <XRefInternal>85</XRefInternal> and <XRefInternal>86</XRefInternal>, <DefinedTermEn>Act</DefinedTermEn> means the <XRefExternal reference-level="federal" reference-type="act">Canada Elections Act</XRefExternal>.</Text></Subsection><Subsection type="transitional"><MarginalNote>Words and expressions</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The words and expressions used in sections <XRefInternal>85</XRefInternal> to <XRefInternal>87</XRefInternal> have the same meaning as in the Act.</Text></Subsection></Section><Heading level="2"><TitleText>Transitional Provisions</TitleText></Heading><Section type="transitional"><MarginalNote>Policy for the protection of personal information — parties already registered, etc.</MarginalNote><Label>85</Label><Subsection type="transitional"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Within three months after the day on which this section comes into force, the leader of a political party must provide the Chief Electoral Officer with the party’s policy for the protection of personal information referred to in subsection 446.6(1) of the Act if</Text><Paragraph type="transitional"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>before the day on which this section comes into force, the leader of the party has applied under section 385 of the Act for the party to become a registered party but, as of that day, the Chief Electoral Officer has not yet informed the leader under subsection 389(1) of the Act whether the party is eligible under section 387 of the Act for registration; or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph type="transitional"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>on the day on which this section comes into force, the party is</Text><Subparagraph type="transitional"><Label>(i)</Label><Text>an eligible party, or</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph type="transitional"><Label>(ii)</Label><Text>a registered party.</Text></Subparagraph></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection type="transitional"><MarginalNote>Failure to comply</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>If the leader of the political party does not comply with subsection (1), then</Text><Paragraph type="transitional"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>in the case of a party referred to in paragraph (1)(a), the party is not eligible under section 387 of the Act for registration;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph type="transitional"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>in the case of a party referred to in subparagraph (1)(b)(i), the party is not permitted to become a registered party under section 390 of the Act; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph type="transitional"><Label>(c)</Label><Text>in the case of a party referred to in subparagraph (1)(b)(ii), the Chief Electoral Officer must implement the procedure for non-voluntary deregistration set out in sections 415, 416 and 418 of the Act.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection type="transitional"><MarginalNote>Deemed inclusion in application for registration</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>If the leader of a political party provides the Chief Electoral Officer with the policy referred to in subsection (1) in compliance with that subsection, or in compliance with a notice referred to in subsection 415(1) of the Act or a notice amended under subsection 415(2) of the Act, then the application for registration referred to in subsection 385(2) of the Act in respect of the party is deemed to include the policy as of the day on which the policy is provided.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section type="transitional"><MarginalNote>Eligibility for registration</MarginalNote><Label>86</Label><Text>Paragraph 387(d) of the Act, does not apply in respect of applications made under subsection 385(1) of the Act before the day on which that paragraph comes into force.</Text></Section><Heading level="2"><TitleText>Application of Amendments</TitleText></Heading><Section type="transitional"><MarginalNote>Election called within six months</MarginalNote><Label>87</Label><Text>Despite subsection 554(1) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Canada Elections Act</XRefExternal>, the amendments to that Act made by sections <XRefInternal>2</XRefInternal> to <XRefInternal>14</XRefInternal>, <XRefInternal>16</XRefInternal>, <XRefInternal>20</XRefInternal>, <XRefInternal>25</XRefInternal>, <XRefInternal>28</XRefInternal> to <XRefInternal>34</XRefInternal>, <XRefInternal>36</XRefInternal>, <XRefInternal>39</XRefInternal>, <XRefInternal>44</XRefInternal>, <XRefInternal>46</XRefInternal> to <XRefInternal>55</XRefInternal>, <XRefInternal>59</XRefInternal> and <XRefInternal>61</XRefInternal> to <XRefInternal>83</XRefInternal> of this Act apply in an election for which the writ is issued within six months after the day on which this Act receives royal assent.</Text></Section><Heading level="1"><Label>PART 2</Label><TitleText>An Act to change the names of certain electoral districts, 2026</TitleText></Heading><Heading level="2"><TitleText>Enactment of Act</TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote>Enactment</MarginalNote><Label>88</Label><Text><XRefExternal reference-type="act">An Act to change the names of certain electoral districts, 2026</XRefExternal> is enacted as follows:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="yes"><BillInternal><LongTitle>An Act to change the names of certain electoral districts, 2026</LongTitle><Preamble><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><MarginalNote>Preamble</MarginalNote><Text>Whereas certain members of the House of Commons have proposed to change the name of the electoral district that they represent;</Text></Provision></Preamble><Enacts><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>Now, therefore, His Majesty, by and with the advice and consent of the Senate and House of Commons of Canada, enacts as follows:</Text></Provision></Enacts><Body><Heading level="1"><TitleText>Definitions</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Definitions</MarginalNote><Label>1</Label><Text>The following definitions apply in this Act.</Text><Definition><Text><DefinedTermEn>first representation order</DefinedTermEn> means the representation order declared in force by proclamation of September 22, 2023 under the <XRefExternal reference-level="federal" reference-type="act">Electoral Boundaries Readjustment Act</XRefExternal> and set out in Schedule A of the proclamation. (<DefinedTermFr>premier décret de représentation électorale</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Definition><Definition><Text><DefinedTermEn>second representation order</DefinedTermEn> means the representation order declared in force by proclamation of September 22, 2023 under the <XRefExternal reference-level="federal" reference-type="act">Electoral Boundaries Readjustment Act</XRefExternal> and set out in Schedule B of the proclamation. (<DefinedTermFr>second décret de représentation électorale</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Definition></Section><Heading level="1"><TitleText>Amendments to the First Representation Order</TitleText></Heading><Heading level="2"><TitleText>Newfoundland and Labrador</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Name changed to “Cape <Preserve keep-together-line="no">Spear—Mount Pearl—Paradise</Preserve>”</MarginalNote><Label>2</Label><Text>The first representation order is amended by replacing the name “Cape Spear” with “Cape <Preserve keep-together-line="no">Spear—Mount Pearl—Paradise</Preserve>” in the heading of paragraph 2 of the part relating to Newfoundland and Labrador.</Text></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Name changed to “Coast of <Preserve keep-together-line="no">Bays—Central—Notre</Preserve> Dame”</MarginalNote><Label>3</Label><Text>The first representation order is amended by replacing the name “Central Newfoundland” with “Coast of <Preserve keep-together-line="no">Bays—Central—Notre</Preserve> Dame” in the heading of paragraph 3 of the part relating to Newfoundland and Labrador.</Text></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Name changed to “The Eastern Peninsulas”</MarginalNote><Label>4</Label><Text>The first representation order is amended by replacing the name “Terra <Preserve keep-together-line="no">Nova—The</Preserve> Peninsulas” with “The Eastern Peninsulas” in the heading of paragraph 7 of the part relating to Newfoundland and Labrador.</Text></Section><Heading level="2"><TitleText>Nova Scotia</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Name changed to “Halifax <Preserve keep-together-line="no">West—Peggy’s</Preserve> Cove”</MarginalNote><Label>5</Label><Text>The first representation order is amended by replacing the name “Halifax West” with “Halifax <Preserve keep-together-line="no">West—Peggy’s</Preserve> Cove” in the heading of paragraph 7 of the part relating to Nova Scotia.</Text></Section><Heading level="2"><TitleText>New Brunswick</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Name changed to “New Brunswick Southwest”</MarginalNote><Label>6</Label><Text>The first representation order is amended by replacing the name “Saint <Preserve keep-together-line="no">John—St.</Preserve> Croix” with “New Brunswick Southwest” in the heading of paragraph 9 of the part relating to New Brunswick.</Text></Section><Heading level="2"><TitleText>Ontario</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Name changed to “<Preserve keep-together-line="no">Brantford—Brant</Preserve> South”</MarginalNote><Label>7</Label><Text>The first representation order is amended by replacing the name “<Preserve keep-together-line="no">Brantford—Brant</Preserve> <Preserve keep-together-line="no">South—Six</Preserve> Nations” with “<Preserve keep-together-line="no">Brantford—Brant</Preserve> South” in the heading of paragraph 15 of the part relating to Ontario.</Text></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Name changed to “<Preserve keep-together-line="no">Hastings—Lennox</Preserve> and Addington”</MarginalNote><Label>8</Label><Text>The first representation order is amended by replacing the name “<Preserve keep-together-line="no">Hastings—Lennox</Preserve> and <Preserve keep-together-line="no">Addington—Tyendinaga</Preserve>” with “<Preserve keep-together-line="no">Hastings—Lennox</Preserve> and Addington” in the heading of paragraph 40 of the part relating to Ontario.</Text></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Name changed to “<Preserve keep-together-line="no">York—South</Preserve> Simcoe”</MarginalNote><Label>9</Label><Text>The first representation order is amended by replacing the name “New <Preserve keep-together-line="no">Tecumseth—Gwillimbury</Preserve>” with “<Preserve keep-together-line="no">York—South</Preserve> Simcoe” in the heading of paragraph 69 of the part relating to Ontario.</Text></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Name changed to “<Preserve keep-together-line="no">Sarnia—Lambton</Preserve>”</MarginalNote><Label>10</Label><Text>The first representation order is amended by replacing the name “<Preserve keep-together-line="no">Sarnia—Lambton—Bkejwanong</Preserve>” with “<Preserve keep-together-line="no">Sarnia—Lambton</Preserve>” in the heading of paragraph 90 of the part relating to Ontario.</Text></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Name changed to “North York”</MarginalNote><Label>11</Label><Text>The first representation order is amended by replacing the name “York Centre” with “North York” in the heading of paragraph 120 of the part relating to Ontario.</Text></Section><Heading level="2"><TitleText>Saskatchewan</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Name changed to “Saskatoon East”</MarginalNote><Label>12</Label><Text>The first representation order is amended by replacing the name “<Preserve keep-together-line="no">Saskatoon—University</Preserve>” with “Saskatoon East” in the heading of paragraph 10 of the part relating to Saskatchewan.</Text></Section><Heading level="2"><TitleText>British Columbia</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Name changed to “<Preserve keep-together-line="no">Cariboo—Prince George—Omineca</Preserve>”</MarginalNote><Label>13</Label><Text>The first representation order is amended by replacing the name “<Preserve keep-together-line="no">Cariboo—Prince</Preserve> George” with “<Preserve keep-together-line="no">Cariboo—Prince George—Omineca</Preserve>” in the heading of paragraph 4 of the part relating to British Columbia.</Text></Section><Heading level="1"><TitleText>Amendments to the Second Representation Order — Quebec</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Name changed to “<Preserve keep-together-line="no">Argenteuil—Papineau—Des</Preserve> Collines”</MarginalNote><Label>14</Label><Text>The second representation order is amended by replacing the name “<Preserve keep-together-line="no">Argenteuil—La</Preserve> Petite‑Nation” with “<Preserve keep-together-line="no">Argenteuil—Papineau—Des Collines</Preserve>” in the heading of paragraph 5.</Text></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Name changed to “Vallée-du-Haut-Saint-Laurent”</MarginalNote><Label>15</Label><Text>The second representation order is amended by replacing the name “<Preserve keep-together-line="no">Beauharnois—Salaberry—Soulanges—Huntingdon</Preserve>” with “Vallée-du-Haut-Saint-Laurent” in the heading of paragraph 7.</Text></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Name changed to “<Preserve keep-together-line="no">Jonquière—Hébertville—Pays-des-Bleuets</Preserve>”</MarginalNote><Label>16</Label><Text>The second representation order is amended by replacing the name “Jonquière” with “<Preserve keep-together-line="no">Jonquière—Hébertville—Pays-des-Bleuets</Preserve>” in the heading of paragraph 30.</Text></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Name changed to “<Preserve keep-together-line="no">Longueuil—Greenfield</Preserve> Park”</MarginalNote><Label>17</Label><Text>The second representation order is amended by replacing the name “<Preserve keep-together-line="no">Longueuil—Charles-LeMoyne</Preserve>” with “<Preserve keep-together-line="no">Longueuil—Greenfield</Preserve> Park” in the heading of paragraph 41.</Text></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Name changed to “<Preserve keep-together-line="no">Saint-Augustin—Portneuf—Jacques-Cartier</Preserve>”</MarginalNote><Label>18</Label><Text>The second representation order is amended by replacing the name “<Preserve keep-together-line="no">Portneuf—Jacques-Cartier</Preserve>” with “<Preserve keep-together-line="no">Saint-Augustin—Portneuf—Jacques-Cartier</Preserve>” in the heading of paragraph 58.</Text></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Name changed to “<Preserve keep-together-line="no">Richmond—Arthabaska—Val-des-Sources</Preserve>”</MarginalNote><Label>19</Label><Text>The second representation order is amended by replacing the name “<Preserve keep-together-line="no">Richmond—Arthabaska</Preserve>” with “<Preserve keep-together-line="no">Richmond—Arthabaska—Val-des-Sources</Preserve>” in the heading of paragraph 61.</Text></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Name changed to “<Preserve keep-together-line="no">Rimouski-Neigette—Mitis—Matapédia—Les</Preserve> Basques”</MarginalNote><Label>20</Label><Text>The second representation order is amended by replacing the name “<Preserve keep-together-line="no">Rimouski—La Matapédia</Preserve>” with “<Preserve keep-together-line="no">Rimouski-Neigette—Mitis—Matapédia—Les</Preserve> Basques” in the heading of paragraph 62.</Text></Section></Body></BillInternal></AmendedText></Section><Heading level="2"><TitleText>Coming into Force</TitleText></Heading><Section type="CIF"><MarginalNote>90th day after royal assent</MarginalNote><Label>89</Label><Text>Section <XRefInternal>88</XRefInternal> comes into force on the 90th day after the day on which this Act receives royal assent.</Text></Section></Body></Bill>