<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><Bill bill-origin="commons" bill-type="private-public" xml:lang="en" date-time="2025-10-22 11:16:28"><Identification><BillNumber>C-257</BillNumber><Parliament><Session>1</Session><Number>45</Number><RegnalYear><Year-s>3-4</Year-s><Monarch>Charles III</Monarch></RegnalYear><Year-s>2025</Year-s></Parliament><LongTitle>An Act to amend the Criminal Code (promotion of terrorist activity or group)</LongTitle><ShortTitle status="unofficial" /><RunningHead>An Act to amend the Criminal Code (promotion of terrorist activity or group)</RunningHead><BillHistory><Stages stage="first-reading-house"><Date><YYYY>2025</YYYY><MM>11</MM><DD>17</DD></Date></Stages></BillHistory><BillSponsor><Emphasis style="smallcaps">Mr. Baber</Emphasis></BillSponsor><BillRefNumber date-time="2025-10-22">451068</BillRefNumber></Identification><Introduction><Summary><TitleText>SUMMARY</TitleText><Provision><Text>This enactment amends the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Criminal Code</XRefExternal> to create an offence of wilfully promoting a terrorist activity or a terrorist group, or any activity of a terrorist group.</Text></Provision></Summary><Enacts><Provision><Text>His Majesty, by and with the advice and consent <Keep>of the</Keep> Senate and House of Commons of Canada, <Keep>enacts</Keep> as follows:</Text></Provision></Enacts></Introduction><Body><Heading level="1"><MarginalNote><HistoricalNote>R.S., c. C-46</HistoricalNote></MarginalNote><TitleText>Criminal Code</TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><Label>1</Label><Text>Paragraph (a) of the definition <DefinitionRef>terrorism offence</DefinitionRef> in section 2 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Criminal Code</XRefExternal> is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>an offence under any of sections 83.02 to 83.04 or <Ins>83.171</Ins> to 83.23,</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>2</Label><Text>The heading before section 83.18 of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><Heading level="1"><TitleText><Ins>Promoting</Ins>, Participating, Facilitating, Instructing and Harbouring</TitleText></Heading><Section change="ins"><MarginalNote>Wilful promotion of terrorist activity or terrorist group</MarginalNote><Label>83.171</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Every person who, by communicating statements, wilfully promotes any terrorist activity or terrorist group, or any activity of a terrorist group, is guilty of an indictable offence and liable to imprisonment for a term of not more than five years.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Prosecution</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>An offence may be committed under subsection (1) whether or not the statements communicated by the accused</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>specifically or generally relate to a terrorist activity or terrorist group, or to an activity of a terrorist group; or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>actually encouraged or instigated any person to participate in a terrorist activity or in an activity of a terrorist group.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Defences</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>No person shall be convicted of an offence under subsection (1) if</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>they establish that the statements communicated were true;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>in good faith, they expressed or attempted to establish by an argument an opinion on a religious subject or an opinion based on a belief in a religious text;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(c)</Label><Text>the statements were relevant to any subject of public interest, the discussion of which was for the public benefit, and they believe on reasonable grounds that the statements are true; or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(d)</Label><Text>in good faith, they intended to point out, for the purpose of removal, matters promoting or tending to promote a terrorist activity or terrorist group, or an activity of a terrorist group.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Definitions</MarginalNote><Label>(4)</Label><Text>In this section, <DefinedTermEn>communicating</DefinedTermEn> and <DefinedTermEn>statements</DefinedTermEn> have the same meaning as in subsection 319(7).</Text></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>3</Label><Text>The portion of section 83.26 of the Act before paragraph (a) is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><Section><MarginalNote>Sentences to be served consecutively</MarginalNote><Label>83.26</Label><Text>A sentence, other than one of life imprisonment, imposed on a person for an offence under any of sections 83.02 to 83.04 and <Ins>83.171</Ins> to 83.23 shall be served consecutively to</Text></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>4</Label><Text>Paragraph (a) of the definition <DefinitionRef>offence</DefinitionRef> in section 183 of the Act is amended by adding the following after subparagraph (xii.3):</Text><AmendedText><SectionPiece><Subparagraph change="ins"><Label>(xii.31)</Label><Text>section 83.171 (wilful promotion of terrorist activity or terrorist group),</Text></Subparagraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Section></Body></Bill>