<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><Bill bill-origin="commons" bill-type="private-public" xml:lang="en" date-time="2025-09-15 16:19:02"><Identification><BillNumber>C-255</BillNumber><Parliament><Session>1</Session><Number>45</Number><RegnalYear><Year-s>3-4</Year-s><Monarch>Charles III</Monarch></RegnalYear><Year-s>2025</Year-s></Parliament><LongTitle>An Act to amend the Criminal Code (mischief — religious property)</LongTitle><ShortTitle status="unofficial" /><RunningHead>An Act to amend the Criminal Code (mischief — religious property)</RunningHead><BillHistory><Stages stage="first-reading-house"><Date><YYYY>2025</YYYY><MM>11</MM><DD>6</DD></Date></Stages></BillHistory><BillSponsor><Emphasis style="smallcaps">Mrs. Block</Emphasis></BillSponsor><BillRefNumber date-time="2025-09-15">451102</BillRefNumber></Identification><Introduction><Summary><TitleText>SUMMARY</TitleText><Provision><Text>This enactment amends the <Emphasis style="italic">Criminal Code</Emphasis> to increase the punishment for mischief relating to religious property.</Text></Provision></Summary><Enacts><Provision><Text>His Majesty, by and with the advice and consent <Keep>of the</Keep> Senate and House of Commons of Canada, <Keep>enacts</Keep> as follows:</Text></Provision></Enacts></Introduction><Body><Heading level="1"><MarginalNote><HistoricalNote>R.S., c. C-46</HistoricalNote></MarginalNote><TitleText>Criminal Code</TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><Label>1</Label><Text>Section 430 of the <Emphasis style="italic">Criminal Code</Emphasis> is amended by adding the following after subsection (4.11):</Text><AmendedText><Subsection change="ins"><MarginalNote>Mischief relating to religious property</MarginalNote><Label>(4.12)</Label><Text>Everyone who commits mischief in relation to a building or structure, or part of a building or structure, that is primarily used for religious worship — including a church, mosque, synagogue or temple — an object associated with religious worship located in or on the grounds of such a building or structure, or a cemetery is guilty of an indictable offence or an offence punishable on summary conviction and is liable,</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>whether the offence is prosecuted by indictment or punishable on summary conviction, to the following minimum punishment, namely,</Text><Subparagraph><Label>(i)</Label><Text>for a first offence, to compensate the property owner an amount of not less than $1,000,</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph><Label>(ii)</Label><Text>for a second offence, to compensate the property owner an amount of not less than $1,000 and to imprisonment for not less than 14 days, and</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph><Label>(iii)</Label><Text>for each subsequent offence, to compensate the property owner an amount of not less than $1,000 and to imprisonment for not less than 30 days;</Text></Subparagraph></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>if the offence is prosecuted by indictment, to imprisonment for a term not exceeding 10 years; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(c)</Label><Text>if the offence is punishable on summary conviction, to imprisonment for a term of not more than two years less a day.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection></AmendedText></Section></Body></Bill>