<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><Bill bill-origin="commons" bill-type="private-public" xml:lang="en" date-time="2026-03-05 10:17:44"><Identification><BillNumber>C-267</BillNumber><Parliament><Session>1</Session><Number>45</Number><RegnalYear><Year-s>3-4</Year-s><Monarch>Charles III</Monarch></RegnalYear><Year-s>2025-2026</Year-s></Parliament><LongTitle>An Act to establish a national framework to promote the durability of electronic products and essential home appliances</LongTitle><ShortTitle status="unofficial" /><RunningHead>National Framework on the Durability of Electronic Products and Essential Home Appliances Act</RunningHead><BillHistory><Stages stage="first-reading-house"><Date><YYYY>2026</YYYY><MM>3</MM><DD>11</DD></Date></Stages></BillHistory><BillSponsor><Emphasis style="smallcaps">Mr. Sari</Emphasis></BillSponsor><BillRefNumber date-time="2026-03-05">451149</BillRefNumber></Identification><Introduction><Summary><TitleText>SUMMARY</TitleText><Provision><Text>This enactment provides for the development of a national framework on the durability and repairability of electronic products and essential home appliances. It also sets out reporting requirements respecting the framework.</Text></Provision></Summary><Preamble><Provision><MarginalNote>Preamble</MarginalNote><Text>Whereas Canadian households bear significant costs when they have to replace electronic products and essential home appliances prematurely;</Text></Provision><Provision><Text>Whereas consumers increasingly depend on electronic products and essential home appliances in their everyday lives;</Text></Provision><Provision><Text>Whereas product durability and repairability help protect consumers, reduce household expenses and boost the competitiveness of a responsible economy;</Text></Provision><Provision><Text>Whereas transparency about the useful life of products and the support available for them fosters a fairer and more competitive market;</Text></Provision><Provision><Text>And whereas Parliament considers it desirable to establish a national framework for products marketed in Canada in order to promote minimum standards of durability and repairability;</Text></Provision></Preamble><Enacts><Provision language-align="yes"><Text>Now, therefore, His Majesty, by and with the advice and consent of the Senate and House of Commons of Canada, enacts as follows:</Text></Provision></Enacts></Introduction><Body><Heading level="1"><TitleText>Short Title</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Short title</MarginalNote><Label>1</Label><Text>This Act may be cited as the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">National Framework on the Durability of Electronic Products and Essential Home Appliances Act</XRefExternal>.</Text></Section><Heading level="1"><TitleText>Interpretation</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Definitions</MarginalNote><Label>2</Label><Text>The following definitions apply in this Act.</Text><Definition><Text><DefinedTermEn>essential home appliance</DefinedTermEn> means a device intended for regular household use, including for food preservation, cooking, washing, heating or communication. (<DefinedTermFr>appareil domestique essentiel</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Definition><Definition><Text><DefinedTermEn>Minister</DefinedTermEn> means the Minister of Industry. (<DefinedTermFr>ministre</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Definition><Definition><Text><DefinedTermEn>useful life</DefinedTermEn> means the period during which a product may be used in a safe and functional manner under normal conditions of use. (<DefinedTermFr>durée de vie utile</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Definition></Section><Heading level="1"><TitleText>National Framework on the Durability of Electronic Products and Essential Home Appliances</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>National framework</MarginalNote><Label>3</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The Minister must, in consultation with the representatives of the provincial governments responsible for consumer protection and, if appropriate, with consumer advocacy groups, develop a national framework on the durability and repairability of electronic products and essential home appliances that are offered for sale, distributed or sold in Canada, whether they are made in Canada or imported.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Content</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The framework must include measures to</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>promote the durability of electronic products and essential home appliances;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>foster transparency about the useful life of those products and appliances and about means of maintaining and repairing them;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(c)</Label><Text>set national standards for the electronic product and essential home appliance industries respecting</Text><Subparagraph><Label>(i)</Label><Text>the minimum useful life of those products and appliances and the labelling or displaying of information about that minimum useful life,</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph><Label>(ii)</Label><Text>their maintenance and repair, including by means of reasonably accessible parts, tools and information,</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph><Label>(iii)</Label><Text>the availability of replacement parts, including the time period during which those parts must be available,</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph><Label>(iv)</Label><Text>the provision of technical documentation, if applicable, and</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph><Label>(v)</Label><Text>the duration of or conditions for software support, if applicable; </Text></Subparagraph></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(d)</Label><Text>inform consumers throughout Canada about the standards referred to in paragraph (c); and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(e)</Label><Text>determine the responsibilities to consumers of any person involved in the sale of those products and appliances, including manufacturers, importers and distributors.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Legislative measures</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>As part of the consultations referred to in subsection (1), the Minister must confer with the representatives of the provincial governments about legislative measures that should be proposed, including</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>obligations to be imposed on manufacturers, importers and distributors of electronic products and essential home appliances;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>inspection mechanisms to ensure the implementation of the measures provided for in the framework; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(c)</Label><Text>penalties for failure to comply with obligations arising from the framework.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection></Section><Heading level="1"><TitleText>Reports to Parliament</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Report</MarginalNote><Label>4</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Within 18 months after the day on which this Act comes into force, the Minister must prepare a report setting out the framework.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Tabling of report</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The Minister must cause the report to be tabled in each House of Parliament on any of the first 15 days on which that House is sitting after it is completed.<PageBreak /></Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Publication</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>The Minister must publish the report on the website of the Department of Industry within 10 days after the day on which the report is tabled in both Houses of Parliament.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Review and report</MarginalNote><Label>5</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Within five years after the day on which the report referred to in section 4 is tabled in both Houses of Parliament, the Minister must, in consultation with the parties referred to in subsection 3(1), undertake a review of the implementation and effectiveness of the framework and prepare a report that sets out the findings and recommendations resulting from that review.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Tabling of report</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The Minister must cause the report to be tabled in each House of Parliament on any of the first 15 days on which that House is sitting after it is completed.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Publication</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>The Minister must publish the report on the website of the Department of Industry within 10 days after the day on which the report is tabled in both Houses of Parliament.</Text></Subsection></Section></Body></Bill>