<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><Bill bill-origin="commons" bill-type="private-public" xml:lang="en" date-time="2023-03-01 13:59:03"><Identification><BillNumber>C-261</BillNumber><Parliament><Session>1</Session><Number>45</Number><RegnalYear><Year-s>3-4</Year-s><Monarch>Charles III</Monarch></RegnalYear><Year-s>2025-2026</Year-s></Parliament><LongTitle>An Act to amend the Old Age Security Act (amount of full pension)</LongTitle><ShortTitle status="unofficial" /><RunningHead>An Act to amend the Old Age Security Act (amount of full pension)</RunningHead><BillHistory><Stages stage="first-reading-house"><Date><YYYY>2026</YYYY><MM>2</MM><DD>9</DD></Date></Stages></BillHistory><BillSponsor><Emphasis style="smallcaps">Ms. DeBellefeuille</Emphasis></BillSponsor><BillRefNumber date-time="2023-03-01">451112</BillRefNumber></Identification><Introduction><Summary><TitleText>SUMMARY</TitleText><Provision><Text>This enactment amends the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Old Age Security Act</XRefExternal> to increase the amount of the full pension to which all pensioners aged 65 or older are entitled by 10% and to raise the exemption for a person芒聙聶s employment income or self-employed earnings that is taken into account in determining the amount of the guaranteed income supplement from $5,000 to $6,500.</Text></Provision></Summary><Enacts><Provision><Text>His Majesty, by and with the advice and consent <Keep>of the</Keep> Senate and House of Commons of Canada, <Keep>enacts</Keep> as follows:</Text></Provision></Enacts></Introduction><Body><Heading level="1"><MarginalNote><HistoricalNote>R.S., c. O-9</HistoricalNote></MarginalNote><TitleText>Old Age Security Act</TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><Label>1</Label><Text>Paragraph (b.1) of the definition <DefinedTermEn>income</DefinedTermEn> in section 2 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Old Age Security Act</XRefExternal> is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(b.1)</Label><Text>for the purpose of determining benefits payable in respect of any month after June <Ins>2025</Ins>, there shall be deducted from a person芒聙聶s combined amount 芒聙聰 which is equal to the aggregate of the person芒聙聶s income from office or employment for the year, as reduced in accordance with paragraph (a), and the person芒聙聶s self-<Keep>employment</Keep> earnings for the year, as reduced in accordance with paragraph (b), if those reduced self-<Keep>employment</Keep> earnings are greater than zero 芒聙聰 an amount that is equal to the aggregate of</Text></Paragraph><Subparagraph><Label>(i)</Label><Text>the lesser of <Ins>$6,500</Ins> and the combined amount, and</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph><Label>(ii)</Label><Text>if the combined amount is greater than <Ins>$6,500</Ins>, the lesser of <Ins>$6,500</Ins> and half of the amount by which the combined amount exceeds <Ins>$6,500</Ins>,</Text></Subparagraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>2</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Subsection 7(1) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><Subsection><MarginalNote>Basic amount of full pension</MarginalNote><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The amount of the full monthly pension that may be paid to any person for a month in the payment quarter commencing on <Ins>July</Ins> 1, <Ins>2025</Ins> is <Ins>eight</Ins> hundred <Ins>and eight</Ins> dollars and <Ins>fourty-five</Ins> cents.</Text></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Subsection 7(5) of the Act is repealed.</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Subsection></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>3</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Subsection 7.1(2) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><Subsection><MarginalNote>Voluntary deferral 芒聙聰 partial monthly pension</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>If a person applies for their pension after they become qualified to receive a partial monthly pension, the amount of that pension, as it is calculated in accordance with subsection 3(3), at the time that they become qualified for that pension, is increased by 0.6% for each month in the period that begins in the month after that time and that ends in the month in which the person芒聙聶s application is approved.</Text></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Subsections 7.1(5) and (6) of the Act are repealed.</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Subsection></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>4</Label><Text>The description of B in paragraph 12(6)(b) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><SectionPiece><FormulaDefinition indent-level="1"><FormulaTerm>B</FormulaTerm><Text>is the product</Text></FormulaDefinition><Clause><Label>(i)</Label><Text>obtained by multiplying the amount of the full monthly pension that might have been paid to a pensioner for any month by the applicant芒聙聶s special qualifying factor for the month, and</Text></Clause><Clause><Label>(ii)</Label><Text>rounded, if that product is not a multiple of four dollars, to the next higher multiple of four dollars; and</Text></Clause></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>5</Label><Text>The definition <DefinedTermEn>pension equivalent</DefinedTermEn> in subsection 22(1) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><SectionPiece><Definition><Text><DefinedTermEn>pension equivalent</DefinedTermEn>芒聙聜means, in respect of any month in a payment quarter, the amount of the full monthly pension payable for that month under section 7;芒聙聜(<DefinedTermFr>valeur de la pension</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Definition></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Section></Body></Bill>