<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><Bill bill-origin="commons" bill-type="private-public" xml:lang="en" date-time="2026-03-05 14:35:59"><Identification><BillNumber>C-266</BillNumber><Parliament><Session>1</Session><Number>45</Number><RegnalYear><Year-s>3-4</Year-s><Monarch>Charles III</Monarch></RegnalYear><Year-s>2025-2026</Year-s></Parliament><LongTitle>An Act to establish a national framework respecting skilled trades and labour mobility</LongTitle><ShortTitle status="unofficial">National Framework on Skilled Trades and Labour Mobility Act</ShortTitle><RunningHead>National Framework on Skilled Trades and Labour Mobility Act</RunningHead><BillHistory><Stages stage="first-reading-house"><Date><YYYY>2026</YYYY><MM>3</MM><DD>11</DD></Date></Stages></BillHistory><BillSponsor><Emphasis style="smallcaps">Mr. Bains</Emphasis></BillSponsor><BillRefNumber date-time="2026-03-05">451158</BillRefNumber></Identification><Introduction><Summary><TitleText>SUMMARY</TitleText><Provision><Text>This enactment provides for the development of a national framework for the recognition of skilled trades, harmonization of credential recognition and mobility of skilled trades workers in Canada.</Text></Provision></Summary><Preamble><Provision><MarginalNote>Preamble</MarginalNote><Text>Whereas the movement of skilled labour across Canada is essential to the country’s economic development, productivity, infrastructure delivery and competitiveness;</Text></Provision><Provision><Text>Whereas regulatory barriers, as well as inconsistencies between certification processes across provinces and territories, hinder the mobility of skilled trades workers and delay national development priorities, including housing construction, transportation infrastructure, energy projects and innovation capacity;</Text></Provision><Provision><Text>Whereas Parliament recognizes the importance of modernizing, harmonizing and streamlining credential recognition for skilled trades across the country while respecting provincial and territorial jurisdiction over training, certification and labour market regulation;</Text></Provision><Provision><Text>And whereas Parliament believes that strengthening recognition and portability in skilled trades will build Canada’s workforce capacity and contribute to a stronger and more resilient national economy;</Text></Provision></Preamble><Enacts><Provision><Text>Now, therefore, His Majesty, by and with the advice and consent <Keep>of the</Keep> Senate and House of Commons of Canada, <Keep>enacts</Keep> as follows:</Text></Provision></Enacts></Introduction><Body><Heading level="1"><TitleText>Short Title</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Short title</MarginalNote><Label>1</Label><Text>This Act may be cited as the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">National Framework on Skilled Trades and Labour Mobility Act</XRefExternal>.</Text></Section><Heading level="1"><TitleText>Interpretation</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Definitions</MarginalNote><Label>2</Label><Text>The following definitions apply in this Act.</Text><Definition><Text><DefinedTermEn>Minister</DefinedTermEn> means the Minister of Employment and Social Development. (<DefinedTermFr>ministre</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Definition><Definition><Text><DefinedTermEn>skilled trade</DefinedTermEn> means any trade that is recognized as a certified or otherwise regulated trade by any province, including any trade for which an endorsement can be obtained under the Interprovincial Standards Red Seal Program or a certification for Achievement in Business Competencies can be obtained under a Blue Seal program. (<DefinedTermFr>métier spécialisé</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Definition></Section><Heading level="1"><TitleText>National Framework Respecting Skilled Trades and Labour Mobility</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Development of national framework</MarginalNote><Label>3</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The Minister must develop a national framework respecting skilled trades and labour mobility to reduce barriers that prevent skilled trades workers from working interprovincially by modernizing, streamlining and harmonizing skilled trades certification processes and credentials across Canada.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Consultations</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>In developing the national framework, the Minister must hold consultations for at least nine months with relevant stakeholders, including representatives of</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>provincial governments;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>skilled trades regulatory bodies;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(c)</Label><Text>industry and employer associations;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(d)</Label><Text>labour unions and apprenticeship organizations;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(e)</Label><Text>Indigenous governing bodies and Indigenous organizations; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(f)</Label><Text>training and education institutions, such as colleges.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Contents</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>The national framework must</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>include a complete list of skilled trades across Canada;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>compare, assess and map equivalencies between provincial standards and credentials for skilled trades; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(c)</Label><Text>include measures to</Text><Subparagraph><Label>(i)</Label><Text>harmonize those standards and credentials across Canada,</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph><Label>(ii)</Label><Text>reduce duplication and streamline regulatory processes in relation to obtaining skilled trade credentials or having them recognized from one province to another,</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph><Label>(iii)</Label><Text>support the modernization of certification processes to reflect new technologies, industry standards and emerging trades,</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph><Label>(iv)</Label><Text>support ongoing collaboration with provinces, Indigenous communities, unions, employers, training institutions and regulatory bodies, and</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph><Label>(v)</Label><Text>promote public awareness of and respect for skilled trades and their economic importance.</Text></Subparagraph></Paragraph></Subsection></Section><Heading level="1"><TitleText>Reports to Parliament</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Tabling of national framework</MarginalNote><Label>4</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Within one year after the day on which this Act comes into force, the Minister must prepare a report setting out the national framework and cause it to be tabled in each House of Parliament on any of the first 15 days on which that House is sitting after the report is completed.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Publication</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The Minister must publish the report on the website of the Department of Employment and Social Development within 30 days after the day on which it is tabled in both Houses of Parliament.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Progress reports</MarginalNote><Label>5</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Within one year after the day on which the report is tabled under subsection 4(1), and every year after that, the Minister must prepare a progress report and cause it to be tabled in each House of Parliament on any of the first 15 days on which that House is sitting after the report is completed.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Contents</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Each progress report must contain</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>information on the progress made towards</Text><Subparagraph><Label>(i)</Label><Text>implementing the national framework,</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph><Label>(ii)</Label><Text>improving skilled trades mobility throughout Canada, and</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph><Label>(iii)</Label><Text>harmonizing, from one province to another, and modernizing skilled trades certification processes and credentials, as well as improving recognition for skilled trades;</Text></Subparagraph></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>outcomes of collaboration and consultations with provincial governments; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(c)</Label><Text>a review of the effectiveness of the framework, including the Minister’s conclusions and recommendations in respect of any updates or revisions to the national framework that the Minister considers appropriate.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Publication</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>The Minister must publish each progress report on the website of the Department of Employment and Social Development within 30 days after the day on which it is tabled in both Houses of Parliament.</Text></Subsection></Section><Heading level="1"><TitleText>Review of the National Framework</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Parliamentary review</MarginalNote><Label>6</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Within five years after the day on which this Act comes into force, a comprehensive review of the national framework must be undertaken by the committee of the Senate, of the House of Commons or of both Houses of Parliament that is designated or established for that purpose.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Report</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The committee must, within a year after the review is undertaken — or within any further period that the Senate, the House of Commons or both Houses of Parliament, as the case may be, authorize — submit a report on the review to the appropriate House, or in the case of a committee of both Houses, to each House, that includes a statement of any changes to the national framework that the committee recommends.</Text></Subsection></Section></Body></Bill>