<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><Bill bill-origin="commons" bill-type="private-public" xml:lang="en" date-time="2026-01-21 15:33:11"><Identification><BillNumber>C-268</BillNumber><Parliament><Session>1</Session><Number>45</Number><RegnalYear><Year-s>3-4</Year-s><Monarch>Charles III</Monarch></RegnalYear><Year-s>2025-2026</Year-s></Parliament><LongTitle>An Act respecting the Spectrum Policy Framework for Canada</LongTitle><ShortTitle status="unofficial" /><RunningHead>Spectrum Policy Framework for Canada Act</RunningHead><BillHistory><Stages stage="first-reading-house"><Date><YYYY>2026</YYYY><MM>3</MM><DD>12</DD></Date></Stages></BillHistory><BillSponsor><Emphasis style="smallcaps">Ms. Dandurand</Emphasis></BillSponsor><BillRefNumber date-time="2026-01-21">451132</BillRefNumber></Identification><Introduction><Summary><TitleText>SUMMARY</TitleText><Provision><Text>This enactment requires the Canadian Radio-television and Telecommunications Commission to establish a process for ensuring the accuracy of the mobile network coverage data provided by Canadian carriers. It also requires the Minister of Industry to maintain and update the Spectrum Policy Framework for Canada. Lastly, the enactment sets out review and reporting requirements respecting the Framework.</Text></Provision></Summary><Preamble><Provision><MarginalNote>Preamble</MarginalNote><Text>Whereas the Spectrum Policy Framework for Canada is a critical instrument for spectrum management and, in turn, for cellular connectivity in Canada;</Text></Provision><Provision><Text>Whereas the Framework was last updated in 2007;</Text></Provision><Provision><Text>Whereas existing mechanisms based on the obligations conveyed in spectrum authorizations are insufficient to resolve cellular connectivity issues, particularly in rural areas;</Text></Provision><Provision><Text>Whereas, due to the lack of competition in the wireless sector, telecommunications service providers
may lack the necessary incentives to expand network deployment in under-served areas, thereby hindering
universal connectivity and public safety;</Text></Provision><Provision><Text>Whereas Parliament considers that maintaining the Framework is necessary to address gaps in connectivity across the country;</Text></Provision><Provision><Text>Whereas service in many rural, remote and Indigenous communities and along lengthy stretches of numbered roads remains poor, undermining public safety and equal access;</Text></Provision><Provision><Text>And whereas it is desirable to create, by statute, an obligation to maintain and update the Framework;</Text></Provision></Preamble><Enacts><Provision language-align="yes"><Text>Now, therefore, His Majesty, by and with the advice and consent of the Senate and House of Commons of Canada, enacts as follows:</Text></Provision></Enacts></Introduction><Body><Heading level="1"><TitleText>Short Title</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Short title</MarginalNote><Label>1</Label><Text>This Act may be cited as the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Spectrum Policy Framework for Canada Act</XRefExternal>.</Text></Section><Heading level="1"><TitleText>Process for Ensuring Accurate Coverage Data</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Establishment of process</MarginalNote><Label>2</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Within six months after the day on which this Act comes into force, the Canadian Radio-television and Telecommunications Commission must establish a process to ensure the accuracy of the mobile network coverage data that <DefinitionRef>Canadian carriers</DefinitionRef>, within the meaning of subsection 2(1) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Telecommunications Act</XRefExternal>, provide to the Commission, including the data on the areas served and deployment requirements.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Clarification</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>For greater certainty, nothing in subsection (1) limits the powers, duties or functions of the Canadian Radio-television and Telecommunications Commission under any Act of Parliament.</Text></Subsection></Section><Heading level="1"><TitleText>Review of Spectrum Policy Framework for Canada</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Review of Framework</MarginalNote><Label>3</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Within 18 months after the day on which this Act comes into force, the Minister of Industry must undertake a comprehensive review of the Spectrum Policy Framework for Canada and cause a report on the review to be tabled in each House of Parliament on any of the first 15 days on which that House is sitting after the report is completed.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Consultations</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>For the purpose of the review, the Minister must consult</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>telecommunications service providers and spectrum licence holders;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>representatives of municipalities in rural and remote areas and of Indigenous communities;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(c)</Label><Text>public safety agencies and emergency services, including first responders;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(d)</Label><Text>researchers and academic experts who specialize in telecommunications and spectrum 
management;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(e)</Label><Text>the Canadian Radio-television and Telecommunications Commission; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(f)</Label><Text>any other stakeholder that the Minister considers appropriate.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Content of report</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>The report on the review must, among other things,</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>state the results of the consultations and take into account the issues raised during them, giving particular attention to competition matters, such as deployment requirements and new licensing of unused spectrum;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>assess connectivity in rural and remote areas and along numbered roads, particularly as regards public safety issues;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(c)</Label><Text>take into account telecommunications network coverage data; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(d)</Label><Text>set out any changes to the Framework that the Minister considers necessary.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Considerations</MarginalNote><Label>(4)</Label><Text>When setting out changes that are to be made to the Framework, the Minister must give priority to connectivity, including for rural and remote areas and numbered roads, taking into account the fact that competition and market forces have so far been insufficient to ensure connectivity across Canada as well as the coverage data that have been verified as accurate through the process established under section 2.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Publication</MarginalNote><Label>(5)</Label><Text>The Minister must publish the report on the website of the Department of Industry within 30 days after the day on which the report is tabled in both Houses of Parliament.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Five-year review</MarginalNote><Label>4</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Within five years after the day on which the report referred to in subsection 3(1) is tabled in both Houses of Parliament, and every five years after that day, the Minister of Industry must prepare a report on the implementation and effectiveness of the Framework that sets out the Minister’s conclusions and recommendations and cause the report to be tabled in each House of Parliament on any of the first 15 days on which that House is sitting after it is completed.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Publication</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The Minister must publish the report on the website of the Department of Industry within 30 days after the day on which the report is tabled in both Houses of Parliament.</Text></Subsection></Section></Body></Bill>