<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><Bill bill-origin="commons" bill-type="private-public" xml:lang="en" date-time="2026-03-23 13:18:42"><Identification><BillNumber>C-272</BillNumber><Parliament><Session>1</Session><Number>45</Number><RegnalYear><Year-s>3-4</Year-s><Monarch>Charles III</Monarch></RegnalYear><Year-s>2025-2026</Year-s></Parliament><LongTitle>An Act to amend the Controlled Drugs and Substances Act (supervised drug consumption sites)</LongTitle><ShortTitle status="unofficial" /><RunningHead>An Act to amend the Controlled Drugs and Substances Act (supervised drug consumption sites)</RunningHead><BillHistory><Stages stage="first-reading-house"><Date><YYYY>2026</YYYY><MM>3</MM><DD>26</DD></Date></Stages></BillHistory><BillSponsor><Emphasis style="smallcaps">Mr. Mazier</Emphasis></BillSponsor><BillRefNumber date-time="2026-03-23">451172</BillRefNumber></Identification><Introduction><Summary><TitleText>SUMMARY</TitleText><Provision><Text>This enactment amends the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Controlled Drugs and Substances Act</XRefExternal> to provide that regulations made and exemptions granted under that Act must not have the effect of allowing a site providing services in relation to the consumption of certain substances to be located within 500 metres of an elementary or secondary school, a daycare centre or a playground.</Text></Provision></Summary><Enacts><Provision><Text>His Majesty, by and with the advice and consent <Keep>of the</Keep> Senate and House of Commons of Canada, <Keep>enacts</Keep> as follows:</Text></Provision></Enacts></Introduction><Body><Heading level="1"><MarginalNote><HistoricalNote>1996, c. 19</HistoricalNote></MarginalNote><TitleText>Controlled Drugs and Substances Act</TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><Label>1</Label><Text>The <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Controlled Drugs and Substances Act</XRefExternal> is amended by adding the following after the heading “Regulations and Exemptions” before section 55:</Text><AmendedText><Section change="ins"><MarginalNote>Restriction — regulations and exemptions</MarginalNote><Label>54.2</Label><Text>Despite any other provision of this Act, regulations made and exemptions granted under this Act must not have the effect of allowing a site providing services in relation to the consumption of any controlled substance or precursor — or any class of either of them — that is obtained in a manner not authorized under this Act to be located within 500 metres of an elementary or secondary school, a daycare centre or a playground.</Text></Section></AmendedText></Section><Heading level="1"><TitleText>Transitional Provision</TitleText></Heading><Section type="transitional"><MarginalNote>Exemptions and authorizations in force</MarginalNote><Label>2</Label><Text>Any exemption or authorization that is granted or issued under the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Controlled Drugs and Substances Act</XRefExternal>, that is valid on the day on which this Act comes into force and that applies, directly or indirectly, in respect of a site providing services in relation to the consumption of any controlled substance or precursor — or any class of either of them — that is obtained in a manner not authorized under that Act is </Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>revoked on that day, to the extent that the exemption or authorization applies in respect of a site located within 500 metres of an elementary or secondary school, a daycare centre or a playground; or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>deemed to include as a condition that such services must not be provided at the site when it is within 500 metres of an elementary or secondary school, a daycare centre or a playground, if the exemption or authorization applies in respect of a mobile site.</Text></Paragraph></Section><Heading level="1"><TitleText>Coming into Force</TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote>180 days after royal assent</MarginalNote><Label>3</Label><Text>This Act comes into force 180 days after the day on which it receives royal assent.</Text></Section></Body></Bill>