<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><Bill bill-origin="senate" bill-type="private-public" xml:lang="en" date-time="2022-10-06 08:44:04"><Identification><BillNumber>S-202</BillNumber><Parliament><Session>1</Session><Number>45</Number><RegnalYear><Year-s>3</Year-s><Monarch>Charles III</Monarch></RegnalYear><Year-s>2025</Year-s></Parliament><LongTitle>An Act to amend the Food and Drugs Act (warning <Keep>label</Keep> on alcoholic beverages)</LongTitle><ShortTitle status="unofficial" /><RunningHead>An Act to amend the Food and Drugs Act (warning label on alcoholic beverages)</RunningHead><BillHistory><Stages stage="first-reading-senate"><Date><YYYY>2025</YYYY><MM>5</MM><DD>28</DD></Date></Stages></BillHistory><BillSponsor>Senator BRAZEAU</BillSponsor><BillRefNumber date-time="">4512223</BillRefNumber></Identification><Introduction><Summary><TitleText>SUMMARY</TitleText><Provision><Text>This enactment amends the <XRefExternal reference-type="act" reference-level="federal">Food and Drugs Act</XRefExternal> to require a warning label on alcoholic beverages.</Text></Provision></Summary><Preamble><Provision language-align="yes"><MarginalNote>Preamble</MarginalNote><Text>Whereas Parliament recognizes that a direct causal link exists between alcohol consumption and the <Keep>development</Keep> of fatal cancers;</Text></Provision><Provision><Text>Whereas, in light of the serious public health risks posed by alcohol consumption, the public must have accurate and current health information relating to <Keep>alcohol</Keep> consumption to make informed decisions about consuming alcohol;</Text></Provision><Provision><Text>And whereas affixing a warning label to alcoholic beverages is an effective way of making consumers aware of this health information;</Text></Provision></Preamble><Enacts><Provision><Text>Now, therefore, His Majesty, by and with the advice and consent of the Senate and House of Commons of Canada, enacts as follows:</Text></Provision></Enacts></Introduction><Body><Heading level="1"><MarginalNote><HistoricalNote>R.S., ch. F-27</HistoricalNote></MarginalNote><TitleText><XRefExternal reference-type="act" reference-level="federal">Food and Drugs Act</XRefExternal></TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><Label>1</Label><Text>The <XRefExternal reference-type="act" reference-level="federal">Food and Drugs Act</XRefExternal> is amended by adding the following after section 5:</Text><AmendedText change="ins"><Section><MarginalNote>Alcoholic beverages — warning</MarginalNote><Label>5.1</Label><Text>No person shall sell a beverage that contains 1.1 per cent or more alcohol by volume unless the package in which it is sold bears, in the prescribed form and manner, a label warning against the risks of alcohol consumption to the health of consumers and showing, in addition to any other prescribed information,</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>the volume of beverage that, in the opinion of the Department, constitutes a standard drink;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>the number of standard drinks in the package;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(c)</Label><Text>the number of standard drinks that, in the opinion of the Department, should not be exceeded in order to avoid significant health risks; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(d)</Label><Text>a message from the Department that sets out the direct causal link between alcohol consumption and the development of fatal cancers.</Text></Paragraph></Section></AmendedText><ExplanatoryNote><TitleText><XRefExternal reference-type="act" reference-level="federal">Food and Drugs Act</XRefExternal></TitleText><Label><Emphasis style="italic">Clause 1</Emphasis>:</Label><ExplanatoryText>New.</ExplanatoryText></ExplanatoryNote></Section><Heading level="1"><TitleText>Coming into Force</TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote>One year after royal assent</MarginalNote><Label>2</Label><Text>This Act comes into force on the first anniversary of the day on which it receives royal assent.</Text></Section></Body></Bill>