<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><Bill bill-origin="senate" bill-type="private-public" xml:lang="en" date-time="2021-09-13 14:58:29"><Identification><BillNumber>S-206</BillNumber><Parliament><Session>1</Session><Number>45</Number><RegnalYear><Year-s>3</Year-s><Monarch>Charles III</Monarch></RegnalYear><Year-s>2025</Year-s></Parliament><LongTitle>An Act to develop a national framework for a guaranteed livable basic income</LongTitle><ShortTitle status="unofficial">National Framework for a Guaranteed Livable Basic Income Act</ShortTitle><RunningHead>National Framework for a Guaranteed Livable Basic Income Act</RunningHead><BillHistory><Stages stage="first-reading-senate"><Date><YYYY>2025</YYYY><MM>5</MM><DD>28</DD></Date></Stages></BillHistory><BillSponsor>Senator PATE</BillSponsor><BillRefNumber date-time="">4512114</BillRefNumber></Identification><Introduction><Summary><TitleText>SUMMARY</TitleText><Provision><Text>This enactment requires the Minister of Finance to develop a national framework to provide all persons over the age of 17 in Canada with access to a guaranteed livable basic income. It also provides for reporting requirements with respect to the framework.</Text></Provision></Summary><Preamble><Provision pointsize="10" topmarginspacing="-6" language-align="yes"><MarginalNote>Preamble</MarginalNote><Text>Whereas every person should have access to a livable basic income;</Text></Provision><Provision><Text>Whereas the provision of a guaranteed livable basic income would go a long way towards eradicating poverty and improving income equality, health conditions, educational outcomes and food and housing security, as well as supporting unremunerated care work and those faced with a precarious labour market;</Text></Provision><Provision><Text>Whereas the provision of a guaranteed livable basic income would benefit individuals, families and communities and protect those who are made most vulnerable in society while also facilitating the transition to an economy that responds to the climate crisis and other current major challenges;</Text></Provision><Provision><Text>And whereas a guaranteed livable basic income program implemented through a national framework would ensure the respect, dignity and security of all persons in Canada;</Text></Provision></Preamble><Enacts><Provision language-align="yes"><Text>Now, therefore, His Majesty, by and with the advice and consent of the Senate and House of Commons of Canada, enacts as follows:
</Text></Provision></Enacts></Introduction><Body><Heading level="1"><TitleText>Short Title</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Short title
</MarginalNote><Label>1</Label><Text>This Act may be cited as the <Emphasis style="italic">National Framework for a Guaranteed Livable Basic Income Act</Emphasis>.</Text></Section><Heading level="1"><TitleText>Interpretation</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Definitions</MarginalNote><Label>2</Label><Text>The following definitions apply in this Act.<DefinedTermEn /></Text><Provision><Text><DefinedTermEn>Indigenous Elder</DefinedTermEn> means an individual who is a member of an Indigenous group, community or People that holds rights recognized and affirmed by section 35 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act" reference-level="federal">Constitution Act, 1982</XRefExternal> and who is recognized by the members of that group, community or People as an Elder. (<DefinedTermFr>Aîné autochtone</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Provision><Provision><Text><DefinedTermEn>Indigenous governing body</DefinedTermEn> means a council, government or other entity that is authorized to act on behalf of an Indigenous group, community or People that holds rights recognized and affirmed by section 35 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Constitution Act, 1982</XRefExternal>. (<DefinedTermFr>corps dirigeant autochtone</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Provision><Provision><Text><DefinedTermEn>Minister</DefinedTermEn> means the Minister of Finance. (<DefinedTermFr>ministre</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Provision></Section><Heading level="1"><TitleText>National Framework</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Development</MarginalNote><Label>3</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The Minister must develop a national framework for the implementation of a guaranteed livable basic <Keep>income</Keep> program throughout Canada for any person over the age of 17.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Consultation</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>In developing the framework, the Minister must consult with the Minister of Health, the ministers responsible for employment, social development, housing and disability, representatives of the provincial governments responsible for health, disability, education, housing and social development, Indigenous Elders, Indigenous governing bodies and other relevant stakeholders, including policy developers and political decision-makers, as well as experts in other guaranteed livable basic income programs.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><Label>(3)</Label><Text>In developing the framework, the Minister must also consider the jurisdictional responsibilities of federal, provincial and Indigenous governments.
</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Content</MarginalNote><Label>(4)</Label><Text>The framework must include measures</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>to determine what constitutes a livable basic income for each region in Canada, taking into account the goods and services that are necessary to ensure that individuals can lead a dignified and healthy life, as well as the cost of those goods and services in accessible markets;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>to create national standards for health and social supports that complement a guaranteed basic income program and guide the implementation of such a program in every province;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(c)</Label><Text>to ensure that participation in education, training or the labour market is not required in order to qualify for a guaranteed livable basic income; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(d)</Label><Text>to ensure that the implementation of a guaranteed livable basic income program does not result in a <Keep>decrease</Keep> in services or benefits meant to meet an individual’s exceptional needs related to health or disability.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection></Section><Heading level="1"><TitleText>Reports to Parliament</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Tabling of framework</MarginalNote><Label>4</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Within one year after the day on which this Act comes into force, the Minister must prepare a report setting out the framework, including any social, health and economic conclusions and recommendations related to its development, and cause the report to be tabled in each House of Parliament on any of the first 15 days on which that House is sitting after the report is completed.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Publication</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The Minister must publish the report on the Department of Finance website within 10 days after the report has been tabled in both Houses of Parliament.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Report</MarginalNote><Label>5</Label><Text>Within two years after the report referred to in section 4 has been tabled in both Houses of Parliament, and every year after that, the Minister must, in consultation with the parties referred to in subsection 3(2), undertake a review of the effectiveness of the framework, prepare a report setting out the social, health and economic findings and recommendations related to the implementation and effectiveness of the framework, and cause the report to be tabled in each House of Parliament on any of the first 15 days on which that House is sitting after it is completed.</Text></Section></Body></Bill>