<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><Bill bill-origin="senate" bill-type="private-public" xml:lang="en" date-time="2024-11-25 10:03:54"><Identification><BillNumber>S-219</BillNumber><Parliament><Session>1</Session><Number>45</Number><RegnalYear><Year-s>3</Year-s><Monarch>Charles III</Monarch></RegnalYear><Year-s>2025</Year-s></Parliament><LongTitle>An Act to establish Judicial Independence Day</LongTitle><ShortTitle status="unofficial">Judicial Independence Day Act</ShortTitle><RunningHead>Judicial Independence Day Act</RunningHead><BillHistory><Stages stage="first-reading-senate"><Date><YYYY>2025</YYYY><MM>5</MM><DD>28</DD></Date></Stages></BillHistory><BillSponsor>Senator MOREAU</BillSponsor><BillRefNumber date-time="">4512408</BillRefNumber></Identification><Introduction><Summary><TitleText>SUMMARY</TitleText><Provision><Text>This enactment designates January 11th in each and every year as “Judicial Independence Day”. </Text></Provision></Summary><Preamble><Provision language-align="yes" pointsize="10" topmarginspacing="-6"><MarginalNote>Preamble</MarginalNote><Text>Whereas the rule of law is fundamental to maintaining a democratic society and upholding human rights;</Text></Provision><Provision><Text>Whereas maintaining the rule of law requires a judiciary consisting of judges who are impartial and <Keep>independent</Keep> in the face of political pressures and <Keep>interference</Keep> attempts;</Text></Provision><Provision><Text>Whereas, in particular, the independence of the judiciary depends on a judicial appointment and promotion process that is based on candidate merit and on fair, impartial and transparent disciplinary mechanisms;</Text></Provision><Provision><Text>Whereas, on January 11, 2020, tens of thousands of people, including hundreds of judges from 22 European countries, took part in the “<Keep>1,000 Robes</Keep> March” in Warsaw to express their opposition to attacks on judicial independence in Poland;</Text></Provision><Provision><Text>Whereas the International Association of Judges formally requested that the United Nations commemorate the <Keep>1,000 Robes</Keep> March, in part to mark judges’ brave and peaceful mobilization for an independent judiciary;</Text></Provision><Provision><Text>And whereas Parliament recognizes the importance of drawing public attention to the threats to judicial independence in many countries of the world;</Text></Provision></Preamble><Enacts><Provision><Text>Now, therefore, His Majesty, by and with the advice and consent of the Senate and House of Commons of Canada, enacts as follows:</Text></Provision></Enacts></Introduction><Body><Heading level="1"><TitleText>Short Title</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Short title</MarginalNote><Label>1</Label><Text>This Act may be cited as the <Emphasis style="italic">Judicial Independence Day Act</Emphasis>.</Text></Section><Heading level="1"><TitleText> Judicial Independence Day</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Judicial Independence Day</MarginalNote><Label>2</Label><Text>Throughout Canada, in each and every year, the 11th day of <Keep>January</Keep> is to be known as “Judicial Independence Day”.</Text></Section></Body></Bill>