<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><Bill bill-origin="senate" bill-type="private-public" xml:lang="en" date-time="2023-09-06 14:59:11"><Identification><BillNumber>S-216</BillNumber><Parliament><Session>1</Session><Number>45</Number><RegnalYear><Year-s>3</Year-s><Monarch>Charles III</Monarch></RegnalYear><Year-s>2025</Year-s></Parliament><LongTitle>An Act to declare the Chignecto Isthmus Dykeland System and related works to be for the general advantage of Canada</LongTitle><ShortTitle status="unofficial">Chignecto Isthmus Dykeland System Act</ShortTitle><RunningHead>Chignecto Isthmus Dykeland System Act</RunningHead><BillHistory><Stages stage="first-reading-senate"><Date><YYYY>2025</YYYY><MM>5</MM><DD>28</DD></Date></Stages></BillHistory><BillSponsor>Senator QUINN</BillSponsor><BillRefNumber date-time="">4512316</BillRefNumber></Identification><Introduction><Summary><TitleText>SUMMARY</TitleText><Provision><Text>This enactment declares the Chignecto Isthmus Dykeland System and related works to be works for the general advantage of Canada.</Text></Provision></Summary><Preamble><Provision pointsize="10" topmarginspacing="-6" language-align="yes"><MarginalNote>Preamble</MarginalNote><Text>Whereas the Chignecto Isthmus, located in Nova Scotia and New Brunswick, is an interprovincial surface and rail trade corridor of national importance;</Text></Provision><Provision><Text>Whereas the Intercolonial Railway constructed along the Chignecto Isthmus, in accordance with section 145 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act" reference-level="federal">Constitution Act, 1867</XRefExternal>, physically united the Canadian federation by linking the province of Nova Scotia with the provinces of Ontario and Quebec;</Text></Provision><Provision><Text>Whereas Parliament passed, in 1948, the <XRefExternal reference-type="act" reference-level="federal">Maritime Marshland Rehabilitation Act</XRefExternal>, which provided for the Government of Canada to construct and reconstruct dykes, aboiteaux and breakwaters;</Text></Provision><Provision><Text>Whereas the Chignecto Isthmus is of critical cultural and historical significance to the Mi芒聙聶kmaq and Acadian peoples;</Text></Provision><Provision><Text>Whereas the Chignecto Isthmus is currently vulnerable to the effects of rising sea levels and increasingly intense severe weather events that threaten this interprovincial surface and rail trade corridor of national importance;</Text></Provision><Provision><Text>And whereas the Governments of Nova Scotia and New Brunswick have undertaken the <XRefExternal reference-type="other" reference-level="provincial">Chignecto Isthmus Climate Change Adaptation Comprehensive <Keep>Engineering</Keep> and Feasibility Study</XRefExternal> to expeditiously mitigate impacts of climate change on the communities and farmlands located within the Chignecto Isthmus;</Text></Provision></Preamble><Enacts><Provision><Text>Now, therefore, His Majesty, by and with the advice and consent of the Senate and House of Commons of Canada, enacts as follows:</Text></Provision></Enacts></Introduction><Body><Heading level="1"><TitleText>Short Title</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Short title</MarginalNote><Label>1</Label><Text>This Act may be cited as the <Emphasis style="italic">Chignecto Isthmus Dykeland System Act</Emphasis>.</Text></Section><Heading level="1"><TitleText>Interpretation</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Definitions</MarginalNote><Label>2</Label><Text>The following definitions apply in this Act.</Text><Definition><Text><DefinedTermEn>Chignecto Isthmus Dykeland System</DefinedTermEn> means</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>a dyke system intended for water management wholly situated in the Nova Scotia portion of the Chignecto Isthmus trade corridor; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>a dyke system intended for water management wholly situated in the New Brunswick portion of the Chignecto Isthmus trade corridor. (<DefinedTermFr>r脙漏seau de digues de l芒聙聶isthme de Chignecto</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Paragraph></Definition><Definition><Text><DefinedTermEn>construction</DefinedTermEn>,芒聙聜in relation to a dyke or a related work, <Keep>includes</Keep> the demolition of existing structures and any other work or activity related to the dyke芒聙聶s or related work芒聙聶s construction. (<DefinedTermFr>construction</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Definition><Definition><Text><DefinedTermEn>dyke</DefinedTermEn> means a dyke, aboiteau or breakwater associated with the Chignecto Isthmus Dykeland System. (<DefinedTermFr>digue</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Definition><Definition><Text><DefinedTermEn>Indigenous governing body</DefinedTermEn> means a
council, government or other entity that is
authorized to act on behalf of an
Indigenous group, community or people
that holds rights recognized and affirmed
by section 35 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act" reference-level="federal">Constitution Act, 1982</XRefExternal>. (<DefinedTermFr>corps dirigeant autochtone</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Definition><Definition><Text><DefinedTermEn>Indigenous organization</DefinedTermEn> means an
Indigenous governing body or any other
entity that represents the interests of an
Indigenous group and its members. (<DefinedTermFr>organisation autochtone</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Definition><Definition><Text><DefinedTermEn>Indigenous peoples</DefinedTermEn> has the meaning
assigned by the definition <DefinitionRef>aboriginal
peoples of Canada</DefinitionRef> in subsection 35(2) of
the <XRefExternal reference-type="act" reference-level="federal">Constitution Act, 1982</XRefExternal>. (<DefinedTermFr>peuples autochtones</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Definition><Definition><Text><DefinedTermEn>Minister</DefinedTermEn> means the Minister of Infrastructure and <Keep>Communities</Keep>. (<DefinedTermFr>ministre</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Definition><Definition><Text><DefinedTermEn>person</DefinedTermEn>芒聙聜means an individual, corporation, partnership, joint venture, Indigenous
governing body or Indigenous
organization.芒聙聜(<DefinedTermFr>personne</DefinedTermFr>)<PageBreak /></Text></Definition><Definition><Text><DefinedTermEn>related work</DefinedTermEn>芒聙聜means any of the following:</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>a water level control structure;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>a steel sheet pile wall; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(c)</Label><Text>any work that is useful for the maintenance or <Keep>operation</Keep> of a dyke or water level control structure. (<DefinedTermFr><Keep>ouvrage</Keep> connexe</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Paragraph></Definition></Section><Heading level="1"><TitleText>Application</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Role of Minister</MarginalNote><Label>3</Label><Text>Except as otherwise provided in this Act, the Minister is responsible for the administration of this Act, and the Minister芒聙聶s powers, duties and functions include all matters relating to the Chignecto Isthmus Dykeland System and related works.</Text></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Declaration</MarginalNote><Label>4</Label><Text>The Chignecto Isthmus Dykeland System and related works are declared to be works for the general advantage of Canada.</Text></Section><Heading level="1"><TitleText>Agreements</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Minister of Public Works and Government Services</MarginalNote><Label>5</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The Minister of Public Works and Government Services may enter into an agreement with any person for any purpose relating to the design, construction or operation of the Chignecto Isthmus Dykeland System or any related work.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Authority to carry out agreement</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The Minister of Public Works and Government Services may take any measures that the minister considers appropriate to carry out the agreement or to protect the interests or enforce the rights of His Majesty in right of Canada under the agreement, including accepting and holding on behalf of His Majesty any security granted <Keep>under</Keep> the agreement or releasing or realizing on that <Keep>security</Keep>.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Not agent of His Majesty</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>A person who enters into an agreement with the <Keep>Minister</Keep> of Public Works and Government Services <Keep>under</Keep> this section is not an agent of His Majesty in right of Canada.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Implementation</MarginalNote><Label>6</Label><Text>The Minister may enter into any agreement that <Keep>relates</Keep> to the Chignecto Isthmus Dykeland System or <Keep>related</Keep> works, or any agreement that is necessary for the implementation of an agreement entered into under <Keep>section</Keep> 4, with any person or with the Government of <Keep>Nova</Keep> Scotia or the Government of New Brunswick or any municipality or agency of either province.</Text></Section><Heading level="1"><TitleText>Order in Council</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Other exemptions</MarginalNote><Label>7</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>In response to an emergency, the Governor in Council may, by order, exempt any person, on any condition that the Governor in Council considers to be in the interest of
preventing damage to the environment or
in the interest of public health or safety,
from any requirement under any federal Act to obtain a permit, <Keep>licence</Keep>, approval or other authorization in relation to the construction of the Chignecto Isthmus Dykeland System or any related work.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Exemption from <XRefExternal reference-type="act" reference-level="federal">Statutory Instruments Act</XRefExternal></MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The <XRefExternal reference-type="act" reference-level="federal">Statutory Instruments Act</XRefExternal> does not apply to an order made under subsection (1), but the order must be published in the <XRefExternal reference-type="other" reference-level="federal">Canada Gazette</XRefExternal>.</Text></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Authorizations deemed issued</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>After completion of the construction of the Chignecto Isthmus Dykeland System or of a related work, as the case may be, any authorization that would have been <Keep>required</Keep> in relation to its construction, if not for an <Keep>exemption</Keep> granted under subsection (1), is deemed to have been issued for the purpose of the application of the federal Act for which the exemption was granted.</Text></Section></Body></Bill>