<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><Bill bill-origin="senate" bill-type="private-public" xml:lang="en" date-time="2022-09-20 11:05:47"><Identification><BillNumber>S-226</BillNumber><Parliament><Session>1</Session><Number>45</Number><RegnalYear><Year-s>3</Year-s><Monarch>Charles III</Monarch></RegnalYear><Year-s>2025</Year-s></Parliament><LongTitle>An Act respecting Jury Duty Appreciation Week</LongTitle><ShortTitle status="unofficial">Jury Duty Appreciation Week Act</ShortTitle><RunningHead>Jury Duty Appreciation Week Act</RunningHead><BillHistory><Stages stage="first-reading-senate"><Date><YYYY>2025</YYYY><MM>6</MM><DD>5</DD></Date></Stages></BillHistory><BillSponsor>Senator MONCION</BillSponsor><BillRefNumber date-time="">4512217</BillRefNumber></Identification><Introduction><Summary><TitleText>SUMMARY</TitleText><Provision><Text>This enactment designates the second week of May in each and every year as “Jury Duty Appreciation Week”.</Text></Provision></Summary><Preamble><Provision language-align="yes"><MarginalNote>Preamble</MarginalNote><Text>Whereas jury duty is a civic duty that thousands of Canadians are called upon to perform every year;</Text></Provision><Provision><Text>Whereas jury duty is a vital component of our justice system and our democracy;</Text></Provision><Provision><Text>Whereas the well-being and mental health of jurors are paramount to the proper functioning of our justice system;</Text></Provision><Provision><Text>And whereas designating a week dedicated to the <Keep>appreciation</Keep> of jury duty will highlight the work that jurors do and will help to educate citizens, organizations, the justice system as a whole, and the provincial and federal governments about the issues involved in fulfilling this civic duty;</Text></Provision></Preamble><Enacts><Provision><Text>Now, therefore, His Majesty, by and with the advice and consent of the Senate and House of Commons of Canada, enacts as follows:</Text></Provision></Enacts></Introduction><Body><Heading level="1"><TitleText>Short Title</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Short title</MarginalNote><Label>1</Label><Text>This Act may be cited as the <Emphasis style="italic">Jury Duty Appreciation Week Act</Emphasis>.</Text></Section><Heading level="1"><TitleText>Jury Duty Appreciation Week</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Jury Duty Appreciation Week</MarginalNote><Label>2</Label><Text>Throughout Canada, in each and every year, the second week of May shall be known as “Jury Duty Appreciation Week”.</Text></Section></Body></Bill>