<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><Bill bill-origin="senate" bill-type="private-public" xml:lang="en" date-time="2023-06-19 15:26:36"><Identification><BillNumber>S-223</BillNumber><Parliament><Session>1</Session><Number>45</Number><RegnalYear><Year-s>3</Year-s><Monarch>Charles III</Monarch></RegnalYear><Year-s>2025</Year-s></Parliament><LongTitle>An Act to amend the Royal Canadian Mounted Police Act</LongTitle><ShortTitle status="unofficial" /><RunningHead>An Act to amend the Royal Canadian Mounted Police Act</RunningHead><BillHistory><Stages stage="first-reading-senate"><Date><YYYY>2025</YYYY><MM>6</MM><DD>3</DD></Date></Stages></BillHistory><BillSponsor>Senator M<Sup>C</Sup>CALLUM</BillSponsor><BillRefNumber date-time="">4512323</BillRefNumber></Identification><Introduction><Summary><TitleText>SUMMARY</TitleText><Provision><Text>This enactment amends the <XRefExternal reference-type="act" reference-level="federal">Royal Canadian Mounted Police Act</XRefExternal> to provide that the duties of members who are peace officers <Keep>include</Keep> the prevention of offences against First Nation laws and the execution of warrants that may, under First Nation laws, be lawfully executed and performed by peace officers.</Text></Provision></Summary><Enacts><Provision><Text>His Majesty, by and with the advice and consent of the Senate and House of Commons of Canada, enacts as follows:</Text></Provision></Enacts></Introduction><Body><Heading level="1"><MarginalNote><HistoricalNote>R.S., c. R-10</HistoricalNote></MarginalNote><TitleText><XRefExternal reference-type="act" reference-level="federal">Royal Canadian Mounted Police Act</XRefExternal></TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><Label>1</Label><Text>Subsection 2(1) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act" reference-level="federal">Royal Canadian Mounted Police Act</XRefExternal> is amended by adding the following in alphabetical order:</Text><AmendedText change="ins"><SectionPiece><Definition><Text><DefinedTermEn>First Nation law</DefinedTermEn> means</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>a bylaw made under the <XRefExternal reference-type="act" reference-level="federal">Indian Act</XRefExternal>;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>a <DefinitionRef>First Nation law</DefinitionRef> as defined in subsection 2(1) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act" reference-level="federal">Framework Agreement on First Nation Land Management Act</XRefExternal>; or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(c)</Label><Text>a law enacted by a council, government or other entity that is authorized to act on behalf of a First <Keep>Nation</Keep> under a self-government agreement implemented by an Act of Parliament. (<DefinedTermFr>texte législatif de première nation</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Paragraph></Definition></SectionPiece></AmendedText><ExplanatoryNote><TitleText><XRefExternal reference-type="act" reference-level="federal">Royal Canadian Mounted Police Act</XRefExternal></TitleText><Label><Emphasis style="italic">Clause 1</Emphasis>:</Label><ExplanatoryText>New.</ExplanatoryText></ExplanatoryNote></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>2</Label><Text>Paragraphs 18(a) and (b) of the Act are replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>to perform all duties that are assigned to peace <Keep>officers</Keep> in relation to the preservation of the peace, the prevention of crime and of offences against the laws of Canada, the laws in force in any province in which they may be employed <Ins>and First Nation laws,</Ins> and the apprehension of criminals and offenders and others who may be lawfully taken into custody;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>to execute all warrants, and perform all duties and services in relation thereto, that may, under this Act or the laws of Canada, the laws in force in any province or <Ins>First Nation laws,</Ins> be lawfully executed and performed by peace officers;</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText><ExplanatoryNote><Label><Emphasis style="italic">Clause 2</Emphasis>:</Label><ExplanatoryText>Text of relevant portions of section 18:</ExplanatoryText><ExistingText><Section><Label>18</Label><Text>It is the duty of members who are peace officers, subject to the orders of the Commissioner,</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text> to perform all duties that are assigned to peace officers in <Keep>relation</Keep> to the preservation of the peace, the prevention of crime and of offences against the laws of Canada and the laws in force in any province in which they may be employed, and the apprehension of criminals and offenders and others who may be lawfully taken into custody;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>to execute all warrants, and perform all duties and services in relation thereto, that may, under this Act or the laws of Canada or the laws in force in any province, be lawfully executed and <Keep>performed</Keep> by peace officers;</Text></Paragraph></Section></ExistingText></ExplanatoryNote></Section></Body></Bill>