<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><Bill bill-origin="senate" bill-type="private-public" xml:lang="en" date-time="2024-10-07 15:44:03"><Identification><BillNumber>S-229</BillNumber><Parliament><Session>1</Session><Number>45</Number><RegnalYear><Year-s>3</Year-s><Monarch>Charles III</Monarch></RegnalYear><Year-s>2025</Year-s></Parliament><LongTitle>An Act to amend the National Capital Act (Gatineau Park)</LongTitle><ShortTitle status="unofficial">Gatineau Park Act</ShortTitle><RunningHead>Gatineau Park Act</RunningHead><BillHistory><Stages stage="first-reading-senate"><Date><YYYY>2025</YYYY><MM>6</MM><DD>10</DD></Date></Stages></BillHistory><BillSponsor>Senator GALVEZ</BillSponsor><BillRefNumber date-time="">4512406</BillRefNumber></Identification><Introduction><Summary><TitleText>SUMMARY</TitleText><Provision><Text>The bill amends the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">National Capital Act</XRefExternal> to, among other things,</Text></Provision><Provision first-line-indent="1" subsequent-line-indent="1" language-align="no"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>establish the boundaries of Gatineau Park;</Text></Provision><Provision first-line-indent="1" subsequent-line-indent="1" language-align="no"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>prioritize the ecological integrity of the park in its management by the National Capital Commission (NCC);</Text></Provision><Provision first-line-indent="1" subsequent-line-indent="1" language-align="no"><Label>(c)</Label><Text>prohibit the sale of public lands located within the park, with certain exceptions;</Text></Provision><Provision first-line-indent="1" subsequent-line-indent="1" language-align="no"><Label>(d)</Label><Text>strengthen consultation and collaboration between the NCC, the Algonquin Anishinabeg Nation and neighbouring municipalities;</Text></Provision><Provision first-line-indent="1" subsequent-line-indent="1" language-align="no"><Label>(e)</Label><Text>promote the use of services from businesses and workers of the Algonquin Anishinabeg Nation for maintenance and conservation activities in Gatineau Park;</Text></Provision><Provision first-line-indent="1" subsequent-line-indent="1" language-align="no"><Label>(f)</Label><Text>authorize the creation of regulations to oversee activities in the park and set corresponding fees.</Text></Provision></Summary><TableOfProvisions><Heading level="1"><TitleText>TABLE OF PROVISIONS</TitleText></Heading><Heading level="1"><TitleText>An Act to amend the National Capital Act (Gatineau Park)</TitleText></Heading><Label /><Text>Preamble</Text><Heading level="1"><TitleText>Short Title</TitleText></Heading><Label>1</Label><Text><Emphasis style="italic">Gatineau Park Act</Emphasis></Text><Heading level="1"><TitleText><XRefExternal reference-type="act" reference-level="federal">National Capital Act</XRefExternal></TitleText></Heading><Label>2</Label><Text>Definitions</Text><Label>3</Label><Text>Amendments</Text><Heading level="1"><TitleText>Consequential Amendments</TitleText></Heading><Label>9</Label><Text>References</Text><Heading level="1"><Label>SCHEDULE</Label></Heading></TableOfProvisions><Preamble><Provision pointsize="10" topmarginspacing="-6" language-align="yes"><MarginalNote>Preamble</MarginalNote><Text>Whereas Parliament recognizes that it is essential to ensure that the natural environment of the National Capital Region, and especially Gatineau Park, is preserved for the enjoyment of all Canadians;</Text></Provision><Provision><Text>Whereas Gatineau Park is located on the unceded traditional lands of the Algonquin Anishinabeg Nation;</Text></Provision><Provision><Text>Whereas it is important to connect Canadians with the natural and cultural heritage of the National Capital Region and with the history of its early Indigenous inhabitants, consistent with the <XRefExternal reference-type="act" reference-level="federal">United Nations Declaration on the Rights of Indigenous Peoples Act</XRefExternal>, and of others who have shaped its landscapes;</Text></Provision><Provision><Text>Whereas the National Capital Commission requires the legislative and regulatory tools necessary to effectively manage Gatineau Park;</Text></Provision><Provision><Text>Whereas Gatineau Park is a regional and national treasure promoting recreational activities respectful of the environment and must be acknowledged and defined as such;</Text></Provision><Provision><Text>Whereas Gatineau Park is home to diverse natural ecosystems and a significant number of plant and animal species at risk;</Text></Provision><Provision><Text>Whereas Parliament recognizes the importance of preserving the ecological integrity of Gatineau Park;</Text></Provision><Provision><Text>And whereas strengthening the effective management of protected areas is a commitment made by the government of Canada under the Kunming-Montreal Global Biodiversity Framework, adopted by the United Nations Biodiversity Conference in Montreal on December 19, 2022;</Text></Provision></Preamble><Enacts><Provision><Text>Now, therefore, His Majesty, by and with the advice and consent of the Senate and House of Commons of Canada, enacts as follows:</Text></Provision></Enacts></Introduction><Body><Heading level="1"><TitleText>Short Title</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Short title</MarginalNote><Label>1</Label><Text>This Act may be cited as the <Emphasis style="italic">Gatineau Park Act</Emphasis>.</Text></Section><Heading level="1"><MarginalNote><HistoricalNote>R.S., c. N-4</HistoricalNote></MarginalNote><TitleText><XRefExternal reference-type="act" reference-level="federal">National Capital Act</XRefExternal></TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote>Definitions</MarginalNote><Label>2</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The definition <DefinedTermEn>National Capital Region</DefinedTermEn> in section 2 of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><SectionPiece><Definition><Text><DefinedTermEn>National Capital Region</DefinedTermEn> means the seat of the Government of Canada and its surrounding area, more particularly described in <Ins>Schedule 1</Ins>; (<DefinedTermFr>rГѓВ©gion de la capitale nationale</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Definition></SectionPiece></AmendedText><ExplanatoryNote><TitleText><XRefExternal reference-type="act" reference-level="federal">National Capital Act</XRefExternal></TitleText><Label><Emphasis style="italic">Clause 2</Emphasis>: (1)</Label><ExplanatoryText>Text of the definition:</ExplanatoryText><ExistingText><SectionPiece><Definition><Text><DefinedTermEn>National Capital Region</DefinedTermEn>ГўВЂВ‚means the seat of the Government of Canada and its surrounding area, more particularly described in the schedule;ГўВЂВ‚<DefinedTermFr>(rГѓВ©gion de la capitale nationale</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Definition></SectionPiece></ExistingText></ExplanatoryNote></Subsection><Subsection><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Section 2 of the Act is amended by adding the following in alphabetical order:</Text><AmendedText change="ins"><SectionPiece><Definition><Text><DefinedTermEn>ecological integrity</DefinedTermEn> means, with respect to a park, a condition that is determined to be characteristic of its natural region and likely to persist, including abiotic components and the composition and abundance of native species and biological communities, rates of change and supporting processes; (<DefinedTermFr>intГѓВ©gritГѓВ© ГѓВ©cologique</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Definition><Definition><Text><DefinedTermEn>enforcement officer</DefinedTermEn> means a person designated under section 10.08 or belonging to a class of persons so designated; (<DefinedTermFr>agent de lГўВЂВ™autoritГѓВ©</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Definition><Definition><Text><DefinedTermEn>Gatineau Park</DefinedTermEn> means the area whose boundaries are named and described in Schedule 2; (<DefinedTermFr>parc de la Gatineau</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Definition></SectionPiece></AmendedText><ExplanatoryNote><Label>(2)</Label><ExplanatoryText>New.</ExplanatoryText></ExplanatoryNote></Subsection></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>3</Label><Text>The Act is amended by adding the following after section 10:</Text><AmendedText change="ins"><Heading level="1"><TitleText>Gatineau Park</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Park dedicated to public</MarginalNote><Label>10.01</Label><Text>Gatineau Park is dedicated to the people of Canada, including the Algonquin Anishinabeg Nation, for their benefit, education and enjoyment, subject to this Act and the regulations, and the Park shall be maintained and made use of ГўВЂВ” and its ecological integrity protected ГўВЂВ” so as to leave it unimpaired for the enjoyment of future generations.</Text></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Ecological integrity</MarginalNote><Label>10.02</Label><Text>Maintenance of ecological integrity, through the protection of natural resources and natural processes, shall be the first priority of the Commission when considering all aspects of the management of Gatineau Park.</Text></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Enlarging Gatineau Park</MarginalNote><Label>10.03</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The Governor in Council may, by order, amend Schedule 2 for the purpose of enlarging Gatineau Park if the Governor in Council is satisfied that His Majesty has title to the lands that can be included in Gatineau Park, regardless of whether there are any charges on title.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Judicial finding as to title</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>If a court of competent jurisdiction finds that His Majesty does not have title to the lands referred to in subsection (1), the Governor in Council may, by order, amend Schedule 2 by altering the description of Gatineau Park to remove those lands from the Park.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>No reduction of park area</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>Except as provided by subsection (2), no amendment may be made by the Governor in Council to Schedule 2 for the purpose of removing any portion of Gatineau Park.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Master Plan</MarginalNote><Label>10.04</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Within 10 years after the day on which this section comes into force, the Commission shall prepare a Gatineau Park Master Plan containing a long-term ecological vision for the park, a set of ecological integrity objectives and indicators, and provisions for resource protection and restoration, zoning, visitor use, public awareness and performance evaluation, and shall cause the plan to be tabled in each House of Parliament.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Review of Master Plan by Commission</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The Commission shall review the Master Plan for Gatineau Park at least every 10 years and shall cause any amendments to the plan to be tabled in each House of Parliament.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Consultation ГўВЂВ” public and Anishinabeg Nation</MarginalNote><Label>10.05</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The Commission shall provide opportunities for public participation at the national, regional and local levels ГўВЂВ” including participation by Algonquin Anishinabeg Nation and the residents of Gatineau Park ГўВЂВ” in the development of regulations relating to Gatineau Park, the formulation of Master Plans, land use planning and any other matters that the Commission considers relevant.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Consultation</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The Commission must be able to demonstrate, in a report published on its website, that it has consulted both the cities and municipalities adjacent to Gatineau Park and the Algonquin Anishinabeg governing bodies of the region and has considered their recommendations.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Prohibition on disposing of public land</MarginalNote><Label>10.06</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Despite any other provision of this Act and subject to subsection (2), no person shall dispose of or grant a right or interest in any public lands in Gatineau Park.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Authority to dispose</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Public lands or a right or interest in public lands in Gatineau Park may be disposed of to</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>an Algonquin Anishinabeg organization or governing body of the region if the disposal is necessary for the establishment of health care, social services, or cultural services for the Anishinabeg Nation; or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>a federal, provincial or municipal authority if the disposal is required for the purpose of installing or maintaining public health care establishments or public infrastructure ГўВЂВ” including public utilities or transportation corridors. </Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Reversion</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>Public lands in Gatineau Park revert to the Commission if those lands cease to be used for the purpose for which they were disposed of or the rights or interests were granted.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Interdiction ГўВЂВ” use of public lands</MarginalNote><Label>10.07</Label><Text>Subject to regulations made under subsection 20(1.1), no person shall use or occupy public lands in Gatineau Park except as permitted by the Commission.</Text></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Designation of enforcement officers</MarginalNote><Label>10.08</Label><Text>The Minister may designate persons or classes of persons employed in the federal public administration or by a provincial, municipal or local authority or an Al<Keep>gonquin</Keep> Anishinabeg governing body, whose duties include law enforcement, to be enforcement officers for the purpose of enforcing the provisions of this Act or the <Keep svc="1">regulations</Keep> in relation to Gatineau Park. For that purpose, enforcement officers have the same powers and are entitled to the same protections provided by law to peace officers within the meaning of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act" reference-level="federal">Criminal Code</XRefExternal>.</Text></Section><Section><MarginalNote><XRefExternal reference-type="act" reference-level="federal">Contraventions Act</XRefExternal></MarginalNote><Label>10.09</Label><Text>The Minister may designate persons or classes of persons employed in the federal public administration or by a provincial, municipal or local authority or by an Algonquin Anishinabeg governing body for the purpose of enforcing this Act or the regulations for Gatineau Park with respect to offences that have been designated as contraventions under the <XRefExternal reference-type="act" reference-level="federal">Contraventions Act</XRefExternal>.</Text></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Maintenance and conservation work</MarginalNote><Label>10.1</Label><Text>The Commission must also consider calling upon the services of businesses and workers from the Al<Keep>gonquin</Keep> Anishinabeg Nation of the region for part of Gatineau ParkГўВЂВ™s maintenance and conservation work.</Text></Section></AmendedText><ExplanatoryNote><Label><Emphasis style="italic">Clause 3</Emphasis>:</Label><ExplanatoryText>New.</ExplanatoryText></ExplanatoryNote></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>4</Label><Text>Subsection 16(3) of the French version of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><Subsection><MarginalNote><Language xml:lang="fr">Parc de la Gatineau</Language></MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text><Language xml:lang="fr">La Commission peut verser aux autoritГѓВ©s compГѓВ©tentes, pour ceux de ses biens immeubles situГѓВ©s dans le <Ins>parc</Ins> de la Gatineau, des subventions nГўВЂВ™excГѓВ©dant pas, dans une annГѓВ©e fiscale donnГѓВ©e, les montants quГўВЂВ™elle estime suffisants pour indemniser ces autoritГѓВ©s des pertes de revenu de taxes municipales et scolaires subies par elles pendant lГўВЂВ™annГѓВ©e en question du fait de lГўВЂВ™acquisition de ces biens par la Commission.</Language></Text></Subsection></AmendedText><ExplanatoryNote><Label><Emphasis style="italic">Clause 4</Emphasis>:</Label><ExplanatoryText>Text of subsection 16(3):</ExplanatoryText><ExistingText><Subsection><Label>(3)</Label><Text>The Commission may pay grants to the appropriate authorities in respect of real property of the Commission situated in Gatineau Park not exceeding in any tax year the amounts estimated by the Commission to be sufficient to compensate such authorities for the loss of tax revenue during that tax year in respect of municipal and school taxes by reason of the acquisition of the property by the Commission.</Text></Subsection></ExistingText></ExplanatoryNote></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>5</Label><Text>Section 20 of the Act is amended by adding the following after subsection (1):</Text><AmendedText change="ins"><Subsection><MarginalNote>Regulations ГўВЂВ” Gatineau Park</MarginalNote><Label>(1.1)</Label><Text>The Governor in Council may also make regulations respecting</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>the restriction or prohibition of activities in and the control of the use of Gatineau Park resources and facilities;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>the determination of fees, rates, rents and other charges for the use of Gatineau Park resources, facilities and services and the issuance and amendment of permits, licences and other authorizing instruments; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(c)</Label><Text>the management of ecological integrity of Gatineau Park.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Amount not to exceed cost</MarginalNote><Label>(1.2)</Label><Text>Fees, rates, rents and other charges that are determined under paragraph (1.1)(b) must not exceed the cost to the Commission of providing the use of Gatineau Park resources, facilities and services or issuing and amending permits, licences and other authorizing instruments.</Text></Subsection></AmendedText><ExplanatoryNote><Label><Emphasis style="italic">Clause 5</Emphasis>:</Label><ExplanatoryText>New.</ExplanatoryText></ExplanatoryNote></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>6</Label><Text>Subsection 20(2) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><Subsection><MarginalNote>Punishment</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text><Ins>Within the limits</Ins> set out in subsection 787(1) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act" reference-level="federal">Criminal Code</XRefExternal><Ins>, the</Ins> Governor in Council may<Ins>,</Ins> by regulation<Ins>,</Ins> prescribe the punishment that may be imposed on summary conviction for the contravention of any regulation <Ins>referred to in</Ins> subsection (1) <Ins>or (1.1)</Ins>.</Text></Subsection></AmendedText><ExplanatoryNote><Label><Emphasis style="italic">Clause 6</Emphasis>:</Label><ExplanatoryText>Text of subsection 20(2):</ExplanatoryText><ExistingText><Subsection><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The Governor in Council may by regulation prescribe the punishment that may be imposed on summary conviction for the contravention of any regulation made under subsection (1), but the punishment so prescribed shall not exceed that set out in subsection 787(1) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act" reference-level="federal">Criminal Code</XRefExternal>.</Text></Subsection></ExistingText></ExplanatoryNote></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>7</Label><Text>The schedule to the Act is renumbered Schedule 1.</Text></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>8</Label><Text>The Act is amended by adding after Schedule 1 the Schedule 2 set out in the schedule to this Act.</Text></Section><Heading level="1"><TitleText>Consequential Amendments</TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote>References</MarginalNote><Label>9</Label><Text>Unless the context requires otherwise, the expression ГўВЂВњthe schedule to the <XRefExternal reference-type="act" reference-level="federal">National Capital Act</XRefExternal>ГўВЂВќ is replaced by ГўВЂВњSchedule 1 to the <XRefExternal reference-type="act" reference-level="federal">National Capital Act</XRefExternal>ГўВЂВќ in any Act of Parliament, and more particularly wherever it occurs in the following provisions:</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>subsection 52(2) and section 60 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Access to Information Act</XRefExternal>;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>subsection 4(1) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act" reference-level="federal">Administrative Tribunals Support Service of Canada Act</XRefExternal>;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(c)</Label><Text>subsection 50(1) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act" reference-level="federal">Broadcasting Act</XRefExternal>;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(d)</Label><Text>section 7 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act" reference-level="federal">Budget Implementation Act, 1997</XRefExternal>;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(e)</Label><Text>section 4 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act" reference-level="federal">Canada Border Services Agency Act</XRefExternal>;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(f)</Label><Text>subsection 2(1) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="regulation" reference-level="federal">Canada Elections Act</XRefExternal>;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(g)</Label><Text>subsection 38.11(1.1) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act" reference-level="federal">Canada Evidence Act</XRefExternal>;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(h)</Label><Text>subsection 10.1(1) and section 13 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act" reference-level="federal">Canada Labour Code</XRefExternal>;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(i)</Label><Text>subsection 3(2) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act" reference-level="federal">Canada School of Public Service Act</XRefExternal>;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(j)</Label><Text>subsections 18(1) and (2) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act" reference-level="federal">Canada Transportation Act</XRefExternal>;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(k)</Label><Text>section 13 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act" reference-level="federal">Canadian Centre on Substance Abuse Act</XRefExternal>;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(l)</Label><Text>section 112 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act" reference-level="federal">Canadian Environmental Assessment Act</XRefExternal>;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(m)</Label><Text>section 9 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act" reference-level="federal">Canadian Food Inspection Agency Act</XRefExternal>;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(n)</Label><Text>subsection 34(1) and sections 48.5 and 48.7 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act" reference-level="federal">Canadian Human Rights Act</XRefExternal>;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(o)</Label><Text>section 11 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act" reference-level="federal">Canadian International Trade Tribunal Act</XRefExternal>;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(p)</Label><Text>subsections 10(1) and 10.1(1) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act" reference-level="federal">Canadian Radio-television and Telecommunications Commission Act</XRefExternal>;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(q)</Label><Text>subsection 3(2) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act" reference-level="federal">Canadian Security Intelligence Service Act</XRefExternal>;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(r)</Label><Text>subsection 13(1) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act" reference-level="federal">Canadian Transportation Accident Investigation and Safety Board Act</XRefExternal>;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(s)</Label><Text>section 7 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act" reference-level="federal">College of Patent Agents and Trademark Agents Act</XRefExternal>;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(t)</Label><Text>subsection 7(1) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act" reference-level="federal">Communications Security Establishment Act</XRefExternal>;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(u)</Label><Text>subsections 6(2) and 148(1) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act" reference-level="federal">Corrections and Conditional Release Act</XRefExternal>;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(v)</Label><Text>subsection 4(1) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act" reference-level="federal">Courts Administration Service Act</XRefExternal>;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(w)</Label><Text>subsection 462.48(12) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act" reference-level="federal">Criminal Code</XRefExternal>;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(x)</Label><Text>subsections 27(1) and 60(1) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act" reference-level="federal">Department of Employment and Social Development Act</XRefExternal>;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(y)</Label><Text>subsection 6(1) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act" reference-level="federal">Energy Supplies Emergency Act</XRefExternal>;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(z)</Label><Text>subsection 17(1) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act" reference-level="federal">Export Development Act</XRefExternal>;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(z.1)</Label><Text>section 11 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act" reference-level="federal">Farm Products Agencies Act</XRefExternal>;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(z.2)</Label><Text>subsection 7(1) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act" reference-level="federal">Federal Courts Act</XRefExternal>;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(z.3)</Label><Text>sections 7 and 13 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act" reference-level="federal">Federal Public Sector Labour Relations and Employment Board Act</XRefExternal>;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(z.4)</Label><Text>subsection 26(2) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act" reference-level="federal">First Nations Fiscal Management Act</XRefExternal>;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(z.5)</Label><Text>subsection 25(2) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act" reference-level="federal">First Nations Jurisdiction over Education in British Columbia Act</XRefExternal>;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(z.6)</Label><Text>subsection 157(1) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act" reference-level="federal">Immigration and Refugee Protection Act</XRefExternal>;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(z.7)</Label><Text>section 164 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act" reference-level="federal">Impact Assessment Act</XRefExternal>;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(z.8)</Label><Text>section 22 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act" reference-level="federal">Indigenous Languages Act</XRefExternal>;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(z.9)</Label><Text>section 12 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act" reference-level="federal">Law Commission of Canada Act</XRefExternal>;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(z.10)</Label><Text>subsection 9(1) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act" reference-level="federal">National Arts Centre Act</XRefExternal>;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(z.11)</Label><Text>subsection 24(3) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act" reference-level="federal">National Security and Intelligence Committee of Parliamentarians Act</XRefExternal>;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(z.12)</Label><Text>subsection 3(1) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act" reference-level="federal">Official Languages Act</XRefExternal>;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(z.13)</Label><Text>subsection 5(1) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act" reference-level="federal">Official Residences Act</XRefExternal>;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(z.14)</Label><Text>section 17 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act" reference-level="federal">Parks Canada Agency Act</XRefExternal>;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(z.15)</Label><Text>paragraph 80(1)(a) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act" reference-level="federal">Parliament of Canada Act</XRefExternal>;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(z.16)</Label><Text>subsection 95(1) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act" reference-level="federal">Patent Act</XRefExternal>;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(z.17)</Label><Text>subsection 52(1) and section 61 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act" reference-level="federal">Privacy Act</XRefExternal>;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(z.18)</Label><Text>subsections 48(1), 60(14), 60.1(13) and 60.3(13) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act" reference-level="federal">Proceeds of Crime (Money Laundering) and Terrorist Financing Act</XRefExternal>;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(z.19)</Label><Text>subsection 6(1) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act" reference-level="federal">Public Complaints and Review Commission Act</XRefExternal>;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(z.20)</Label><Text>subsection 3(4) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act" reference-level="federal">Public Sector Pension Investment Board Act</XRefExternal>;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(z.21)</Label><Text>subsection 6(2) and section 8 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act" reference-level="federal">Public Service Employment Act</XRefExternal>;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(z.22)</Label><Text>subsection 38.3(2) and paragraph 38.3(3)(c) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act" reference-level="federal">Countering Foreign Interference Act</XRefExternal>;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(z.23)</Label><Text>subsection 3(3) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act" reference-level="federal">Royal Canadian Mint Act</XRefExternal>;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(z.24)</Label><Text>section 13 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act" reference-level="federal">Shared Services Canada Act</XRefExternal>;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(z.25)</Label><Text>section 10 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act" reference-level="federal">Standards Council of Canada Act</XRefExternal>;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(z.26)</Label><Text>sections 8 and 14 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act" reference-level="federal">Supreme Court Act</XRefExternal>;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(z.27)</Label><Text>subsection 6(1) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act" reference-level="federal">Tax Court of Canada Act</XRefExternal>; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(z.28)</Label><Text>section 9 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act" reference-level="federal">Transportation Appeal Tribunal of Canada Act</XRefExternal>.</Text></Paragraph></Section></Body><Schedule><ScheduleFormHeading><Label>
SCHEDULE</Label><OriginatingRef><Emphasis style="bold">(Section 9)</Emphasis></OriginatingRef></ScheduleFormHeading><Schedule>

<ScheduleFormHeading>
<Label>SCHEDULE 2</Label>
<OriginatingRef>(Sections 2 and 10.3)</OriginatingRef>


<TitleText>Description of Gatineau Park Boundaries</TitleText>
</ScheduleFormHeading>
<BillPiece><Heading level="1"><TitleText>1 ГўВЂВ” Purpose</TitleText></Heading></BillPiece><Provision>
<Text>The boundaries of Gatineau Park are within the registration divisions of Hull, Gatineau and Pontiac, Province of Quebec, are located in the municipalities of Chelsea, La PГѓВЄche, Pontiac and the City of Gatineau, and form part of the cadastres of the Township of Aldfield, the Township of Eardley, the Township of Hull, the Township of Masham, the Township of Onslow and the Cadastre du QuГѓВ©bec. Included within these boundaries are, in particular, the lots described below.</Text>
</Provision>


<BillPiece><Heading level="1"><TitleText>2 ГўВЂВ” Description</TitleText></Heading><Heading level="2"><TitleText>2.1 Section 1</TitleText></Heading></BillPiece><Provision>
<Text>This portion of Gatineau Park, described in SectionГўВЂВЇ1, is included in the registration divisions of Gatineau and Hull, located in the City of Gatineau, and forms part of the cadastre of the Township of Hull and the Cadastre du QuГѓВ©bec.</Text>
</Provision>

<BillPiece><Heading level="3"><TitleText>City of Gatineau</TitleText></Heading></BillPiece><Provision justification="justify">
<Text>Commencing at the north corner of lot <Keep>3ГўВЂВЇ557ГўВЂВЇ256</Keep>, thence in a general southeasterly direction, following the southwest boundary of boulevard de la CitГѓВ©-des-Jeunes comprising lots <Keep>1ГўВЂВЇ090ГўВЂВЇ869</Keep>, <Keep>3ГўВЂВЇ557ГўВЂВЇ257</Keep>, <Keep>1ГўВЂВЇ090ГўВЂВЇ833</Keep>, <Keep>1ГўВЂВЇ090ГўВЂВЇ817</Keep>, <Keep>3ГўВЂВЇ690ГўВЂВЇ369</Keep>, <Keep>1ГўВЂВЇ345ГўВЂВЇ137</Keep>, <Keep>1ГўВЂВЇ345ГўВЂВЇ120</Keep>, <Keep>1ГўВЂВЇ345ГўВЂВЇ121</Keep>, <Keep>1ГўВЂВЇ345ГўВЂВЇ115</Keep>, <Keep>1ГўВЂВЇ345ГўВЂВЇ101</Keep>, <Keep>1ГўВЂВЇ345ГўВЂВЇ114</Keep>, <Keep>1ГўВЂВЇ344ГўВЂВЇ870</Keep> and <Keep>1ГўВЂВЇ814ГўВЂВЇ247</Keep>, to the intersection of the division line between lots <Keep>3ГўВЂВЇ119ГўВЂВЇ481</Keep> and <Keep>4ГўВЂВЇ158ГўВЂВЇ497</Keep> to the west boundary of lot <Keep>1ГўВЂВЇ814ГўВЂВЇ247</Keep>; thence, westerly, following the division line between lots <Keep>4ГўВЂВЇ158ГўВЂВЇ496</Keep> and <Keep>4ГўВЂВЇ158ГўВЂВЇ497</Keep> to the northwest corner of lot <Keep>4ГўВЂВЇ158ГўВЂВЇ496</Keep>; thence, in a general westerly direction, following the division line between lot <Keep>4ГўВЂВЇ158ГўВЂВЇ497</Keep> and lots <Keep>2ГўВЂВЇ744ГўВЂВЇ929</Keep>, <Keep>2ГўВЂВЇ744ГўВЂВЇ928</Keep>, <Keep>2ГўВЂВЇ744ГўВЂВЇ927</Keep>, <Keep>2ГўВЂВЇ744ГўВЂВЇ926</Keep>, <Keep>2ГўВЂВЇ744ГўВЂВЇ925</Keep>, <Keep>2ГўВЂВЇ744ГўВЂВЇ924</Keep>, <Keep>2ГўВЂВЇ744ГўВЂВЇ923</Keep>, <Keep>2ГўВЂВЇ744ГўВЂВЇ922</Keep>, <Keep>2ГўВЂВЇ744ГўВЂВЇ921</Keep>, <Keep>2ГўВЂВЇ744ГўВЂВЇ920</Keep>, <Keep>2ГўВЂВЇ481ГўВЂВЇ516</Keep>, <Keep>2ГўВЂВЇ481ГўВЂВЇ515</Keep>, <Keep>2ГўВЂВЇ481ГўВЂВЇ514</Keep>, <Keep>2ГўВЂВЇ481ГўВЂВЇ513</Keep> and <Keep>1ГўВЂВЇ794ГўВЂВЇ609</Keep>, to the northwest corner of lot <Keep>1ГўВЂВЇ794ГўВЂВЇ609</Keep>; thence, southerly, following the division line between lots <Keep>4ГўВЂВЇ158ГўВЂВЇ497</Keep> and <Keep>1ГўВЂВЇ794ГўВЂВЇ609</Keep>, to the northeast corner of lot <Keep>1ГўВЂВЇ795ГўВЂВЇ143</Keep> (rue des FГѓВ©es); thence, westerly, following the <Keep>division</Keep> line between lot <Keep>4ГўВЂВЇ158ГўВЂВЇ497</Keep> and lots <Keep>1ГўВЂВЇ795ГўВЂВЇ143</Keep> and <Keep>1ГўВЂВЇ794ГўВЂВЇ577</Keep>, to the northwest corner of lot <Keep>1ГўВЂВЇ794ГўВЂВЇ577</Keep>; thence, southerly, following the division line between lot <Keep>4ГўВЂВЇ158ГўВЂВЇ497</Keep> and lots <Keep>1ГўВЂВЇ794ГўВЂВЇ577</Keep>, <Keep>1ГўВЂВЇ794ГўВЂВЇ575</Keep>, <Keep>1ГўВЂВЇ 794ГўВЂВЇ573</Keep>, <Keep>2ГўВЂВЇ401ГўВЂВЇ402</Keep> (rue des Lutins), <Keep>1ГўВЂВЇ794ГўВЂВЇ568</Keep>, <Keep>1ГўВЂВЇ794ГўВЂВЇ 569</Keep>, <Keep>2ГўВЂВЇ401ГўВЂВЇ400</Keep> (rue Merlin), <Keep>1ГўВЂВЇ794ГўВЂВЇ565</Keep>, <Keep>1ГўВЂВЇ794ГўВЂВЇ564</Keep>, <Keep>2ГўВЂВЇ401ГўВЂВЇ398</Keep> (rue des Feux-Follets), to the southwest corner of lot <Keep>2ГўВЂВЇ401ГўВЂВЇ398</Keep> (rue des Feux-Follets ); thence, northeasterly, following the division line between lots <Keep>4ГўВЂВЇ158ГўВЂВЇ497</Keep> and <Keep>2ГўВЂВЇ401ГўВЂВЇ398</Keep> (rue des Feux-Follets) to the most westerly corner of lot <Keep>1ГўВЂВЇ794ГўВЂВЇ567</Keep>; thence, southeasterly, following the division line between lots <Keep>4ГўВЂВЇ158ГўВЂВЇ497</Keep> and <Keep>1ГўВЂВЇ794ГўВЂВЇ567</Keep>, to the most southerly corner of lot <Keep>1ГўВЂВЇ794ГўВЂВЇ567</Keep>; thence, northeasterly, following the <Keep>division</Keep> line between lots <Keep>4ГўВЂВЇ158ГўВЂВЇ497</Keep> and <Keep>1ГўВЂВЇ794ГўВЂВЇ567</Keep>, to the most easterly corner of lot <Keep>1ГўВЂВЇ794ГўВЂВЇ567</Keep>; thence, northwesterly, following the division line between lots <Keep>4ГўВЂВЇ158ГўВЂВЇ497</Keep> and <Keep>1ГўВЂВЇ794ГўВЂВЇ567</Keep>, to the southwest corner of lot <Keep>1ГўВЂВЇ794ГўВЂВЇ580</Keep>; thence, easterly, following the division line between lot <Keep>4ГўВЂВЇ158ГўВЂВЇ497</Keep> and lots <Keep>1ГўВЂВЇ794ГўВЂВЇ580</Keep> and <Keep>1ГўВЂВЇ794ГўВЂВЇ582</Keep>, to the northwest corner of lot <Keep>1ГўВЂВЇ794ГўВЂВЇ585</Keep>; thence, southerly, following the division line between lot <Keep>4ГўВЂВЇ158ГўВЂВЇ497</Keep> and lots <Keep>1ГўВЂВЇ794ГўВЂВЇ585</Keep>, <Keep>1ГўВЂВЇ795ГўВЂВЇ137</Keep> (rue des Farfadets), <Keep>1ГўВЂВЇ794ГўВЂВЇ670</Keep> and <Keep>1ГўВЂВЇ794ГўВЂВЇ673</Keep>, to the southwest corner of lot <Keep>1ГўВЂВЇ794ГўВЂВЇ673</Keep>; thence, southerly, following the extension of the division line between lots <Keep>1ГўВЂВЇ794ГўВЂВЇ673</Keep> and <Keep>4ГўВЂВЇ158ГўВЂВЇ497</Keep>, crossing lots <Keep>1ГўВЂВЇ814ГўВЂВЇ190</Keep> (rue Gamelin) and <Keep>3ГўВЂВЇ754ГўВЂВЇ072</Keep>, to a point located on the division line between lots <Keep>3ГўВЂВЇ754ГўВЂВЇ072</Keep> and <Keep>4ГўВЂВЇ139ГўВЂВЇ221</Keep>; thence, northeasterly, following the division line between lots <Keep>3ГўВЂВЇ754ГўВЂВЇ072</Keep> and <Keep>4ГўВЂВЇ139ГўВЂВЇ221</Keep> to a southwest corner of lot <Keep>1ГўВЂВЇ814ГўВЂВЇ190</Keep> (rue Gamelin); thence, northeasterly, following the division line between lots <Keep>1ГўВЂВЇ814ГўВЂВЇ190</Keep> (rue Gamelin) and <Keep>4ГўВЂВЇ139ГўВЂВЇ221</Keep>, to the easterly corner of lot <Keep>1ГўВЂВЇ814ГўВЂВЇ190</Keep> (rue Gamelin), a distance of 60.96ГўВЂВЇm; thence, northeasterly, following the division line between lots <Keep>3ГўВЂВЇ754ГўВЂВЇ073</Keep> and <Keep>4ГўВЂВЇ139ГўВЂВЇ221</Keep>, to the northeast corner of lot <Keep>4ГўВЂВЇ139ГўВЂВЇ221</Keep>; thence, in a general southerly direction, following the division line between lots <Keep>4ГўВЂВЇ139ГўВЂВЇ220</Keep> and <Keep>4ГўВЂВЇ139ГўВЂВЇ221</Keep>; <Keep>4ГўВЂВЇ139ГўВЂВЇ216</Keep> and <Keep>4ГўВЂВЇ139ГўВЂВЇ217</Keep>; <Keep>4ГўВЂВЇ139ГўВЂВЇ218</Keep> and <Keep>4ГўВЂВЇ139ГўВЂВЇ219</Keep>; <Keep>4ГўВЂВЇ139ГўВЂВЇ215</Keep> and <Keep>4ГўВЂВЇ139ГўВЂВЇ216</Keep>; <Keep>4ГўВЂВЇ139ГўВЂВЇ211</Keep> and <Keep>4ГўВЂВЇ139ГўВЂВЇ212</Keep>; <Keep>4ГўВЂВЇ139ГўВЂВЇ213</Keep> and <Keep>4ГўВЂВЇ139ГўВЂВЇ214</Keep>; <Keep>4ГўВЂВЇ139ГўВЂВЇ209</Keep> and <Keep>4ГўВЂВЇ139ГўВЂВЇ211</Keep>, to a southwest corner of lot <Keep>4ГўВЂВЇ139ГўВЂВЇ211</Keep>; thence, easterly following the division line between lots <Keep>4ГўВЂВЇ139ГўВЂВЇ209</Keep> and <Keep>4ГўВЂВЇ139ГўВЂВЇ211</Keep> to the northwest corner of lot <Keep>1ГўВЂВЇ288ГўВЂВЇ391</Keep>; thence, southerly, following the division line between lots <Keep>4ГўВЂВЇ139ГўВЂВЇ209</Keep> and lot <Keep>1ГўВЂВЇ288ГўВЂВЇ391</Keep>, to the southwest corner of lot <Keep>1ГўВЂВЇ288ГўВЂВЇ391</Keep>; thence, easterly, following the division line between lot <Keep>4ГўВЂВЇ139ГўВЂВЇ209</Keep> and lots <Keep>1ГўВЂВЇ288ГўВЂВЇ391</Keep> and <Keep>1ГўВЂВЇ288ГўВЂВЇ388</Keep>, to the northwest corner of lot <Keep>1ГўВЂВЇ288ГўВЂВЇ387</Keep>; thence, southerly, following the division line between lot <Keep>4ГўВЂВЇ139ГўВЂВЇ209</Keep> and lots <Keep>1ГўВЂВЇ288ГўВЂВЇ387</Keep>, <Keep>1ГўВЂВЇ288ГўВЂВЇ386</Keep>, <Keep>1ГўВЂВЇ288ГўВЂВЇ385</Keep> and <Keep>4ГўВЂВЇ139ГўВЂВЇ210</Keep>, to the southwest corner of lot <Keep>4ГўВЂВЇ139ГўВЂВЇ210</Keep>; thence, easterly, following the division line <Keep>between</Keep> lots <Keep>4ГўВЂВЇ139ГўВЂВЇ209</Keep> and <Keep>4ГўВЂВЇ139ГўВЂВЇ210</Keep>, to the southeast corner of lot <Keep>4ГўВЂВЇ139ГўВЂВЇ210</Keep>; thence, southerly, following the division line between lots <Keep>4ГўВЂВЇ139ГўВЂВЇ209</Keep> and lot <Keep>3ГўВЂВЇ620ГўВЂВЇ965</Keep>, to the southwest corner of lot <Keep>3ГўВЂВЇ620ГўВЂВЇ965</Keep>; thence, easterly, following the division line between lots <Keep>4ГўВЂВЇ139ГўВЂВЇ209</Keep> and <Keep>3ГўВЂВЇ620ГўВЂВЇ965</Keep>, to the northwest corner of lot <Keep>1ГўВЂВЇ286ГўВЂВЇ748</Keep>; thence, southerly, following the division line between lot <Keep>4ГўВЂВЇ139ГўВЂВЇ209</Keep> and lots <Keep>1ГўВЂВЇ286ГўВЂВЇ748</Keep>, <Keep>1ГўВЂВЇ288ГўВЂВЇ419</Keep>, <Keep>1ГўВЂВЇ286ГўВЂВЇ749</Keep> and <Keep>1ГўВЂВЇ288ГўВЂВЇ383</Keep>, to the most westerly corner of lot <Keep>1ГўВЂВЇ288ГўВЂВЇ383</Keep>; thence, southeasterly, following the division line between lot <Keep>4ГўВЂВЇ139ГўВЂВЇ209</Keep> and lots <Keep>1ГўВЂВЇ288ГўВЂВЇ383</Keep>, <Keep>1ГўВЂВЇ286ГўВЂВЇ750</Keep>, <Keep>2ГўВЂВЇ555ГўВЂВЇ266</Keep>, <Keep>2ГўВЂВЇ555ГўВЂВЇ265</Keep>, <Keep>1ГўВЂВЇ288ГўВЂВЇ381</Keep>, <Keep>1ГўВЂВЇ288ГўВЂВЇ379</Keep>, <Keep>1ГўВЂВЇ288ГўВЂВЇ380</Keep> and <Keep>1ГўВЂВЇ286ГўВЂВЇ746</Keep>; to the southwest corner of lot <Keep>1ГўВЂВЇ286ГўВЂВЇ746</Keep>; thence, westerly, following the division line between lots <Keep>4ГўВЂВЇ139ГўВЂВЇ209</Keep> and <Keep>4ГўВЂВЇ045ГўВЂВЇ687</Keep>, to the northwest corner of lot <Keep>4ГўВЂВЇ045ГўВЂВЇ687</Keep>; thence, northerly, following the division line between lots <Keep>4ГўВЂВЇ139ГўВЂВЇ209</Keep> and <Keep>1ГўВЂВЇ286ГўВЂВЇ685</Keep>, to the northeast corner of lot <Keep>1ГўВЂВЇ286ГўВЂВЇ685</Keep>; thence, westerly, following the division line between lots <Keep>4ГўВЂВЇ139ГўВЂВЇ209</Keep> and <Keep>1ГўВЂВЇ286ГўВЂВЇ685</Keep>, to the northwest corner of lot <Keep>1ГўВЂВЇ286ГўВЂВЇ685</Keep>, a distance of 41.16ГўВЂВЇm; thence, northwesterly, following the northeast boundary of rue Boucherville, the division line between lot <Keep>4ГўВЂВЇ139ГўВЂВЇ209</Keep> and lots <Keep>1ГўВЂВЇ288ГўВЂВЇ281</Keep> and <Keep>1ГўВЂВЇ288ГўВЂВЇ280</Keep>, to the northwest corner of lot <Keep>1ГўВЂВЇ288ГўВЂВЇ280</Keep> (rue Boucherville); thence, southerly, following the division line between lot <Keep>1ГўВЂВЇ288ГўВЂВЇ280</Keep> (rue Boucherville) and lots <Keep>4ГўВЂВЇ139ГўВЂВЇ214</Keep>, <Keep>1ГўВЂВЇ288ГўВЂВЇ549</Keep> and <Keep>1ГўВЂВЇ288ГўВЂВЇ157</Keep>, to the southeast corner of lot <Keep>1ГўВЂВЇ288ГўВЂВЇ157</Keep>; thence, westerly, crossing lot <Keep>1ГўВЂВЇ286ГўВЂВЇ450</Keep>, to the southeast corner of lot <Keep>1ГўВЂВЇ288ГўВЂВЇ158</Keep>, a distance of 64.88ГўВЂВЇm; thence, southerly, following the division line between lots <Keep>4ГўВЂВЇ160ГўВЂВЇ587</Keep> and lot <Keep>1ГўВЂВЇ286ГўВЂВЇ450</Keep>, to the northeast corner of lot <Keep>1ГўВЂВЇ286ГўВЂВЇ553</Keep>; thence, northwesterly, following the division line between lot <Keep>4ГўВЂВЇ160ГўВЂВЇ587 </Keep>and lots <Keep>1ГўВЂВЇ286ГўВЂВЇ553</Keep>, <Keep>1ГўВЂВЇ286ГўВЂВЇ552</Keep>, <Keep>1ГўВЂВЇ286ГўВЂВЇ906</Keep> and <Keep>1ГўВЂВЇ286ГўВЂВЇ451</Keep>, to the north corner of lot <Keep>1ГўВЂВЇ286ГўВЂВЇ451</Keep>; thence, westerly, following the division line between lot <Keep>4ГўВЂВЇ160ГўВЂВЇ587</Keep> and lots <Keep>1ГўВЂВЇ286ГўВЂВЇ451</Keep>, <Keep>1ГўВЂВЇ286ГўВЂВЇ449</Keep>, <Keep>1ГўВЂВЇ286ГўВЂВЇ448</Keep> and <Keep>1ГўВЂВЇ286ГўВЂВЇ447</Keep>, to the north corner of lot <Keep>1ГўВЂВЇ286ГўВЂВЇ447</Keep>; thence, westerly, following the division line between lot <Keep>4ГўВЂВЇ160ГўВЂВЇ587</Keep> and lots <Keep>1ГўВЂВЇ286ГўВЂВЇ447</Keep>, <Keep>1ГўВЂВЇ286ГўВЂВЇ446</Keep>, <Keep>1ГўВЂВЇ286ГўВЂВЇ445</Keep> and <Keep>1ГўВЂВЇ286ГўВЂВЇ444</Keep>, to the northwest corner of lot <Keep>1ГўВЂВЇ286ГўВЂВЇ444</Keep>; thence, northerly, following the division line between lots <Keep>4 160 587</Keep> and <Keep>1ГўВЂВЇ286ГўВЂВЇ443</Keep>, to the northeast corner of lot <Keep>1ГўВЂВЇ286ГўВЂВЇ443</Keep>; thence, westerly, following the division line between lots <Keep>4ГўВЂВЇ160ГўВЂВЇ587</Keep> and <Keep>1ГўВЂВЇ286ГўВЂВЇ443</Keep>, to the northwest corner of lot <Keep>1ГўВЂВЇ286ГўВЂВЇ443</Keep>; thence, southerly, following the division line between lots <Keep>4ГўВЂВЇ160ГўВЂВЇ587</Keep> and <Keep>1ГўВЂВЇ286ГўВЂВЇ443</Keep>, to the southwest corner of lot <Keep>1ГўВЂВЇ286ГўВЂВЇ443</Keep>; thence, southerly, following the lines between lot <Keep>4ГўВЂВЇ160ГўВЂВЇ587</Keep> and lots <Keep>1ГўВЂВЇ288ГўВЂВЇ289</Keep> (rue Augustin-Thibeault), <Keep>1ГўВЂВЇ288ГўВЂВЇ294</Keep> (rue Hormidas-Dupuis), to the southwest corner of lot <Keep>1ГўВЂВЇ288ГўВЂВЇ294</Keep> (rue Hormidas-Dupuis); thence, in a general southeasterly direction, following the division line between lots <Keep>4ГўВЂВЇ160ГўВЂВЇ587</Keep> and <Keep>1ГўВЂВЇ288ГўВЂВЇ295</Keep> (rue Hormidas-Dupuis), to a point located at the northeast corner of lot <Keep>4ГўВЂВЇ160ГўВЂВЇ586</Keep>; thence, westerly, following the division line between lots <Keep>4ГўВЂВЇ160ГўВЂВЇ586</Keep> and <Keep>4ГўВЂВЇ160ГўВЂВЇ587</Keep>, to a point located at the northwest corner of lot <Keep>4ГўВЂВЇ160ГўВЂВЇ586</Keep>; thence, northerly, following the division line between lot <Keep>4ГўВЂВЇ160ГўВЂВЇ587</Keep> and lots <Keep>1ГўВЂВЇ876ГўВЂВЇ616</Keep>, <Keep>1ГўВЂВЇ876ГўВЂВЇ615</Keep> and <Keep>1ГўВЂВЇ286ГўВЂВЇ289</Keep>, to the northeast corner of lot <Keep>1ГўВЂВЇ286ГўВЂВЇ289</Keep>; thence, westerly, following the division line between lots <Keep>4ГўВЂВЇ160ГўВЂВЇ587</Keep> and <Keep>1ГўВЂВЇ286ГўВЂВЇ289</Keep>, to a point located at the intersection of the east boundary of lot <Keep>3ГўВЂВЇ558ГўВЂВЇ336</Keep>; thence, northerly, following the division line between lot <Keep>4ГўВЂВЇ160ГўВЂВЇ587</Keep> and lots <Keep>3ГўВЂВЇ558ГўВЂВЇ336</Keep>, <Keep>3ГўВЂВЇ558ГўВЂВЇ337 </Keep>and <Keep>1ГўВЂВЇ286ГўВЂВЇ192</Keep>, to the northeast corner of lot <Keep>1ГўВЂВЇ286ГўВЂВЇ192</Keep>; thence, westerly, following the division line between lots <Keep>4ГўВЂВЇ160ГўВЂВЇ587</Keep> and <Keep>1ГўВЂВЇ286 ГўВЂВЇ192</Keep>, to a point located at the tangent point of a curve 24.80ГўВЂВЇm in radius, a distance of 12.29ГўВЂВЇm; thence, northeasterly, northerly and northwesterly, following the division line between lots <Keep>4ГўВЂВЇ160ГўВЂВЇ587</Keep> and <Keep>1ГўВЂВЇ288ГўВЂВЇ296</Keep> (rue Gendron), to the southerly corner of lot <Keep>1ГўВЂВЇ286ГўВЂВЇ239</Keep>; thence, northwesterly, following the division line between lots <Keep>1ГўВЂВЇ288ГўВЂВЇ296</Keep> (rue Gendron) and <Keep>1ГўВЂВЇ286ГўВЂВЇ239</Keep>, to the southeast corner of lot <Keep>1ГўВЂВЇ286ГўВЂВЇ238</Keep>; thence, northeasterly, following the division line between lots <Keep>1ГўВЂВЇ286ГўВЂВЇ238</Keep> and <Keep>1ГўВЂВЇ286 239</Keep>, a distance of 4.21ГўВЂВЇm, to the southeast corner of lot <Keep>1ГўВЂВЇ286ГўВЂВЇ238</Keep>; thence, northerly, following the division line between lots <Keep>1ГўВЂВЇ286ГўВЂВЇ238</Keep> and <Keep>1ГўВЂВЇ286ГўВЂВЇ239</Keep>, to the northwest corner of lot <Keep>1ГўВЂВЇ286ГўВЂВЇ239</Keep>; thence, westerly, following the division line between lot <Keep>4ГўВЂВЇ160ГўВЂВЇ587</Keep> and lots <Keep>1ГўВЂВЇ286ГўВЂВЇ238</Keep> and <Keep>1ГўВЂВЇ286ГўВЂВЇ237</Keep>, to the northwest corner of lot <Keep>1ГўВЂВЇ286ГўВЂВЇ237</Keep>; thence, northerly, following the division line between lots <Keep>4ГўВЂВЇ160ГўВЂВЇ587</Keep> and <Keep>1ГўВЂВЇ286ГўВЂВЇ442</Keep>, to the northeast corner of lot <Keep>1ГўВЂВЇ286ГўВЂВЇ442</Keep>; thence, northwesterly, following the division line between lots <Keep>1ГўВЂВЇ286ГўВЂВЇ442</Keep> and <Keep>1ГўВЂВЇ286ГўВЂВЇ441</Keep>, to the north corner of lot <Keep>1ГўВЂВЇ286ГўВЂВЇ442</Keep>; thence, northwesterly, following the division line between lots <Keep>1ГўВЂВЇ286ГўВЂВЇ442</Keep> and <Keep>1ГўВЂВЇ286ГўВЂВЇ441</Keep>, to the northwest corner of lot <Keep>1ГўВЂВЇ286ГўВЂВЇ442</Keep>; thence, northeasterly, to a point located at the intersection of the northeast boundary of lot <Keep>1ГўВЂВЇ286ГўВЂВЇ441</Keep>, a distance of 50.05ГўВЂВЇm; thence, northwesterly, following the division line between lots <Keep>1ГўВЂВЇ286ГўВЂВЇ441</Keep> and <Keep>1ГўВЂВЇ288ГўВЂВЇ534</Keep>, to the west corner of lot <Keep>1ГўВЂВЇ288ГўВЂВЇ534</Keep>, a distance of 80.36ГўВЂВЇm; thence, westerly, following the division line between lots <Keep>1ГўВЂВЇ086ГўВЂВЇ216</Keep> and <Keep>1ГўВЂВЇ286ГўВЂВЇ441</Keep>, to the northwest corner of lot <Keep>1ГўВЂВЇ286ГўВЂВЇ441</Keep>; thence, southerly, following the division line between lot <Keep>4ГўВЂВЇ160ГўВЂВЇ640</Keep> and lots <Keep>1ГўВЂВЇ286ГўВЂВЇ441</Keep>, <Keep>1ГўВЂВЇ286ГўВЂВЇ440</Keep> and <Keep>1ГўВЂВЇ286ГўВЂВЇ441</Keep>, to the southeast corner of lot <Keep>4ГўВЂВЇ160ГўВЂВЇ640</Keep>; thence, westerly, following the division line between lots <Keep>4ГўВЂВЇ160ГўВЂВЇ639</Keep> and <Keep>4ГўВЂВЇ160ГўВЂВЇ640</Keep>, to the northwest corner of lot <Keep>4ГўВЂВЇ160ГўВЂВЇ639</Keep>; thence, northerly, <Keep>following</Keep> the division line between lot <Keep>4ГўВЂВЇ160ГўВЂВЇ640</Keep> and lots <Keep>1ГўВЂВЇ794ГўВЂВЇ544</Keep>, <Keep>1ГўВЂВЇ794ГўВЂВЇ546</Keep>, <Keep>1ГўВЂВЇ794ГўВЂВЇ547</Keep>, <Keep>1ГўВЂВЇ794ГўВЂВЇ549</Keep>, <Keep>1ГўВЂВЇ795ГўВЂВЇ107</Keep> (rue Des PrГѓВ©s) and <Keep>1ГўВЂВЇ794ГўВЂВЇ551</Keep>, to the northeast corner of lot <Keep>1ГўВЂВЇ794ГўВЂВЇ551</Keep>; thence, westerly, following the division line between lot <Keep>4ГўВЂВЇ160ГўВЂВЇ640</Keep> and lots <Keep>1ГўВЂВЇ794ГўВЂВЇ551</Keep>, <Keep>1ГўВЂВЇ794ГўВЂВЇ550</Keep> and <Keep>1ГўВЂВЇ794ГўВЂВЇ542</Keep>, to the northwest corner of lot <Keep>1ГўВЂВЇ794ГўВЂВЇ542</Keep>; thence, westerly, following the division line between lots <Keep>3ГўВЂВЇ119ГўВЂВЇ485</Keep> (boulevard Saint-Raymond) and <Keep>1ГўВЂВЇ795ГўВЂВЇ133</Keep> (boulevard Saint-Raymond), to the southwest corner of lot <Keep>3ГўВЂВЇ119ГўВЂВЇ485</Keep> (boulevard Saint-Raymond); thence, northerly, following the division line between lot <Keep>1ГўВЂВЇ795ГўВЂВЇ165</Keep> (boulevard Saint-Raymond) and lots <Keep>3ГўВЂВЇ119ГўВЂВЇ485 </Keep>(boulevard Saint-Raymond) and <Keep>4ГўВЂВЇ160ГўВЂВЇ640</Keep>, to a point located at a distance of 317.65ГўВЂВЇm; thence, northerly, crossing lot <Keep>1ГўВЂВЇ795ГўВЂВЇ165</Keep> (boulevard Saint-Raymond), a distance of 117.04ГўВЂВЇm, to the southeast corner of lot <Keep>3ГўВЂВЇ119ГўВЂВЇ490</Keep>; thence, in a general northwesterly direction, following the line between lots <Keep>3ГўВЂВЇ119ГўВЂВЇ490</Keep> and <Keep>3ГўВЂВЇ119ГўВЂВЇ488</Keep>, to the southeast corner of lot <Keep>1ГўВЂВЇ814ГўВЂВЇ268</Keep> (rue des ConifГѓВЁres); thence, northerly, following the division line between lots <Keep>1ГўВЂВЇ795ГўВЂВЇ163</Keep> (rue des ConifГѓВЁres) and <Keep>1ГўВЂВЇ814ГўВЂВЇ268</Keep> (rue des ConifГѓВЁres), to the northeast corner of lot <Keep>1ГўВЂВЇ814ГўВЂВЇ268</Keep> (rue des ConifГѓВЁres); thence, in a general northerly direction, following the line between lots <Keep>3ГўВЂВЇ119ГўВЂВЇ481 </Keep>(boulevard Saint-Raymond) and <Keep>4ГўВЂВЇ158ГўВЂВЇ497</Keep> (boulevard Saint-Raymond), at successive distances of 58.55ГўВЂВЇm, 39.74ГўВЂВЇm and 37.32ГўВЂВЇm; thence, northerly, crossing lot <Keep>3ГўВЂВЇ119ГўВЂВЇ481</Keep> (boulevard Saint-Raymond) and lot <Keep>3ГўВЂВЇ119ГўВЂВЇ478</Keep> (chemin Pink), to a point located at the division line between lots <Keep>3ГўВЂВЇ119ГўВЂВЇ478</Keep> (chemin Pink) and <Keep>3ГўВЂВЇ119ГўВЂВЇ479</Keep>, a distance of 167.17ГўВЂВЇm; thence, northwesterly, following the division line between lots <Keep>3ГўВЂВЇ119ГўВЂВЇ478</Keep> (rue Pink) and <Keep>3ГўВЂВЇ119ГўВЂВЇ479</Keep>, to the west corner of lot <Keep>3ГўВЂВЇ119ГўВЂВЇ479</Keep>; thence, in a general northwesterly and westerly direction, following the division line between lots <Keep>1ГўВЂВЇ344ГўВЂВЇ862 </Keep>(chemin Pink) and <Keep>1ГўВЂВЇ341ГўВЂВЇ362</Keep>, to the southeast corner of lot <Keep>1ГўВЂВЇ344ГўВЂВЇ861</Keep> (chemin de la Montagne nord); thence, northwesterly, following the division line between lots <Keep>1ГўВЂВЇ341ГўВЂВЇ362</Keep> and <Keep>1ГўВЂВЇ344ГўВЂВЇ861</Keep> (chemin de la Montagne nord), at successive distances of 72.92ГўВЂВЇm and 10.50ГўВЂВЇm, to the northwest corner of lot <Keep>1ГўВЂВЇ344ГўВЂВЇ861</Keep> (chemin de la Montagne nord); thence, on an azimuth bearing of 314Г‹Вљ09ГўВЂВІ, following the northeast boundary of chemin de la Montagne nord (as shown on the original cadastral plan), a distance of 101.11ГўВЂВЇm; thence, on an azimuth bearing of 314Г‹Вљ00ГўВЂВІ, following the northeast boundary of chemin de la Montagne nord (as shown on the original cadastral plan), a distance of 69.40ГўВЂВЇm; thence, on an azimuth bearing of 313Г‹Вљ48ГўВЂВІ, following the northeast boundary of chemin de la Montagne nord (as shown on the original cadastral plan), a distance of 51.31ГўВЂВЇm; thence, on an azimuth bearing of 312Г‹Вљ49ГўВЂВІ, following the northeast boundary of chemin de la Montagne nord (as shown on the original cadastral plan), a distance of 61.49ГўВЂВЇm; thence, on an azimuth bearing of 303Г‹Вљ50ГўВЂВІ, following the northeast boundary of chemin de la Montagne nord (as shown on the original cadastral plan), a distance of 39.68ГўВЂВЇm; thence, on an azimuth bearing of 305Г‹Вљ36ГўВЂВІ, following the northeast boundary of chemin de la Montagne nord (as shown on the original cadastral plan), a distance of 75.58ГўВЂВЇm; thence, on an azimuth bearing of 301Г‹Вљ35ГўВЂВІ, following the northeast boundary of chemin de la Montagne nord (as shown on the original cadastral plan), a distance of 64.99ГўВЂВЇm; thence, on an azimuth bearing of 305Г‹Вљ41ГўВЂВІ, following the northeast boundary of chemin de la Montagne nord (as shown on the original cadastral plan), a distance of 41.19ГўВЂВЇm; thence, on an azimuth bearing of 315Г‹Вљ15ГўВЂВІ, following the northeast boundary of chemin de la Montagne nord (as shown on the original cadastral plan), a distance of 35.86ГўВЂВЇm; thence, on an azimuth bearing of 319Г‹Вљ27ГўВЂВІ, following the northeast boundary of chemin de la Montagne nord (as shown on the original cadastral plan), a distance of 58.37ГўВЂВЇm; thence, on an azimuth bearing of 317Г‹Вљ24ГўВЂВІ, following the northeast boundary of chemin de la Montagne nord (as shown on the original cadastral plan), a distance of 30.36ГўВЂВЇm; thence, on an azimuth bearing of 313Г‹Вљ20ГўВЂВІ, following the northeast boundary of chemin de la Montagne nord (as shown on the original cadastral plan), a distance of 54.89ГўВЂВЇm; thence, on an azimuth bearing of 308Г‹Вљ49ГўВЂВІ, following the northeast boundary of chemin de la Montagne nord (as shown on the original cadastral plan), a distance of 44.32ГўВЂВЇm; thence, on an azimuth bearing of 303Г‹Вљ33ГўВЂВІ, following the northeast boundary of chemin de la Montagne nord (as shown on the original cadastral plan), a distance of 34.20ГўВЂВЇm; thence, on an azimuth bearing of 294Г‹Вљ05ГўВЂВІ, following the northeast boundary of chemin de la Montagne nord (as shown on the original cadastral plan), a distance of 39.18ГўВЂВЇm; thence, on an azimuth bearing of 288Г‹Вљ49ГўВЂВІ, following the north boundary of chemin de la Montagne nord (as shown on the original cadastral plan), a distance of 67.92ГўВЂВЇm; thence, on an azimuth bearing of 286Г‹Вљ18ГўВЂВІ, following the north boundary of chemin de la Montagne nord (as shown on the original cadastral plan), a distance of 56.40ГўВЂВЇm; thence, on an azimuth bearing of 280Г‹Вљ45ГўВЂВІ, following the north boundary of chemin de la Montagne nord (as shown on the original cadastral plan), a distance of 32.00ГўВЂВЇm; thence, on an azimuth bearing of 277Г‹Вљ34ГўВЂВІ, following the north boundary of chemin de la Montagne nord (as shown on the original cadastral plan), a distance of 136.62ГўВЂВЇm; thence, on an azimuth bearing of 279Г‹Вљ59ГўВЂВІ, following the north boundary of chemin de la Montagne nord (as shown on the original cadastral plan), a distance of 22.28ГўВЂВЇm; thence, on an azimuth bearing of 282Г‹Вљ07ГўВЂВІ, following the north boundary of chemin de la Montagne nord (as shown on the original cadastral plan), a distance of 37.99ГўВЂВЇm; thence, on an azimuth bearing of 287Г‹Вљ33ГўВЂВІ, following the north boundary of chemin de la Montagne nord (as shown on the original cadastral plan), a distance of 21.87ГўВЂВЇm; thence, on an azimuth bearing of 294Г‹Вљ55ГўВЂВІ, following the northeast boundary of chemin de la Montagne nord (as shown on the original cadastral plan), a distance of 34.39ГўВЂВЇm; thence, on an azimuth bearing of 304Г‹Вљ04ГўВЂВІ, following the northeast boundary of chemin de la Montagne nord (as shown on the original cadastral plan), a distance of 66.77ГўВЂВЇm; thence, on an azimuth bearing of 307Г‹Вљ52ГўВЂВІ, following the northeast boundary of chemin de la Montagne nord (as shown on the original cadastral plan), a distance of 28.36ГўВЂВЇm; thence, on an azimuth bearing of 316Г‹Вљ49ГўВЂВІ, following the northeast boundary of chemin de la Montagne nord (as shown on the original cadastral plan), a distance of 37.89ГўВЂВЇm; thence, on an azimuth bearing of 322Г‹Вљ11ГўВЂВІ, following the northeast boundary of chemin de la Montagne nord (as shown on the original cadastral plan), a distance of 24.17ГўВЂВЇm; thence, on an azimuth bearing of 320Г‹Вљ04ГўВЂВІ, following the northeast boundary of chemin de la Montagne nord (as shown on the original cadastral plan), a distance of 32.61ГўВЂВЇm; thence, on an azimuth bearing of 316Г‹Вљ01ГўВЂВІ, following the northeast boundary of chemin de la Montagne nord (as shown on the original cadastral plan), to a point located at the intersection of the said boundary and the division line between lots 12 and <Keep>13B</Keep>, range 5, cadastre of the Township of Hull, a distance of 63.76ГўВЂВЇm; thence, on an azimuth bearing of 316Г‹Вљ03ГўВЂВІ, following the northeast boundary of chemin de la Montagne nord (as shown on the original cadastral plan), a distance of 79.76ГўВЂВЇm; thence, on an azimuth bearing of 317Г‹Вљ30ГўВЂВІ, following the northeast boundary of chemin de la Montagne nord (as shown on the original cadastral plan), a distance of 80.13ГўВЂВЇm; thence, on an azimuth bearing of 317Г‹Вљ48ГўВЂВІ, following the northeast boundary of chemin de la Montagne nord (as shown on the original cadastral plan), a distance of 38.15ГўВЂВЇm; thence, on an azimuth bearing of 315Г‹Вљ06ГўВЂВІ, following the northeast boundary of chemin de la Montagne nord (as shown on the original cadastral plan), a distance of 36.10ГўВЂВЇm; thence, on an azimuth bearing of 310Г‹Вљ22ГўВЂВІ , following the northeast boundary of chemin de la Montagne nord (as shown on the original cadastral plan), a distance of 42.66ГўВЂВЇm; thence, on an azimuth bearing of 312Г‹Вљ00ГўВЂВІ, following the northeast boundary of chemin de la Montagne nord (as shown on the original cadastral plan), a distance of 109.83ГўВЂВЇm; thence, on an azimuth bearing of 315Г‹Вљ25ГўВЂВІ, following the northeast boundary of chemin de la Montagne nord (as shown on the original cadastral plan), a distance of 21.00ГўВЂВЇm; thence, on an azimuth bearing of 321Г‹Вљ07ГўВЂВІ, following the northeast boundary of chemin de la Montagne nord (as shown on the original cadastral plan), a distance of 25.17ГўВЂВЇm; thence, on an azimuth bearing of 324Г‹Вљ21ГўВЂВІ, following the northeast boundary of chemin de la Montagne nord (as shown on the original cadastral plan), a distance of 48.12ГўВЂВЇm; thence, on an azimuth bearing of 326Г‹Вљ52ГўВЂВІ, following the northeast boundary of chemin de la Montagne nord (as shown on the original cadastral plan), to a point located at the intersection of the said boundary and the division line between lots <Keep>13B</Keep> and <Keep>13A</Keep>, range 5, cadastre of the Township of Hull, a distance of 51.01ГўВЂВЇm; thence, on an azimuth bearing of 336Г‹Вљ12ГўВЂВІ, following the northeast boundary of chemin de la Montagne nord (as shown on the original cadastral plan), a distance of 33.62ГўВЂВЇm; thence, on an azimuth bearing of 337Г‹Вљ26ГўВЂВІ, following the northeast boundary of chemin de la Montagne nord (as shown on the original cadastral plan), a distance of 27.89ГўВЂВЇm; thence, on an azimuth bearing of 327Г‹Вљ38ГўВЂВІ, following the northeast boundary of chemin de la Montagne nord (as shown on the original cadastral plan), a distance of 27.49ГўВЂВЇm; thence, on an azimuth bearing of 316Г‹Вљ30ГўВЂВІ, following the northeast boundary of chemin de la Montagne nord (as shown on the original cadastral plan), a distance of 25.42ГўВЂВЇm; thence, on an azimuth bearing of 305Г‹Вљ46ГўВЂВІ, following the northeast boundary of chemin de la Montagne nord (as shown on the original cadastral plan), a distance of 25.96ГўВЂВЇm; thence, on an azimuth bearing of 291Г‹Вљ37ГўВЂВІ, following the north boundary of chemin de la Montagne nord (as shown on the original cadastral plan), a distance of 22.70ГўВЂВЇm; thence, on an azimuth bearing of 280Г‹Вљ05ГўВЂВІ, following the north boundary of chemin de la Montagne nord (as shown on the original cadastral plan), a distance of 22.05ГўВЂВЇm; thence, on an azimuth bearing of 277Г‹Вљ26ГўВЂВІ, following the north boundary of chemin de la Montagne nord (as shown on the original cadastral plan), a distance of 30.31ГўВЂВЇm; thence, on an azimuth bearing of 277Г‹Вљ08ГўВЂВІ, following the north boundary of chemin de la Montagne nord (as shown on the original cadastral plan), a distance of 44.27ГўВЂВЇm; thence, on an azimuth bearing of 276Г‹Вљ24ГўВЂВІ, following the north boundary of chemin de la Montagne nord (as shown on the original cadastral plan), to a point located at the intersection of the said boundary and the division line between lots <Keep>13A</Keep> and <Keep>14A</Keep>, range 5, cadastre of the Township of Hull, a distance of 28.13ГўВЂВЇm; thence, on an azimuth bearing of 276Г‹Вљ32ГўВЂВІ, following the north boundary of chemin de la Montagne nord (as shown on the original cadastral plan), a distance of 52.12ГўВЂВЇm; thence, on an azimuth bearing of 280Г‹Вљ11ГўВЂВІ, following the north boundary of chemin de la Montagne nord (as shown on the original cadastral plan), a distance of 30.81ГўВЂВЇm; thence, on an azimuth bearing of 285Г‹Вљ57ГўВЂВІ, following the north boundary of chemin de la Montagne nord (as shown on the original cadastral plan), a distance of 39.13ГўВЂВЇm; thence, on an azimuth bearing of 285Г‹Вљ13ГўВЂВІ, following the north boundary of chemin de la Montagne nord (as shown on the original cadastral plan), a distance of 59.80ГўВЂВЇm; thence, on an azimuth bearing of 287Г‹Вљ08ГўВЂВІ, following the north boundary of chemin de la Montagne nord (as shown on the original cadastral plan), a distance of 19.48ГўВЂВЇm; thence, on an azimuth bearing of 292Г‹Вљ50ГўВЂВІ, following the northeast boundary of chemin de la Montagne nord (as shown on the original cadastral plan), to a point located at the intersection of the said boundary and the division line between lots <Keep>14A</Keep>, range 5, and lot 14, range 6, all part of the cadastre of the Township of Hull, a distance of 26.87ГўВЂВЇm; thence, on an azimuth bearing of 293Г‹Вљ14ГўВЂВІ, following the northeast boundary of chemin de la Montagne nord (as shown on the original cadastral plan), a distance of 68.54ГўВЂВЇm; thence, on an azimuth bearing of 292Г‹Вљ28ГўВЂВІ, following the north boundary of chemin de la Montagne nord (as shown on the original cadastral plan), a distance of 55.88ГўВЂВЇm; thence, on an azimuth bearing of 294Г‹Вљ43ГўВЂВІ, following the northeast boundary of chemin de la Montagne nord (as shown on the original cadastral plan), a distance of 92.77ГўВЂВЇm; thence, on an azimuth bearing of 290Г‹Вљ42ГўВЂВІ, following the north boundary of chemin de la Montagne nord (as shown on the original cadastral plan), a distance of 53.02ГўВЂВЇm; thence, on an azimuth bearing of 285Г‹Вљ18ГўВЂВІ, following the north boundary of chemin de la Montagne nord (as shown on the original cadastral plan), a distance of 44.21ГўВЂВЇm; thence, on an azimuth bearing of 277Г‹Вљ16ГўВЂВІ, following the north boundary of chemin de la Montagne nord (as shown on the original cadastral plan), to a point located at the intersection of the said boundary and the division line between lots 14 and 15, range 6, cadastre of the Township of Hull, a distance of 18.50ГўВЂВЇm; thence, on an azimuth bearing of 270Г‹Вљ54ГўВЂВІ, following the north boundary of chemin de la Montagne nord (as shown on the original cadastral plan), a distance of 21.73ГўВЂВЇm; thence, on an azimuth bearing of 259Г‹Вљ54ГўВЂВІ, following the north boundary of chemin de la Montagne nord (as shown on the original cadastral plan), a distance of 36.79ГўВЂВЇm; thence, on an azimuth bearing of 257Г‹Вљ18ГўВЂВІ, following the north boundary of chemin de la Montagne nord (as shown on the original cadastral plan), a distance of 43.29ГўВЂВЇm; thence, on an azimuth bearing of 262Г‹Вљ56ГўВЂВІ, following the north boundary of chemin de la Montagne nord (as shown on the original cadastral plan), a distance of 28.82ГўВЂВЇm; thence, on an azimuth bearing of 274Г‹Вљ39ГўВЂВІ, following the north boundary of chemin de la Montagne nord (as shown on the original cadastral plan), a distance of 23.87ГўВЂВЇm; thence, on an azimuth bearing of 284Г‹Вљ08ГўВЂВІ, following the north boundary of chemin de la Montagne nord (as shown on the original cadastral plan), a distance of 20.68ГўВЂВЇm; thence, on an azimuth bearing of 297Г‹Вљ25ГўВЂВІ, following the northeast boundary of chemin de la Montagne nord (as shown on the original cadastral plan), a distance of 16.22ГўВЂВЇm; thence, on an azimuth bearing of 297Г‹Вљ28ГўВЂВІ, following the northeast boundary of chemin de la Montagne nord (as shown on the original cadastral plan), a distance of 105.55ГўВЂВЇm; thence, on an azimuth bearing of 302Г‹Вљ41ГўВЂВІ, following the northeast boundary of chemin de la Montagne nord (as shown on the original cadastral plan), a distance of 27.53ГўВЂВЇm; thence, on an azimuth bearing of 314Г‹Вљ58ГўВЂВІ, following the northeast boundary of chemin de la Montagne nord (as shown on the original cadastral plan), a distance of 17.80ГўВЂВЇm; thence, on an azimuth bearing of 316Г‹Вљ03ГўВЂВІ, following the northeast boundary of chemin de la Montagne nord (as shown on the original cadastral plan), a distance of 39.62ГўВЂВЇm; thence, on an azimuth bearing of 310Г‹Вљ41ГўВЂВІ, following the northeast boundary of chemin de la Montagne nord (as shown on the original cadastral plan), a distance of 27.14ГўВЂВЇm; thence, on an azimuth bearing of 307Г‹Вљ17ГўВЂВІ, following the northeast boundary of chemin de la Montagne nord (as shown on the original cadastral plan), a distance of 54.95ГўВЂВЇm; thence, on an azimuth bearing of 308Г‹Вљ33ГўВЂВІ, following the northeast boundary of chemin de la Montagne nord (as shown on the original cadastral plan) and the southwest boundary of Skyridge Road (lot <Keep>15-4</Keep>, range 6, cadastre of the Township of Hull), a distance of 32.01ГўВЂВЇm; thence, on an azimuth bearing of 301Г‹Вљ39ГўВЂВІ, following the northeast boundary of chemin de la Montagne nord (as shown on the original cadastral plan), a distance of 40.33ГўВЂВЇm; thence, on an azimuth bearing of 285Г‹Вљ25ГўВЂВІ, following the north boundary of chemin de la Montagne nord (as shown on the original cadastral plan), a distance of 66.57ГўВЂВЇm; thence, on an azimuth bearing of 280Г‹Вљ13ГўВЂВІ, following the north boundary of chemin de la Montagne nord (as shown on the original cadastral plan), to a point located at the intersection of the division line between lots 15 and <Keep>16C</Keep>, range 6, cadastre of the Township of Hull, a distance of 39.26ГўВЂВЇm; thence, on an azimuth bearing of 276Г‹Вљ25ГўВЂВІ, following the north boundary of chemin de la Montagne nord (as shown on the original cadastral plan), a distance of 33.10ГўВЂВЇm; thence, on an azimuth bearing of 285Г‹Вљ47ГўВЂВІ, following the north boundary of chemin de la Montagne nord (as shown on the original cadastral plan), a distance of 21.80ГўВЂВЇm; thence, on an azimuth bearing of 292Г‹Вљ13ГўВЂВІ, following the north boundary of chemin de la Montagne nord (as shown on the original cadastral plan), a distance of 20.77ГўВЂВЇm; thence, on an azimuth bearing of 296Г‹Вљ10ГўВЂВІ, following the northeast boundary of chemin de la Montagne nord (as shown on the original cadastral plan), a distance of 25.71ГўВЂВЇm; thence, on an azimuth bearing of 297Г‹Вљ07ГўВЂВІ, following the northeast boundary of chemin de la Montagne nord (as shown on the original cadastral plan), a distance of 101.29ГўВЂВЇm; thence, on an azimuth bearing of 296Г‹Вљ21ГўВЂВІ, following the northeast boundary of chemin de la Montagne nord (as shown on the original cadastral plan), a distance of 69.42ГўВЂВЇm; thence, on an azimuth bearing of 303Г‹Вљ30ГўВЂВІ, following the northeast boundary of chemin de la Montagne nord (as shown on the original cadastral plan), a distance of 129.60ГўВЂВЇm; thence, on an azimuth bearing of 302Г‹Вљ10ГўВЂВІ, following the northeast boundary of chemin de la Montagne nord (as shown on the original cadastral plan), a distance of 59.21ГўВЂВЇm; thence, northwesterly, following the northeast boundary of chemin de la Montagne nord (as shown on the original cadastral plan), 29.15ГўВЂВЇm following the arc of a circle 75.65ГўВЂВЇm in radius; thence, on an azimuth bearing of 324Г‹Вљ15ГўВЂВІ, following the northeast boundary of chemin de la Montagne nord (as shown on the original cadastral plan), a distance of 34.06ГўВЂВЇm; thence, northwesterly, following the northeast boundary of chemin de la Montagne nord (as shown on the original cadastral plan), 61.46ГўВЂВЇm following the arc of a circle 99.70ГўВЂВЇm in radius; thence, on an azimuth bearing of 286Г‹Вљ04ГўВЂВІ, following the north boundary of chemin de la Montagne nord (as shown on the original cadastral plan), a distance of 40.03ГўВЂВЇm; thence, on an azimuth bearing of 288Г‹Вљ56ГўВЂВІ, following the north boundary of chemin de la Montagne nord (as shown on the original cadastral plan), a distance of 40.00ГўВЂВЇm; thence, on an azimuth bearing of 278Г‹Вљ29ГўВЂВІ, following the north boundary of chemin de la Montagne nord (as shown on the original cadastral plan), to a point located at the intersection of the division line between lots <Keep>16C</Keep> and 17, range 6, cadastre of the Township of Hull, a distance of 20.34ГўВЂВЇm; thence, on an azimuth bearing of 288Г‹Вљ38ГўВЂВІ, following the north boundary of chemin de la Montagne nord (as shown on the original cadastral plan), a distance of 62.53ГўВЂВЇm; thence, on an azimuth bearing of 303Г‹Вљ48ГўВЂВІ, following the northeast boundary of chemin de la Montagne nord (as shown on the original cadastral plan), a distance of 21.43ГўВЂВЇm; thence, on an azimuth bearing of 311Г‹Вљ14ГўВЂВІ, following the northeast boundary of chemin de la Montagne nord (as shown on the original cadastral plan), a distance of 41.42ГўВЂВЇm; thence, on an azimuth bearing of 315Г‹Вљ58ГўВЂВІ, following the northeast boundary of chemin de la Montagne nord (as shown on the original cadastral plan), a distance of 42.52ГўВЂВЇm; thence, on an azimuth bearing of 316Г‹Вљ39ГўВЂВІ, following the northeast boundary of chemin de la Montagne nord (as shown on the original cadastral plan), a distance of 48.57ГўВЂВЇm; thence, on an azimuth bearing of 316Г‹Вљ04ГўВЂВІ, following the northeast boundary of chemin de la Montagne nord (as shown on the original cadastral plan), a distance of 35.96ГўВЂВЇm; thence, on an azimuth bearing of 301Г‹Вљ20ГўВЂВІ, following the northeast boundary of chemin de la Montagne nord (as shown on the original cadastral plan), a distance of 19.48ГўВЂВЇm; thence, on an azimuth bearing of 295Г‹Вљ17ГўВЂВІ, following the northeast boundary of chemin de la Montagne nord (as shown on the original cadastral plan), a distance of 22.45ГўВЂВЇm; thence, on an azimuth bearing of 290Г‹Вљ56ГўВЂВІ, following the north boundary of chemin de la Montagne nord (as shown on the original cadastral plan), a distance of 53.54ГўВЂВЇm; thence, on an azimuth bearing of 289Г‹Вљ43ГўВЂВІ, following the north boundary of chemin de la Montagne nord (as shown on the original cadastral plan), a distance of 68.60ГўВЂВЇm; thence, on an azimuth bearing of 281Г‹Вљ52ГўВЂВІ, following the north boundary of chemin de la Montagne nord (as shown on the original cadastral plan), a distance of 26.85ГўВЂВЇm; thence, on an azimuth bearing of 272Г‹Вљ32ГўВЂВІ, following the north boundary of chemin de la Montagne nord (as shown on the original cadastral plan), a distance of 31.55ГўВЂВЇm; thence, on an azimuth bearing of 270Г‹Вљ47ГўВЂВІ, following the north boundary of chemin de la Montagne nord (as shown on the original cadastral plan), a distance of 77.11ГўВЂВЇm; thence, on an azimuth bearing of 268Г‹Вљ26ГўВЂВІ, following the north boundary of chemin de la Montagne nord (as shown on the original cadastral plan), a distance of 41.15ГўВЂВЇm; thence, on an azimuth bearing of 265Г‹Вљ19ГўВЂВІ, following the north boundary of chemin de la Montagne nord (as shown on the original cadastral plan), a distance of 34.02ГўВЂВЇm; thence, on an azimuth bearing of 262Г‹Вљ41ГўВЂВІ, following the north boundary of chemin de la Montagne nord (as shown on the original cadastral plan), a distance of 78.44ГўВЂВЇm; thence, on an azimuth bearing of 262Г‹Вљ13ГўВЂВІ, following the north boundary of chemin de la Montagne nord (as shown on the original cadastral plan), a distance of 27.43ГўВЂВЇm; thence, on an azimuth bearing of 262Г‹Вљ27ГўВЂВІ, following the north boundary of chemin de la Montagne nord (as shown on the original cadastral plan), a distance of 59.96ГўВЂВЇm; thence, on an azimuth bearing of 262Г‹Вљ24ГўВЂВІ, following the north boundary of chemin de la Montagne nord (as shown on the original cadastral plan), a distance of 190.90ГўВЂВЇm; thence, on an azimuth bearing of 261Г‹Вљ37ГўВЂВІ, following the north boundary of chemin de la Montagne nord (as shown on the original cadastral plan), a distance of 65.23ГўВЂВЇm; thence, on an azimuth bearing of 263Г‹Вљ50ГўВЂВІ, following the north boundary of chemin de la Montagne nord (as shown on the original cadastral plan), to a point located at the intersection of the division line between lots 18 and <Keep>19A</Keep>, range 6, cadastre of the Township of Hull, a distance of 112.25ГўВЂВЇm; thence, on an azimuth bearing of 267Г‹Вљ22ГўВЂВІ, following the north boundary of chemin de la Montagne nord (as shown on the original cadastral plan), a distance of 101.16ГўВЂВЇm; thence, on an azimuth bearing of 266Г‹Вљ28ГўВЂВІ, following the north boundary of chemin de la Montagne nord (as shown on the original cadastral plan), a distance of 96.29ГўВЂВЇm; thence, on an azimuth bearing of 272Г‹Вљ26ГўВЂВІ, following the north boundary of chemin de la Montagne nord (as shown on the original cadastral plan), a distance of 72.29ГўВЂВЇm; thence, on an azimuth bearing of 280Г‹Вљ29ГўВЂВІ, following the north boundary of chemin de la Montagne nord (as shown on the original cadastral plan), a distance of 48.24ГўВЂВЇm; thence, on an azimuth bearing of 282Г‹Вљ48ГўВЂВІ, following the north boundary of chemin de la Montagne nord (as shown on the original cadastral plan), a distance of 47.43ГўВЂВЇm; thence, on an azimuth bearing of 283Г‹Вљ31ГўВЂВІ, following the north boundary of chemin de la Montagne nord (as shown on the original cadastral plan), a distance of 73.12ГўВЂВЇm; thence, on an azimuth bearing of 284Г‹Вљ40ГўВЂВІ, following the north boundary of chemin de la Montagne nord (as shown on the original cadastral plan), a distance of 45.35ГўВЂВЇm; thence, on an azimuth bearing of 287Г‹Вљ50ГўВЂВІ, following the north boundary of chemin de la Montagne nord (as shown on the original cadastral plan), a distance of 34.74ГўВЂВЇm; thence, on an azimuth bearing of 293Г‹Вљ56ГўВЂВІ, following the northeast boundary of chemin de la Montagne nord (as shown on the original cadastral plan), a distance of 18.26ГўВЂВЇm; thence, on an azimuth bearing of 297Г‹Вљ21ГўВЂВІ, following the northeast boundary of chemin de la Montagne nord (as shown on the original cadastral plan), to a point located at the intersection of the division line between lots <Keep>19A</Keep> and <Keep>20A</Keep>, range 6, cadastre of the Township of Hull, a distance of 22.00ГўВЂВЇm; thence, on an azimuth bearing of 303Г‹Вљ31ГўВЂВІ, following the northeast boundary of chemin de la Montagne nord (as shown on the original cadastral plan), a distance of 51.72ГўВЂВЇm; thence, on an azimuth bearing of 288Г‹Вљ45ГўВЂВІ, following the north boundary of chemin de la Montagne nord (as shown on the original cadastral plan), a distance of 45.53ГўВЂВЇm; thence, on an azimuth bearing of 286Г‹Вљ26ГўВЂВІ, following the north boundary of chemin de la Montagne nord (as shown on the original cadastral plan), a distance of 34.92ГўВЂВЇm; thence, on an azimuth bearing of 297Г‹Вљ34ГўВЂВІ, following the northeast boundary of chemin de la Montagne nord (as shown on the original cadastral plan), a distance of 28.82ГўВЂВЇm; thence, on an azimuth bearing of 308Г‹Вљ26ГўВЂВІ, following the northeast boundary of chemin de la Montagne nord (as shown on the original cadastral plan), a distance of 26.29ГўВЂВЇm; thence, on an azimuth bearing of 311Г‹Вљ05ГўВЂВІ, following the northeast boundary of chemin de la Montagne nord (as shown on the original cadastral plan), a distance of 70.68ГўВЂВЇm; thence, on an azimuth bearing of 312Г‹Вљ45ГўВЂВІ, following the northeast boundary of chemin de la Montagne nord (as shown on the original cadastral plan), a distance of 93.11ГўВЂВЇm; thence, on an azimuth bearing of 311Г‹Вљ56ГўВЂВІ, following the northeast boundary of chemin de la Montagne nord (as shown on the original cadastral plan), a distance of 44.83ГўВЂВЇm; thence, on an azimuth bearing of 310Г‹Вљ44ГўВЂВІ, following the northeast boundary of chemin de la Montagne nord (as shown on the original cadastral plan), a distance of 106.35ГўВЂВЇm; thence, on an azimuth bearing of 305Г‹Вљ12ГўВЂВІ, following the northeast boundary of chemin de la Montagne nord (as shown on the original cadastral plan), a distance of 38.47ГўВЂВЇm; thence, on an azimuth bearing of 304Г‹Вљ20ГўВЂВІ, following the northeast boundary of chemin de la Montagne nord (as shown on the original cadastral plan), a distance of 62.26ГўВЂВЇm; thence, on an azimuth bearing of 308Г‹Вљ42ГўВЂВІ, following the northeast boundary of chemin de la Montagne nord (as shown on the original cadastral plan), a distance of 33.63ГўВЂВЇm; thence, on an azimuth bearing of 311Г‹Вљ04ГўВЂВІ, following the northeast boundary of chemin de la Montagne nord (as shown on the original cadastral plan), a distance of 50.27ГўВЂВЇm; thence, on an azimuth bearing of 315Г‹Вљ14ГўВЂВ™, following the northeast boundary of chemin de la Montagne nord (as shown on the original cadastral plan), a distance of 37.19ГўВЂВЇm; thence, on an azimuth bearing of 317Г‹Вљ26ГўВЂВ™, following the northeast boundary of chemin de la Montagne nord (as shown on the original cadastral plan), to a point located at the intersection of the division line between lots 20 and 21, range 7, cadastre of the Township of Hull, a distance of 6.20ГўВЂВЇm; thence, on an azimuth bearing of 317Г‹Вљ26ГўВЂВ™, following the northeast boundary of chemin de la Montagne nord (as shown on the original cadastral plan), a distance of 89.64ГўВЂВЇm; thence, on an azimuth bearing of 319Г‹Вљ45ГўВЂВ™, following the northeast boundary of chemin de la Montagne nord (as shown on the original cadastral plan), a distance of 145.42ГўВЂВЇm; thence, on an azimuth bearing of 319Г‹Вљ17ГўВЂВ™, following the northeast boundary of chemin de la Montagne nord (as shown on the original cadastral plan), a distance of 83.89ГўВЂВЇm; thence, on an azimuth bearing of 318Г‹Вљ39ГўВЂВ™, following the northeast boundary of chemin de la Montagne nord (as shown on the original cadastral plan), a distance of 29.39ГўВЂВЇm; thence, on an azimuth bearing of 315Г‹Вљ12ГўВЂВ™, following the northeast boundary of chemin de la Montagne nord (as shown on the original cadastral plan), a distance of 31.51ГўВЂВЇm; thence, on an azimuth bearing of 311Г‹Вљ03ГўВЂВ™, following the northeast boundary of chemin de la Montagne nord (as shown on the original cadastral plan), a distance of 69.43ГўВЂВЇm; thence, on an azimuth bearing of 312Г‹Вљ55ГўВЂВ™, following the northeast boundary of chemin de la Montagne nord (as shown on the original cadastral plan), a distance of 33.54ГўВЂВЇm; thence, on an azimuth bearing of 319Г‹Вљ53ГўВЂВ™, following the northeast boundary of chemin de la Montagne nord (as shown on the original cadastral plan), a distance of 58.23ГўВЂВЇm; thence, on an azimuth bearing of 328Г‹Вљ34ГўВЂВ™, following the northeast boundary of chemin de la Montagne nord (as shown on the original cadastral plan), a distance of 66.81ГўВЂВЇm; thence, on an azimuth bearing of 328Г‹Вљ01ГўВЂВ™, following the northeast boundary of chemin de la Montagne nord (as shown on the original cadastral plan), a distance of 115.41ГўВЂВЇm; thence, on an azimuth bearing of 325Г‹Вљ14ГўВЂВ™, following the northeast boundary of chemin de la Montagne nord (as shown on the original cadastral plan), a distance of 133.25ГўВЂВЇm; thence, on an azimuth bearing of 326Г‹Вљ35ГўВЂВ™, following the northeast boundary of chemin de la Montagne nord (as shown on the original cadastral plan), to a point located at the intersection of the division line between lots 21 and 22, range 7, cadastre of the Township of Hull, a distance of 119.94ГўВЂВЇm; thence, on an azimuth bearing of 325Г‹Вљ40ГўВЂВ™, following the northeast boundary of chemin de la Montagne nord (as shown on the original cadastral plan), a distance of 33.57ГўВЂВЇm; thence, on an azimuth bearing of 320Г‹Вљ24ГўВЂВ™, following the northeast boundary of chemin de la Montagne nord (as shown on the original cadastral plan), a distance of 35.04ГўВЂВЇm; thence, on an azimuth bearing of 312Г‹Вљ03ГўВЂВ™, following the northeast boundary of chemin de la Montagne nord (as shown on the original cadastral plan), a distance of 104.08ГўВЂВЇm; thence, on an azimuth bearing of 314Г‹Вљ10ГўВЂВ™, following the northeast boundary of chemin de la Montagne nord (as shown on the original cadastral plan), a distance of 54.26ГўВЂВЇm; thence, on an azimuth bearing of 318Г‹Вљ29ГўВЂВ™, following the northeast boundary of chemin de la Montagne nord (as shown on the original cadastral plan), a distance of 35.35ГўВЂВЇm; thence, on an azimuth bearing of 320Г‹Вљ33ГўВЂВ™, following the northeast boundary of chemin de la Montagne nord (as shown on the original cadastral plan), a distance of 110.86ГўВЂВЇm; thence, on an azimuth bearing of 322Г‹Вљ14ГўВЂВ™, following the northeast boundary of chemin de la Montagne nord (as shown on the original cadastral plan), a distance of 81.36ГўВЂВЇm; thence, on an azimuth bearing of 324Г‹Вљ16ГўВЂВ™, following the northeast boundary of chemin de la Montagne nord (as shown on the original cadastral plan), a distance of 33.47ГўВЂВЇm; thence, on an azimuth bearing of 331Г‹Вљ58ГўВЂВ™, following the northeast boundary of chemin de la Montagne nord (as shown on the original cadastral plan), a distance of 60.65ГўВЂВЇm; thence, on an azimuth bearing of 340Г‹Вљ13ГўВЂВ™, following the east boundary of chemin de la Montagne nord (as shown on the original cadastral plan), a distance of 33.32ГўВЂВЇm; thence, on an azimuth bearing of 356Г‹Вљ47ГўВЂВ™, following the east boundary of chemin de la Montagne nord (as shown on the original cadastral plan), a distance of 28.69ГўВЂВЇm; thence, on an azimuth bearing of 3Г‹Вљ27ГўВЂВ™, following the east boundary of chemin de la Montagne nord (as shown on the original cadastral plan), a distance of 126.46ГўВЂВЇm; thence, on an azimuth bearing of 358Г‹Вљ40ГўВЂВ™, following the east boundary of chemin de la Montagne nord (as shown on the original cadastral plan), a distance of 25.67ГўВЂВЇm; thence, on an azimuth bearing of 350Г‹Вљ44ГўВЂВ™, following the east boundary of chemin de la Montagne nord (as shown on the original cadastral plan), a distance of 15.95ГўВЂВЇm; thence, on an azimuth bearing of 348Г‹Вљ11ГўВЂВ™, following the east boundary of chemin de la Montagne nord (as shown on the original cadastral plan), a distance of 31.70ГўВЂВЇm; thence, on an azimuth bearing of 319Г‹Вљ05ГўВЂВ™, following the northeast boundary of chemin de la Montagne nord (as shown on the original cadastral plan), a distance of 35.36ГўВЂВЇm; thence, on an azimuth bearing of 323Г‹Вљ06ГўВЂВ™, following the northeast boundary of chemin de la Montagne nord (as shown on the original cadastral plan), a distance of 27.24ГўВЂВЇm; thence, on an azimuth bearing of 319Г‹Вљ53ГўВЂВ™, following the northeast boundary of chemin de la Montagne nord (as shown on the original cadastral plan), a distance of 31.04ГўВЂВЇm; thence, on an azimuth bearing of 317Г‹Вљ38ГўВЂВ™, following the northeast boundary of chemin de la Montagne nord (as shown on the original cadastral plan), a distance of 23.45ГўВЂВЇm; thence, on an azimuth bearing of 314Г‹Вљ51ГўВЂВ™, following the northeast boundary of chemin de la Montagne nord (as shown on the original cadastral plan), to a point located at the intersection of the division line between lot 22, range 7, cadastre of the Township of Hull and lot <Keep>2ГўВЂВЇ635ГўВЂВЇ271</Keep>, Cadastre du QuГѓВ©bec, a distance of 9.68ГўВЂВЇm.</Text>
</Provision>
<BillPiece><Heading level="2"><TitleText>2.2 Section 2</TitleText></Heading></BillPiece><Provision>
<Text>This portion of Gatineau Park, described in SectionГўВЂВЇ2, is included in the registration division of Gatineau, located in the Municipality of Chelsea, and forms part of the Cadastre du QuГѓВ©bec.</Text>
</Provision><BillPiece><Heading level="3"><TitleText>Municipality of Chelsea</TitleText></Heading></BillPiece><Provision topmarginspacing="-.75">
<Text>
Beginning at the southeast corner of lot <Keep>2ГўВЂВЇ636ГўВЂВЇ632</Keep> (chemin de la Montagne nord), northwesterly, following the division lines between lots <Keep>2ГўВЂВЇ636ГўВЂВЇ632</Keep> (chemin de la Montagne nord) and <Keep>2ГўВЂВЇ635ГўВЂВЇ271</Keep>, to the west corner of lot <Keep>2ГўВЂВЇ635ГўВЂВЇ271</Keep>; thence, northwesterly, following the division lines between lots <Keep>2ГўВЂВЇ636ГўВЂВЇ632</Keep> (chemin de la Montagne nord) and <Keep>2ГўВЂВЇ635ГўВЂВЇ272</Keep>, to the west corner of lot <Keep>2ГўВЂВЇ635ГўВЂВЇ272</Keep>; thence, in a general northwesterly direction, following the division lines between lots <Keep>2ГўВЂВЇ636ГўВЂВЇ632</Keep> (chemin de la Montagne nord) and <Keep>2ГўВЂВЇ635ГўВЂВЇ270</Keep>, to the west corner of lot <Keep>2ГўВЂВЇ635ГўВЂВЇ270</Keep>; thence, westerly, following the division line between lots <Keep>2ГўВЂВЇ636ГўВЂВЇ632</Keep> (chemin de la Montagne nord) and <Keep>2ГўВЂВЇ635ГўВЂВЇ272</Keep>, to the west corner of lot <Keep>2ГўВЂВЇ635ГўВЂВЇ272</Keep>; thence, westerly, following the division lines between lot <Keep>2ГўВЂВЇ636ГўВЂВЇ632</Keep> (chemin de la Montagne nord) and lots <Keep>2ГўВЂВЇ635ГўВЂВЇ270</Keep>, <Keep>2ГўВЂВЇ635ГўВЂВЇ272</Keep> and <Keep>2ГўВЂВЇ635ГўВЂВЇ273</Keep>, to the northwest corner of lot <Keep>2ГўВЂВЇ636ГўВЂВЇ632</Keep> (chemin de la Montagne nord); thence, westerly, following the division lines <Keep>between</Keep> lots <Keep>2ГўВЂВЇ735ГўВЂВЇ412</Keep> (chemin de la Montagne nord) and <Keep>2ГўВЂВЇ635ГўВЂВЇ273</Keep>, to the southeast corner of lot <Keep>2ГўВЂВЇ635ГўВЂВЇ259</Keep>; thence, in a general westerly direction, following the division lines between lots <Keep>2ГўВЂВЇ735ГўВЂВЇ412</Keep> (chemin de la Montagne nord) and <Keep>2ГўВЂВЇ635ГўВЂВЇ259</Keep>, to the northwest corner of lot <Keep>2ГўВЂВЇ735ГўВЂВЇ412</Keep>; thence, westerly, following the division lines between lots <Keep>2ГўВЂВЇ735ГўВЂВЇ411</Keep> (chemin de la Montagne nord) and <Keep>2ГўВЂВЇ635ГўВЂВЇ259</Keep>, to the southwest corner of lot <Keep>2ГўВЂВЇ635ГўВЂВЇ259</Keep>; thence, in a general westerly direction, following the division lines between lots <Keep>2ГўВЂВЇ735ГўВЂВЇ411</Keep> (chemin de la Montagne nord) and <Keep>2ГўВЂВЇ635ГўВЂВЇ273</Keep>, to the northwest corner of lot <Keep>2ГўВЂВЇ735ГўВЂВЇ411</Keep>; thence, northwesterly, following the division lines between lots <Keep>2ГўВЂВЇ735ГўВЂВЇ408</Keep> (chemin de la Montagne nord) and <Keep>2ГўВЂВЇ635ГўВЂВЇ273</Keep>, to the north corner of lot <Keep>2ГўВЂВЇ735ГўВЂВЇ408</Keep>; thence, in a general northwesterly direction, following the division lines between lots <Keep>2ГўВЂВЇ735ГўВЂВЇ407</Keep> (chemin de la Montagne nord) and <Keep>2ГўВЂВЇ635ГўВЂВЇ273</Keep>, to the northwest corner of lot <Keep>2ГўВЂВЇ735ГўВЂВЇ407</Keep>; thence, westerly, following the division lines between lots <Keep>2ГўВЂВЇ636ГўВЂВЇ633</Keep> (chemin de la Montagne nord) and <Keep>2ГўВЂВЇ635ГўВЂВЇ273</Keep>, to the northwest corner of lot <Keep>2ГўВЂВЇ636ГўВЂВЇ633</Keep>; thence, in a general westerly direction, following the division lines between lots <Keep>2ГўВЂВЇ735ГўВЂВЇ406</Keep> (chemin de la Montagne nord) and <Keep>2ГўВЂВЇ635ГўВЂВЇ273</Keep>, to the southeast corner of lot <Keep>2ГўВЂВЇ635ГўВЂВЇ406</Keep>; thence, northwesterly, following the division lines between lots <Keep>2ГўВЂВЇ735ГўВЂВЇ404</Keep> (chemin de la Montagne nord) and <Keep>2ГўВЂВЇ635ГўВЂВЇ406</Keep>, to the north corner of lot <Keep>2ГўВЂВЇ735ГўВЂВЇ404</Keep>; thence, northwesterly, following the division line between lot <Keep>2ГўВЂВЇ735ГўВЂВЇ403</Keep> (chemin de la Montagne nord) and lots <Keep>2ГўВЂВЇ635ГўВЂВЇ406</Keep> and <Keep>2ГўВЂВЇ635ГўВЂВЇ074</Keep>, to the north corner of lot <Keep>2ГўВЂВЇ735ГўВЂВЇ403</Keep>; thence, in a general northwesterly direction, following the division lines between lots <Keep>2ГўВЂВЇ735ГўВЂВЇ402</Keep> (chemin de la Montagne nord) and <Keep>2ГўВЂВЇ635ГўВЂВЇ074</Keep>, to the northwest corner of lot <Keep>2ГўВЂВЇ735ГўВЂВЇ402</Keep>; thence, westerly, following the division lines between lots <Keep>2ГўВЂВЇ636ГўВЂВЇ634</Keep> (chemin de la Montagne nord) and <Keep>2ГўВЂВЇ635ГўВЂВЇ074</Keep>, to the northwest corner of lot <Keep>2ГўВЂВЇ636ГўВЂВЇ634</Keep>; thence, westerly, following the lines between lot <Keep>2ГўВЂВЇ735ГўВЂВЇ399</Keep> (chemin de la Montagne nord) and lots <Keep>2ГўВЂВЇ635ГўВЂВЇ074</Keep>, <Keep>2ГўВЂВЇ635ГўВЂВЇ020</Keep> and <Keep>2ГўВЂВЇ635ГўВЂВЇ074</Keep>, to the northwest corner of lot <Keep>2ГўВЂВЇ735ГўВЂВЇ399</Keep>; thence, westerly, following the division lines between lots <Keep>2ГўВЂВЇ636ГўВЂВЇ635</Keep> (chemin de la Montagne nord) and <Keep>2ГўВЂВЇ635ГўВЂВЇ074</Keep>, to the northwest corner of lot <Keep>2ГўВЂВЇ636ГўВЂВЇ635</Keep>; thence, westerly, following the division lines between lots <Keep>2ГўВЂВЇ735ГўВЂВЇ398</Keep> (chemin de la Montagne nord) and <Keep>2ГўВЂВЇ635ГўВЂВЇ074</Keep>, to the northwest corner of lot <Keep>2ГўВЂВЇ735ГўВЂВЇ398</Keep>.</Text>
</Provision>
<BillPiece><Heading level="2"><TitleText>2.3 Section 3</TitleText></Heading></BillPiece><Provision>
<Text>This portion of Gatineau Park, described in SectionГўВЂВЇ3, is included in the registration divisions of Gatineau and Pontiac, located in the Municipalities of Pontiac and La PГѓВЄche and forms part of the cadastres of the Township of Aldfield, the Township of Eardley, the Township of Masham, the Township of Onslow and the Cadastre du QuГѓВ©bec.</Text>
</Provision><BillPiece><Heading level="3"><TitleText>Municipality of Pontiac</TitleText></Heading></BillPiece>
<Provision>
<Text>Beginning at the southeast corner of lot <Keep>2ГўВЂВЇ684ГўВЂВЇ171</Keep>, westerly and then northwesterly, following the division lines between lots <Keep>2ГўВЂВЇ756ГўВЂВЇ027</Keep> (chemin de la Montagne nord) and <Keep>2ГўВЂВЇ684ГўВЂВЇ171</Keep>, to the northwest corner of lot <Keep>2ГўВЂВЇ756ГўВЂВЇ027</Keep>; thence, in a general northwesterly direction, following the division lines between lots <Keep>2ГўВЂВЇ756ГўВЂВЇ028</Keep> (chemin de la Montagne nord) and <Keep>2ГўВЂВЇ684ГўВЂВЇ171</Keep>, to the northwest corner of lot <Keep>2ГўВЂВЇ684ГўВЂВЇ171</Keep>; thence, easterly, following the division line between lots <Keep>2ГўВЂВЇ684ГўВЂВЇ171</Keep> and <Keep>2ГўВЂВЇ750ГўВЂВЇ617</Keep>, to the most southwesterly corner of lot <Keep>2ГўВЂВЇ683ГўВЂВЇ938</Keep>, a distance of 20.77ГўВЂВЇm; thence, easterly, following the division line between lots <Keep>2ГўВЂВЇ683ГўВЂВЇ938</Keep> and <Keep>2ГўВЂВЇ750ГўВЂВЇ617</Keep>, to a point located at a distance of 31.44ГўВЂВЇm; thence, northeasterly, following the division line <Keep>between</Keep> lots <Keep>2ГўВЂВЇ683ГўВЂВЇ938</Keep> and <Keep>2ГўВЂВЇ750ГўВЂВЇ617</Keep>, to a point located at a distance of 16.83ГўВЂВЇm; thence, in a general northerly-northwesterly direction, following the division lines between lots <Keep>2ГўВЂВЇ683ГўВЂВЇ938</Keep> and <Keep>2ГўВЂВЇ750ГўВЂВЇ617</Keep>, to a point located at the northwest corner of lot <Keep>2ГўВЂВЇ750ГўВЂВЇ617</Keep>; thence, westerly and northwesterly, following the division line between lots <Keep>2ГўВЂВЇ683ГўВЂВЇ938</Keep> and <Keep>2ГўВЂВЇ683ГўВЂВЇ923</Keep>, to a point located at the northwest corner of lot <Keep>2ГўВЂВЇ683ГўВЂВЇ923</Keep>; thence, northwesterly, northerly and westerly, following the division lines between lots <Keep>2ГўВЂВЇ683ГўВЂВЇ937</Keep> and <Keep>2ГўВЂВЇ683ГўВЂВЇ938</Keep>, to a point located at the northeast corner of lot <Keep>2ГўВЂВЇ683ГўВЂВЇ821</Keep>; thence, westerly, following the division line between lots <Keep>2ГўВЂВЇ683ГўВЂВЇ821</Keep> and <Keep>2ГўВЂВЇ683ГўВЂВЇ938</Keep>, to a point located at the northwest corner of lot <Keep>2ГўВЂВЇ683ГўВЂВЇ821</Keep>; thence, westerly, following the division line between lots <Keep>2ГўВЂВЇ683ГўВЂВЇ820</Keep> and <Keep>2ГўВЂВЇ683ГўВЂВЇ938</Keep>, to a point located at the northwest corner of lot <Keep>2ГўВЂВЇ683ГўВЂВЇ820</Keep>; thence, in a general northwesterly direction, following the division line between lots <Keep>2ГўВЂВЇ683ГўВЂВЇ819</Keep> and <Keep>2ГўВЂВЇ683ГўВЂВЇ938</Keep>, to a point located at the northwest corner of lot <Keep>2ГўВЂВЇ683ГўВЂВЇ819</Keep>; thence, northwesterly, following the division line between lots <Keep>2ГўВЂВЇ683ГўВЂВЇ938</Keep> and <Keep>2ГўВЂВЇ683ГўВЂВЇ818</Keep>, to the north corner of lot <Keep>2ГўВЂВЇ683ГўВЂВЇ818</Keep>; thence, westerly, following the division line between lots <Keep>2ГўВЂВЇ683ГўВЂВЇ818</Keep> and <Keep>2ГўВЂВЇ683ГўВЂВЇ822</Keep>, to a point located at a distance of approximately 103ГўВЂВЇm; thence, on an azimuth bearing of 350Г‹Вљ53ГўВЂВІ, to a point located at 287.90ГўВЂВЇm; thence, on an azimuth bearing of 315Г‹Вљ35ГўВЂВІ, to a point located at 3.85ГўВЂВЇm; thence, on an azimuth bearing of 263Г‹Вљ05ГўВЂВІ, to a point located at the intersection of the east boundary of lot <Keep>2ГўВЂВЇ683ГўВЂВЇ751</Keep>; thence, northerly, following the division line between lots <Keep>2ГўВЂВЇ683ГўВЂВЇ751</Keep> and <Keep>2ГўВЂВЇ683ГўВЂВЇ822</Keep>, to a point located at the northeast corner of lot <Keep>2ГўВЂВЇ683ГўВЂВЇ751</Keep>; thence, westerly, following the division lines between lots <Keep>2ГўВЂВЇ683ГўВЂВЇ751</Keep> and <Keep>2ГўВЂВЇ683ГўВЂВЇ822</Keep>, to a point located at the northwest corner of lot <Keep>2ГўВЂВЇ683ГўВЂВЇ751</Keep>; thence, westerly, following the division lines between lots <Keep>2ГўВЂВЇ755ГўВЂВЇ775</Keep> and <Keep>2ГўВЂВЇ683ГўВЂВЇ822</Keep>, to a point located at the southeast corner of lot <Keep>2ГўВЂВЇ683ГўВЂВЇ558</Keep>; thence, northerly, following the division line between lots <Keep>2ГўВЂВЇ683ГўВЂВЇ558</Keep> and <Keep>2ГўВЂВЇ683ГўВЂВЇ822</Keep>, to a point located at the northeast corner of lot <Keep>2ГўВЂВЇ683ГўВЂВЇ558</Keep>; thence, westerly, following the division lines between lots <Keep>2ГўВЂВЇ683ГўВЂВЇ558</Keep> and <Keep>2ГўВЂВЇ683ГўВЂВЇ822</Keep>, to a point located at the northwest corner of lot <Keep>2ГўВЂВЇ683ГўВЂВЇ558</Keep>; thence, southwesterly, following the division lines between lots <Keep>2ГўВЂВЇ755ГўВЂВЇ775</Keep> and <Keep>2ГўВЂВЇ683ГўВЂВЇ822</Keep>, to a point located at distances of 32.50ГўВЂВЇm and 35.65ГўВЂВЇm; thence, westerly, following the division line between lots <Keep>2ГўВЂВЇ755ГўВЂВЇ775</Keep> and <Keep>2ГўВЂВЇ683ГўВЂВЇ822</Keep>, to a point located at the northwest corner of lot <Keep>2ГўВЂВЇ755ГўВЂВЇ775</Keep>; thence, southerly, following the division line between lots <Keep>2ГўВЂВЇ683ГўВЂВЇ822</Keep> and <Keep>2ГўВЂВЇ755ГўВЂВЇ775</Keep>, to the northeast corner of lot <Keep>2ГўВЂВЇ683ГўВЂВЇ557</Keep>; thence, westerly, following the division line between lots <Keep>2ГўВЂВЇ683ГўВЂВЇ822</Keep> and <Keep>2ГўВЂВЇ683ГўВЂВЇ557</Keep>, to a point located at the northwest corner of lot <Keep>2ГўВЂВЇ683ГўВЂВЇ557</Keep>; thence, northerly, following the division line between lots <Keep>2ГўВЂВЇ683ГўВЂВЇ822</Keep> and <Keep>2ГўВЂВЇ683ГўВЂВЇ556</Keep>, to a point located at the northeast corner of lot <Keep>2ГўВЂВЇ683ГўВЂВЇ556</Keep>; thence, westerly, following the division lines between lots <Keep>2ГўВЂВЇ683ГўВЂВЇ822</Keep> and <Keep>2ГўВЂВЇ683ГўВЂВЇ556</Keep>, to a point located at the northwest corner of lot <Keep>2ГўВЂВЇ683ГўВЂВЇ556</Keep>; thence, westerly, following the division line between lot <Keep>2ГўВЂВЇ683ГўВЂВЇ822</Keep> and lots <Keep>2ГўВЂВЇ755ГўВЂВЇ747</Keep> and <Keep>2ГўВЂВЇ755ГўВЂВЇ746</Keep> to a point located at the northwest corner of lot <Keep>2ГўВЂВЇ755ГўВЂВЇ746</Keep>; thence, northwesterly, crossing lot <Keep>2ГўВЂВЇ683ГўВЂВЇ464</Keep>, to a point located at the southeast corner of lot <Keep>2ГўВЂВЇ750ГўВЂВЇ624</Keep>; thence, northwesterly, crossing lot <Keep>2ГўВЂВЇ750ГўВЂВЇ624</Keep>, to a point located at the northwest corner of lot <Keep>2ГўВЂВЇ750ГўВЂВЇ624</Keep>; thence, northerly, following the division line between lots <Keep>2ГўВЂВЇ750ГўВЂВЇ622</Keep> and <Keep>2ГўВЂВЇ864ГўВЂВЇ183</Keep> (chemin de lГўВЂВ™HГѓВґtel-de-Ville), to a point located at the northeast corner of lot <Keep>2ГўВЂВЇ864ГўВЂВЇ183</Keep> (chemin de lГўВЂВ™HГѓВґtel-de-Ville); thence, westerly, following the division line between lots <Keep>2ГўВЂВЇ750ГўВЂВЇ622</Keep> and <Keep>2ГўВЂВЇ864ГўВЂВЇ183</Keep> (chemin de lГўВЂВ™HГѓВґtel-de-Ville), to a point located at the southeast corner of lot <Keep>2ГўВЂВЇ750ГўВЂВЇ623</Keep>; thence, westerly, following the division line between lots <Keep>2ГўВЂВЇ750ГўВЂВЇ623</Keep> and <Keep>2ГўВЂВЇ864ГўВЂВЇ183</Keep> (chemin de lГўВЂВ™HГѓВґtel-de-Ville), to a point located at the southwest corner of lot <Keep>2ГўВЂВЇ750ГўВЂВЇ623</Keep>; thence, westerly, following the division line between lots <Keep>2ГўВЂВЇ889ГўВЂВЇ768</Keep> and <Keep>2ГўВЂВЇ864ГўВЂВЇ182</Keep> (chemin de lГўВЂВ™HГѓВґtel-de-Ville), to a point located at the southeast corner of lot <Keep>2ГўВЂВЇ683ГўВЂВЇ360</Keep>; thence, northerly, following the division line between lots <Keep>2ГўВЂВЇ889ГўВЂВЇ768</Keep> and <Keep>2ГўВЂВЇ683ГўВЂВЇ360</Keep>, to a point located at the northwest corner of lot <Keep>2ГўВЂВЇ889ГўВЂВЇ768</Keep>; thence, in a westerly, northerly and westerly directions, following the division line between lots <Keep>2ГўВЂВЇ683ГўВЂВЇ360</Keep> and <Keep>2ГўВЂВЇ750ГўВЂВЇ622</Keep>, to a point located at the intersection of the east boundary of lot <Keep>2ГўВЂВЇ682ГўВЂВЇ401</Keep>; thence, northerly, following the division line between lot <Keep>2ГўВЂВЇ750ГўВЂВЇ622</Keep> and lots <Keep>2ГўВЂВЇ682ГўВЂВЇ401</Keep> and <Keep>2ГўВЂВЇ683ГўВЂВЇ356</Keep>, to a point located at the northeast corner of lot <Keep>2ГўВЂВЇ683ГўВЂВЇ356</Keep>; thence, westerly, following the division line between lot <Keep>2ГўВЂВЇ750ГўВЂВЇ622</Keep> and lots <Keep>2ГўВЂВЇ683ГўВЂВЇ356</Keep>, <Keep>2ГўВЂВЇ755ГўВЂВЇ693</Keep> and <Keep>2ГўВЂВЇ683ГўВЂВЇ351</Keep>, to a point located at the intersection of the east boundary of lot <Keep>2ГўВЂВЇ683ГўВЂВЇ347</Keep>; thence, northerly, northwesterly and southwesterly, following the division line between lots <Keep>2ГўВЂВЇ750ГўВЂВЇ622</Keep> and <Keep>2ГўВЂВЇ683ГўВЂВЇ347</Keep>, to a point located at the northwest corner of lot <Keep>2ГўВЂВЇ683ГўВЂВЇ347</Keep>; thence, northerly, following the division line between lot <Keep>2ГўВЂВЇ750ГўВЂВЇ622</Keep> and lots <Keep>2ГўВЂВЇ683ГўВЂВЇ100</Keep>, <Keep>2ГўВЂВЇ864ГўВЂВЇ184</Keep>, <Keep>2ГўВЂВЇ683ГўВЂВЇ102</Keep>, <Keep>2ГўВЂВЇ683ГўВЂВЇ141</Keep>, <Keep>2ГўВЂВЇ683ГўВЂВЇ140</Keep>, <Keep>2ГўВЂВЇ683ГўВЂВЇ142</Keep> and <Keep>2ГўВЂВЇ683ГўВЂВЇ143</Keep>, to a point located at the east corner of lot <Keep>2ГўВЂВЇ683ГўВЂВЇ143</Keep>; thence, northwesterly, following the division line between lot <Keep>2ГўВЂВЇ750ГўВЂВЇ622</Keep> and lots <Keep>2ГўВЂВЇ683ГўВЂВЇ143</Keep>, <Keep>2ГўВЂВЇ683ГўВЂВЇ144</Keep> and <Keep>2ГўВЂВЇ683ГўВЂВЇ138</Keep>, to a point located at the northwest corner of lot <Keep>2ГўВЂВЇ750ГўВЂВЇ622</Keep>; thence, westerly, following the division line between lot <Keep>2ГўВЂВЇ756ГўВЂВЇ039</Keep> and lots <Keep>2ГўВЂВЇ683ГўВЂВЇ138</Keep>, <Keep>2ГўВЂВЇ683ГўВЂВЇ129</Keep> and <Keep>2ГўВЂВЇ683ГўВЂВЇ128</Keep>, to a point located at the northwest corner of lot <Keep>2ГўВЂВЇ683ГўВЂВЇ128</Keep>; thence, northerly, following the division line between lots <Keep>2ГўВЂВЇ756ГўВЂВЇ039</Keep> and <Keep>2ГўВЂВЇ683ГўВЂВЇ117</Keep>, to a point located at the northeast corner of lot <Keep>2ГўВЂВЇ683ГўВЂВЇ117</Keep>; thence, northwesterly, following the division line between lots <Keep>2ГўВЂВЇ756ГўВЂВЇ039</Keep> and <Keep>2ГўВЂВЇ683ГўВЂВЇ117</Keep>, to a point located at the northwest corner of lot <Keep>2ГўВЂВЇ683ГўВЂВЇ117</Keep>; thence, northwesterly, following the division line between lots <Keep>2ГўВЂВЇ756ГўВЂВЇ039</Keep> and <Keep>2ГўВЂВЇ683ГўВЂВЇ103</Keep>, to a point located at the northwest corner of lot <Keep>2ГўВЂВЇ683ГўВЂВЇ103</Keep>; thence, northwesterly, following the division line between lots <Keep>2ГўВЂВЇ756ГўВЂВЇ039</Keep> and <Keep>2ГўВЂВЇ872ГўВЂВЇ193</Keep>, to a point located at the north corner of lot <Keep>2ГўВЂВЇ872ГўВЂВЇ193</Keep>; thence, in a general northwesterly direction, following the division lines between lots <Keep>2ГўВЂВЇ756ГўВЂВЇ039</Keep> and <Keep>2ГўВЂВЇ750ГўВЂВЇ627</Keep>, to a point located at the northwest corner of lot <Keep>2ГўВЂВЇ750ГўВЂВЇ627</Keep>; thence, southerly, following the division line between lots <Keep>2ГўВЂВЇ750ГўВЂВЇ627</Keep> and <Keep>2ГўВЂВЇ750ГўВЂВЇ628</Keep>, to a point located at the southwest corner of lot <Keep>2ГўВЂВЇ750ГўВЂВЇ627</Keep>; thence, westerly, following the division line between lot <Keep>2ГўВЂВЇ750ГўВЂВЇ628</Keep> and lots <Keep>2ГўВЂВЇ682ГўВЂВЇ987</Keep>, <Keep>2ГўВЂВЇ755ГўВЂВЇ643</Keep>, <Keep>2ГўВЂВЇ682ГўВЂВЇ904</Keep>, <Keep>2ГўВЂВЇ750ГўВЂВЇ709</Keep>, <Keep>2ГўВЂВЇ682ГўВЂВЇ899</Keep>, <Keep>2ГўВЂВЇ682ГўВЂВЇ896</Keep> and <Keep>2ГўВЂВЇ864ГўВЂВЇ191</Keep>, to a point located at the southwest corner of lot <Keep>2ГўВЂВЇ750ГўВЂВЇ628</Keep>; thence, westerly, crossing lots <Keep>2ГўВЂВЇ682ГўВЂВЇ908</Keep> and <Keep>2ГўВЂВЇ682ГўВЂВЇ889</Keep>, to a point located at the southeast corner of lot <Keep>2ГўВЂВЇ682ГўВЂВЇ670</Keep>; thence, westerly, following the division lines between lots <Keep>2ГўВЂВЇ682ГўВЂВЇ666</Keep> and <Keep>2ГўВЂВЇ682ГўВЂВЇ670</Keep>, to a point located at the southwest corner of lot <Keep>2ГўВЂВЇ682ГўВЂВЇ670</Keep>; thence, on an azimuth bearing of 295Г‹Вљ24ГўВЂВ™, to a point located at a distance of 72.02ГўВЂВЇm; thence, on an azimuth bearing of 350Г‹Вљ47ГўВЂВ™, to a point located at a distance of 283.68ГўВЂВЇm; thence, northwesterly, crossing lots <Keep>2ГўВЂВЇ682ГўВЂВЇ669</Keep>, <Keep>2ГўВЂВЇ750ГўВЂВЇ682</Keep>, <Keep>2ГўВЂВЇ682ГўВЂВЇ667</Keep> and <Keep>2ГўВЂВЇ872ГўВЂВЇ186</Keep>, to a point located at the intersection of the division line between lots <Keep>2ГўВЂВЇ756ГўВЂВЇ041</Keep> and <Keep>2ГўВЂВЇ872ГўВЂВЇ186</Keep>, at an approximate distance of 677ГўВЂВЇm. This point is also located at an approximate distance of 235ГўВЂВЇm easterly of the northwest corner of lot <Keep>2ГўВЂВЇ682ГўВЂВЇ507</Keep>; thence, westerly, following the division line between lot <Keep>2ГўВЂВЇ756ГўВЂВЇ041</Keep> and lots <Keep>2ГўВЂВЇ872ГўВЂВЇ186</Keep>, <Keep>2ГўВЂВЇ682ГўВЂВЇ507</Keep>, <Keep>2ГўВЂВЇ750ГўВЂВЇ676</Keep> and <Keep>2ГўВЂВЇ750ГўВЂВЇ675</Keep>, to a point located at the northwest corner of lot <Keep>2ГўВЂВЇ750ГўВЂВЇ675</Keep>; thence, westerly, crossing lot <Keep>2ГўВЂВЇ864ГўВЂВЇ194</Keep>, to a point located at the northeast corner of lot <Keep>2ГўВЂВЇ750ГўВЂВЇ674</Keep>; thence, westerly, following the division line between lots <Keep>2ГўВЂВЇ682ГўВЂВЇ498</Keep> and <Keep>2ГўВЂВЇ750ГўВЂВЇ674</Keep>, to the southwest corner of lot <Keep>2ГўВЂВЇ682ГўВЂВЇ498</Keep>; thence, northerly, following the division line between lots <Keep>2ГўВЂВЇ682ГўВЂВЇ498</Keep> and <Keep>2ГўВЂВЇ872ГўВЂВЇ178</Keep>, and then following the division line between lots <Keep>2ГўВЂВЇ682ГўВЂВЇ499</Keep> and <Keep>2ГўВЂВЇ872ГўВЂВЇ179</Keep>, to the northwest corner of lot <Keep>2ГўВЂВЇ682ГўВЂВЇ499</Keep>; thence, westerly, following the division line between lots <Keep>2ГўВЂВЇ682ГўВЂВЇ501</Keep> and <Keep>2ГўВЂВЇ872ГўВЂВЇ179</Keep>, to the northwest corner of lot <Keep>2ГўВЂВЇ872ГўВЂВЇ179</Keep>; thence, westerly, following the division lines between lot <Keep>2ГўВЂВЇ750ГўВЂВЇ673</Keep> and lots <Keep>2ГўВЂВЇ682ГўВЂВЇ501</Keep> and <Keep>2ГўВЂВЇ750ГўВЂВЇ633</Keep>, to the northwest corner of lot <Keep>2ГўВЂВЇ750ГўВЂВЇ673</Keep>; thence, westerly, following the division line between lot <Keep>2ГўВЂВЇ864ГўВЂВЇ199</Keep> and lots <Keep>2ГўВЂВЇ682ГўВЂВЇ500</Keep> and <Keep>2ГўВЂВЇ682ГўВЂВЇ472</Keep>, to a point located at an approximate distance of 521.6ГўВЂВЇm; thence, northerly, to a point located at the intersection of the south boundary of lot <Keep>3ГўВЂВЇ964ГўВЂВЇ882</Keep>, at an approximate distance of 403.1ГўВЂВЇm; thence, westerly, following the deflections of the division line between lot <Keep>3ГўВЂВЇ964ГўВЂВЇ882</Keep> and <Keep>2ГўВЂВЇ682ГўВЂВЇ472</Keep>, to the southwest corner of lot <Keep>3ГўВЂВЇ964ГўВЂВЇ882</Keep>, at distances of 122.30ГўВЂВЇm and 192.75ГўВЂВЇm; thence, northerly, following the division line between lots <Keep>2ГўВЂВЇ682ГўВЂВЇ472</Keep> and <Keep>3ГўВЂВЇ964 882</Keep>, to the northeast corner of lot <Keep>2ГўВЂВЇ682ГўВЂВЇ472</Keep>; thence, westerly, following the division line between lots <Keep>2ГўВЂВЇ682ГўВЂВЇ472</Keep> and <Keep>3ГўВЂВЇ964ГўВЂВЇ882</Keep>, to the northwest corner of lot <Keep>2ГўВЂВЇ682ГўВЂВЇ472</Keep>; thence, in a general northeasterly direction, following the deflections of the east and southeast boundaries of chemin Eardley-Masham, namely, the division lines between lots <Keep>3ГўВЂВЇ754ГўВЂВЇ086</Keep> and <Keep>3ГўВЂВЇ964ГўВЂВЇ882</Keep>; <Keep>3ГўВЂВЇ754ГўВЂВЇ087</Keep> and <Keep>3ГўВЂВЇ964ГўВЂВЇ882</Keep>; <Keep>3ГўВЂВЇ754ГўВЂВЇ088</Keep> and <Keep>2ГўВЂВЇ682ГўВЂВЇ471</Keep>, to the northeast corner of lot <Keep>3ГўВЂВЇ754ГўВЂВЇ088</Keep> (chemin Eardley-Masham); thence, westerly, following the division line between lots <Keep>3ГўВЂВЇ754ГўВЂВЇ088</Keep> and <Keep>3ГўВЂВЇ754ГўВЂВЇ089</Keep>, to the west corner of lot <Keep>3ГўВЂВЇ754ГўВЂВЇ089</Keep>; thence, westerly, following the division line between lots <Keep>2ГўВЂВЇ750ГўВЂВЇ634</Keep> and <Keep>2ГўВЂВЇ682ГўВЂВЇ469</Keep>, to the northwest corner of lot <Keep>2ГўВЂВЇ682ГўВЂВЇ469</Keep>; thence, westerly, following the deflections of the division line between lots <Keep>2ГўВЂВЇ682ГўВЂВЇ402</Keep> and <Keep>2ГўВЂВЇ750ГўВЂВЇ634</Keep>, to the northwest corner of lot <Keep>2ГўВЂВЇ682ГўВЂВЇ402</Keep>; thence, westerly, crossing lot <Keep>2ГўВЂВЇ682ГўВЂВЇ400</Keep> in a straight line and then lot <Keep>2ГўВЂВЇ872ГўВЂВЇ173</Keep>, to the southeast corner of lot <Keep>2ГўВЂВЇ889ГўВЂВЇ747</Keep>; thence, westerly, following the deflections of the division line between lot <Keep>2ГўВЂВЇ889ГўВЂВЇ747</Keep> and lots <Keep>2ГўВЂВЇ682ГўВЂВЇ399</Keep> and <Keep>2ГўВЂВЇ682ГўВЂВЇ398</Keep>, to the southwest corner of lot <Keep>2ГўВЂВЇ889ГўВЂВЇ747</Keep>; thence, on an azimuth bearing of 257Г‹Вљ19ГўВЂВІ29ГўВЂВі to a point located on the division line between lots <Keep>28C</Keep> and <Keep>28B</Keep>, range 6, cadastre of the Township of Onslow, a distance of 270.87ГўВЂВЇm; thence, on an azimuth bearing of 281Г‹Вљ17ГўВЂВІ52ГўВЂВі to a point located on the division line between lots <Keep>28B</Keep> and <Keep>27C</Keep>, range 6, cadastre of the Township of Onslow, a distance of 268.35ГўВЂВЇm; thence, on an azimuth bearing of 311Г‹Вљ05ГўВЂВІ59ГўВЂВі to a point located at a distance of 229.29ГўВЂВЇm; thence, on an azimuth bearing of 264Г‹Вљ51ГўВЂВІ24ГўВЂВі, to a point located at a distance of 204.61ГўВЂВЇm; thence, on an azimuth bearing of 266Г‹Вљ55ГўВЂВІ21ГўВЂВі, to a point located on the division line between lots <Keep>27A</Keep> and <Keep>26C</Keep>, range 6, cadastre of the Township of Onslow, a distance of 156.85ГўВЂВЇm; thence, on an azimuth bearing of 262Г‹Вљ08ГўВЂВІ55ГўВЂВі, to a point located on the division line between lots <Keep>26C</Keep> and <Keep>26B</Keep>, range 6, cadastre of the Township of Onslow, a distance of 262.26ГўВЂВЇm; thence, on an azimuth bearing of 288Г‹Вљ35ГўВЂВІ18ГўВЂВі, to a point located on the division line between lots <Keep>26B</Keep> and <Keep>25B</Keep>, range 6, cadastre of the Township of Onslow, a distance of 282.32ГўВЂВЇm; thence, on an azimuth bearing of 321Г‹Вљ07ГўВЂВІ40ГўВЂВі to a point located on the division line between the ranges 6 and 7, cadastre of the Township of Onslow, a distance of 164.54ГўВЂВЇm; thence, following the division line between the ranges 6 and 7, cadastre of the Township of Onslow, on an azimuth bearing of 265Г‹Вљ18ГўВЂВІ24ГўВЂВі to the east boundary of chemin Wilson a distance of 418.49ГўВЂВЇm; thence, on an azimuth bearing of 295Г‹Вљ30ГўВЂВІ01ГўВЂВі, to a point located at a distance of 12.63ГўВЂВЇm; thence, on an azimuth bearing of 265Г‹Вљ33ГўВЂВІ46ГўВЂВі, to a point located on the division line between lots <Keep>24A</Keep> and <Keep>23B</Keep>, range 7, cadastre of the Township of Onslow, a distance of 516.54ГўВЂВЇm; thence, on an azimuth bearing of 260Г‹Вљ51ГўВЂВІ03ГўВЂВі, to a point located at a distance of 18.97ГўВЂВЇm; thence, on an azimuth bearing of 224Г‹Вљ48ГўВЂВІ09ГўВЂВі, to a point located at a distance of 64.20ГўВЂВЇm; thence, on an azimuth bearing of 243Г‹Вљ04ГўВЂВІ58ГўВЂВі, to a point located at a distance of 53.53ГўВЂВЇm; thence, on an azimuth bearing of 259Г‹Вљ54ГўВЂВІ37ГўВЂВі, to a point located at a distance of 32.50ГўВЂВЇm; thence, on an azimuth bearing of 266Г‹Вљ24ГўВЂВІ48ГўВЂВі, to a point located at a distance of 100.18ГўВЂВЇm; thence, on an azimuth bearing of 272Г‹Вљ34ГўВЂВІ10ГўВЂВі, to a point located on the division line between lots <Keep>23B</Keep> and <Keep>22B</Keep>, range 7, cadastre of the Township of Onslow, a distance of 274.02ГўВЂВЇm; thence, on an azimuth bearing of 357Г‹Вљ37ГўВЂВІ00ГўВЂВі to a point located at the southwest corner of lot <Keep>23A</Keep>, range 7, cadastre of the Township of Onslow, a distance of 28.99ГўВЂВЇm; thence, on an azimuth bearing of 268Г‹Вљ33ГўВЂВІ20ГўВЂВі, to a point located at the southwest corner of lot <Keep>22A</Keep>, range 7, cadastre of the Township of Onslow, a distance of 537.48ГўВЂВЇm; thence, on an azimuth bearing of 268Г‹Вљ02ГўВЂВІ14ГўВЂВі, to a point located at a distance of 251.05ГўВЂВЇm; thence, on an azimuth bearing of 5Г‹Вљ09ГўВЂВІ19ГўВЂВі, to a point located at a distance of 59.28ГўВЂВЇm; thence, on an azimuth bearing of 280Г‹Вљ48ГўВЂВІ18ГўВЂВі, to a point located at a distance of 213.14ГўВЂВЇm; thence, on an azimuth bearing of 316Г‹Вљ27ГўВЂВІ24ГўВЂВі, to a point located at a distance of 181.95ГўВЂВЇm; thence, on an azimuth bearing of 296Г‹Вљ49ГўВЂВІ22ГўВЂВі, to a point located at a distance of 74.39ГўВЂВЇm; thence, on an azimuth bearing of 292Г‹Вљ01ГўВЂВІ21ГўВЂВі, to a point located at a distance of 128.91ГўВЂВЇm; thence, on an azimuth bearing of 280Г‹Вљ31ГўВЂВІ18ГўВЂВі, to a point located at a distance of 71.10ГўВЂВЇm; thence, on an azimuth bearing of 296Г‹Вљ11ГўВЂВІ22ГўВЂВі, to a point located at a distance of 87.77ГўВЂВЇm; thence, on an azimuth bearing of 292Г‹Вљ53ГўВЂВІ21ГўВЂВі, to a point located at a distance of 72.23ГўВЂВЇm; thence, on an azimuth bearing of 289Г‹Вљ25ГўВЂВІ20ГўВЂВі, to a point located at a distance of 191.35ГўВЂВЇm; thence, on an azimuth bearing of 283Г‹Вљ52ГўВЂВІ19ГўВЂВі, to a point located on the division line between lots <Keep>20A</Keep> and <Keep>19A</Keep>, range 7, cadastre of the Township of Onslow, a distance of 110.65ГўВЂВЇm; thence, on an azimuth bearing of 255Г‹Вљ44ГўВЂВІ08ГўВЂВі, to a point located at a distance of 231.75ГўВЂВЇm; thence, on an azimuth bearing of 281Г‹Вљ16ГўВЂВІ18ГўВЂВі, to a point located at a distance of 131.35ГўВЂВЇm; thence, on an azimuth bearing of 261Г‹Вљ34ГўВЂВІ11ГўВЂВі, to a point located on the division line between lots <Keep>19A</Keep> and <Keep>18A</Keep>, range 7, cadastre of the Township of Onslow, a distance of 221.49ГўВЂВЇm; thence, on an azimuth bearing of 267Г‹Вљ03ГўВЂВІ13ГўВЂВі, to a point located at a distance of 376.93ГўВЂВЇm; thence, on an azimuth bearing of 274Г‹Вљ28ГўВЂВІ23ГўВЂВі, to a point located on the division line between lots <Keep>18A</Keep> and <Keep>17A</Keep>, range 7, cadastre of the Township of Onslow, a distance of 107.71ГўВЂВЇm; thence, on an azimuth bearing of 269Г‹Вљ16ГўВЂВІ22ГўВЂВі, to a point located on the division line between lots <Keep>17A</Keep> and <Keep>16C</Keep>, range 7, cadastre of the Township of Onslow, a distance of 534.44ГўВЂВЇm; thence, on an azimuth bearing of 258Г‹Вљ19ГўВЂВІ17ГўВЂВі, to a point located on the division line between lots <Keep>16B</Keep> and <Keep>15A</Keep>, range 7, cadastre of the Township of Onslow, a distance of 533.21ГўВЂВЇm; thence, on an azimuth bearing of 274Г‹Вљ56ГўВЂВІ23ГўВЂВі, to a point located at a distance of 257.29ГўВЂВЇm; thence, on an azimuth bearing of 277Г‹Вљ08ГўВЂВІ36ГўВЂВі, to a point located on the division line between lots <Keep>15A</Keep> and <Keep>14B</Keep>, range 7, cadastre of the Township of Onslow, a distance of 276.49ГўВЂВЇm; thence, on an azimuth bearing of 258Г‹Вљ06ГўВЂВІ34ГўВЂВі, to a point located at a distance of 462.20ГўВЂВЇm; thence, on an azimuth bearing of 257Г‹Вљ34ГўВЂВІ34ГўВЂВі, to a point located on the division line between lots <Keep>13C</Keep> and <Keep>12B</Keep>, range 7, cadastre of the Township of Onslow, a distance of 578.97ГўВЂВЇm; thence, on an azimuth bearing of 245Г‹Вљ26ГўВЂВІ38ГўВЂВі, to a point located at a distance of 281.55ГўВЂВЇm; thence, on an azimuth bearing of 266Г‹Вљ34ГўВЂВІ34ГўВЂВі, to a point located at a distance of 169.05ГўВЂВЇm; thence, on an azimuth bearing of 276Г‹Вљ18ГўВЂВІ36ГўВЂВі, to a point located at a distance of 239.01ГўВЂВЇm; thence, on an azimuth bearing of 261Г‹Вљ08ГўВЂВІ34ГўВЂВі, to a point located at a distance of 286.52ГўВЂВЇm; thence, on an azimuth bearing of 284Г‹Вљ26ГўВЂВІ40ГўВЂВі, to a point located on the division line between lots <Keep>11B</Keep> and <Keep>10A</Keep>, range 7, cadastre of the Township of Onslow, a distance of 132.77ГўВЂВЇm; thence, on an azimuth bearing of 268Г‹Вљ21ГўВЂВІ12ГўВЂВі, to a point located on the division line between lots <Keep>10A</Keep> and <Keep>9B</Keep>, range 7, cadastre of the Township of Onslow, a distance of 545.37ГўВЂВЇm; thence, on an azimuth bearing of 252Г‹Вљ55ГўВЂВІ35ГўВЂВі, to a point located on the division line between lots <Keep>8B</Keep> and <Keep>9B</Keep>, range 7, cadastre of the Township of Onslow, a distance of 524.27ГўВЂВЇm; thence, northerly following the division line between lots <Keep>8A</Keep> and <Keep>9A</Keep>, range 7, cadastre of the Township of Onslow, a distance of 474.68ГўВЂВЇm; thence, northerly following the division line between lots <Keep>8A</Keep> and <Keep>9A</Keep>, range 7, cadastre of the Township of Onslow, a distance of 730.13ГўВЂВЇm; thence, northerly following the division line between lots <Keep>8A</Keep> and <Keep>9A</Keep>, range 7, then lots <Keep>8B</Keep> and <Keep>9A</Keep>, range 8, then lots <Keep>8D</Keep> and <Keep>9C</Keep>, range 8, all in the cadastre of the Township of Onslow, a distance of 992.58ГўВЂВЇm; thence, northerly following the division line between lots <Keep>8D</Keep> and <Keep>9C</Keep>, range 8, to the southwest corner of lot <Keep>9A</Keep>, range 9, all in the cadastre of the Township of Onslow, a distance of 752.24ГўВЂВЇm; thence, northerly, following the division line between lot <Keep>8A</Keep> from lots <Keep>9A</Keep> and <Keep>9B</Keep>, range 9, then following the division line between lot <Keep>8B</Keep> from lots <Keep>9C</Keep> and <Keep>9D</Keep>, range 9, to the northwest corner of lot <Keep>9D</Keep>, range 9, all in the cadastre of the Township of Onslow; thence, northerly following the division line between lot <Keep>8B</Keep> from lots <Keep>9A</Keep> and <Keep>9B</Keep>, range 10, to the northwest corner of lot <Keep>9B</Keep>, range 10, all in the cadastre of the Township of Onslow; thence, northerly following the division line between lots 8 and 9, range 11, to the northwest corner of lot 9, range 11, all in the cadastre of the Township of Onslow; thence, northerly, following the division line between lot <Keep>8A</Keep> from lots <Keep>9A</Keep> and <Keep>9B</Keep>, range 12, then following the division line between lot <Keep>8B</Keep> from lots <Keep>9B</Keep> and <Keep>9C</Keep>, range 12, to the northwest corner of lot <Keep>9C</Keep>, range 12, all in the cadastre of the Township of Onslow; thence, northerly following the division line between lot <Keep>8C</Keep> from lots <Keep>9A</Keep> and <Keep>9B</Keep>, range 13, to the northwest corner of lot <Keep>9B</Keep>, range 13, cadastre of the Township of Onslow, located on the division line between the Townships of Aldfield and Onslow; thence, easterly following the division line between the Townships of Aldfield and Onslow to a point located at the northwest corner of lot <Keep>10C</Keep>, range 13, cadastre of the Township of Onslow; thence, easterly following the division line between the Townships of Aldfield and Onslow, to a point located at a distance of 1,432.50ГўВЂВЇm; thence, easterly following the division line between the Townships of Aldfield and Onslow, to a point located at the northeast corner of lot <Keep>15B</Keep>, range 13, cadastre of the Township of Onslow, a distance of 1,695.73ГўВЂВЇm; thence, easterly following the division line between the Townships of Aldfield and Onslow, to a point located at the northwest corner of lot <Keep>17C</Keep>, range 13, cadastre of the Township of Onslow, a distance of 525.87ГўВЂВЇm; thence, easterly following the division line between the Townships of Aldfield and Onslow, to a point located on the west boundary of chemin Gauvin, a distance of 12.92ГўВЂВЇm; thence, southwesterly, following the northwest boundary of chemin Gauvin, at distances of 27.71ГўВЂВЇm and 16.44ГўВЂВЇm; thence, southerly, following the west boundary of chemin Gauvin, at distances of 106.63ГўВЂВЇm and 29.67ГўВЂВЇm; thence, southeasterly, following the southwest boundary of chemin Gauvin, at distances of 29.95ГўВЂВЇm, 39.95ГўВЂВЇm, 27.98ГўВЂВЇm, 26.75ГўВЂВЇm and 25.99ГўВЂВЇm; thence, easterly following the south boundary of the chemin Gauvin, a distance of 136.53ГўВЂВЇm; thence, southeasterly, crossing chemin du Lac-La-PГѓВЄche, following the southwest boundary of chemin Gauvin, a distance of 15.55ГўВЂВЇm; thence, southeasterly, following the southwest boundary of chemin Gauvin, at distances of 11.65ГўВЂВЇm, 34.05ГўВЂВЇm and 13.04ГўВЂВЇm; thence, easterly, following the south boundary of chemin Gauvin, at distances of 10.07ГўВЂВЇm, 21.72ГўВЂВЇm, 13.51ГўВЂВЇm and 10.88ГўВЂВЇm; thence, southeasterly, following the southwest boundary of chemin Gauvin, a distance of 29.84ГўВЂВЇm; thence, easterly, following the south boundary of chemin Gauvin, at distances of 30.55ГўВЂВЇm, 81.02ГўВЂВЇm, 41.05ГўВЂВЇm, 32.62ГўВЂВЇm and 28.89ГўВЂВЇm; thence, northeasterly, following the southeast boundary of chemin Gauvin, a distance of 22.30ГўВЂВЇm; thence, easterly, following the south boundary of chemin Gauvin, at distances of 11.99ГўВЂВЇm, 35.90ГўВЂВЇm, 27.85ГўВЂВЇm, 40.14ГўВЂВЇm, 22.33ГўВЂВЇm and 9.07ГўВЂВЇm; thence, northeasterly, following the southeast boundary of chemin Gauvin, at distances of 12.51ГўВЂВЇm and 28.00ГўВЂВЇm; thence, following the southwest shore of ruisseau du Lac-des-Loups to the intersection of the division line between lots <Keep>18A</Keep> and <Keep>18B</Keep>, range 13, cadastre of the Township of Onslow; thence, northerly following the division line between lots <Keep>18A</Keep> and <Keep>18B</Keep>, range 13, cadastre of the Township of Onslow, towards the intersection of the division line between the Townships of Aldfield and Onslow, also known as the northwest corner of lot <Keep>18B</Keep>, range 13, cadastre of the Township of Onslow; thence, easterly, following the division line between the Townships of Aldfield and Onslow, towards the southwest corner of lot 12, range 1, cadastre of the Township of Aldfield, a distance of 1,760.22ГўВЂВЇm.</Text>
</Provision>
<BillPiece><Heading level="3"><TitleText>Municipality of La PГѓВЄche</TitleText></Heading></BillPiece>

<Provision>
<Text>Beginning at the southwest corner of lotГўВЂВЇ12, rangeГўВЂВЇ1, cadastre of the Township of Aldfield; thence, northerly following the division line between lotsГўВЂВЇ12 andГўВЂВЇ<Keep>13A</Keep>, rangeГўВЂВЇ1, Township of Aldfield, towards the intersection at the south boundary of <Keep>RouteГўВЂВЇ366</Keep> (chemin Pontbriand), a distance of 422.88ГўВЂВЇm; thence, easterly following the south boundary of <Keep>RouteГўВЂВЇ366</Keep> (chemin Pontbriand), at distances of 79.58ГўВЂВЇm, 82.18ГўВЂВЇm and 43.03ГўВЂВЇm; thence, southeasterly, following the southwest boundary of <Keep>RouteГўВЂВЇ366</Keep> (chemin Pontbriand), at distances of 41.52ГўВЂВЇm, 75.96ГўВЂВЇm and 45.06ГўВЂВЇm; thence, easterly following the South boundary of <Keep>RouteГўВЂВЇ366</Keep> (chemin Pontbriand), a distance of 52.42ГўВЂВЇm; thence, southeasterly, following the southwest boundary of <Keep>RouteГўВЂВЇ366</Keep> (chemin Pontbriand), at distances of 51.22ГўВЂВЇm, 54.54ГўВЂВЇm, 100.89ГўВЂВЇm and 45.93ГўВЂВЇm; thence, easterly following the south boundary of <Keep>RouteГўВЂВЇ366</Keep> (chemin Pontbriand), a distance of 49.17ГўВЂВЇm; thence, easterly following the south boundary of <Keep>RouteГўВЂВЇ366</Keep> (chemin Pontbriand), to the intersection of the division line between lotsГўВЂВЇ<Keep>9A</Keep> andГўВЂВЇ10, rangeГўВЂВЇ1, cadastre of the Township of Aldfield, a distance of 141.82ГўВЂВЇm; thence, southerly following the division line between lotsГўВЂВЇ<Keep>9A</Keep> andГўВЂВЇ10, rangeГўВЂВЇ1, cadastre of the Township of Aldfield, towards the southeast corner of lotГўВЂВЇ10, rangeГўВЂВЇ1, cadastre of the Township of Aldfield.</Text>
</Provision>


<BillPiece><Heading level="3"><TitleText>Municipality of Pontiac</TitleText></Heading></BillPiece><Provision>
<Text>Beginning at the southeast corner of lotГўВЂВЇ10, rangeГўВЂВЇ1, cadastre of the Township of Aldfield; thence, easterly following the <Keep>division</Keep> line between the Townships of Aldfield and Onslow, to the intersection of the south boundary of <Keep>RouteГўВЂВЇ366</Keep>, a distance of 78.41ГўВЂВЇm; thence, southeasterly, following the southwest boundary of <Keep>RouteГўВЂВЇ366</Keep>, at distances of 216.83ГўВЂВЇm, 78.78ГўВЂВЇm, 135.30ГўВЂВЇm, 56.26ГўВЂВЇm, 61.53ГўВЂВЇm, 22.15ГўВЂВЇm, 85.68ГўВЂВЇm and 47.32ГўВЂВЇm; thence, easterly following the southwest of <Keep>RouteГўВЂВЇ366</Keep>, at distances of 28.49ГўВЂВЇm, 33.10ГўВЂВЇm, 47.66ГўВЂВЇm, 35.82ГўВЂВЇm, 122.39ГўВЂВЇm, 113.79ГўВЂВЇm, 29.34ГўВЂВЇm, 30.78ГўВЂВЇm, 49.76ГўВЂВЇm and 158.29ГўВЂВЇm; thence, southeasterly, following the southwest boundary of <Keep>RouteГўВЂВЇ366</Keep>, to the intersection of the division line between lotsГўВЂВЇ<Keep>25B</Keep> andГўВЂВЇ<Keep>26B</Keep>, rangeГўВЂВЇ13, cadastre of the Township of <Keep>Onslow</Keep>, a distance of 19.68ГўВЂВЇm; thence, southerly to the intersection of the division line between the rangesГўВЂВЇ12 andГўВЂВЇ13 and the division line between lotsГўВЂВЇ<Keep>25B</Keep> and <Keep>26A</Keep>, rangeГўВЂВЇ12, all in the Township of Onslow, a distance of 1,139.03ГўВЂВЇm; thence, easterly following the division line between the rangesГўВЂВЇ12 andГўВЂВЇ13, cadastre of the Township of Onslow, at distances of 263.87ГўВЂВЇm, 259.55ГўВЂВЇm, 265.33ГўВЂВЇm and 261.51ГўВЂВЇm; thence, southerly, following the division line between lots <Keep>27C</Keep> and <Keep>28B</Keep>, rangeГўВЂВЇ12, then lotsГўВЂВЇ<Keep>27B</Keep> and <Keep>28A</Keep>, rangeГўВЂВЇ12, to the southeast corner of lotГўВЂВЇ<Keep>27B</Keep>, rangeГўВЂВЇ12, all in the cadastre of the said Township, a distance of 1,714.29ГўВЂВЇm; thence, easterly following the division line between the rangesГўВЂВЇ11 andГўВЂВЇ12, to the northeast corner of lotГўВЂВЇ28, rangeГўВЂВЇ11, all in the cadastre of the Township of Onslow, a distance of 114.88ГўВЂВЇm; thence, southerly following the division line between the Township of Masham and the Township of Onslow, towards the southeast corner of lotГўВЂВЇ28, rangeГўВЂВЇ11, cadastre of the Township of Onslow, a distance of 1,701.74ГўВЂВЇm; thence, southerly following the division line between the Township of Masham and the Township of Onslow, towards the northwest corner of lot <Keep>2ГўВЂВЇ755ГўВЂВЇ996</Keep> (Cadastre du QuГѓВ©bec), a distance of 1,235.70ГўВЂВЇm.</Text>
</Provision>
<BillPiece><Heading level="3"><TitleText>Municipality of La PГѓВЄche</TitleText></Heading></BillPiece>


<Provision>
<Text>Beginning at the northwest corner of lot <Keep>2ГўВЂВЇ755ГўВЂВЇ996</Keep> (Cadastre du QuГѓВ©bec), following segments of the north boundary of said lot, to the northeast corner of lot <Keep>2ГўВЂВЇ755ГўВЂВЇ996</Keep>; thence, easterly and crossing chemin Eardley-Masham, to the northwest corner of lot <Keep>2ГўВЂВЇ755ГўВЂВЇ995</Keep>; thence, easterly following the north boundary of lots <Keep>2ГўВЂВЇ755ГўВЂВЇ995</Keep>, <Keep>3ГўВЂВЇ117ГўВЂВЇ982</Keep>, <Keep>3ГўВЂВЇ117ГўВЂВЇ981</Keep>, <Keep>2ГўВЂВЇ755ГўВЂВЇ994</Keep> and <Keep>3ГўВЂВЇ117ГўВЂВЇ980</Keep>, to the northeast corner of lot <Keep>3ГўВЂВЇ117ГўВЂВЇ980</Keep>; thence, southerly following the east boundary of lot <Keep>3ГўВЂВЇ117ГўВЂВЇ980</Keep>, to the southeast corner of said lot; thence, easterly following the north boundary of lots <Keep>2ГўВЂВЇ755ГўВЂВЇ991</Keep> and <Keep>2ГўВЂВЇ755ГўВЂВЇ990</Keep> and following segments of the north boundary of lot <Keep>2ГўВЂВЇ684ГўВЂВЇ840</Keep>, to the intersection with the southeast corner of lot <Keep>2ГўВЂВЇ685ГўВЂВЇ155</Keep>; thence, northerly following the division line between lots <Keep>2ГўВЂВЇ685ГўВЂВЇ155</Keep> and <Keep>2ГўВЂВЇ685ГўВЂВЇ822</Keep>, to the northeast corner of lot <Keep>2ГўВЂВЇ685ГўВЂВЇ155</Keep>; thence, easterly following the south boundaries of lots <Keep>2ГўВЂВЇ685ГўВЂВЇ203</Keep> and <Keep>2ГўВЂВЇ685ГўВЂВЇ402</Keep>, to the southeast corner of lot <Keep>2ГўВЂВЇ685ГўВЂВЇ402</Keep>; thence, northerly following the division line between lots <Keep>2ГўВЂВЇ685ГўВЂВЇ402</Keep> and <Keep>2ГўВЂВЇ685ГўВЂВЇ822</Keep>, to the southwest corner of lot <Keep>2ГўВЂВЇ685ГўВЂВЇ406</Keep>; thence, easterly following the south boundary of lot <Keep>2ГўВЂВЇ685ГўВЂВЇ406</Keep>, to the southeast corner of said lot; thence, southeasterly, to the <Keep>intersection</Keep> at the northwest corner of lot <Keep>2ГўВЂВЇ685ГўВЂВЇ428</Keep> and the southwest boundary of lot <Keep>2ГўВЂВЇ864ГўВЂВЇ213</Keep> (chemin de la Prairie); thence, southeasterly, easterly, northeasterly, easterly, southeasterly and easterly following the south boundary of lots <Keep>2ГўВЂВЇ864ГўВЂВЇ213</Keep>, <Keep>2ГўВЂВЇ864ГўВЂВЇ212</Keep> and <Keep>2ГўВЂВЇ864ГўВЂВЇ211</Keep> (chemin de la Prairie), to the northeast corner of lot <Keep>2ГўВЂВЇ756ГўВЂВЇ053</Keep>; thence, northerly crossing chemin de la Prairie, to the southeast corner of lot <Keep>2ГўВЂВЇ685ГўВЂВЇ601</Keep>; thence, northerly following the division line between lots <Keep>2ГўВЂВЇ685ГўВЂВЇ601</Keep> and <Keep>2ГўВЂВЇ685ГўВЂВЇ822</Keep>, the division line between lots <Keep>2ГўВЂВЇ685ГўВЂВЇ600</Keep> and <Keep>2ГўВЂВЇ685ГўВЂВЇ822</Keep>, then the division line between lots <Keep>2ГўВЂВЇ685ГўВЂВЇ430</Keep> and <Keep>2ГўВЂВЇ685ГўВЂВЇ822</Keep>, towards the southwest corner of lot <Keep>2ГўВЂВЇ685ГўВЂВЇ608</Keep>; thence, easterly following the south boundary of lot <Keep>2ГўВЂВЇ685ГўВЂВЇ608</Keep>, to the southeast corner of said lot; thence, northerly following the east boundary of lot <Keep>2ГўВЂВЇ685ГўВЂВЇ608</Keep>, to the northeast corner of said lot; thence, northerly crossing chemin Schnob, to the southwest corner of lot <Keep>2ГўВЂВЇ756ГўВЂВЇ050</Keep>; thence, northerly following the west boundary of lot <Keep>2ГўВЂВЇ756ГўВЂВЇ050</Keep>, to the intersection at the northwest corner of said lot and the south shore of RiviГѓВЁre la PГѓВЄche (Undivided territory); thence, in a general easterly direction, following the south shore of RiviГѓВЁre la PГѓВЄche (Undivided territory), to the intersection with the southerly extension of the west boundary of lot <Keep>2ГўВЂВЇ756ГўВЂВЇ119</Keep>; thence, northerly, crossing RiviГѓВЁre la PГѓВЄche (Undivided territory) and following the west boundary of lot <Keep>2ГўВЂВЇ756ГўВЂВЇ119</Keep>, to the northwest corner of said lot; thence, easterly following the north boundary of lot <Keep>2ГўВЂВЇ756ГўВЂВЇ119</Keep>, to the northeast corner of said lot, also located on the west boundary of lot <Keep>2ГўВЂВЇ864ГўВЂВЇ223</Keep> (chemin Brazeau); thence, southerly and southeasterly following the east boundary of lot <Keep>2ГўВЂВЇ756ГўВЂВЇ119</Keep>, to the intersection at the north shore of RiviГѓВЁre la PГѓВЄche (Undivided territory), being the southeast corner of lot <Keep>2ГўВЂВЇ756ГўВЂВЇ119</Keep>; thence, southeasterly, crossing RiviГѓВЁre la PГѓВЄche (Undivided territory), to the northeast corner of lot <Keep>2ГўВЂВЇ756ГўВЂВЇ050</Keep>; thence, following the division line between the south shore of RiviГѓВЁre la PГѓВЄche (Undivided territory) and following the north boundaries of lots <Keep>3ГўВЂВЇ274ГўВЂВЇ668</Keep> (chemin Brazeau), <Keep>2ГўВЂВЇ685ГўВЂВЇ630</Keep>, <Keep>2ГўВЂВЇ685ГўВЂВЇ633</Keep>, <Keep>2ГўВЂВЇ685ГўВЂВЇ824</Keep>, <Keep>3ГўВЂВЇ579ГўВЂВЇ542</Keep>, <Keep>3ГўВЂВЇ389ГўВЂВЇ947</Keep> and <Keep>3ГўВЂВЇ389ГўВЂВЇ948</Keep>, to the intersection of the southerly extension of the division line between lots <Keep>3ГўВЂВЇ389ГўВЂВЇ960</Keep> and <Keep>3ГўВЂВЇ654ГўВЂВЇ717</Keep>; thence, northerly crossing RiviГѓВЁre la PГѓВЄche (Undivided territory) to the intersection of the division line between lots <Keep>3ГўВЂВЇ389ГўВЂВЇ960</Keep> and <Keep>3ГўВЂВЇ654ГўВЂВЇ717</Keep> and the north shore of said River; thence, northerly following the division line between lots <Keep>3ГўВЂВЇ654ГўВЂВЇ717</Keep> and <Keep>3ГўВЂВЇ389ГўВЂВЇ960</Keep>, a distance of 77.57ГўВЂВЇm; thence, northeasterly following the division line between lots <Keep>3ГўВЂВЇ654ГўВЂВЇ717</Keep> and <Keep>3ГўВЂВЇ389ГўВЂВЇ960</Keep>, a distance of 20.42ГўВЂВЇm; thence, northeasterly crossing lots <Keep>3ГўВЂВЇ654ГўВЂВЇ717</Keep> and <Keep>3ГўВЂВЇ389ГўВЂВЇ949</Keep>, to the southwest corner of lot <Keep>3ГўВЂВЇ390ГўВЂВЇ091</Keep>; thence, easterly following the north boundary of lot <Keep>3ГўВЂВЇ389ГўВЂВЇ949</Keep>, to the southeast corner of lot <Keep>3ГўВЂВЇ390ГўВЂВЇ090</Keep>; thence, easterly following the division line between lots <Keep>3ГўВЂВЇ389ГўВЂВЇ949</Keep> and <Keep>3ГўВЂВЇ389ГўВЂВЇ950</Keep>, then the division line between lots <Keep>3ГўВЂВЇ389ГўВЂВЇ950</Keep> and <Keep>3ГўВЂВЇ654ГўВЂВЇ718</Keep>, towards the southeast corner of lot <Keep>3ГўВЂВЇ389ГўВЂВЇ950</Keep>; thence, northerly following the division line between lots <Keep>3ГўВЂВЇ389ГўВЂВЇ950</Keep> and <Keep>3ГўВЂВЇ654ГўВЂВЇ718</Keep>, at a northwest corner of lot <Keep>3ГўВЂВЇ654ГўВЂВЇ718</Keep>; thence, southeasterly following the southwest boundary of <Keep>RouteГўВЂВЇ366</Keep> (Principale est), being lots <Keep>3ГўВЂВЇ654ГўВЂВЇ734</Keep>, <Keep>3ГўВЂВЇ654ГўВЂВЇ218</Keep> and <Keep>3ГўВЂВЇ654ГўВЂВЇ220</Keep>, towards the northwest corner of lot <Keep>3ГўВЂВЇ654ГўВЂВЇ223</Keep>; thence, southeasterly following the southwest boundary of <Keep>RouteГўВЂВЇ366</Keep> (Principale est), being lot <Keep>3ГўВЂВЇ654ГўВЂВЇ223</Keep>, towards the south corner of lot <Keep>3ГўВЂВЇ654ГўВЂВЇ223</Keep>; thence, southeasterly following the southwest and west boundary of <Keep>RouteГўВЂВЇ366</Keep> (Principale est), being lot <Keep>3ГўВЂВЇ654ГўВЂВЇ253</Keep>, at successive distances of 216.74ГўВЂВЇm, 73.18ГўВЂВЇm, 103.09ГўВЂВЇm, then southerly, following the west boundary of <Keep>RouteГўВЂВЇ366</Keep> (Principale est), distances of 99.00ГўВЂВЇm and 30.00ГўВЂВЇm; thence, easterly, crossing lots <Keep>3ГўВЂВЇ654ГўВЂВЇ223</Keep>, <Keep>3ГўВЂВЇ654ГўВЂВЇ253</Keep>, <Keep>3ГўВЂВЇ654ГўВЂВЇ256</Keep>, <Keep>3ГўВЂВЇ654ГўВЂВЇ257</Keep> <Keep>(RouteГўВЂВЇ366</Keep> (Principale est)) and <Keep>3ГўВЂВЇ654ГўВЂВЇ259</Keep> <Keep>(AutorouteГўВЂВЇ5)</Keep>, to the northwest corner of lot <Keep>3ГўВЂВЇ391ГўВЂВЇ737</Keep>; thence, easterly following the division line between lots <Keep>3ГўВЂВЇ391ГўВЂВЇ737</Keep> and <Keep>3ГўВЂВЇ389ГўВЂВЇ951</Keep>, to the far southwest corner of lot <Keep>3ГўВЂВЇ391ГўВЂВЇ738</Keep>, at distances of 63.10ГўВЂВЇm, 74.88ГўВЂВЇm, 9.58ГўВЂВЇm, 17.51ГўВЂВЇm and 9.35ГўВЂВЇm; thence, easterly, following the division line between lots <Keep>3ГўВЂВЇ389ГўВЂВЇ951</Keep> and <Keep>3ГўВЂВЇ391ГўВЂВЇ738</Keep>, a distance of 10.55ГўВЂВЇm; thence, northeasterly, following the division line between lots <Keep>3ГўВЂВЇ389ГўВЂВЇ951</Keep> and <Keep>3ГўВЂВЇ391ГўВЂВЇ738</Keep>, to the northeast corner of lot <Keep>3ГўВЂВЇ391ГўВЂВЇ738</Keep>, at distances of 9.72ГўВЂВЇm, 13.84ГўВЂВЇm, 62.31ГўВЂВЇm, 40.90ГўВЂВЇm, 21.09ГўВЂВЇm, 23.10ГўВЂВЇm, 45.26ГўВЂВЇm and 2.35ГўВЂВЇm; thence, northeasterly, following the division line between lots <Keep>3ГўВЂВЇ389ГўВЂВЇ951</Keep> and <Keep>3ГўВЂВЇ391ГўВЂВЇ732</Keep>, to the northwestern corner of lot <Keep>3ГўВЂВЇ391ГўВЂВЇ732</Keep>, at distances of 6.25ГўВЂВЇm, 13.60ГўВЂВЇm, 61.77ГўВЂВЇm and 27.73ГўВЂВЇm; thence, easterly, following the division line between lots <Keep>3ГўВЂВЇ389ГўВЂВЇ951</Keep> and <Keep>3ГўВЂВЇ391ГўВЂВЇ732</Keep>, to the northwest corner of lot <Keep>3ГўВЂВЇ391ГўВЂВЇ736</Keep>, a distance of 246.25ГўВЂВЇm; thence, southerly, following the division line between lots <Keep>3ГўВЂВЇ391ГўВЂВЇ736</Keep> and <Keep>3ГўВЂВЇ391ГўВЂВЇ732</Keep>, to the southwest corner of lot <Keep>3ГўВЂВЇ391ГўВЂВЇ736</Keep>; thence, easterly, following the division line between lots <Keep>3ГўВЂВЇ391ГўВЂВЇ736</Keep> and <Keep>3ГўВЂВЇ391ГўВЂВЇ732</Keep>, to the southeast corner of lot <Keep>3ГўВЂВЇ391ГўВЂВЇ736</Keep>; thence, southerly, following the division line between lots <Keep>3ГўВЂВЇ391ГўВЂВЇ670</Keep> and <Keep>3ГўВЂВЇ391ГўВЂВЇ732</Keep>, to the southwest corner of lot <Keep>3ГўВЂВЇ391ГўВЂВЇ670</Keep>; thence, easterly, following the division line between lots <Keep>3ГўВЂВЇ391ГўВЂВЇ670</Keep> and <Keep>3ГўВЂВЇ391ГўВЂВЇ732</Keep>, to the south corner of lot <Keep>3ГўВЂВЇ391ГўВЂВЇ670</Keep>; thence, northeasterly, following the division line between lots <Keep>3ГўВЂВЇ391ГўВЂВЇ732</Keep> and <Keep>3ГўВЂВЇ391ГўВЂВЇ670</Keep>, to the northeast corner of lot <Keep>3ГўВЂВЇ391ГўВЂВЇ732</Keep>, a distance of 1.95ГўВЂВЇm; thence, southerly, following the division line between lots <Keep>3ГўВЂВЇ391ГўВЂВЇ675</Keep> and <Keep>3ГўВЂВЇ391ГўВЂВЇ732</Keep>, to the intersection of the north shore of the RiviГѓВЁre la PГѓВЄche (Undivided territory); thence, southerly, crossing RiviГѓВЁre la PГѓВЄche (Undivided territory), to a point located at the intersection of the south shore of said river and the division line between lots <Keep>3ГўВЂВЇ391ГўВЂВЇ748</Keep> and <Keep>3ГўВЂВЇ364ГўВЂВЇ796</Keep>; thence, southerly, following the division line between lots <Keep>3ГўВЂВЇ391ГўВЂВЇ748</Keep> and <Keep>3ГўВЂВЇ654ГўВЂВЇ796</Keep>, to a point located at the intersection of the north boundary of lot <Keep>3ГўВЂВЇ654ГўВЂВЇ317</Keep> (chemin Mill); thence, crossing lot <Keep>3ГўВЂВЇ654ГўВЂВЇ317</Keep> (chemin Mill), to a point located at the intersection of the south boundary of said chemin Mill and the division line between lots <Keep>3 391 750</Keep> and <Keep>3 391 773</Keep>; thence, southerly, following the division line between lots <Keep>3ГўВЂВЇ391ГўВЂВЇ773</Keep> and <Keep>3ГўВЂВЇ391ГўВЂВЇ750</Keep>, to the southwest corner of lot <Keep>3ГўВЂВЇ391ГўВЂВЇ750</Keep>; thence, westerly following the division line between lots <Keep>3ГўВЂВЇ391ГўВЂВЇ773</Keep> and <Keep>3ГўВЂВЇ654ГўВЂВЇ775</Keep>, to the north corner of lot <Keep>3ГўВЂВЇ654ГўВЂВЇ775</Keep>, at successive distances of 45.15ГўВЂВЇm, 214.92ГўВЂВЇm and 27.92ГўВЂВЇm; thence, southwesterly, following the division line between lots <Keep>3ГўВЂВЇ391ГўВЂВЇ773</Keep> and <Keep>3ГўВЂВЇ654ГўВЂВЇ775</Keep>, a distance of 203.89ГўВЂВЇm; thence, westerly following the division line between lots <Keep>3ГўВЂВЇ391ГўВЂВЇ773</Keep> and <Keep>3ГўВЂВЇ654ГўВЂВЇ775</Keep>, to the intersection with the southeast boundary of lot <Keep>3ГўВЂВЇ654ГўВЂВЇ244</Keep> (chemin Mill), successive distances of 84.42ГўВЂВЇm and 93.58ГўВЂВЇm; thence, southwesterly following the southeast boundary of lot <Keep>3ГўВЂВЇ654ГўВЂВЇ244</Keep> (chemin Mill), at distances of 25.93ГўВЂВЇm and 18.49ГўВЂВЇm, then westerly, a distance of 20.71ГўВЂВЇm, then to the southwest, a distance of 6.94ГўВЂВЇm, to the northwest corner of lot <Keep>3ГўВЂВЇ391ГўВЂВЇ769</Keep>; thence, westerly, crossing <Keep>AutorouteГўВЂВЇ5</Keep>, being lot <Keep>3ГўВЂВЇ654ГўВЂВЇ238</Keep>, to the northeast corner of lot <Keep>3ГўВЂВЇ654ГўВЂВ‰100</Keep>, following the south boundary of the old chemin Mill; thence, westerly, to the northwest corner of lot <Keep>3ГўВЂВ‰654ГўВЂВ‰100</Keep> at successive distances of 28.76ГўВЂВЇm and 17.13ГўВЂВЇm; thence, in a general southeasterly direction, following the southwest boundary of the proposed <Keep>AutorouteГўВЂВЇ5</Keep>, being lots <Keep>3ГўВЂВ‰654ГўВЂВ‰100</Keep> and <Keep>3ГўВЂВ‰391ГўВЂВ‰986</Keep>, to the southwest corner of lot <Keep>3ГўВЂВ‰391ГўВЂВ‰986</Keep>; thence, in a general southeasterly direction, following the southwest boundary of the proposed <Keep>AutorouteГўВЂВЇ5</Keep> and crossing lot <Keep>3ГўВЂВ‰389ГўВЂВ‰945</Keep>, to the northwest corner of lot <Keep>3ГўВЂВ‰391ГўВЂВ‰995</Keep>; thence, in a general southeasterly direction, following the southwest boundary of the proposed <Keep>AutorouteГўВЂВЇ5</Keep>, being lot <Keep>3ГўВЂВ‰391ГўВЂВ‰997</Keep>, to the east corner of lot <Keep>3ГўВЂВ‰391ГўВЂВ‰995</Keep>.</Text>
</Provision>
<BillPiece><Heading level="2"><TitleText>2.4 Section 4</TitleText></Heading></BillPiece><Provision>
<Text>This portion of Gatineau Park, described in SectionГўВЂВЇ4, is included in the registration division of Gatineau, located in the Municipality of Chelsea, and forms part of the Cadastre du QuГѓВ©bec.</Text>
</Provision><BillPiece><Heading level="3"><TitleText>Municipality of Chelsea</TitleText></Heading></BillPiece>
<Provision>
<Text>Beginning at the east corner of lot <Keep>3ГўВЂВЇ391ГўВЂВЇ995</Keep>, in a general southeasterly direction, following the southwest boundary of the proposed AutorouteГўВЂВЇ5, being lots <Keep>4ГўВЂВЇ138ГўВЂВЇ880</Keep>, <Keep>3ГўВЂВЇ264ГўВЂВЇ820</Keep>, <Keep>3ГўВЂВЇ264ГўВЂВЇ830</Keep>, <Keep>3ГўВЂВЇ264ГўВЂВЇ860</Keep>, <Keep>3ГўВЂВЇ264ГўВЂВЇ906</Keep> and <Keep>3ГўВЂВЇ264ГўВЂВЇ908</Keep>; thence, in a general southeasterly direction, following the southwest boundary of AutorouteГўВЂВЇ5, being lots <Keep>3ГўВЂВЇ264ГўВЂВЇ970</Keep>, <Keep>3ГўВЂВЇ265ГўВЂВЇ005</Keep>, <Keep>3ГўВЂВЇ265ГўВЂВЇ028</Keep>, <Keep>3ГўВЂВЇ265ГўВЂВЇ027</Keep>, <Keep>3ГўВЂВЇ265ГўВЂВЇ072</Keep>, <Keep>3ГўВЂВЇ265ГўВЂВЇ073</Keep> and <Keep>2ГўВЂВЇ924ГўВЂВЇ035</Keep>, to the intersection of the south boundary of lot <Keep>2 924 035</Keep> (AutorouteГўВЂВЇ5) and of the west boundary of lot <Keep>2ГўВЂВЇ924ГўВЂВЇ014</Keep> (chemin Scott); thence, in a general southerly direction, following the west boundaries of <Keep>2ГўВЂВЇ924ГўВЂВЇ014</Keep>, <Keep>2ГўВЂВЇ735ГўВЂВЇ360</Keep>, <Keep>2ГўВЂВЇ735ГўВЂВЇ361</Keep>, <Keep>2ГўВЂВЇ636ГўВЂВЇ730</Keep>, <Keep>2ГўВЂВЇ735ГўВЂВЇ385</Keep> and <Keep>2ГўВЂВЇ636ГўВЂВЇ729</Keep> (chemin Scott), to the southeast corner of lot <Keep>3ГўВЂВЇ754ГўВЂВЇ061</Keep>; thence, southerly, crossing lots <Keep>2ГўВЂВЇ924ГўВЂВЇ047</Keep> and <Keep>2ГўВЂВЇ636ГўВЂВЇ722</Keep> (chemin Old Chelsea), to the northwest corner of lot <Keep>2ГўВЂВЇ635ГўВЂВЇ548</Keep>; thence, southerly, following the division line <Keep>between</Keep> lot <Keep>2ГўВЂВЇ635ГўВЂВЇ548</Keep> and lots <Keep>2ГўВЂВЇ924ГўВЂВЇ048</Keep> and <Keep>4ГўВЂВЇ138ГўВЂВЇ881</Keep>, to the southwest corner of lot <Keep>2ГўВЂВЇ635ГўВЂВЇ548</Keep>; thence, easterly, following the division line between lot <Keep>4ГўВЂВЇ138ГўВЂВЇ881</Keep> and lots <Keep>2ГўВЂВЇ635ГўВЂВЇ548</Keep> and <Keep>2ГўВЂВЇ635ГўВЂВЇ547</Keep>, to the southwest corner of lot <Keep>2ГўВЂВЇ635 ГўВЂВЇ547</Keep>, a distance of 42.98ГўВЂВЇm; thence, southerly, following the division line between lots <Keep>2ГўВЂВЇ635ГўВЂВЇ547</Keep> and <Keep>4ГўВЂВЇ138ГўВЂВЇ881</Keep>, to the southwest corner of lot <Keep>2ГўВЂВЇ635ГўВЂВЇ547</Keep>, a distance of 26.82ГўВЂВЇm; thence, easterly, following the division line between lots <Keep>2ГўВЂВЇ635ГўВЂВЇ547</Keep> and <Keep>4ГўВЂВЇ138ГўВЂВЇ881</Keep>, to the southeast corner of lot <Keep>2ГўВЂВЇ635ГўВЂВЇ547</Keep>, a distance of 14.30ГўВЂВЇm; thence, northerly, following the division line between lots <Keep>2ГўВЂВЇ635ГўВЂВЇ547</Keep> and <Keep>4ГўВЂВЇ138ГўВЂВЇ881</Keep>, to the southeast corner of lot <Keep>2ГўВЂВЇ635ГўВЂВЇ547</Keep>, a distance of 26.82ГўВЂВЇm; thence, easterly, following the division line between lots <Keep>2ГўВЂВЇ635ГўВЂВЇ547</Keep> and <Keep>4ГўВЂВЇ138ГўВЂВЇ881</Keep>, to the southeast corner of lot <Keep>2ГўВЂВЇ635ГўВЂВЇ547</Keep>, a distance of 6.55ГўВЂВЇm; thence, northerly, following the division line between lots <Keep>2ГўВЂВЇ635ГўВЂВЇ547</Keep> and <Keep>4ГўВЂВЇ138ГўВЂВЇ881</Keep>, to the northeast corner of lot <Keep>2ГўВЂВЇ635ГўВЂВЇ547</Keep>, a distance of 42.15ГўВЂВЇm; thence, easterly, following the division line between lots <Keep>2ГўВЂВЇ635ГўВЂВЇ551</Keep> and <Keep>4ГўВЂВЇ138ГўВЂВЇ881</Keep>, to the southeast corner of lot <Keep>2ГўВЂВЇ635ГўВЂВЇ551</Keep>, a distance of 10.83ГўВЂВЇm; thence, northerly, following the division line between lots <Keep>2ГўВЂВЇ635ГўВЂВЇ551</Keep> and <Keep>4ГўВЂВЇ138ГўВЂВЇ881</Keep>, to the northeast corner of lot <Keep>2ГўВЂВЇ635ГўВЂВЇ551</Keep>, a distance of 18.23ГўВЂВЇm; thence, easterly, following the division line between lots <Keep>2ГўВЂВЇ924ГўВЂВЇ049</Keep> and <Keep>4ГўВЂВЇ138ГўВЂВЇ881</Keep>, to the northwest corner of lot <Keep>4ГўВЂВЇ138ГўВЂВЇ882</Keep>; thence, southerly, to the southwest corner of lot <Keep>4ГўВЂВЇ138ГўВЂВЇ882</Keep>, a distance of 65.87ГўВЂВЇm; thence, easterly, to the southwest corner of lot <Keep>2ГўВЂВЇ635ГўВЂВЇ573</Keep>, a distance of 76.01ГўВЂВЇm; thence, easterly, following the division line between lots <Keep>2ГўВЂВЇ635ГўВЂВЇ573</Keep> and <Keep>4ГўВЂВЇ138ГўВЂВЇ881</Keep>, to the southeast corner of lot <Keep>2ГўВЂВЇ635ГўВЂВЇ573</Keep>; thence, southerly, following the division line between lots <Keep>2ГўВЂВЇ635ГўВЂВЇ585</Keep> and <Keep>4ГўВЂВЇ138ГўВЂВЇ881</Keep>, to the southwest corner of lot <Keep>2ГўВЂВЇ635ГўВЂВЇ585</Keep>; thence, westerly, following the division line between lots <Keep>2ГўВЂВ‰635ГўВЂВ‰583</Keep> and <Keep>4ГўВЂВЇ138ГўВЂВЇ881</Keep>, to the southwest corner of lot <Keep>2ГўВЂВЇ635ГўВЂВЇ583</Keep>; thence, southerly, following the division line between lots <Keep>2ГўВЂВЇ635ГўВЂВЇ583</Keep> and <Keep>4ГўВЂВЇ138ГўВЂВЇ881</Keep>, to the southeast corner of lot <Keep>4ГўВЂВЇ138ГўВЂВЇ881</Keep>; thence, northwesterly, following the division line between lots <Keep>2ГўВЂВЇ635ГўВЂВЇ493</Keep> and <Keep>4ГўВЂВЇ138ГўВЂВЇ881</Keep>, to the north corner of lot <Keep>2ГўВЂВЇ635ГўВЂВЇ493</Keep>; thence, northwesterly, following the division line between lots <Keep>2ГўВЂВЇ635ГўВЂВЇ533</Keep> and <Keep>4ГўВЂВЇ138ГўВЂВЇ881</Keep>, to the northeast corner of lot <Keep>2ГўВЂВЇ635ГўВЂВЇ533</Keep>; thence, westerly, following the division line between lots <Keep>4ГўВЂВЇ138ГўВЂВЇ881</Keep> and <Keep>2ГўВЂВЇ635ГўВЂВЇ533</Keep>, to the intersection of the eastern boundary of lot <Keep>2ГўВЂВЇ735ГўВЂВЇ434</Keep> (chemin Kingsmere); thence, westerly, following the extension of the division line between lots <Keep>2ГўВЂВЇ635ГўВЂВЇ533</Keep> and <Keep>4ГўВЂВЇ138ГўВЂВЇ881</Keep>, crossing lot <Keep>2ГўВЂВЇ735ГўВЂВЇ434</Keep> (chemin Kingsmere), to the intersection of the west boundary of said lot <Keep>2ГўВЂВЇ735ГўВЂВЇ434</Keep>, a distance of 12.24ГўВЂВЇm; thence, southerly, following the west boundary of lot <Keep>2ГўВЂВЇ735ГўВЂВЇ434</Keep> (chemin Kingsmere), to the southwest corner of lot <Keep>2ГўВЂВЇ735ГўВЂВЇ434</Keep>; thence, southwesterly, following the northwest boundary of lot <Keep>2ГўВЂВЇ636ГўВЂВЇ668</Keep> (chemin Kingsmere), to the southwest corner of said lot <Keep>2ГўВЂВЇ636ГўВЂВЇ668</Keep>; thence, southwesterly, crossing lot <Keep>2ГўВЂВЇ735ГўВЂВЇ441</Keep> (chemin Kingsmere), to the northwest corner of lot <Keep>2ГўВЂВЇ735ГўВЂВЇ433</Keep> (chemin Notch); thence, southerly, following the west boundary of chemin Notch, being lots <Keep>2ГўВЂВЇ735ГўВЂВЇ433</Keep>, <Keep>2ГўВЂВЇ735ГўВЂВЇ431</Keep>, <Keep>2ГўВЂВЇ735ГўВЂВЇ464</Keep>, <Keep>2ГўВЂВЇ735ГўВЂВЇ463</Keep> and <Keep>2ГўВЂВЇ636ГўВЂВЇ667</Keep>, to the southwest corner of lot <Keep>2ГўВЂВЇ636ГўВЂВЇ667</Keep>; thence, easterly, following the division line between lot <Keep>2ГўВЂВЇ636ГўВЂВЇ667</Keep> (chemin Notch) and lots <Keep>2ГўВЂВЇ635ГўВЂВЇ407</Keep> and <Keep>2ГўВЂВЇ735ГўВЂВЇ329</Keep> (chemin Notch), to the southeast corner of lot <Keep>2ГўВЂВЇ636ГўВЂВЇ667</Keep> (chemin Notch); thence, easterly, then southerly, following the division line between lots <Keep>2ГўВЂВЇ735ГўВЂВЇ342</Keep> (chemin de la Mine) and <Keep>2ГўВЂВЇ735ГўВЂВЇ329</Keep> (chemin Notch), to the northwest corner of lot <Keep>2ГўВЂВЇ635ГўВЂВЇ425</Keep>; thence, in a general southeasterly direction, following the southwest boundary of chemin de la Mine, being lots <Keep>2ГўВЂВЇ735ГўВЂВЇ342</Keep>, <Keep>2ГўВЂВЇ735ГўВЂВЇ341</Keep>, <Keep>2ГўВЂВЇ636ГўВЂВЇ585</Keep> and <Keep>2ГўВЂВЇ735ГўВЂВЇ338</Keep>, <Keep>2ГўВЂВЇ735ГўВЂВЇ336</Keep>, <Keep>2ГўВЂВЇ735ГўВЂВЇ333</Keep>, <Keep>2ГўВЂВЇ636ГўВЂВЇ583</Keep>, <Keep>2ГўВЂВЇ735ГўВЂВЇ331</Keep>, <Keep>2ГўВЂВЇ735ГўВЂВЇ330</Keep>, which becomes the boulevard de la CitГѓВ©-des-Jeunes, lot <Keep>2ГўВЂВЇ636ГўВЂВЇ582</Keep>, to the north corner of lot <Keep>3ГўВЂВЇ557ГўВЂВЇ256</Keep>, to the point of commencement.</Text>
</Provision><BillPiece><Heading level="1"><TitleText>3 ГўВЂВ” System of Measurement</TitleText></Heading></BillPiece><Provision>
<Text>In this description, measurements are in metres (SI) and bearings are in reference of the geodetic system of plane coordinates of Quebec (SCOPQ).</Text>
</Provision>
</Schedule></Schedule><Schedule><ScheduleFormHeading><Label />
<OriginatingRef><Emphasis style="bold" /></OriginatingRef>
</ScheduleFormHeading></Schedule>
</Bill>