<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><Bill bill-origin="senate" bill-type="private-public" xml:lang="en" date-time="2022-09-27 12:36:26"><Identification><BillNumber>S-232</BillNumber><Parliament><Session>1</Session><Number>45</Number><RegnalYear><Year-s>3</Year-s><Monarch>Charles III</Monarch></RegnalYear><Year-s>2025</Year-s></Parliament><LongTitle>An Act respecting non-disclosure agreements</LongTitle><ShortTitle status="unofficial">Can’t Buy Silence Act</ShortTitle><RunningHead>Can’t Buy Silence Act</RunningHead><BillHistory><Stages stage="first-reading-senate"><Date><YYYY>2025</YYYY><MM>6</MM><DD>12</DD></Date></Stages></BillHistory><BillSponsor>Senator M<Sup>c</Sup>PHEDRAN</BillSponsor><BillRefNumber date-time="">4512215</BillRefNumber></Identification><Introduction><Summary><TitleText>SUMMARY</TitleText><Provision language-align="yes"><Text>This enactment requires the President of the Treasury Board to report on the use of certain non-disclosure agreements in the federal public sector. It also requires Parliament to undertake a review of the Act every two years after it enters into force.</Text></Provision><Provision language-align="yes"><Text>It amends the <XRefExternal reference-type="act" reference-level="federal">Financial Administration Act</XRefExternal> and the <XRefExternal reference-type="act" reference-level="federal">Parliament of Canada Act</XRefExternal> in respect of the use of public money to enter into non-disclosure agreements and to litigate non-disclosure agreements against complainants.</Text></Provision><Provision language-align="yes"><Text>It amends the <XRefExternal reference-type="act" reference-level="federal">Financial Administration Act</XRefExternal> to require federal officials empowered to make grants and contributions to take measures to ensure that public money is not used to</Text></Provision><Provision first-line-indent="1" subsequent-line-indent="1"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>pay for settlements in relation to harassment and violence or discrimination if the settlement is to include a non-disclosure agreement; or </Text></Provision><Provision first-line-indent="1" subsequent-line-indent="1"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>litigate non-disclosure agreements against complainants.</Text></Provision><Provision language-align="yes"><Text>Finally, it amends the <XRefExternal reference-type="act" reference-level="federal">Financial Administration Act</XRefExternal> to require non-government entities receiving a grant or contribution of federal funds to report to the President of the Treasury Board on their use of non-disclosure agreements.</Text></Provision></Summary><Enacts><Provision><Text>His Majesty, by and with the advice and consent of the Senate and House of Commons of Canada, enacts as follows:</Text></Provision></Enacts></Introduction><Body><Heading level="1"><TitleText>Short Title</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Short title</MarginalNote><Label>1</Label><Text>This Act may be cited as the <Emphasis style="italic">Can’t Buy Silence Act</Emphasis>.</Text></Section><Heading level="1"><TitleText>Interpretation</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Definitions</MarginalNote><Label>2</Label><Text>The following definitions apply in this Act.</Text><Definition><Text><DefinedTermEn>complainant</DefinedTermEn> has the meaning assigned by subsection 25.1(4) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Financial Administration Act</XRefExternal>. (<DefinedTermFr>plaignant</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Definition><Definition><Text><DefinedTermEn>non-disclosure agreement</DefinedTermEn> has the meaning assigned by subsection 25.1(4) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act" reference-level="federal">Financial Administration Act</XRefExternal>. (<DefinedTermFr>accord de non-divulgation</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Definition></Section><Heading level="1"><TitleText>Annual Report — Public Sector</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Information</MarginalNote><Label>3</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Beginning in the first year after this Act receives royal assent, the President of the Treasury Board must cause to be tabled, in both Houses of Parliament, not later than 45 days after the fiscal year ends, a report containing the following information about the previous <Keep>fiscal</Keep> year for each entity whose financial information is included in the Public Accounts prepared under the <XRefExternal reference-type="act" reference-level="federal"><Keep>Financial</Keep> Administration Act</XRefExternal>:</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>the number of non-disclosure agreements entered into; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>the total dollar amount of agreements containing non-disclosure agreements.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Information from non-governmental entities</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The report referred to in subsection (1) must also contain the information provided to the President of the Treasury Board under subsection 25.1(2) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act" reference-level="federal">Financial Administration Act</XRefExternal>.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Certification</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>In the report, the President of the Treasury Board must certify that they are satisfied that the entities whose financial information is included in the Public Accounts prepared under the <XRefExternal reference-type="act" reference-level="federal">Financial Administration Act</XRefExternal> have provided accurate information for the purposes of the <Keep>report</Keep>.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Anonymous data</MarginalNote><Label>(4)</Label><Text>The information in subsection (1) must be provided in a manner that is not likely to reveal a person’s identity.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Privilege</MarginalNote><Label>(5)</Label><Text>The information in subsection (1) must be provided regardless of whether it is</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>subject to any privilege, including parliamentary privilege, solicitor-client privilege or the professional secrecy of advocates and notaries, or litigation privilege; or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>a confidence of the King’s Privy Council for Canada to which subsection 39(1) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act" reference-level="federal">Canada <Keep>Evidence</Keep> Act</XRefExternal> applies.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Certainty</MarginalNote><Label>(6)</Label><Text>For greater certainty, parliamentary privilege is expressly waived to provide the information required under this section, but it is not waived in respect of that information for any other purpose.</Text></Subsection></Section><Heading level="1"><TitleText>Parliamentary Review</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Parliamentary review</MarginalNote><Label>4</Label><Text>As soon as feasible after the second anniversary of the day on which this Act comes into force and every two years after that, a review of this Act and of its administration and operation is to be undertaken by a committee of the Senate, of the House of Commons or of both Houses of Parliament that may be designated or established for that purpose.</Text></Section><Heading level="1"><MarginalNote><HistoricalNote>R.S., ch. F-11</HistoricalNote></MarginalNote><TitleText><XRefExternal reference-type="act">Financial Administration Act</XRefExternal></TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><Label>5</Label><Text>The <XRefExternal reference-type="act" reference-level="federal">Financial Administration Act</XRefExternal> is amended by adding the following after section 25:</Text><AmendedText change="ins"><Section><MarginalNote>Restrictions — grants and contributions</MarginalNote><Label>25.1</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Any statutory authority that allows for the making of a grant or a contribution of public money to an entity whose financial information is not included in the Public Accounts prepared under this Act must be exercised in a way that prevents public money from being used to</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>pay for settlements in relation to harassment and violence or discrimination based on a prohibited ground of discrimination within the meaning of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Canadian Human Rights Act</XRefExternal> if the settlement is to <Keep>include</Keep> a non-disclosure agreement; or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>litigate non-disclosure agreements against complainants.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Report to President of Treasury Board</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>An agreement that provides for a grant or contribution of public money to an entity whose financial information is not included in the Public Accounts must <Keep>include</Keep> a provision requiring the entity to report to the President of the Treasury Board, on an annual basis, <Keep>information</Keep> on</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>the number of non-disclosure agreements entered into; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>the total dollar amount of agreements containing non-disclosure agreements.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Anonymous data</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>The information in subsection (2) must be provided in a manner that is not likely to reveal a person’s identity.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Definitions</MarginalNote><Label>(4)</Label><Text>The following definitions apply in this section and in section 40.01.</Text><Definition><Text><DefinedTermEn>complainant</DefinedTermEn> means any person who alleges having been the subject of harassment and violence or discrimination. (<DefinedTermFr>plaignant</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Definition><Definition><Text><DefinedTermEn>harassment and violence</DefinedTermEn> means any action, conduct or comment, including of a sexual nature, that can reasonably be expected to cause offence, humiliation or other physical or psychological injury or illness to an individual, including any prescribed action, conduct or comment. (<DefinedTermFr>harcèlement et violence</DefinedTermFr>) </Text></Definition><Definition><Text><DefinedTermEn>non-disclosure agreement</DefinedTermEn> means a provision of a written agreement, however called, that is entered into after this section comes into force and is between a complainant and an entity whose financial information is <Keep>included</Keep> in the Public Accounts prepared under this Act or an entity that receives a grant or contribution of public money, and under which a complainant agrees not to disclose any material information regarding any of the following:</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>a circumstance of harassment and violence or discrimination based on a prohibited ground of discrimination within the meaning of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act" reference-level="federal">Canadian Human Rights Act</XRefExternal> experienced or alleged by the complainant;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>the resolution of a complaint, including the details of any formal or informal process to address the allegation; or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(c)</Label><Text>the monetary value of a written settlement insofar as it relates to the allegation.</Text></Paragraph><ContinuedDefinition><Text>For greater certainty, it includes a non-disparagement agreement if its purpose or effect is to require a complainant not to disclose information described in paragraphs (a) to (c). (<DefinedTermFr>accord de non-divulgation</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></ContinuedDefinition></Definition></Subsection></Section></AmendedText><ExplanatoryNote><TitleText><XRefExternal reference-type="act">Financial Administration Act</XRefExternal></TitleText><Label><Emphasis style="italic">Clause 5</Emphasis>:</Label><ExplanatoryText>New.</ExplanatoryText></ExplanatoryNote></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>6</Label><Text>The Act is amended by adding the following <Keep>after</Keep> section 40:</Text><AmendedText change="ins"><Section><MarginalNote>Restriction — non-disclosure agreements</MarginalNote><Label>40.01</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>No department, departmental corporation or Crown corporation may enter into a non-disclosure agreement unless the complainant, after having had the opportunity to obtain independent legal advice that <Keep>includes</Keep> advice on alternative means to protect the confidentiality of their personal information, makes a specific and voluntary written request for a non-disclosure agreement before the agreement is entered into.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Permitted disclosures</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>A non-disclosure agreement entered into in accordance with subsection (1) does not apply to</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>any information disclosure that is protected or <Keep>required</Keep> under an Act of Parliament or the laws of a province or territory;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>artistic expression by the complainant that does not identify</Text><Subparagraph><Label>(i)</Label><Text> the party responsible or the person who committed or is alleged to have
committed the harassment and violence or discrimination, or</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph><Label>(ii)</Label><Text>the terms of the non-disclosure agreement; or</Text></Subparagraph></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(c)</Label><Text>any communication relating to the harassment and violence or discrimination between the complainant and</Text><Subparagraph><Label>(i)</Label><Text>a person whose duties include the enforcement of an Act of Parliament or the laws of a province or territory if the communication is in respect of a matter within the person’s official duties,</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph><Label>(ii)</Label><Text>a person entitled to practise law by the law society of a province or territory,</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph><Label>(iii)</Label><Text>a community elder, spiritual counsellor or counsellor who is providing
culturally specific services to the complainant,</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph><Label>(iv)</Label><Text>a medical practitioner or nurse practitioner as defined in section 241.1 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act" reference-level="federal">Criminal Code</XRefExternal>,</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph><Label>(v)</Label><Text>a psychologist or psychological associate authorized to practise as such under the laws of a province or territory,</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph><Label>(vi)</Label><Text>a registered nurse authorized to practise as such under the laws of a province or territory,</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph><Label>(vii)</Label><Text>a social worker authorized to practise as such under the laws of a province or territory,</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph><Label>(viii)</Label><Text>a person who provides victim services pursuant to the laws of a province or territory, or</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph><Label>(ix)</Label><Text>a friend, family member or other personal <Keep>supporter</Keep>.</Text></Subparagraph></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Restriction — public money</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>No department, departmental corporation or Crown corporation may use public money to litigate a non-disclosure agreement against a complainant.</Text></Subsection></Section></AmendedText><ExplanatoryNote><Label><Emphasis style="italic">Clause 6</Emphasis>:</Label><ExplanatoryText>New.</ExplanatoryText></ExplanatoryNote></Section><Heading level="1"><MarginalNote><HistoricalNote>R.S., ch. P-1</HistoricalNote></MarginalNote><TitleText><XRefExternal reference-type="act">Parliament of Canada Act</XRefExternal></TitleText></Heading><Heading level="2"><TitleText>Senate — Committee on Internal Economy, Budgets and Administration</TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><Label>7</Label><Text>Section 19.2 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Parliament of Canada Act</XRefExternal> is amended by adding the following after subsection (2):</Text><AmendedText change="ins"><Subsection><MarginalNote>Restriction — non-disclosure agreement</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>Despite subsection (1), the Committee may not permit public money to be used to</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>enter into a non-disclosure agreement as defined in subsection 25.1(4) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Financial Administration Act</XRefExternal> unless the complainant, after having had the <Keep>opportunity</Keep> to obtain independent legal advice that includes advice on alternative means to protect the confidentiality of their personal information, makes a specific and voluntary written request for a non-disclosure agreement before the agreement is entered <Keep>into</Keep>; or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>litigate non-disclosure agreements against complainants.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Permitted disclosures</MarginalNote><Label>(4)</Label><Text>A non-disclosure agreement entered into in accordance with subsection (3) does not apply to</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>any information disclosure that is protected or <Keep>required</Keep> under an Act of Parliament or the laws of a province or territory;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>artistic expression by the complainant that does not identify</Text><Subparagraph><Label>(i)</Label><Text> the party responsible or the person who committed or is alleged to have
committed the harassment and violence or discrimination, or</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph><Label>(ii)</Label><Text>the terms of the non-disclosure agreement; or</Text></Subparagraph></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(c)</Label><Text>any communication relating to the harassment and violence or discrimination between the complainant and</Text><Subparagraph><Label>(i)</Label><Text>a person whose duties include the enforcement of an Act of Parliament or the laws of a province or territory if the communication is in respect of a matter within the person’s official duties,</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph><Label>(ii)</Label><Text>a person entitled to practise law by the law society of a province or territory,</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph><Label>(iii)</Label><Text>a community elder, spiritual counsellor or counsellor who is providing
culturally specific services to the complainant,</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph><Label>(iv)</Label><Text>a medical practitioner or nurse practitioner as defined in section 241.1 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act" reference-level="federal">Criminal Code</XRefExternal>,</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph><Label>(v)</Label><Text>a psychologist or psychological associate authorized to practise as such under the laws of a province or territory,</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph><Label>(vi)</Label><Text>a registered nurse authorized to practise as such under the laws of a province or territory,</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph><Label>(vii)</Label><Text>a social worker authorized to practise as such under the laws of a province or territory,</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph><Label>(viii)</Label><Text>a person who provides victim services pursuant to the laws of a province or territory, or</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph><Label>(ix)</Label><Text>a friend, family member or other personal <Keep>supporter</Keep>.</Text></Subparagraph></Paragraph></Subsection></AmendedText><ExplanatoryNote><TitleText><XRefExternal reference-type="act">Parliament of Canada Act</XRefExternal></TitleText><Label><Emphasis style="italic">Clause 7</Emphasis>:</Label><ExplanatoryText>New.</ExplanatoryText></ExplanatoryNote></Section><Heading level="2"><TitleText>House of Commons — Board of Internal Economy</TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><Label>8</Label><Text>Section 52.2 of the Act is amended by adding the following after subsection (2):</Text><AmendedText change="ins"><Subsection><MarginalNote>Restriction — non-disclosure agreement</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>Despite subsection (1), the Board may not permit public money to be used to</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>enter into a non-disclosure agreement as defined in subsection 25.1(4) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act" reference-level="federal">Financial Administration Act</XRefExternal> unless the complainant, after having had the <Keep>opportunity</Keep> to obtain independent legal advice that includes advice on alternative means to protect the confidentiality of their personal information, makes a specific and voluntary written request for a non-disclosure agreement before the agreement is entered <Keep>into</Keep>; or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>litigate non-disclosure agreements against complainants.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Permitted disclosures</MarginalNote><Label>(4)</Label><Text>A non-disclosure agreement entered into in accordance with subsection (3) does not apply to an information disclosure, artistic expression or communication <Keep>referred</Keep> to in subsection 19.2(4).</Text></Subsection></AmendedText><ExplanatoryNote><Label><Emphasis style="italic">Clause 8</Emphasis>:</Label><ExplanatoryText>New.</ExplanatoryText></ExplanatoryNote></Section><Heading level="2"><TitleText>Library of Parliament</TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><Label>9</Label><Text>Section 75 of the Act is amended by adding the following after subsection (2):</Text><AmendedText change="ins"><Subsection><MarginalNote>Restriction — non-disclosure agreement</MarginalNote><Label>(2.1)</Label><Text>Despite anything in this Act, the Parliamentary <Keep>Librarian</Keep> may not</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>enter into a non-disclosure agreement as defined in subsection 25.1(4) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act" reference-level="federal">Financial Administration Act</XRefExternal> unless the complainant, after having had the <Keep>opportunity</Keep> to obtain independent legal advice that includes advice on alternative means to protect the confidentiality of their personal information, makes a specific and voluntary written request for a non-disclosure agreement in writing before the agreement is entered into; or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>litigate non-disclosure agreements against complainants.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Permitted disclosures</MarginalNote><Label>(2.2)</Label><Text>A non-disclosure agreement entered into in accordance with subsection (2.1) does not apply to an information disclosure, artistic expression or communication <Keep>referred</Keep> to in subsection 19.2(4).</Text></Subsection></AmendedText><ExplanatoryNote><Label><Emphasis style="italic">Clause 9</Emphasis>:</Label><ExplanatoryText>New.</ExplanatoryText></ExplanatoryNote></Section><Heading level="2"><TitleText>Parliamentary Protective Service</TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><Label>10</Label><Text>Section 79.53 of the Act is amended by adding the following after subsection (3):</Text><AmendedText change="ins"><Subsection><MarginalNote>Restriction — non-disclosure agreement</MarginalNote><Label>(4)</Label><Text>Despite anything in this Act, the Service may not</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>enter into a non-disclosure agreement as defined in subsection 25.1(4) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act" reference-level="federal">Financial Administration Act</XRefExternal> unless the complainant, after having had the <Keep>opportunity</Keep> to obtain independent legal advice that includes advice on alternative means to protect the confidentiality of their personal information, makes a specific and voluntary written request for a non-disclosure agreement before the agreement is entered <Keep>into</Keep>; or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>litigate non-disclosure agreements against complainants.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Permitted disclosures</MarginalNote><Label>(5)</Label><Text>A non-disclosure agreement entered into in accordance with subsection (4) does not apply to an <Keep svc="1">information</Keep> disclosure, artistic expression or communication <Keep>referred</Keep> to in subsection 19.2(4).</Text></Subsection></AmendedText><ExplanatoryNote><Label><Emphasis style="italic">Clause 10</Emphasis>:</Label><ExplanatoryText>New.</ExplanatoryText></ExplanatoryNote></Section><Heading level="1"><TitleText>Coming into Force</TitleText></Heading><Section type="CIF"><MarginalNote>Sixty days after royal assent</MarginalNote><Label>11</Label><Text>This Act comes into force 60 days after the day on which it receives royal assent.</Text></Section></Body></Bill>