<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><Bill bill-origin="senate" bill-type="private-public" xml:lang="en" date-time="2023-02-13 15:43:16"><Identification><BillNumber>S-244</BillNumber><Parliament><Session>1</Session><Number>45</Number><RegnalYear><Year-s>3-4</Year-s><Monarch>Charles III</Monarch></RegnalYear><Year-s>2025</Year-s></Parliament><LongTitle>An Act respecting National Diffuse Intrinsic Pontine Glioma Awareness Day</LongTitle><ShortTitle status="unofficial">National Diffuse Intrinsic Pontine Glioma Awareness Day Act</ShortTitle><RunningHead>National Diffuse Intrinsic Pontine Glioma Awareness Day Act</RunningHead><BillHistory><Stages stage="first-reading-senate"><Date><YYYY>2025</YYYY><MM>12</MM><DD>10</DD></Date></Stages></BillHistory><BillSponsor>Senator MARTIN</BillSponsor><BillRefNumber date-time="">4512227</BillRefNumber></Identification><Introduction><Summary><TitleText>SUMMARY</TitleText><Provision><Text>This enactment designates the 17th day of May in each and <Keep>every</Keep> year as “National Diffuse Intrinsic Pontine Glioma Awareness Day”.</Text></Provision></Summary><Preamble><Provision pointsize="10" topmarginspacing="-6" language-align="yes"><MarginalNote>Preamble</MarginalNote><Text>Whereas diffuse intrinsic pontine glioma is an aggressive brain tumour that attacks the brainstem and slowly destroys all vital functions even as cognitive functions remain intact, rendering the affected person a prisoner in their own body;</Text></Provision><Provision><Text>Whereas diffuse intrinsic pontine glioma typically <Keep>affects</Keep> children who are five to seven years of age;</Text></Provision><Provision><Text>Whereas diffuse intrinsic pontine glioma remains <Keep>inoperable</Keep>, incurable and fatal;</Text></Provision><Provision><Text>Whereas the prognosis and treatments have not <Keep>improved</Keep> in more than 40 years;</Text></Provision><Provision><Text>Whereas the Parliament of Canada wishes to increase awareness of this disease among Canadians in order to encourage public and private investment in research to improve the prognosis and treatments;</Text></Provision><Provision><Text>Whereas it is important to honour those who have died of this disease;</Text></Provision><Provision><Text>And whereas the 17th day of May of each year is recognized in a number of other countries as a diffuse intrinsic pontine glioma awareness day;</Text></Provision></Preamble><Enacts><Provision><Text>His Majesty, by and with the advice and consent of the Senate and House of Commons of Canada, enacts as follows:</Text></Provision></Enacts></Introduction><Body><Section><MarginalNote>Short title</MarginalNote><Label>1</Label><Text>This Act may be cited as the <Emphasis style="italic">National Diffuse Intrinsic Pontine Glioma Awareness Day Act</Emphasis>.</Text></Section><Section><MarginalNote>National Diffuse Intrinsic Pontine Glioma Awareness Day</MarginalNote><Label>2</Label><Text>Throughout Canada, in each and every year, the 17th day of May is to be known as “National Diffuse Intrinsic Pontine Glioma Awareness Day”.</Text></Section></Body></Bill>