<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><Bill bill-origin="senate" bill-type="private-public" xml:lang="en" date-time="2018-02-21 11:37:19"><Identification><BillNumber>S-242</BillNumber><Parliament><Session>1</Session><Number>45</Number><RegnalYear><Year-s>3-4</Year-s><Monarch>Charles III</Monarch></RegnalYear><Year-s>2025</Year-s></Parliament><LongTitle>An Act respecting national action for the prevention of intimate partner violence</LongTitle><ShortTitle status="unofficial">Georgina’s Law</ShortTitle><RunningHead>Georgina’s Law</RunningHead><BillHistory><Stages stage="third-reading-senate"><Date><YYYY>2026</YYYY><MM>2</MM><DD>24</DD></Date></Stages></BillHistory><BillRefNumber date-time="">4511723</BillRefNumber></Identification><Introduction><Summary><TitleText>SUMMARY</TitleText><Provision><Text>This enactment provides for the continuation of national action for the prevention of intimate partner violence.</Text></Provision></Summary><Enacts><Provision><Text>His Majesty, by and with the advice and consent of the Senate and House of Commons of Canada, enacts as follows:</Text></Provision></Enacts></Introduction><Body><Heading level="1"><TitleText>Short Title</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Short title</MarginalNote><Label>1</Label><Text>This Act may be cited as <Emphasis style="italic">Georgina’s Law</Emphasis>.</Text></Section><Heading level="1"><TitleText>Interpretation</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Definitions </MarginalNote><Label>2</Label><Text>The following definitions apply in this Act.</Text><Definition><Text><DefinedTermEn>intimate partner</DefinedTermEn>, with respect to a person, includes their current or former spouse, common-law partner and dating partner. (<DefinedTermFr>partenaire intime</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Definition><Definition><Text><DefinedTermEn>Minister </DefinedTermEn> means the Minister for Women and Gender Equality. (<DefinitionFrOnly>ministre</DefinitionFrOnly>)</Text></Definition></Section><Heading level="1"><TitleText>National Action for the Prevention of Intimate Partner Violence</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>National action</MarginalNote><Label>3</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The Minister must continue to lead national action to prevent and address intimate partner violence.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Engagements</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>In leading national action to prevent and address <Keep>intimate</Keep> partner violence, the Minister must engage annually with other federal ministers and with provincial ministers responsible for the status of women and <Keep svc="1">regularly</Keep> with Indigenous partners, victims and survivors, and stakeholders with respect to</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>the adequacy of current programs and strategies aimed at preventing intimate partner violence and at protecting and assisting victims of intimate partner <Keep>violence</Keep>;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>partnerships in the prevention of intimate partner violence and the protection of victims of intimate partner violence;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(c)</Label><Text>the financial and other costs of action to prevent and address intimate partner violence; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(d)</Label><Text>any constitutional, legal or jurisdictional implications of action to prevent and address intimate partner violence.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Initiation of engagements</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>The engagements referred to in subsection (2) must begin within one year after the day on which this Act <Keep>receives</Keep> royal assent.</Text></Subsection></Section><Heading level="1"><TitleText>Report and Publication</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Report to Parliament</MarginalNote><Label>4</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Within two years after this Act receives royal assent and every two years after that, the Minister must prepare a report setting out progress on action to prevent and address intimate partner violence and cause a copy of the report to be tabled in each House of Parliament.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Publication of report</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The Minister must post the report on the departmental website within 30 days after the day on which the <Keep>report</Keep> is tabled in both Houses of Parliament.</Text></Subsection></Section></Body></Bill>