<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!--Arbortext, Inc., 1988-2010, v.4002--><Bill bill-origin="senate" bill-type="govt-public" xml:lang="en"><!--Authoring to Exchange Transform created with transform.acl--><Identification><BillNumber>S-3</BillNumber><Parliament><Session>1</Session><Number>45</Number><RegnalYear><Year-s>3-4</Year-s><Monarch>Charles III</Monarch></RegnalYear><Year-s>2025</Year-s></Parliament><LongTitle>An Act to amend the Weights and Measures Act, the Electricity and Gas Inspection Act, the Weights and Measures Regulations and the Electricity and Gas <Keep>Inspection</Keep> Regulations</LongTitle><ShortTitle status="unofficial">An Act to amend the Weights and Measures Act, the Electricity and Gas Inspection Act, the Weights and Measures Regulations and the Electricity and Gas Inspection Regulations</ShortTitle><RunningHead>An Act to amend the Weights and Measures Act, the Electricity and Gas Inspection Act, the Weights and Measures Regulations and the ...</RunningHead><BillHistory><Stages stage="first-reading-senate"><Date><YYYY>2025</YYYY><MM>10</MM><DD>28</DD></Date></Stages></BillHistory><BillSponsor>THE HONOURABLE SENATOR MOREAU, P.C.</BillSponsor><BillRefNumber date-time="2025-10-20">91246</BillRefNumber></Identification><Introduction><Summary><TitleText>SUMMARY</TitleText><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>This enactment amends the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Weights and Measures Act</XRefExternal> to, among other things, clarify existing powers, duties and functions of the Minister of Industry and inspectors, provide the Minister with certain powers, including with respect to sampling when devices are examined and with respect to corrective and preventive measures, and provide inspectors with certain powers.</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>It also amends the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Electricity and Gas Inspection Act</XRefExternal> to, among other things, broaden the definition of “meter”, provide the president with the authority to grant certain exemptions, clarify the steps required to put a device into service, clarify existing powers, duties and functions of the Minister and inspectors, provide the Minister with certain powers, including with respect to sampling when meters are examined and with respect to corrective and preventive measures, and provide inspectors with certain powers.</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>It also repeals certain provisions in the <XRefExternal reference-level="federal" reference-type="regulation">Weights and Measures Regulations</XRefExternal> and the <XRefExternal reference-level="federal" reference-type="regulation">Electricity and Gas Inspection Regulations</XRefExternal>. Finally, it includes transitional provisions.</Text></Provision></Summary><Enacts><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>His Majesty, by and with the advice and consent of the Senate and House of Commons of Canada, enacts as follows:</Text></Provision></Enacts></Introduction><Body><Heading level="1"><MarginalNote><HistoricalNote>R.S., c. W-6</HistoricalNote></MarginalNote><TitleText><XRefExternal reference-type="act">Weights and Measures Act</XRefExternal></TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><Label>1</Label><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The definition <DefinedTermEn>inspector</DefinedTermEn> in section 2 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Weights and Measures Act</XRefExternal> is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><SectionPiece><Definition><Text><DefinedTermEn>inspector</DefinedTermEn> means a person who is designated under subsection 16.1(1) to verify compliance <Ins>or prevent non-compliance</Ins> with this Act; (<DefinedTermFr>inspecteur</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Definition></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Paragraph (b) of the definition <DefinedTermEn>reference standard</DefinedTermEn> in section 2 of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><SectionPiece><Definition><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>has been calibrated and certified by the National Research Council of Canada <Ins>or by an entity that is <Keep>authorized</Keep> under section 3.1 to calibrate and certify reference standards</Ins>, and</Text></Paragraph></Definition></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(3)</Label><Text>Section 2 of the Act is amended by adding the following in alphabetical order:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><SectionPiece><Definition change="ins"><Text><DefinedTermEn>vehicle</DefinedTermEn> means a vessel, aircraft, train, motor vehicle, trailer or other means of transportation and includes a cargo container; (<DefinedTermFr>véhicule</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Definition></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>2</Label><Text>The heading before section 3 of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Heading level="1"><TitleText>Approval <Ins>and Authorization</Ins> by Minister</TitleText></Heading></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>3</Label><Text>The Act is amended by adding the following after section 3:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Section change="ins"><MarginalNote>Authorization of entity</MarginalNote><Label>3.1</Label><Text>The Minister may authorize any entity to calibrate and certify reference standards.</Text></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>4</Label><Text>The portion of section 8 of the Act before paragraph (a) is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Section><MarginalNote>Approval, examination and certification of devices</MarginalNote><Label>8</Label><Text><Ins>Subject to section 8.1, a</Ins> trader <Ins>must not</Ins> use, or have in their possession for use, in trade, any device unless</Text></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>5</Label><Text>The Act is amended by adding the following after section 8:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Section change="ins"><MarginalNote>Temporary permission</MarginalNote><Label>8.1</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The Minister may permit a trader to use, or have in their possession for use, in trade, any device on a temporary basis for any period and under any conditions that the Minister specifies, without approval or examination.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Suspension or revocation of permission</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Subject to subsection (4), the Minister may, by written notice, suspend or revoke the permission.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Effect of suspension or revocation</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>The Minister must specify in the notice the effect of the suspension or revocation and, in the case of a suspension, may specify any conditions that must be met for the suspension to be lifted.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Right to make representations</MarginalNote><Label>(4)</Label><Text>The Minister must not suspend or revoke the permission unless</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>a notice of intention to suspend or revoke it has been given in writing;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>any interested person who objects to the suspension or revocation has been given a reasonable opportunity to make representations with respect to their objections; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(c)</Label><Text>the representations, if any, have been taken into account in deciding whether to suspend or revoke the permission.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>6</Label><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Paragraph 10(1)(k) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(k)</Label><Text>respecting the detention of things seized under paragraph 17(<Ins>1.1</Ins>)(c);</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Paragraphs 10(1)(q) to (s) of the Act are replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(q)</Label><Text><Ins>respecting</Ins> fees or charges <Ins>to be paid in relation to the administration and enforcement of</Ins> this Act;</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(3)</Label><Text>Paragraph 10(1)(t) of the Act is repealed.</Text></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(4)</Label><Text>Subsections 10(2) and (3) of the Act are repealed.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>7</Label><Text>The Act is amended by adding the following after section 10.1:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Section change="ins"><MarginalNote>Ministerial regulations — disputes</MarginalNote><Label>10.2</Label><Text>The Minister may make regulations respecting</Text><Paragraph change="ins"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>examinations that may be performed for the purpose of making determinations on disputes between traders and any other persons about the accuracy of devices; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph change="ins"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>rules, conditions or criteria regarding the accuracy of a device that is the subject of a dispute.</Text></Paragraph></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>8</Label><Text>Subsection 12(1) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Section><MarginalNote>Calibration and certification of standards</MarginalNote><Label>12</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The reference standards and other standards of measurement that are <Ins>used</Ins> for the purpose of determining the accuracy of local standards or of standards that are used by inspectors under the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Electricity and Gas <Keep>Inspection</Keep> Act</XRefExternal> <Ins>must</Ins>, at the request of the Minister, be calibrated and certified by the National Research Council of Canada, <Ins>or by an entity that is authorized under section 3.1, based on</Ins> the units of measurement set out and defined in Schedule I or II.</Text></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>9</Label><Text>Section 13 of the Act is amended by adding the following after subsection (2):</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Subsection change="ins"><MarginalNote>Exemption</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>The Minister may, by order, exempt, for <Ins>any</Ins> period and under <Ins>any</Ins> conditions that the Minister specifies, any local standard from the application of the periods referred to in subsection (2).</Text></Subsection><Subsection change="ins"><MarginalNote><XRefExternal reference-type="act">Statutory Instruments Act</XRefExternal></MarginalNote><Label>(4)</Label><Text>The <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Statutory Instruments Act</XRefExternal> does not apply to an order made under subsection (3).</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>10</Label><Text>The Act is amended by adding the following after section 15.1:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Section change="ins"><MarginalNote>Examination by sampling</MarginalNote><Label>15.2</Label><Subsection change="ins"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The examination of a device may be performed using any means, including by sampling devices of the same class, type or design.</Text></Subsection><Subsection change="ins"><MarginalNote>Sampling results</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>If the examination of a device is performed by means of sampling, the results of the examination may be applied, in accordance with the directions issued under subsection 15.3(1), to any device of the same class, type or design for the purpose of issuing a certificate or statement under subsection 19(1) or attaching seals or tags under subsection 19(2) or (3).</Text></Subsection></Section><Section change="ins"><MarginalNote>Directions</MarginalNote><Label>15.3</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The Minister may issue written directions respecting the examination of devices, including examination conducted by means of sampling.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Application</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The Minister may specify the circumstances in which, the persons to whom and the classes, types or designs of devices to which the directions apply.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Accessibility</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>The directions must be made accessible to the public.</Text></Subsection><Subsection change="ins"><MarginalNote><XRefExternal reference-type="act">Statutory Instruments Act</XRefExternal></MarginalNote><Label>(4)</Label><Text>The <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Statutory Instruments Act</XRefExternal> does not apply to a direction issued under subsection (1).</Text></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>11</Label><Text>Subsections 16.1(1.1) and (2) of the Act are replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Subsection><MarginalNote>Limitation</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The Minister may designate only persons employed in the federal public administration to exercise powers under any of sections 17 to 18, subsection 19(3), <Ins>section 19.1, subsection 19.3(1)</Ins>, section 21 or subsection 22.11(1).</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>12</Label><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Subsection 17(1) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Section><MarginalNote>Authority to enter</MarginalNote><Label>17</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text><Ins>Subject to subsection 17.1(1),</Ins> an inspector may, for <Ins>any</Ins> purpose <Ins>related to</Ins> verifying compliance or <Ins>preventing non-compliance</Ins> with this Act, enter <Ins>any</Ins> place, including a vehicle, <Ins>if they have</Ins> reasonable grounds to believe that</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>an activity regulated by this Act is conducted in the place; or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text><Ins>anything</Ins> to which this Act applies is located in or on the place.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Powers</MarginalNote><Label><Ins>(1.1)</Ins></Label><Text><Ins>In the place entered, the inspector may, for the purposes referred to in subsection (1),</Ins></Text><Paragraph><Label><Ins>(a)</Ins></Label><Text>examine the place;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label><Ins>(b)</Ins></Label><Text><Ins>examine</Ins> or <Ins>test</Ins> anything found in or on the place;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(c)</Label><Text>seize and detain anything in or on the place;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(d)</Label><Text>use, or cause to be used, any means of communication in the place;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(e)</Label><Text>use, or cause to be used, any computer <Ins>or telecommunication</Ins> system in the place to examine data contained in or available to <Ins>the system</Ins>;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph change="ins"><Label>(f)</Label><Text>reproduce, or cause to be reproduced, any data that is contained in or available to a system referred to in paragraph (e);</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(g)</Label><Text>prepare, or cause to be prepared, a document based on the data;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(h)</Label><Text>use, or cause to be used, any copying equipment in the place;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph change="ins"><Label>(i)</Label><Text>take photographs or make recordings, sketches or any other representation of anything located in or on the place;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph change="ins"><Label>(j)</Label><Text>order any person in the place to establish their identity to the inspector’s satisfaction;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label><Ins>(k)</Ins></Label><Text><Ins>order</Ins> any person to put anything in or on the place into operation or to cease operating it; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label><Ins>(l)</Ins></Label><Text>prohibit or limit access to all or part of the place.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Subsection 17(3) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Subsection><MarginalNote>Duty to assist</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>The owner or person in charge of the place and every person <Ins>employed</Ins> in the place <Ins>must</Ins> give all assistance that is reasonably required to enable the inspector to verify compliance <Ins>or prevent non-compliance</Ins> with this Act and <Ins>must</Ins> provide <Ins>anything</Ins> that <Ins>is</Ins> reasonably required for <Ins>those purposes</Ins>.</Text></Subsection><Subsection change="ins"><MarginalNote>Access by means of telecommunication</MarginalNote><Label>(4)</Label><Text>For the purposes of subsection (1), an inspector is considered to have entered a place if they have accessed it remotely by a means of telecommunication.</Text></Subsection><Subsection change="ins"><MarginalNote>Limitation — access</MarginalNote><Label>(5)</Label><Text>An inspector who enters a place that is not accessible to the public must do so at a reasonable time, with the knowledge of the owner or person in charge of the place and only for the period necessary for the purposes referred to in subsection (1).</Text></Subsection><Subsection change="ins"><MarginalNote>Provision of anything</MarginalNote><Label>(6)</Label><Text>An inspector may, for the purposes referred to in subsection (1), order a person to provide them with anything on the date, at the time and place and in the manner specified by the inspector.</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Subsection></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>13</Label><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Paragraph 17.1(2)(b) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>entry to the dwelling-house is necessary <Ins>for a purpose referred to in that subsection</Ins>; and</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Section 17.1 of the Act is amended by adding the following after subsection (2):</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Subsection change="ins"><MarginalNote>Warrant — means of telecommunication</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>An application for a warrant under subsection (2) may be submitted, and the warrant may be issued, by a means of telecommunication, and section 487.1 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Criminal Code</XRefExternal> applies for those purposes with any necessary modifications.</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Subsection></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>14</Label><Text>Section 18 of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Section><MarginalNote>Examination of vehicle</MarginalNote><Label>18</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>A member of the Royal Canadian Mounted Police or of any provincial or municipal police force may, at the request and in the company of an inspector, stop and detain any vehicle so that the inspector may examine it for <Ins>any purpose related to</Ins> verifying compliance <Ins>or preventing non-compliance</Ins> with this Act.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Vehicle to be moved</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text><Ins>An</Ins> inspector may <Ins>order</Ins> the <Ins>owner or person having possession, care or control</Ins> of <Ins>a</Ins> vehicle to <Ins>stop it or</Ins> proceed with it to an appropriate place if doing so is necessary to <Ins>perform</Ins> the examination.</Text></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>15</Label><Text>Subsection 19(3) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Subsection><MarginalNote>Marking of devices — requirements not met</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text><Ins>If</Ins> an inspector determines that a device referred to in paragraph (1)(a) does not meet the requirements of this Act and the regulations, the inspector <Ins>must</Ins> attach to the device <Ins>any</Ins> tags and seals <Ins>that</Ins> may be prescribed to prevent the use of that device.</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>16</Label><Text>Section 20 of the Act and the heading before it are replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Heading level="2"><TitleText><Ins>Remedial and Preventive Measures</Ins></TitleText></Heading><Section change="ins"><MarginalNote>Measures</MarginalNote><Label>19.1</Label><Text>If an inspector has reasonable grounds to believe that a person has contravened or is likely to contravene this Act, the inspector may order the person to take any measures that the inspector considers necessary to remedy or prevent the contravention.</Text></Section><Section change="ins"><MarginalNote>Directions — plans, procedures or processes</MarginalNote><Label>19.2</Label><Subsection change="ins"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The Minister may issue written directions respecting the development or implementation, by a person who conducts any activity regulated under this Act, of plans, procedures or processes aimed at remedying or preventing a contravention of this Act.</Text></Subsection><Subsection change="ins"><MarginalNote>Accessibility</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The directions must be made accessible to the public.</Text></Subsection><Subsection change="ins"><MarginalNote><XRefExternal reference-type="act">Statutory Instruments Act</XRefExternal></MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>The <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Statutory Instruments Act</XRefExternal> does not apply to a direction issued under subsection (1).</Text></Subsection></Section><Section change="ins"><MarginalNote>Development and implementation</MarginalNote><Label>19.3</Label><Subsection change="ins"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The Minister or an inspector may order a person who conducts any activity regulated under this Act to develop or implement a plan, procedure or process in accordance with the directions issued under subsection 19.2(1).</Text></Subsection><Subsection change="ins"><MarginalNote>Inconsistency or conflict</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>In the event of an inconsistency or conflict between anything that is ordered to be done by the Minister and anything that is ordered to be done by an inspector, what the Minister orders to be done prevails to the extent of the inconsistency or conflict.</Text></Subsection></Section><Heading level="1"><TitleText>Fees and Charges</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Payment of fees and charges</MarginalNote><Label>20</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Subject to the regulations, the fees and charges <Ins>that are</Ins> payable in respect of an examination or service performed by an inspector under this Act are payable after the examination or service is performed.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Debt to His Majesty</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Fees and charges <Ins>that are</Ins> payable under this Act may be recovered as a debt due to <Ins>His Majesty</Ins>.</Text></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>17</Label><Text>Section 21 of the Act is amended by adding the following after subsection (2):</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Subsection change="ins"><MarginalNote>Calculation of amount</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>For greater certainty, if the device is found to be inaccurate, the inspector may calculate the amount that would have been payable by the other person had the device not been inaccurate.</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>18</Label><Text>Subsection 26(2) of the Act is repealed.</Text></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>19</Label><Text>Section 28 of the Act is repealed.</Text></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>20</Label><Text>Subsection 31(3) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Subsection><MarginalNote>Interference with seized thing</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>Every person who, without an inspector’s permission, removes, alters or interferes in any way with anything seized and detained by an inspector under paragraph 17(<Ins>1.1</Ins>)(c) is guilty of an offence.</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>21</Label><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The portion of section 32 of the French version of the Act before paragraph (a) is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no" xml:lang="fr"><Section><MarginalNote>Défaut d’immobiliser son véhicule</MarginalNote><Label>32</Label><Text>Commet une infraction tout conducteur d’un véhicule qui <Ins>omet</Ins> volontairement :</Text></Section></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Paragraphs 32(a) and (b) of the Act are replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>to bring the vehicle to a stop <Ins>when required to do so</Ins> under subsection 18(1); or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text><Ins>to bring</Ins> the vehicle <Ins>to a stop or</Ins> to proceed with <Ins>it</Ins> to an appropriate place <Ins>when ordered to do so</Ins> by an inspector under subsection 18(2).</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>22</Label><Text>The Act is amended by adding the following after section 34:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Section change="ins"><MarginalNote>Failure to comply</MarginalNote><Label>34.1</Label><Text>Every person is guilty of an offence who fails to do anything that they were ordered to do by the Minister or an inspector, as the case may be, under paragraph 17(1.1)(j) or (k), subsection 17(6), section 19.1 or subsection 19.3(1), or who enters a place or part of a place after an inspector has prohibited or limited access to it under paragraph 17(1.1)(l).</Text></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>23</Label><Text>Section 36 of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Section><MarginalNote>Presumption</MarginalNote><Label>36</Label><Text><Ins>If</Ins> a trader <Ins>uses or</Ins> has in <Ins>their</Ins> possession any device that is not marked as prescribed to show that it is not for use in trade, the trader <Ins>is</Ins>, in the absence of evidence to the contrary, deemed <Ins>to use</Ins> that device <Ins>in trade or</Ins> to have <Ins>it</Ins> in <Ins>their</Ins> possession for use in trade.</Text></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>24</Label><Text>Subsection 37(1) of the French version of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no" xml:lang="fr"><Section><MarginalNote>Infraction commise par un employé ou un mandataire</MarginalNote><Label>37</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Dans les poursuites pour infraction à la présente loi, il suffit, pour prouver l’infraction, d’établir qu’elle a été commise par un employé ou un mandataire de l’accusé, que cet employé ou ce mandataire ait été ou non identifié ou poursuivi. L’accusé peut se disculper en prouvant que la perpétration a eu lieu à son insu ou sans son consentement et qu’il avait pris <Ins>toutes</Ins> les <Ins>précautions voulues</Ins> pour l’empêcher.</Text></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>25</Label><Text>Subsection 39(1) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Section><MarginalNote>Examination and samples of seized things</MarginalNote><Label>39</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>If an inspector seizes and detains anything under paragraph 17(<Ins>1.1</Ins>)(c), they <Ins>must</Ins>, at the request of the person from whom the thing is seized, allow that person or any person authorized by that person to examine the seized thing and, if possible, provide that person with a sample of it.</Text></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>26</Label><Text>Subsection 41(1) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Section><MarginalNote>Forfeiture on consent</MarginalNote><Label>41</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>If the owner or the person in lawful possession of a thing at the time it is seized under paragraph 17(<Ins>1.1</Ins>)(c) consents in writing to its forfeiture, it is forfeited to <Ins>His</Ins> Majesty.</Text></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>27</Label><Text>The Act is amended by adding the following after section 41:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Heading change="ins" level="1"><TitleText>Review of Act</TitleText></Heading><Section change="ins"><MarginalNote>Review</MarginalNote><Label>42</Label><Subsection change="ins"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Before the 10th anniversary of the day on which this section comes into force and before the end of each subsequent period of 10 years, the Minister must cause to be completed a review of this Act and its operation.</Text></Subsection><Subsection change="ins"><MarginalNote>Report</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The Minister must cause a report of the review to be laid before each House of Parliament on any of the first 15 days on which that House is sitting after the report has been completed.</Text></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Section><Heading level="1"><MarginalNote><HistoricalNote>R.S., c. E-4</HistoricalNote></MarginalNote><TitleText><XRefExternal reference-type="act">Electricity and Gas Inspection Act</XRefExternal></TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><Label>28</Label><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The definitions <DefinedTermEn>accredited meter verifier</DefinedTermEn> and <DefinedTermEn>director</DefinedTermEn> in subsection 2(1) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Electricity and Gas Inspection Act</XRefExternal> are repealed.</Text></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The definitions <DefinedTermEn>apparatus</DefinedTermEn>, <DefinedTermEn>inspector</DefinedTermEn> and <DefinedTermEn>meter</DefinedTermEn> in subsection 2(1) of the Act are replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><SectionPiece><Definition><Text><DefinedTermEn>apparatus</DefinedTermEn> includes any machine, instrument, device or <Ins>software</Ins>; (<DefinedTermFr>appareil</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Definition><Definition><Text><DefinedTermEn>inspector</DefinedTermEn> means any officer <Ins>who is</Ins> appointed under <Ins>subsection 26(1) and</Ins> designated <Ins>as</Ins> an <Ins>inspector</Ins> under <Ins>section 7</Ins> of the <Ins><XRefExternal reference-type="act">Department of Industry Act</XRefExternal></Ins> for the purpose of <Ins>verifying compliance or preventing non-compliance with</Ins> this Act; (<DefinedTermFr>inspecteur</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Definition><Definition><Text><DefinedTermEn>meter</DefinedTermEn> means an electricity or gas meter and includes any apparatus used for the purpose of making measurements of, or obtaining the basis of a charge for, electricity or gas supplied to a purchaser, <Ins>or any part of such an apparatus</Ins>; (<DefinedTermFr>compteur</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Definition></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(3)</Label><Text>Subsection 2(1) of the Act is amended by adding the following in alphabetical order:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><SectionPiece><Definition change="ins"><Text><DefinedTermEn>authorized service provider</DefinedTermEn> means any person to whom an authorization is granted under subsection 10(1); (<DefinedTermFr>fournisseur de services autorisé</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Definition><Definition change="ins"><Text><DefinedTermEn>designated inspector</DefinedTermEn> means any person who is designated under subsection 26(3); (<DefinedTermFr>inspecteur désigné</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Definition><Definition change="ins"><Text><DefinedTermEn>president</DefinedTermEn> means the president appointed under subsection 26(1); (<DefinedTermFr>président</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Definition><Definition change="ins"><Text><DefinedTermEn>vehicle</DefinedTermEn> means a vessel, aircraft, train, motor vehicle, trailer or other means of transportation and includes a cargo container; (<DefinedTermFr>véhicule</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Definition></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>29</Label><Text>Section 4 of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Section><MarginalNote>Standard apparatus</MarginalNote><Label>4</Label><Text><Ins>The</Ins> standard apparatus necessary to establish the units of measurement for sales referred to in section 3 <Ins>are</Ins> the <Ins>responsibility</Ins> of the Minister and form part of the system of reference standards referred to in the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Weights and Measures Act</XRefExternal>.</Text></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>30</Label><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The portion of section 5 of the Act before paragraph (a) is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Section><MarginalNote>Calibration of measuring apparatus</MarginalNote><Label>5</Label><Text>An <Ins>authorized service provider may use an</Ins> apparatus that is <Ins>not</Ins> a <DefinitionRef><Ins>local</Ins> standard</DefinitionRef>, <Ins>as defined in section 2</Ins> of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Weights and Measures Act</XRefExternal>, for <Ins>measuring</Ins> electricity or gas or <Ins>for verifying</Ins> meters <Ins>only if, in accordance with the regulations,</Ins></Text></Section></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Paragraph 5(a) of the French version of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no" xml:lang="fr"><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>a)</Label><Text>l’appareil <Ins>est</Ins> calibré;</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(3)</Label><Text>Section 5 of the Act is amended by replacing paragraph (b) and the portion after paragraph (b) with the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text><Ins>the</Ins> calibration is certified.</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>31</Label><Text>The heading before section 6 of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Heading level="1"><TitleText><Ins>Register of Contractors</Ins></TitleText></Heading></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>32</Label><Text>Subsection 6(1) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Section><MarginalNote>Register</MarginalNote><Label>6</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The president <Ins>must</Ins> maintain, in accordance with the regulations, a register of contractors <Ins>who hold a certificate of registration</Ins>.</Text></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>33</Label><Text>The Act is amended by adding the following after section 6:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Section change="ins"><MarginalNote>Suspension or revocation</MarginalNote><Label>6.1</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Subject to subsection (3), the president may, by written notice, suspend or revoke any certificate issued under subsection 6(2).</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Effect of suspension or revocation</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The president must specify in the notice the effect of the suspension or revocation and, in the case of a suspension, may specify any conditions that must be met for the suspension to be lifted.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Right to make representations</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>The president must not suspend or revoke the certificate unless</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>a notice of intention to suspend or revoke it has been given in writing;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>the contractor who objects to the suspension or revocation has been given a reasonable opportunity to make representations with respect to their objections; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(c)</Label><Text>the representations, if any, have been taken into account in deciding whether to suspend or revoke the certificate.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection></Section><Section change="ins"><MarginalNote>Exemption of contractors</MarginalNote><Label>6.2</Label><Subsection change="ins"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The president may exempt, under any conditions and for the period that the president specifies, any contractor or class of contractors from the application of any provision of this Act, except subsection 6(2), or the regulations.</Text></Subsection><Subsection change="ins"><MarginalNote>Register of exempt contractors</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text><Ins>The president may maintain a register of contractors who are exempt from the application of any provision of this Act or the regulations.</Ins></Text></Subsection><Subsection change="ins"><MarginalNote>Amendment or cancellation</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>Subject to subsection (5), the president may, by written notice, amend or cancel the exemption.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Effect of cancellation</MarginalNote><Label>(4)</Label><Text>The president must specify in the notice the effect of the cancellation.</Text></Subsection><Subsection change="ins"><MarginalNote>Right to make representations</MarginalNote><Label>(5)</Label><Text>The president must not amend or cancel the exemption unless</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>a notice of intention to amend or cancel it has been given in writing;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>the contractor who objects to the amendment or cancellation has been given a reasonable opportunity to make representations with respect to their objections; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(c)</Label><Text>the representations, if any, have been taken into account in deciding whether to amend or cancel the exemption.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>34</Label><Text>Sections 8 to 10 of the Act are replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Section><MarginalNote>Service pressure reports</MarginalNote><Label>8</Label><Text><Ins>If required by</Ins> the regulations, a contractor <Ins>must</Ins> report to the <Ins>president</Ins>, at prescribed intervals, <Ins>the</Ins> particulars of prescribed service pressures in respect of any gas supplied by the contractor.</Text></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Approval, verification and sealing</MarginalNote><Label>9</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Subject to subsections (2) and (3), <Ins>if</Ins> a contractor or purchaser intends to use or cause to be used a meter <Ins>to obtain</Ins> the basis of a charge for the <Ins>supply</Ins> of electricity or gas by or to <Ins>them</Ins>, the meter <Ins>must</Ins> not be put into service <Ins>unless</Ins></Text><Paragraph change="ins"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>the meter or the meter’s class, type or design has been approved by the president in the prescribed manner; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label><Ins>(b)</Ins></Label><Text><Ins>the meter</Ins> has been verified and sealed in accordance with this Act.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection change="ins"><MarginalNote>Conditions</MarginalNote><Label>(1.1)</Label><Text>The approval is subject to any conditions that the president specifies.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Permission to put into service temporarily</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The <Ins>president</Ins> may <Ins>permit</Ins> any meter or <Ins>the meters</Ins> of any class, type or design <Ins>to be temporarily put</Ins> into service, for <Ins>any</Ins> period and under <Ins>any</Ins> conditions <Ins>that the president specifies</Ins>, without <Ins>approval</Ins>, verification or sealing.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Permission to put into service indefinitely</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>The <Ins>president</Ins> may <Ins>permit</Ins> any meter or <Ins>the meters</Ins> of any class, type or design <Ins>to be indefinitely put</Ins> into service, <Ins>under any conditions that the president specifies</Ins>, without approval, verification or sealing.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Authorized service providers</MarginalNote><Label>10</Label><Subsection><Label><Ins>(1)</Ins></Label><Text>Subject to <Ins>subsection (2)</Ins>, the <Ins>president</Ins> may <Ins>authorize</Ins> any person, <Ins>or an</Ins> employee <Ins>or an</Ins> agent or mandatary <Ins>of the person, to perform any</Ins> functions <Ins>related to</Ins> the verification, sealing, reverification and resealing of any meter or any class, type or design of meter. <Ins>If an authorization is given</Ins>, the <Ins>president must issue</Ins> a certificate of <Ins>authorization to</Ins> the <Ins>person</Ins>.</Text></Subsection><Subsection change="ins"><MarginalNote>Directions</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The president may issue written directions respecting</Text><Paragraph change="ins"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>the authorization referred to in subsection (1);</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph change="ins"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>the classes of authorized service providers to which the directions apply; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph change="ins"><Label>(c)</Label><Text>the functions referred to in subsection (1) that may be performed by authorized service providers or classes of authorized service providers.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection change="ins"><MarginalNote>Accessibility</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>The directions must be made accessible to the public.</Text></Subsection><Subsection change="ins"><MarginalNote><XRefExternal reference-type="act">Statutory Instruments Act</XRefExternal></MarginalNote><Label>(4)</Label><Text>The <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Statutory Instruments Act</XRefExternal> does not apply to a direction issued under subsection (2).</Text></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>35</Label><Text>Sections 11 to 14 of the Act are replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Section><MarginalNote>Reverification</MarginalNote><Label>12</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text><Ins>Subject to subsection (3), every</Ins> meter <Ins>must</Ins> be <Ins>reverified</Ins></Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text><Ins>in</Ins> the <Ins>case</Ins> of a meter used <Ins>to obtain</Ins> the basis of a charge for the <Ins>supply</Ins> of electricity, <Ins>before the eighth anniversary of the day on which the meter was verified or last reverified</Ins>;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text><Ins>in</Ins> the <Ins>case</Ins> of a meter used <Ins>to obtain</Ins> the basis of a charge for the <Ins>supply</Ins> of gas, <Ins>before the seventh anniversary of the day on which the meter was verified or last reverified</Ins>; or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(c)</Label><Text>in any case or class of cases <Ins>that the president determines</Ins>, any other period <Ins>that</Ins> the <Ins>president specifies</Ins>.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Seal and mark</MarginalNote><Label><Ins>(1.1)</Ins></Label><Text><Ins>Subject to subsection (3), after each</Ins> reverification, the meter <Ins>must</Ins> be <Ins>resealed</Ins> or <Ins>marked again</Ins>, or <Ins>have its</Ins> seal or mark <Ins>cancelled</Ins>, as the case may <Ins>be, in accordance</Ins> with this Act.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Shorter period</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The period specified under paragraph (1)(c) for any reverification <Ins>must not</Ins> be shorter than the period <Ins>referred to</Ins> in paragraph (1)(a) or (b) <Ins>except</Ins> with the approval of the Minister, in which <Ins>case</Ins> the <Ins>president must</Ins> cause <Ins>a</Ins> prior notice to be given within the prescribed time and in the prescribed manner.</Text></Subsection><Subsection change="ins"><MarginalNote>Temporary permission without reverification or resealing</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>The president may <Ins>permit</Ins> any meter or the meters of any class, type or design to remain in service, for <Ins>any</Ins> period and under <Ins>any</Ins> conditions that the president specifies, without reverification or resealing.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section change="ins"><MarginalNote>Verification and reverification by sampling</MarginalNote><Label>12.1</Label><Subsection change="ins"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The verification and reverification of a meter may be conducted using any means, including by sampling meters of the same class, type or design.</Text></Subsection><Subsection change="ins"><MarginalNote>Sampling results</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>If the verification or reverification of a meter is conducted by means of sampling, the results of the verification or reverification may be applied, in accordance with the directions issued under subsection 12.2(1), to any meter of the same class, type or design for the purpose of issuing a certificate under section 14, sealing under paragraph 9(1)(b) or resealing under subsection 12(1.1).</Text></Subsection></Section><Section change="ins"><MarginalNote>Directions</MarginalNote><Label>12.2</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The Minister may issue written directions respecting the verification or reverification of meters, including verification or reverification conducted by means of sampling.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Application</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The Minister may specify the circumstances in which, the persons to whom and the classes, types or designs of meters to which the directions apply.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Accessibility</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>The directions must be made accessible to the public.</Text></Subsection><Subsection change="ins"><MarginalNote><XRefExternal reference-type="act">Statutory Instruments Act</XRefExternal></MarginalNote><Label>(4)</Label><Text>The <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Statutory Instruments Act</XRefExternal> does not apply to a direction issued under subsection (1).</Text></Subsection></Section><Section change="ins"><MarginalNote>Suspension or revocation</MarginalNote><Label>12.3</Label><Subsection change="ins"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Subject to subsection (3), the president may, by written notice, suspend or revoke</Text><Paragraph change="ins"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>an approval granted under paragraph 9(1)(a);</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph change="ins"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>a permission granted under subsection 9(2) or (3);</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph change="ins"><Label>(c)</Label><Text>an authorization granted under subsection 10(1); or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph change="ins"><Label>(d)</Label><Text>a permission granted under subsection 12(3).</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection change="ins"><MarginalNote>Effect of suspension or revocation</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The president must specify in the notice the effect of the suspension or revocation and, in the case of a suspension, may specify any conditions that must be met for the suspension to be lifted.</Text></Subsection><Subsection change="ins"><MarginalNote>Right to make representations</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>An approval, permission or authorization must not be suspended or revoked unless</Text><Paragraph change="ins"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>a notice of intention to suspend or revoke it has been given in writing;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph change="ins"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>any interested person who objects to the suspension or revocation has been given a reasonable opportunity to make representations with respect to their objections; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph change="ins"><Label>(c)</Label><Text>the representations, if any, have been taken into account in deciding whether to suspend or revoke the approval, permission or authorization.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Exercise of powers by inspector</MarginalNote><Label>13</Label><Text>An inspector may, on the general or special instructions of the <Ins>president</Ins>, deal with a meter in any manner provided <Ins>for under</Ins> or referred to in section 12 or specified <Ins>in, provided for</Ins> or authorized <Ins>in directions issued under section 12.2 or under</Ins> paragraph 28(1)(c), <Ins>even if</Ins> the meter may be or has been dealt with <Ins>in that manner</Ins> by an <Ins>authorized service provider</Ins>.</Text></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Certificates</MarginalNote><Label>14</Label><Text><Ins>After the</Ins> verification or reverification of a meter, an inspector, or an <Ins>authorized service provider</Ins> who is not the owner of the meter, <Ins>must</Ins> issue to the owner, in the prescribed manner, a certificate containing <Ins>the</Ins> prescribed <Ins>information</Ins> respecting the verification or reverification.</Text></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>36</Label><Text>Subsection 15(1) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Section><MarginalNote>Authorized persons — verification and sealing</MarginalNote><Label>15</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text><Ins>Only</Ins> an inspector or an <Ins>authorized service provider may verify, seal, reverify</Ins> or <Ins>reseal a</Ins> meter.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Breaking seal</MarginalNote><Label>(<Ins>1.1</Ins>)</Label><Text><Ins>Unless</Ins> otherwise <Ins>prescribed, only</Ins> an inspector, an <Ins>authorized service provider</Ins> or the owner <Ins>may</Ins> break the seal of a verified meter.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Breaking seal — dispute</MarginalNote><Label>(<Ins>1.2</Ins>)</Label><Text><Ins>If</Ins> the correctness of <Ins>a</Ins> verified meter is in dispute, <Ins>only</Ins> an inspector <Ins>may</Ins> break <Ins>its</Ins> seal.</Text></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>37</Label><Text>Subsection 16(1) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Section><MarginalNote>Owner’s liability</MarginalNote><Label>16</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The owner of each verified meter that is in use <Ins>must</Ins> keep it in good repair and is responsible for causing it to be dealt with in accordance with the requirements of this Act and the regulations, and, subject to those requirements, the owner is liable to pay any fees for dealing with the meter in accordance with those requirements.</Text></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>38</Label><Text>Sections 17 and 18 of the Act are replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Section><MarginalNote>Records of authorized service providers</MarginalNote><Label>17</Label><Text>Every <Ins>authorized service provider must</Ins> keep records containing <Ins>the prescribed</Ins> information related to the administration of this Act, in <Ins>the</Ins> form, at <Ins>the</Ins> place and for <Ins>the</Ins> period <Ins>that is</Ins> prescribed.</Text></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Examination of records</MarginalNote><Label>18</Label><Text><Ins>The</Ins> records kept <Ins>in accordance with</Ins> sections 16 and 17 <Ins>may</Ins> be <Ins>examined</Ins> by an inspector and the inspector may make <Ins>any</Ins> copies or extracts as <Ins>they</Ins> may require.</Text></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>39</Label><Text>Sections 20 and 21 of the Act are replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Section><MarginalNote>Entry by authorized service provider</MarginalNote><Label>20</Label><Text><Ins>An authorized service provider</Ins> may <Ins>enter a place</Ins> at all reasonable times <Ins>if they believe</Ins> on reasonable grounds <Ins>that</Ins> entry <Ins>is</Ins> required <Ins>to perform</Ins> any functions <Ins>related</Ins> to <Ins>verifying, sealing, reverifying</Ins> or <Ins>resealing</Ins> a meter <Ins>that is</Ins> in or on <Ins>the place</Ins>.</Text></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Duty to assist</MarginalNote><Label>21</Label><Text>The owner or person in charge of, and every person employed in, <Ins>a place</Ins> entered by an <Ins>authorized service provider under</Ins> section 20 or an inspector <Ins>under</Ins> subsection <Ins>26.1(1) must</Ins> give the inspector or <Ins>authorized service provider</Ins> all assistance <Ins>that is reasonably required</Ins> to enable the inspector or <Ins>authorized service provider</Ins> to <Ins>perform their respective</Ins> functions and <Ins>must provide anything that is</Ins> reasonably <Ins>required for that purpose</Ins>.</Text></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>40</Label><Text>Subsections 23(3) and (4) of the Act are replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Subsection change="ins"><MarginalNote>Calculation of amount</MarginalNote><Label>(2.1)</Label><Text>For greater certainty, if an inspector proceeds in the matter of a request under subsection (1), the inspector may calculate the amount payable for the supply of electricity or gas.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Reference to president for reconsideration</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text><Ins>If</Ins> a person who is provided with a certificate of findings by an inspector <Ins>under</Ins> subsection (2) gives notice to the inspector within <Ins>the</Ins> prescribed time that <Ins>the person</Ins> is dissatisfied with the findings, the inspector <Ins>must</Ins> refer the matter to the <Ins>president</Ins> for reconsideration in <Ins>the</Ins> prescribed manner.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>President’s decision final</MarginalNote><Label>(4)</Label><Text>The <Ins>president’s</Ins> decision on a matter referred to <Ins>them under</Ins> subsection (3) is final and conclusive.</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>41</Label><Text>Subsection 24(5) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Subsection><MarginalNote>Liability</MarginalNote><Label>(5)</Label><Text>A contractor or purchaser, as the case may be, is liable for the amount of the charge for <Ins>the supply of</Ins> electricity or gas determined on the basis of the full error and the time for which the error is, as provided in subsection (1), (2) or (3) or <Ins>in accordance with</Ins> subsection (4), deemed or determined to have existed.</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>42</Label><Text>The heading before section 25 and sections 25 to 27 of the Act are replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Heading level="1"><TitleText><Ins>Appointment and Designation</Ins></TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Staff</MarginalNote><Label>26</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>A <Ins>president</Ins> and <Ins>any</Ins> other officers and employees <Ins>that</Ins> are necessary for the administration of this Act <Ins>are to</Ins> be appointed in accordance with the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Public Service Employment Act</XRefExternal>.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>President’s functions</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The <Ins>president</Ins> has, under the Minister, the direction and general supervision of the administration and enforcement of this Act.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Designated inspectors</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text><Ins>Subject to subsection</Ins> (5), the Minister may <Ins>designate</Ins> any person to <Ins>perform</Ins> any functions of an inspector <Ins>that</Ins> the <Ins>Minister specifies</Ins>, except <Ins>the</Ins> functions <Ins>set out in subsection 29.12(1)</Ins>.</Text></Subsection><Subsection change="ins"><MarginalNote>Certificate of designation</MarginalNote><Label>(3.1)</Label><Text>The Minister must provide each inspector and designated inspector with a certificate of designation.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Privileges and immunities — designated inspectors</MarginalNote><Label>(4)</Label><Text>A designated <Ins>inspector</Ins> has, in relation to the <Ins>performance</Ins> of <Ins>the</Ins> functions <Ins>specified by the Minister under subsection (3)</Ins>, the privileges and immunities of <Ins>an</Ins> inspector.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Restrictions</MarginalNote><Label>(5)</Label><Text><Ins>A</Ins> person who is an <Ins>authorized service provider</Ins> or a seller of electricity, gas or meters or who is employed by or is the agent or mandatary of an <Ins>authorized service provider</Ins> or a seller of electricity, gas or meters <Ins>must not</Ins> be appointed or designated under this section or act as a person appointed or designated <Ins>under this section</Ins>.</Text></Subsection></Section><Heading level="1"><TitleText><Ins>Inspector Functions</Ins></TitleText></Heading><Section change="ins"><MarginalNote>Authority to enter</MarginalNote><Label>26.1</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Subject to subsection 26.2(1), an inspector may, for any purpose related to verifying compliance or preventing non-compliance with this Act, enter any place, including a vehicle, if they have reasonable grounds to believe that</Text><Paragraph change="ins"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>an activity <Ins>that is</Ins> regulated <Ins>by</Ins> this Act <Ins>is conducted in the place; or</Ins></Text></Paragraph><Paragraph change="ins"><Label>(b)</Label><Text><Ins>anything</Ins> to which this Act applies is located in or on <Ins>the</Ins> place.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection change="ins"><MarginalNote>Powers</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>In the place entered, the inspector may, for the purposes referred to in subsection (1),</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>examine the place;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>examine <Ins>or test</Ins> anything found in or on the place;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(c)</Label><Text>seize and detain anything that is located in or on the place, except a meter that is in service;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(d)</Label><Text>use, or cause to be used, any means of communication in the place;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(e)</Label><Text>use, or cause to be used, any computer or telecommunication system in the place to examine data contained in or available to the system;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(f)</Label><Text>reproduce, or cause to be reproduced, any data that is contained in or available to a system referred to in paragraph (e);</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(g)</Label><Text>prepare, or cause to be prepared, a document based on the data;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(h)</Label><Text>use, or cause to be used, any copying equipment in the place;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(i)</Label><Text>take photographs or make recordings, sketches or any other representation of anything located in or on the place;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(j)</Label><Text>order any person in the place to establish their identity to the inspector’s satisfaction;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(k)</Label><Text>order any person to put anything in or on the place into operation or to cease operating it; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(l)</Label><Text>prohibit or limit access to all or part of the place.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection change="ins"><MarginalNote>Certificate to be produced</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>On entering the place, the inspector must, on request, produce their certificate of designation to the person in charge of that place.</Text></Subsection><Subsection change="ins"><MarginalNote>Access by means of telecommunication</MarginalNote><Label>(4)</Label><Text>For the purposes of subsection (1), an inspector is considered to have entered a place if they have accessed it remotely by a means of telecommunication.</Text></Subsection><Subsection change="ins"><MarginalNote>Limitation — access</MarginalNote><Label>(5)</Label><Text>An inspector who enters a place that is not accessible to the public must do so at a reasonable time, with the knowledge of the owner or person in charge of the place and only for the period necessary for the purposes referred to in subsection (1).</Text></Subsection><Subsection change="ins"><MarginalNote>Provision of anything</MarginalNote><Label>(6)</Label><Text>An inspector may, for the purposes referred to in subsection (1), order a person to provide anything on the date, at the time and place and in the manner specified by the inspector.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Warrant required to enter dwelling-house</MarginalNote><Label><Ins>26.2</Ins></Label><Subsection><Label><Ins>(1)</Ins></Label><Text><Ins>If the place</Ins> is a dwelling-house, an inspector <Ins>must</Ins> not enter that dwelling-house without the consent of the occupant except under the authority of a warrant issued under subsection (<Ins>2</Ins>).</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Authority to issue warrant</MarginalNote><Label><Ins>(2)</Ins></Label><Text>On <Language xml:lang="la">ex parte</Language> application, a justice of the peace may issue a warrant authorizing an inspector <Ins>who is named in it</Ins> to enter a dwelling-house, subject to any conditions specified in the warrant, <Ins>if</Ins> the justice is satisfied by information on oath that</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>entry to the dwelling-house is necessary for the purpose of performing <Ins>the inspector’s functions</Ins>; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>entry to the dwelling-house has been refused or there are reasonable grounds for believing that entry will be refused.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection change="ins"><MarginalNote>Warrant — means of telecommunication</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>An application for a warrant under subsection (2) may be submitted, and the warrant may be issued, by a means of telecommunication, and section 487.1 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Criminal Code</XRefExternal> applies for those purposes with any necessary modifications.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Use of force</MarginalNote><Label><Ins>26.3</Ins></Label><Text>In executing a warrant issued under subsection <Ins>26.2(2)</Ins>, the inspector named <Ins>in the warrant must</Ins> not use force unless the inspector is accompanied by a peace officer and the use of force has been specifically authorized in the warrant.</Text></Section><Section change="ins"><MarginalNote>Examination of vehicle</MarginalNote><Label>26.4</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>A member of the Royal Canadian Mounted Police or of any provincial or municipal police force may, at the request and in the company of an inspector, stop and detain any vehicle so that the inspector may examine it for any purpose related to verifying compliance or preventing non-compliance with this Act.</Text></Subsection><Subsection change="ins"><MarginalNote>Vehicle to be moved</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>An inspector may order the owner or person having possession, care or control of a vehicle to stop it or proceed with it to an appropriate place if doing so is necessary to perform the examination.</Text></Subsection></Section><Heading level="1"><TitleText><Ins>Remedial and Preventive Measures</Ins></TitleText></Heading><Section change="ins"><MarginalNote>Measures</MarginalNote><Label>26.5</Label><Text>If an inspector has reasonable grounds to believe that a person has contravened or is likely to contravene this Act, the inspector may order the person to take any measures that the inspector considers necessary to remedy or prevent the contravention.</Text></Section><Section change="ins"><MarginalNote>Directions — plans, procedures or processes</MarginalNote><Label>26.6</Label><Subsection change="ins"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The Minister may issue written directions respecting the development or implementation, by a person who conducts any activity regulated under this Act, of plans, procedures or processes aimed at remedying or preventing a contravention of this Act.</Text></Subsection><Subsection change="ins"><MarginalNote>Accessibility</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The directions must be made accessible to the public.</Text></Subsection><Subsection change="ins"><MarginalNote><XRefExternal reference-type="act">Statutory Instruments Act</XRefExternal></MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>The <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Statutory Instruments Act</XRefExternal> does not apply to a direction issued under subsection (1).</Text></Subsection></Section><Section change="ins"><MarginalNote>Development and implementation</MarginalNote><Label>26.7</Label><Subsection change="ins"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The Minister or an inspector may order a person who conducts any activity regulated under this Act to develop or implement a plan, procedure or process in accordance with the directions issued under subsection 26.6(1).</Text></Subsection><Subsection change="ins"><MarginalNote>Inconsistency or conflict</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>In the event of an inconsistency or conflict between anything that is ordered to be done by the Minister and anything that is ordered to be done by an inspector, what the Minister orders to be done prevails to the extent of the inconsistency or conflict.</Text></Subsection></Section><Heading level="1"><TitleText><Ins>Fees and Charges</Ins></TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Payment of fees and charges</MarginalNote><Label>27</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text><Ins>Subject to the regulations, the fees and charges that are payable</Ins> in respect of the execution of the functions of inspectors <Ins>are payable after the function has been executed.</Ins></Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Debt to His Majesty</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Fees and charges that are payable <Ins>under</Ins> this Act <Ins>may</Ins> be <Ins>recovered</Ins> as a debt due to <Ins>His Majesty</Ins>.</Text></Subsection></Section><Heading level="1"><TitleText><Ins>Regulations</Ins></TitleText></Heading></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>43</Label><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Paragraph 28(1)(d) of the Act is repealed.</Text></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Paragraphs 28(1)(e) to (g) of the Act are replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(e)</Label><Text><Ins>respecting fees or charges to be paid in relation to the administration and enforcement of this Act;</Ins></Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(3)</Label><Text>Paragraph 28(1)(j) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(j)</Label><Text>prescribing the procedure for <Ins>applying</Ins> for any <Ins>exemption</Ins>, approval, permission or <Ins>authorization under</Ins> this Act or for <Ins>registering</Ins> under section 6;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label><Ins>(j.1)</Ins></Label><Text><Ins>prescribing the</Ins> requirements to be satisfied before the <Ins>president</Ins> may grant any <Ins>exemption</Ins>, approval, permission or <Ins>authorization under</Ins> this Act;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label><Ins>(j.2)</Ins></Label><Text>specifying or providing for <Ins>the</Ins> specification of <Ins>the</Ins> conditions <Ins>on</Ins> which any <Ins>exemption, approval, permission or authorization under this Act must</Ins> or may be made;</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(4)</Label><Text>Paragraph 28(1)(p) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(p)</Label><Text>authorizing the <Ins>president</Ins> to delegate <Ins>their</Ins> functions, other than <Ins>the functions set out in</Ins> subsection 11(1) or section 22;</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(5)</Label><Text>Subsections 28(2) and (3) of the Act are repealed.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>44</Label><Text>Section 29 of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Heading change="ins" level="1"><TitleText>Review of Act</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Review</MarginalNote><Label>29</Label><Subsection change="ins"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Before the 10th anniversary of the day on which section <XRefSection lawid="1">44</XRefSection> of the <XRefExternal reference-level="federal" reference-type="act">Act to amend the Weights and Measures Act, the Electricity and Gas Inspection Act, the Weights and Measures Regulations and the Electricity and Gas Inspection Regulations</XRefExternal> comes into force and before the end of each subsequent period of 10 years, the Minister must cause to be completed a review of this Act and its operation.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Report</MarginalNote><Label><Ins>(2)</Ins></Label><Text>The <Ins>Minister must cause</Ins> a report of the <Ins>review to be laid</Ins> before <Ins>each House</Ins> of Parliament on any of the first 15 days on which that House is sitting after the report <Ins>has been completed</Ins>.</Text></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>45</Label><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Paragraph 33(1)(c) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(c)</Label><Text>puts into service or causes to be put into service any meter contrary to <Ins>paragraph</Ins> 9(1)<Ins>(b)</Ins>,</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Paragraph 33(1)(f) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(f)</Label><Text>contrary to subsection 15(1) verifies, seals, reverifies or reseals any meter;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph change="ins"><Label>(f.1)</Label><Text>contrary to subsection 15(1.1) or (1.2), breaks or causes to be broken the seal of any meter;</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(3)</Label><Text>Paragraph 33(1)(h) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(h)</Label><Text>being an <Ins>authorized service provider</Ins>, contravenes section 17,</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(4)</Label><Text>Paragraph 33(1)(j) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><SectionPiece><Paragraph change="ins"><Label>(i.1)</Label><Text>fails to do anything that the person was ordered to do by the Minister or an inspector, as the case may be, under paragraph 26.1(2)(j) or (k), subsection 26.1(6) or 26.4(2), section 26.5 or subsection 26.7(1);</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph change="ins"><Label>(i.2)</Label><Text>enters a place or part of a place after an inspector has prohibited or limited access to it under paragraph 26.1(2)(l);</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(j)</Label><Text>not being an inspector, <Ins>a designated inspector</Ins> or an <Ins>authorized service provider</Ins>, marks, or issues a certificate as to the accuracy or condition of, any meter after it has been installed for use, or</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>46</Label><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Paragraph 39(1)(b) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>any supply or class or type of supply of any energy or source <Ins>of energy</Ins>, in <Ins>any</Ins> form, <Ins>for which an</Ins> approval granted under <Ins>paragraph</Ins> 9<Ins>(1)(a) did</Ins> not, before the making of the order, <Ins>contemplate</Ins> the use of a meter.</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Subsection 39(3) of the Act is repealed.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>47</Label><Text>Subsection 46(2) of the Act is repealed.</Text></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>48</Label><Text>The Act is amended by replacing “director” with “president” in the following provisions:</Text><Paragraph type="amending"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>subsections 6(1) and (3);</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph type="amending"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>the portion of section 19 after paragraph (b); and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph type="amending"><Label>(c)</Label><Text>subsection 22(1).</Text></Paragraph></Section><Heading level="1"><MarginalNote><HistoricalNote>C.R.C., c. 1605; SOR/2017-198, s. 1</HistoricalNote></MarginalNote><TitleText><XRefExternal reference-level="federal" reference-type="regulation">Weights and Measures Regulations</XRefExternal></TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><Label>49</Label><Text>Part IV of the <XRefExternal reference-level="federal" reference-type="regulation">Weights and Measures Regulations</XRefExternal> is repealed.</Text></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>50</Label><Text>Schedule V to the Regulations is repealed.</Text></Section><Heading level="1"><MarginalNote><HistoricalNote>SOR/86-131</HistoricalNote></MarginalNote><TitleText><XRefExternal reference-level="federal" reference-type="regulation">Electricity and Gas Inspection Regulations</XRefExternal></TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><Label>51</Label><Text>Part X of the <XRefExternal reference-level="federal" reference-type="regulation">Electricity and Gas Inspection Regulations</XRefExternal> is repealed.</Text></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>52</Label><Text>Schedule 1 to the Regulations is repealed.</Text></Section><Heading level="1"><TitleText>Transitional Provisions</TitleText></Heading><Section type="transitional"><MarginalNote>Definitions</MarginalNote><Label>53</Label><Text>The following definitions apply in this section and sections <XRefInternal>54</XRefInternal> to <XRefInternal>58</XRefInternal>.</Text><Definition type="transitional"><Text><DefinedTermEn>accredited meter verifier</DefinedTermEn> has the same meaning as in subsection 2(1) of the former Act. (<DefinedTermFr>vérificateur accrédité</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Definition><Definition type="transitional"><Text><DefinedTermEn>authorized service provider</DefinedTermEn> has the same meaning as in subsection 2(1) of the new Act. (<DefinedTermFr>fournisseur de services autorisé</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Definition><Definition type="transitional"><Text><DefinedTermEn>commencement day</DefinedTermEn> means the day on which this section comes into force. (<DefinedTermFr>date de référence</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Definition><Definition type="transitional"><Text><DefinedTermEn>designated inspector</DefinedTermEn> has the same meaning as in subsection 2(1) of the new Act. (<DefinedTermFr>inspecteur désigné</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Definition><Definition type="transitional"><Text><DefinedTermEn>director</DefinedTermEn> has the same meaning as in subsection 2(1) of the former Act. (<DefinedTermFr>directeur</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Definition><Definition type="transitional"><Text><DefinedTermEn>former Act</DefinedTermEn> means the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Electricity and Gas Inspection Act</XRefExternal> as it read immediately before the commencement day. (<DefinedTermFr>ancienne loi</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Definition><Definition type="transitional"><Text><DefinedTermEn>new Act</DefinedTermEn> means the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Electricity and Gas Inspection Act</XRefExternal> as it reads on the commencement day. (<DefinedTermFr>nouvelle loi</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Definition><Definition type="transitional"><Text><DefinedTermEn>president</DefinedTermEn> has the same meaning as in subsection 2(1) of the new Act. (<DefinedTermFr>président</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Definition></Section><Section type="transitional"><MarginalNote>Verification and sealing</MarginalNote><Label>54</Label><Subsection type="transitional"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Any verification or sealing completed under subsection 9(1) of the former Act that is still valid on the commencement day is deemed to have been completed under paragraph 9(1)(b) of the new Act.</Text></Subsection><Subsection type="transitional"><MarginalNote>Permissions</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Any permission granted under subsection 9(2) of the former Act that is still valid on the commencement day is deemed to have been granted under subsection 9(2) of the new Act.</Text></Subsection><Subsection type="transitional"><MarginalNote>Approvals — subsection 9(3) of former Act</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>Any approval granted under subsection 9(3) of the former Act that is still valid on the commencement day is deemed to be a permission granted under subsection 9(3) of the new Act.</Text></Subsection><Subsection type="transitional"><MarginalNote>Approvals — subsection 9(4) of former Act</MarginalNote><Label>(4)</Label><Text>Any approval granted under subsection 9(4) of the former Act that is still valid on the commencement day is deemed to be an approval granted under paragraph 9(1)(a) of the new Act.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section type="transitional"><MarginalNote>Resealing and marks</MarginalNote><Label>55</Label><Text>Any resealing completed or mark made under subsection 12(1) of the former Act that is still valid on the commencement day is deemed to have been completed or made under subsection 12(1.1) of the new Act.</Text></Section><Section type="transitional"><MarginalNote>Authorized service providers</MarginalNote><Label>56</Label><Subsection type="transitional"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Nothing in this Act is to be construed as affecting the status of any person who, immediately before the commencement day, is an accredited meter verifier, except that, as of that day, the person is an authorized service provider.</Text></Subsection><Subsection type="transitional"><MarginalNote>Deeming — actions of authorized service providers</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Everything done or purported to have been done under the former Act by an accredited meter verifier before the commencement day is deemed, as of that day, to have been done by an authorized service provider under the new Act.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section type="transitional"><MarginalNote>President</MarginalNote><Label>57</Label><Subsection type="transitional"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Nothing in this Act is to be construed as affecting the status of the person who, immediately before the commencement day, occupies the position of director, except that, as of that day, the person occupies the position of president.</Text></Subsection><Subsection type="transitional"><MarginalNote>Deeming — actions of president</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Everything done or purported to have been done under the former Act by the director before the commencement day is deemed, as of that day, to have been done by the president under the new Act.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section type="transitional"><MarginalNote>Designated inspectors</MarginalNote><Label>58</Label><Subsection type="transitional"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Nothing in this Act is to be construed as affecting the status of any person who, immediately before the commencement day, is a person designated under subsection 26(3) of the former Act, except that, as of that day, the person is a designated inspector.</Text></Subsection><Subsection type="transitional"><MarginalNote>Deeming — actions of designated inspectors</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Everything done or purported to have been done by a person designated under subsection 26(3) of the former Act before the commencement day is deemed, as of that day, to have been done by a designated inspector under the new Act.</Text></Subsection></Section><Heading level="1"><TitleText>Coming into Force</TitleText></Heading><Section type="CIF"><MarginalNote>Order in council</MarginalNote><Label>59</Label><Subsection type="CIF"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Sections <XRefInternal>1</XRefInternal> to <XRefInternal>5</XRefInternal>, subsections <XRefInternal>6</XRefInternal>(1), (3) and (4), sections <XRefInternal>7</XRefInternal> to <XRefInternal>30</XRefInternal> and <XRefInternal>34</XRefInternal> to <XRefInternal>42</XRefInternal>, subsections <XRefInternal>43</XRefInternal>(1) and (3) to (5) and sections <XRefInternal>44</XRefInternal> to <XRefInternal>48</XRefInternal> and <XRefInternal>53</XRefInternal> to <XRefInternal>58</XRefInternal> come into force on a day to be fixed by order of the Governor in Council.</Text></Subsection><Subsection type="CIF"><MarginalNote>Order in council</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Sections <XRefInternal>31</XRefInternal> to <XRefInternal>33</XRefInternal> come into force on a day to be fixed by order of the Governor in Council, but that day must not be before the day referred to in subsection (1).</Text></Subsection><Subsection type="CIF"><MarginalNote>Order in council</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>Subsection <XRefInternal>6</XRefInternal>(2) and sections <XRefInternal>49</XRefInternal> and <XRefInternal>50</XRefInternal> come into force on a day to be fixed by order of the Governor in Council.</Text></Subsection><Subsection type="CIF"><MarginalNote>Order in council</MarginalNote><Label>(4)</Label><Text>Subsection <XRefInternal>43</XRefInternal>(2) and sections <XRefInternal>51</XRefInternal> and <XRefInternal>52</XRefInternal> come into force on a day to be fixed by order of the Governor in Council.</Text></Subsection></Section></Body></Bill>