<?xml version="1.0"?>
<Bill RHead_reign="52-53 Eliz. II" RHead_ParlYear="2004" DocumentTitle="BILL S-12" Bill_No="S-12" Document_No="0312" xml:lang="EN" Bill_Type="Non-amending" Stage_Name="First-Reading-Senate" Reprint="No" xml:space="preserve" ChapterNo_E="C. " ChapterNo_F="ch. " Bill-Origin="senate"><Bill_Part Part_Type="Cover" CountLines="No"><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="CovBillNo">S-12</Para></Block><Block><Para TopMargin="24" Size="9" Leading="10" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0" TextAlign="Center">Third Session, Thirty-seventh Parliament,</Para></Block><Block><Para Size="9" Leading="10" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0" TextAlign="Center">52-53 Elizabeth II, 2004</Para></Block><Block><Para TopMargin="48" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0" Bold="Yes" TextAlign="Center">SENATE OF CANADA</Para></Block><Block><Para TopMargin="42" Size="18" Leading="20" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0" Bold="Yes" TextAlign="Center">BILL S-12</Para></Block><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="CovLongTitle">An Act to amend the Royal Canadian Mounted Police Act (modernization of employment and labour relations)</Para></Block><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="COV_StageLine"></Para></Block><Block><Para Size="9" AllCaps="Yes" Hyphenate="OFF">first reading, February 12, 2004</Para></Block><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="COV_StageLine"></Para></Block><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="Cover_Sponsors"><SC SC_PerCent="85">The Honourable Senator Nolin</SC></Para></Block><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="Cover_DocNo">0312</Para></Block></Bill_Part><Bill_Part CountLines="No" Part_Type="InsideCover"><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="BPT_InsideCoverE">Available on the Parliament of Canada Web Site at the following address:<br/><B>http://www.parl.gc.ca</B></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><Para TopMargin="108" BottomMargin="4" Size="10" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center"><SC SC_PerCent="85">Summary</SC></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" Size="8" Leading="9" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">This enactment amends the <I>Royal Canadian Mounted Police Act</I> to provide for a comprehensive system for the certification of a police association composed of members of the Royal Canadian Mounted Police and for collective bargaining rights. It also eliminates the External Review Committee and creates a new regime respecting grievances with a right to refer all disciplinary matters not resolved by the grievance process to adjudication.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" Size="8" Leading="9" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">The enactment replaces Parts II and III of the Act with a new Part II. Division I of the new Part II establishes the Public Service Staff Relations Board as the competent body for dealing with certain matters related to labour relations between the employer and the employees.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" Size="8" Leading="9" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">Division II deals with the certification of bargaining agents and the negotiation of collective agreements.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" Size="8" Leading="9" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">Division III sets out a dispute resolution process where the parties have failed to reach agreement in their collective bargaining.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" Size="8" Leading="9" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">Division IV replaces the existing grievance regime and also makes available adjudication services to be provided by the Public Service Staff Relations Board.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" Size="8" Leading="9" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">Division V includes provisions that prohibit a strike by employees and provide for an offence on summary conviction for breaching this prohibition.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" Size="8" Leading="9" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">The enactment also makes consequential changes to other Parts of the Act.</Para></Block></Bill_Part><Bill_Part Part_Type="MainText" CountLines="Yes" RunningHead_E="Royal Canadian Mounted Police"><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="MainText_DocNo">0312</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes"><Para Style="Session_Reign">3rd Session, 37th Parliament,</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes"><Para Style="Session_Reign">52-53 Elizabeth II, 2004</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes"><Para Style="MainBillOrigin">senate of canada</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes"><Para Bold="Yes" Style="MAIN@BillNo_Title">BILL S-12</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes"><Para Style="MAIN@ti;04">An Act to amend the Royal Canadian Mounted Police Act (modernization of employment and labour relations)</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">WHEREAS the Royal Canadian Mounted Police, founded on May 23, 1873 and originally known as the North-West Mounted Police, constitutes by reason of its traditions, professionalism and excellent international reputation a major source of pride for Canadians and a symbol of Canada;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">WHEREAS since 1974 some members of the Royal Canadian Mounted Police have sought, through legitimate means, the right to certification and collective bargaining;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">WHEREAS the refusal to grant members of the Royal Canadian Mounted Police the right to collective bargaining is a source of injustice and frustration and is furthermore inconsistent with fundamental principles of labour relations in Canada;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">WHEREAS the Government of Canada has ratified Convention No. 87 of the International Labour Organization concerning Freedom of Association and Protection of the Right to Organize;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">WHEREAS there is in Canada a tradition of labour legislation and policy designed for the promotion of the common well-being through the encouragement of free collective bargaining and the constructive settlement of disputes;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">WHEREAS members of the Royal Canadian Mounted Police are employed in the public service of Canada yet do not have the rights enjoyed by other employees of the Government of Canada since March 13, 1967 under the <I>Public Service Staff Relations Act</I>;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">WHEREAS members of the Royal Canadian Mounted Police do not have the same protection with respect to union activities as other persons employed in the public service of Canada;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">WHEREAS effective employer-employee relations constitute the basis of sound human resource management, and cooperation through communication and sustained dialogue enables the public service of Canada to better serve and protect the public interest;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">WHEREAS members of the Royal Canadian Mounted Police, unlike members of most civilian police forces in Canada, do not have the right of accreditation and collective bargaining;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">WHEREAS the Royal Canadian Mounted Police, to enjoy the trust and respect of the public, must be accountable to Canadians not only through the Royal Canadian Mounted Police Public Complaints Commission, but also through an internal discipline and grievance procedure that is consistent with the principles governing due process of law, notably fairness, impartiality, independence and expeditiousness;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">AND WHEREAS the Parliament of Canada considers that good staff relations and the constructive and transparent settlement of disputes within the Royal Canadian Mounted Police are in the best interests of Canada, help to maintain a responsible and effective national civilian police force and enhance public protection;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">NOW, THEREFORE, Her Majesty, by and with the advice and consent of the Senate and House of Commons of Canada, enacts as follows:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>1.</B> (1) The definition “Committee” in section 2 of the <I>Royal Canadian Mounted Police Act</I> is repealed.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes">(2) The definition “Committee Chairman” in section 2 of the English version of the Act is repealed.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>2.</B> The definition “Commission” in section 2 of the French version of the Act is replaced by the following:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>“Commission”<br/>« Commission »<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0">“<I>Commission</I>”<AltLang xml:lang="fr"> Sauf à la partie II, la Commission des plaintes du public contre la Gendarmerie royale du Canada constituée par l’article 45.29.</AltLang></Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>3.</B> Subsection 5(2) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Delegation<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(2) The Commissioner may delegate to any member any of the Commissioner’s powers, duties or functions under this Act, except the power to delegate under this subsection, the power to make rules under this Act and the powers, duties or functions under subsections 45.46(1) and (2).</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>4.</B> Paragraph 24.1(6)(<I>b</I>) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>b</I>) any answer or statement made in response to a question described in subsection 40(2) or 45.45(9);</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>5.</B> Subsection 24.1(8) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Answer not receivable<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(8) Where the witness is a member, no answer or statement made in response to a question described in subsection (7) shall be used or receivable against the witness in any proceedings in respect of an allegation of contravention of the Code of Conduct by the witness, other than a hearing into an allegation that with intent to mislead the witness gave the answer or statement knowing it to be false.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>6.</B> Parts II and III of the Act are replaced by the following:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:PART II--><Para TopMargin="10" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">PART II</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:STAFF RELATIONS--><Para TopMargin="5" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">STAFF RELATIONS</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:Interpretation--><Para TopMargin="5" Italic="Yes" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">Interpretation</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Definitions<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>25.</B> (1) The following definitions apply in this Part.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><MarginalNote>“adjudicator”<br/>« <I>arbitre</I> »<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0">“adjudicator” means, subject to subsection 33.1(4), a member of the Board assigned to hear and determine a grievance referred to adjudication and includes, where the context permits, a board of adjudication established under paragraph 33.1(2)(<I>c</I>), a person named as an adjudicator in a collective agreement for the purposes of that agreement and a person otherwise selected as an adjudicator by the parties to the grievance.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><MarginalNote>“arbitral award”<br/>« <I>décision arbitrale</I> »<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0">“arbitral award” means an award made by the Board or an arbitrator appointed under section 29.05 in respect of a matter in dispute.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><MarginalNote>“bargaining agent”<br/>« <I>agent négociateur</I> »<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0">“bargaining agent” means an employee organization</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>a</I>) that has been certified by the Board as bargaining agent for a bargaining unit; and</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>b</I>) the certification of which has not been revoked.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><MarginalNote>“bargaining unit”<br/>« <I>unité de négociation</I> »<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0">“bargaining unit” means a group of two or more employees that is determined, in accordance with this Part, to constitute a unit of employees appropriate for collective bargaining.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><MarginalNote>“Board”<br/>« <I>Commission</I> »<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0">“Board” means the Public Service Staff Relations Board established by section 11 of the <I>Public Service Staff Relations Act</I>.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><MarginalNote>“Chairperson”<br/>« <I>president</I> »<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0">“Chairperson” means the Chairperson of the Board.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><MarginalNote>“collective agreement”<br/>« <I>convention collective</I> »<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0">“collective agreement” means an agreement in writing entered into under this Part between the employer and a bargaining agent, containing provisions respecting terms and conditions of employment and related matters.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><MarginalNote>“conciliator”<br/>« <I>conciliateur</I> »<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0">“conciliator” means a person appointed by the Chairperson under section 29.01 to assist the parties to collective bargaining in reaching agreement.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><MarginalNote>“Deputy Chairperson”<br/>« <I>président suppléant</I> »<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0">“Deputy Chairperson” means a Deputy Chairperson of the Board.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><MarginalNote>“dispute”<br/>« <I>différend</I> »<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0">“dispute” means a dispute or difference that arises in connection with the entering into, renewal or revision of a collective agreement, in respect of which the assistance of a conciliator is desired as provided in section 29.01 or arbitration is requested pursuant to section 29.06.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><MarginalNote>“employee”<br/>« <I>employé</I> »<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0">“employee” means a person who is a member or special constable of the Force or who is employed by the Force under terms and conditions substantially the same as those of one of its members, other than</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>a</I>) a person appointed by the Governor in Council;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>b</I>) a person employed on a term basis, unless the term of employment is for a period of three months or more or the person has been so employed for a period of three months or more; or</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>c</I>) a person employed in a managerial or confidential capacity.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><MarginalNote>“employee organization”<br/>« <I>organisation syndicale</I> »<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0">“employee organization” means any police association the purposes of which include the regulation of relations between the employer and its employees for the purposes of this Part and includes, unless the context otherwise requires, a council of employee organizations.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><MarginalNote>“employer”<br/>« <I>employeur</I> »<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0">“employer” means Her Majesty in right of Canada as represented by the Treasury Board.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><MarginalNote>“grievance”<br/>« <I>grief</I> »<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0">“grievance” means a complaint in writing presented in accordance with this Part by an employee on his or her own behalf or on behalf of the employee and one or more other employees, except that</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>a</I>) for the purposes of any of the provisions of this Part respecting grievances, a reference to an “employee” includes a person who would be an employee but for the fact that the person is a person employed in a managerial or confidential capacity; and</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>b</I>) for the purposes of any of the provisions of this Part respecting grievances with respect to action resulting in termination or suspension, a reference to an “employee” includes a former employee or a person who would be a former employee but for the fact that, at the time of the person’s termination or suspension, the person was a person employed in a managerial or confidential capacity.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><MarginalNote>“member of the Board”<br/>« <I>commissaire</I> »<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0">“member of the Board” includes a full-time member and a part-time member of the Board.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><MarginalNote>“parties”<br/>« <I>parties</I> »<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0">“parties” means</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>a</I>) in relation to collective bargaining, arbitration or a dispute, the employer and a bargaining agent; and</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>b</I>) in relation to a grievance, the employer and the employee who presented the grievance.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><MarginalNote>“person employed in a managerial or confidential capacity”<br/>« <I>personne occupant un poste de direction ou de confiance</I> »<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0">“person employed in a managerial or confidential capacity” means any person who is employed by the employer and, in connection with an application for certification of a bargaining agent for a bargaining unit, is designated by the Board, or, in any case where a bargaining agent for a bargaining unit has been certified by the Board, is designated in the prescribed manner by the employer or by the Board on objection thereto by the bargaining agent, to be a person</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>a</I>) who has executive duties and responsibilities in relation to the development and administration of employer programs;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>b</I>) whose duties include those of a personnel administrator or who has duties that cause the person to be directly involved in the process of collective bargaining on behalf of the employer;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>c</I>) who is required by reason of the duties and responsibilities of that person to deal formally on behalf of the employer with a grievance presented in accordance with the grievance process provided by this Part;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>d</I>) who is employed in a position confidential to any person described in paragraph (<I>a</I>), (<I>b</I>) or (<I>c</I>); or</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>e</I>) who is not otherwise described in paragraph (<I>a</I>), (<I>b</I>), (<I>c</I>) or (<I>d</I>) but who, in the opinion of the Board, should not be included in a bargaining unit by reason of the person’s duties and responsibilities to the employer.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><MarginalNote>“police association”<br/>« <I>association de policiers</I> »<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0">“police association” means an association whose members are employees of the Force, and whose objects include the improvement of their working conditions and remuneration.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><MarginalNote>“prescribed”<br/>« <I>règlement</I> » <I>et</I> « <I>réglementaire</I> »<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0">“prescribed” means prescribed by regulation of the Board.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><MarginalNote>“strike”<br/>« <I>grève</I> »<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0">“strike” includes a cessation of work or a refusal to work or to continue to work by employees in combination or in concert or in accordance with a common understanding, or a slow-down of work or other concerted activity on the part of employees designed to restrict or limit output.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><MarginalNote>“Vice-Chairperson”<br/>« <I>vice-président</I> »<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0">“Vice-Chairperson” means the Vice-Chairperson of the Board.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Employee status preserved<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(2) A person does not cease to be an employee by reason only that the person ceases to work as a result of a strike or by reason only of the termination of the person’s employment contrary to this Act or any other Act of Parliament.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:General--><Para TopMargin="10" Italic="Yes" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">General</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:Rights--><Para TopMargin="5" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">Rights</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Employment rights<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>26.</B> (1) The purpose of this Part is to provide to certain persons employed in the Force collective bargaining and other rights in respect of their employment.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Right of membership in employee organization<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(2) Every employee may be a member of an employee organization and may participate in the lawful activities of the employee organization of which the employee is a member.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Right of employer<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(3) Nothing in this Part shall be construed to affect the right or authority of the employer to determine the organization of the employer and to assign duties and classify positions of employment.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:Prohibitions--><Para TopMargin="10" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">Prohibitions</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Employer participation in employee organization<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>26.01</B> (1) No person who is employed in a managerial or confidential capacity, whether or not the person is acting on behalf of the employer, shall participate in or interfere with the formation or administration of an employee organization or the representation of employees by such an organization.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Discrimination against members and intimidation<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(2) Subject to subsection (3), no person shall</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>a</I>) refuse to employ or to continue to employ, or otherwise discriminate against any person in regard to employment or, any term or condition of employment because the person is a member of an employee organization or was or is exercising any right under this Part;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>b</I>) impose any condition on an appointment or in a contract of employment, or propose the imposition of any condition on an appointment or in a contract of employment, that seeks to restrain an employee or a person seeking employment from becoming a member of an employee organization or exercising any right under this Part; or</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>c</I>) seek, by intimidation, by threat of dismissal or any other kind of threat, by the imposition of a pecuniary or any other penalty or by any other means, to compel an employee</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="4" FirstLineIndent="0">(i) to become, refrain from becoming or cease to be, or, except as otherwise provided in a collective agreement, to continue to be, a member of an employee organization, or</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="4" FirstLineIndent="0">(ii) to refrain from exercising any other right under this Part.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Exception<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(3) A person does not contravene subsection (2) by reason only of any act or thing done or omitted in relation to a person employed, or proposed to be employed, in a managerial or confidential capacity.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Discrimination against employee organization<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>26.02</B> (1) Except in accordance with this Part or any regulation, collective agreement or arbitral award, no person employed in a managerial or confidential capacity, whether or not the person acts on behalf of the employer, shall discriminate against an employee organization.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Saving provision<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(2) Nothing in subsection (1) shall be construed to prevent a person employed in a managerial or confidential capacity from receiving representations from, or holding discussions with, the representatives of any employee organization.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Soliciting membership during working hours<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>26.03</B> Except with the consent of the employer, no officer or representative of an employee organization shall attempt, on the employer’s premises during the working hours of an employee, to persuade the employee to become, refrain from becoming, continue to be or to cease to be a member of an employee organization.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:DIVISION I--><Para TopMargin="10" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">DIVISION I</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:PUBLIC SERVICE STAFF RELATIONS BOARD--><Para TopMargin="5" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">PUBLIC SERVICE STAFF RELATIONS BOARD</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:Public Service Staff Relations Act Provisions--><Para TopMargin="5" Italic="Yes" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">Public Service Staff Relations Act Provisions</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Application of Part I of <I>Public Service Staff Relations Act</I><br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>26.04</B> Unless otherwise provided in this Part, the provisions of Part I of the <I>Public Service Staff Relations Act</I> respecting the Public Service Staff Relations Board apply also in respect of this Part except that, for the purpose of that application,</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>a</I>) a reference to that Act in any of those provisions shall be read as a reference to this Part; and</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>b</I>) words and expressions used in those provisions that are defined by this Part shall have the meaning given to them by this Part.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:Powers and Duties of the Board--><Para TopMargin="10" Italic="Yes" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">Powers and Duties of the Board</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Powers and duties of the Board<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>26.05</B> The Board shall administer this Part and shall exercise such powers and perform such duties as are conferred or imposed on it by, or as may be incidental to the attainment of the purposes of, this Part including, without restricting the generality of the foregoing, the making of orders requiring compliance with this Part, with any regulation made hereunder or with any decision made in respect of a matter coming before it.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Delegation of powers to Vice-Chairperson and Deputy Chairperson<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>26.06</B> The Vice-Chairperson and each Deputy Chairperson may exercise such of the powers and perform such of the duties and functions of the Board under this Part as may be assigned to them by the Board other than the power to make regulations of general application under section 26.07.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Authority of Board to make regulations<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>26.07</B> (1) The Board may make regulations of general application respecting</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>a</I>) the manner in which persons shall be designated by the employer, or by the Board on objection thereto by a bargaining agent, to be persons described in paragraphs (<I>a</I>) to (<I>e</I>) of the definition “person employed in a managerial or confidential capacity” in subsection 25(1);</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>b</I>) the determination of units of employees appropriate for collective bargaining;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>c</I>) the certification of bargaining agents for bargaining units;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>d</I>) the hearing or determination of any matter relating to or arising out of the revocation of certification of a bargaining agent, including the rights and privileges that have accrued to and are retained by any employee notwithstanding the revocation;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>e</I>) the rights, privileges and duties that are acquired or retained by an employee organization in respect of a bargaining unit or any employee included in the unit where there is any merger, amalgamation or transfer of jurisdiction between two or more such organizations;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>f</I>) the establishment of rules of procedure for its hearings and those of an adjudicator;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>g</I>) the specification of the time within which and the persons to whom notices and other documents shall be sent and when the notices shall be deemed to have been given and received;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>h</I>) the determination of the form in which, and the time as of which, evidence</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="4" FirstLineIndent="0">(i) as to membership of employees in an employee organization,</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="4" FirstLineIndent="0">(ii) of objection by employees to certification of an employee organization, or</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="4" FirstLineIndent="0">(iii) of signification by employees that they no longer wish to be represented by an employee organizationshall be presented to the Board on an application for certification of or for revocation of certification of a bargaining agent, and the circumstances in which evidence as to membership of employees in an employee organization may be received by the Board as evidence that the employees wish that employee organization to represent them as their bargaining agent;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>i</I>) the hearing of complaints under section 26.08;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>j</I>) the authority vested in a council of employee organizations that shall be considered appropriate authority within the meaning of paragraph 27.01(2)(<I>b</I>); and</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>k</I>) such other matters and things as may be incidental or conducive to the objects and purposes of the Board, the exercise of its powers and the attainment of the purpose of this Part.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>When regulations effective<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(2) Regulations made under subsection (1) have effect on publication in the <I>Canada Gazette</I>.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Complaints<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>26.08</B> (1) The Board shall examine and inquire into any complaint made to it that the employer or an employee organization, or any person acting on behalf of the employer or an employee organization, has failed</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>a</I>) to observe any prohibition contained in section 26.01, 26.02 or 26.03;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>b</I>) to give effect to any provision of an arbitral award;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>c</I>) to give effect to a decision of an adjudicator with respect to a grievance; or</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>d</I>) to comply with any regulation respecting grievances made by the Board pursuant to section 34.1.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Order of Board directing compliance<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(2) Where under subsection (1) the Board determines that any person has failed to observe any prohibition, to give effect to any provision or decision or to comply with any regulation as described in that subsection, it may make an order, addressed to that person, directing the person to observe the prohibition, give effect to the provision or decision or comply with the regulation, as the case may be, or take such action as may be required in that behalf within such specified period as the Board may consider appropriate and,</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>a</I>) where that person has acted or purported to act on behalf of the employer, it shall direct its order as well to the employer; and</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>b</I>) where that person has acted or purported to act on behalf of an employee organization, it shall direct its order as well to the chief officer of that employee organization.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Where order not complied with<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>26.09</B> Where any order made under section 26.08 directs some action to be taken and is not complied with within the period specified in the order for the taking of that action, the Board shall cause a copy of its order, a report of the circumstances and all documents relevant thereto to be laid before each House of Parliament within fifteen days after the expiration of the period or, if that House is not then sitting, on any of the first fifteen days next thereafter on which that House is sitting.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Powers of Board in proceedings<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>26.1</B> The Board has, in relation to the hearing or determination of any proceeding before it, the power</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>a</I>) to summon and enforce the attendance of witnesses and compel them to give oral or written evidence on oath, and to produce such documents and things as the Board deems requisite to the full investigation and consideration of matters within its jurisdiction, in the same manner and to the same extent as a superior court of record;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>b</I>) to administer oaths and solemn affirmations;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>c</I>) to receive and accept such evidence and information on oath, affidavit or otherwise as in its discretion it sees fit, whether admissible in a court of law or not, and, without limiting the generality of the foregoing, to refuse to accept any evidence that is not presented in the form and within the time prescribed;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>d</I>) to require the employer to post and keep posted in appropriate places any notices that the Board deems necessary to bring to the attention of any employees in any matter or proceeding before the Board;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>e</I>) to enter on the premises of the employer for the purpose of conducting representation votes during working hours; and</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>f</I>) to authorize any person to do anything that the Board may do under paragraphs (<I>b</I>) to (<I>e</I>) and to require the person to report to the Board thereon.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Application of orders<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>26.11</B> Where under this Part the Board may make or issue any order or direction, prescribe any term or condition or do any other thing in relation to any person, the Board may do so either generally or in any particular case or class of cases.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Review or amendment of orders<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>26.12</B> (1) Subject to subsection (2), the Board may review, rescind, amend, alter or vary any decision or order made by it, and may re-hear any application before making an order in respect thereof.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Exception<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(2) Any rights acquired by virtue of any decision or order that is reviewed, rescinded, amended, altered or varied pursuant to subsection (1) shall not be altered or extinguished with effect from a day earlier than the day on which the review, rescission, amendment, alteration or variation is made.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:DIVISION II--><Para TopMargin="10" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">DIVISION II</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:COLLECTIVE BARGAINING AND COLLECTIVE AGREEMENTS--><Para TopMargin="5" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">COLLECTIVE BARGAINING AND COLLECTIVE AGREEMENTS</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:Certification of Bargaining Agents--><Para TopMargin="5" Italic="Yes" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">Certification of Bargaining Agents</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:Application for Certification--><Para TopMargin="5" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">Application for Certification</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Application by employee organization<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>27.</B> (1) An employee organization seeking to be certified as bargaining agent for a group of employees that it considers constitutes a unit of employees appropriate for collective bargaining may, subject to subsection (2) and section 27.04, apply in the prescribed manner to the Board for certification as bargaining agent for the proposed bargaining unit. The Board must notify the employer of the application without delay.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Police association<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(2) Only a police association may seek to be certified as a bargaining agent for a group of employees.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Affiliation of police association<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(3) A police association may be affiliated with another organization only if that organization is composed exclusively of employees.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Application by council of organizations<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>27.01</B> (1) Where two or more employee organizations have come together to form a council of employee organizations, the council so formed may, subject to section 27.04, apply in the prescribed manner to the Board for certification under section 27.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Conditions for certification of council<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(2) The Board may certify a council of employee organizations as bargaining agent for a bargaining unit where the Board is satisfied that</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>a</I>) the requirements for certification established by this Part are met; and</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>b</I>) each of the employee organizations forming the council has vested appropriate authority in the council to enable it to discharge the duties and responsibilities of a bargaining agent.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Council deemed to be employee organization<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>27.02</B> A council of employee organizations shall, for all purposes of this Part except subsection 27.01(2), be deemed to be an employee organization, and membership in any employee organization that is part of a council of employee organizations shall for the same purposes be deemed to be membership in the council.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Continuation of terms and conditions<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>27.03</B> After being notified of an application for certification made in accordance with this Part, the employer shall not, except under a collective agreement or with the consent of the Board, alter the terms and conditions of employment that are applicable to the employees in the proposed bargaining unit and that may be included in a collective agreement until</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>a</I>) the application has been withdrawn by the employee organization or dismissed by the Board; or</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>b</I>) 90 days have elapsed after the day on which the Board certifies the employee organization as the bargaining agent for the unit.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:When Application for Certification may be Made--><Para TopMargin="10" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">When Application for Certification may be Made</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Where  agreement is for term of not more than two years<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>27.04</B> (1) Where a collective agreement or an arbitral award is in force and is for a term of not more than two years, an employee organization may apply to the Board for certification as bargaining agent for any of the employees in the bargaining unit to which the agreement or award applies only after the commencement of the last two months of its operation.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Where agreement is for term of more than two years<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(2) Where a collective agreement or an arbitral award is in force and is for a term of more than two years, an employee organization may apply to the Board for certification as bargaining agent for any of the employees in the bargaining unit to which the agreement or award applies only</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>a</I>) after the commencement of the twenty-third month of its operation and before the commencement of the twenty-fifth month of its operation;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>b</I>) during the two-month period immediately preceding the end of each year that the agreement or award continues to operate after the second year of its operation; or</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>c</I>) after the commencement of the last two months of its operation.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Where agreement is for indefinite term<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(3) Where a collective agreement referred to in subsection (1) or (2) provides that it will continue to operate after the term specified therein for a further term or successive terms if either party fails to give to the other notice of termination or of its desire to bargain with a view to the renewal, with or without modifications, of the collective agreement, an employee organization may apply to the Board for certification as bargaining agent for any of the employees in the bargaining unit to whom the collective agreement applies at any time permitted by subsection (1) or (2), as the case may be, or during the two-month period immediately preceding the end of each year that the collective agreement continues to operate after the term specified therein.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Where no collective agreement or award is in force<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(4) Where no collective agreement or arbitral award in respect of a bargaining unit is in force but an employee organization has been certified as bargaining agent for any of the employees in the bargaining unit, an employee organization may, after the expiration of twelve months from the date of that certification or, with the consent of the Board, at an earlier time, apply to the Board for certification as bargaining agent for any of the employees in the bargaining unit.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>No certification where previous application refused within six months<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>27.05</B> Where an application for certification of an employee organization as bargaining agent for a proposed bargaining unit has been refused by the Board, the Board shall not certify the employee organization as bargaining agent for the same or substantially the same proposed bargaining unit until at least six months have elapsed from the day on which the Board last refused certification, unless the Board is satisfied that the previous application was refused by reason only of a technical error or omission made in connection therewith.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:Determination of Appropriate Bargaining Units--><Para TopMargin="10" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">Determination of Appropriate Bargaining Units</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Determination of unit<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>27.06</B> (1) Where an employee organization has applied to the Board for certification as described in section 27, the Board shall determine the relevant group of employees that constitutes a unit appropriate for collective bargaining.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Matters to be taken into account<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(2) In determining whether a group of employees constitutes a unit appropriate for collective bargaining, the Board shall take into account, having regard to the proper functioning of this Part, the duties and classification of the employees in the proposed bargaining unit in relation to any plan of classification as it may apply to the employees in the proposed bargaining unit.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Composition of bargaining unit<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(3) For the purposes of this Part, a unit of employees may be determined by the Board to constitute a unit appropriate for collective bargaining whether or not its composition is identical with the group of employees in respect of which application for certification was made.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Determination of membership in bargaining units<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>27.07</B> Where, at any time following the determination by the Board that a group of employees constitutes a unit appropriate for collective bargaining, any question arises as to whether any employee or class of employees is or is not included therein or is included in any other unit, the Board shall, on application by the employer or any employee organization affected, determine the question.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:Certification--><Para TopMargin="10" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">Certification</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Certification of employee organization as bargaining unit<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>27.08</B> Where the Board</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>a</I>) has received from an employee organization an application for certification as bargaining agent for a bargaining unit in accordance with this Part,</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>b</I>) has determined the group of employees that constitutes a unit appropriate for collective bargaining in accordance with section 27.06,</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>c</I>) is satisfied that a majority of employees in the bargaining unit wish the employee organization to represent them as their bargaining agent, and</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>d</I>) is satisfied that the persons representing the employee organization in the making of the application have been duly authorized to make the application,</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0">the Board shall, subject to this Part, certify the employee organization making the application as bargaining agent for the employees in that bargaining unit.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Powers of Board in relation to certification<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>27.09</B> (1) For the purpose of enabling the Board to discharge any obligation imposed by section 27.08 to satisfy itself as to the matters described in paragraphs (<I>c</I>) and (<I>d</I>) of that section, the Board may</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>a</I>) examine, in accordance with any regulations that may be made by the Board in that behalf, such evidence as is submitted to it respecting membership of the employees in the proposed bargaining unit in the employee organization seeking certification;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>b</I>) make or cause to be made such examination of records or make such inquiries as it deems necessary; and</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>c</I>) examine documents forming or relating to the constitution or articles of association of the employee organization seeking certification.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Representation vote directed to be taken<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(2) For the purpose of satisfying itself under paragraph 27.08(<I>c</I>) that a majority of employees in the bargaining unit wish the employee organization to represent them as their bargaining agent, the Board, in its sole discretion, may direct that a representation vote be taken among the employees in the bargaining unit.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Arrangements to be made for representation vote<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(3) Where under subsection (2) the Board directs that a representation vote be taken, the Board shall</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">(<I>a</I>) determine the employees that are eligible to vote; an</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">(<I>b</I>) make such arrangements and give such directions as it deems requisite for the proper conduct of the representation vote, including the preparation of ballots, the method of casting and counting ballots and the custody and sealing of ballot boxes.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:Where Certification Prohibited--><Para TopMargin="10" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">Where Certification Prohibited</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Where participation by employer in formation of employee organization<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>27.1</B> (1) The Board shall not certify as bargaining agent for a bargaining unit any employee organization in the formation or administration of which there has been or is, in the opinion of the Board, participation by the employer or by any person acting on behalf of the employer of such a nature as to impair its fitness to represent the interests of employees in the bargaining unit.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Where money received or paid for activities by political party<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(2) The Board shall not certify as bargaining agent for a bargaining unit any employee organization that</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>a</I>) receives from any of its members who are employees,</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>b</I>) handles or pays in its own name on behalf of members who are employees, or</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>c</I>) requires as a condition of membership therein the payment by any of its members of</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0">any money for activities carried on by or on behalf of any political party.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Discrimination<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(3) The Board shall not certify an employee organization as a bargaining agent if it discriminates against any employee on a prohibited ground of discrimination within the meaning of the <I>Canadian Human Rights Act</I>.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:Effect of Certification--><Para TopMargin="10" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">Effect of Certification</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Effect ofcertification<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>27.11</B> (1) Where an employee organization is certified under this Part as the bargaining agent for a bargaining unit, the employee organization has the exclusive right under this Part</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>a</I>) to bargain collectively on behalf of employees in the bargaining unit and to bind them by a collective agreement until its certification in respect of the bargaining unit is revoked; and</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>b</I>) to represent, in accordance with this Part, an employee in the presentation or reference to adjudication of a grievance relating to the interpretation or application of a collective agreement or arbitral award applying to the bargaining unit to which the employee belongs.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Effect ofcertification on previously certified bargaining agent<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(2) Where an employee organization is certified under this Part as the bargaining agent for a bargaining unit and another employee organization had been previously certified as bargaining agent in respect of employees in the bargaining unit, the certification of the previously certified bargaining agent is thereupon revoked in respect of those employees.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Effect of certification on existing collective agreement or arbitral award<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(3) Where an employee organization is certified under this Part as the bargaining agent for a bargaining unit and at the time of certification a collective agreement or arbitral award binding on the employees in the bargaining unit is in force, the employee organization</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>a</I>) shall be substituted as a party to the agreement or award in place of the bargaining agent that had been a party thereto; and</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>b</I>) may, notwithstanding anything contained in the agreement or award, terminate the agreement or award, in so far as it applies to the employees in the bargaining unit, on two months’ notice to the employer given within one month from the certification.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Rights of previous or new bargaining agent<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(4) In any case where subsection (2) or (3) applies, any question as to any right or duty of the previous bargaining agent or the new bargaining agent arising by reason of the application of that subsection shall, on application by the employer or the previous or the new bargaining agent, be determined by the Board.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:Revocation of Certification--><Para TopMargin="10" Italic="Yes" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">Revocation of Certification</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:On Application--><Para TopMargin="5" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">On Application</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Application for declaration that employee organization no longer represents employees<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>27.12</B> (1) Where a collective agreement or an arbitral award is in force in respect of a bargaining unit, any person claiming to represent a majority of the employees in that bargaining unit may, in accordance with subsection (2), apply to the Board for a declaration that the employee organization certified as bargaining agent for that bargaining unit no longer represents a majority of the employees therein.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>When application may be made<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(2) An application under subsection (1) may be made</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>a</I>) where the collective agreement or arbitral award is for a term of not more than two years, only after the commencement of the last two months of its operation;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>b</I>) where the collective agreement or arbitral award is for a term of more than two years, only after the commencement of the twenty-third month of its operation and before the commencement of the twenty-fifth month of its operation, during the two month period immediately preceding the end of each year that it continues to operate after the second year of its operation, or after the commencement of the last two months of its operation, as the case may be; and</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>c</I>) where the collective agreement provides that it will continue to operate after the term specified therein for a further term or successive terms if either party fails to give to the other notice of termination or of its desire to bargain with a view to the renewal, with or without modifications, of the agreement or with a view to the making of a new collective agreement, at any time permitted by paragraph (<I>a</I>) or (<I>b</I>), as the case may be, or during the two-month period immediately preceding the end of each year that the agreement continues to operate after the term specified therein.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Where no collective agreement or award in force<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(3) Where no collective agreement or arbitral award is in force in respect of a bargaining unit, any person claiming to represent a majority of the employees in that bargaining unit may, at any time after the expiration of twelve months from the date of certification of the bargaining agent for that bargaining unit, apply to the Board for a declaration that the employee organization certified as bargaining agent for that bargaining unit no longer represents a majority of the employees therein.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Taking of representation vote<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(4) On an application under subsection (1) or (3), the Board in its sole discretion may direct the taking of a representation vote in order to determine whether a majority of the employees in the bargaining unit no longer wish to be represented by the employee organization that is the bargaining agent for that bargaining unit, and in relation to the taking of any such vote the provisions of subsection 27.09(3) apply.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Revocation of certification of employee organization<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(5) After hearing any application under subsection (1) or (3), the Board shall revoke the certification of an employee organizationas bargaining agent for a bargaining unit if it is satisfied that a majority of the employees in that bargaining unit no longer wish to be represented by the employee organization.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:For Abandonment or Other Cause--><Para TopMargin="10" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">For Abandonment or Other Cause</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Abandonment of certification<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>27.13</B> (1) The Board shall revoke the certification of a bargaining agent where the bargaining agent advises the Board that it wishes to give up or abandon its certification or where the Board, on application by the employer or any employee affected, determines that the bargaining agent has ceased to act as bargaining agent.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Revocation where certification prohibited under s. 27.1<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(2) Where the Board, on application to it by the employer or employee, determines that a bargaining agent would not, if it were an employee organization applying for certification, be certified by the Board by reason of a prohibition contained in section 27.1, the Board shall revoke the certification of the bargaining agent.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:For Fraud--><Para TopMargin="10" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">For Fraud</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Certification obtained by fraud<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>27.14</B> (1) Where at any time the Board is satisfied that an employee organization has obtained certification as bargaining agent for a bargaining unit by fraud, the Board shall revoke the certification of the employee organization.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Effect of revocation<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(2) An employee organization the certification of which is revoked pursuant to subsection (1) is not entitled to claim any right or privilege flowing from that certification, and any collective agreement or arbitral award applying to the bargaining unit for which it was certified, to which the employee organization was a party, is void.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:Revocation of Certification of Council--><Para TopMargin="10" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">Revocation of Certification of Council</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Revocation of certification of council<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>27.15</B> (1) Where an employee organization that is a council of employee organizations has been certified as bargaining agent for a bargaining unit, the Board, on application to it by the employer or an employee organization that forms or has formed part of the council, shall revoke the certification of the council where it determines that the council no longer meets the additional requirements for certification required for a council of employee organizations by subsection 27.01(2) by reason of an alteration in the constituent membership of the council or any other circumstance.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Subsection (1) is in addition to other circumstances<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(2) The circumstances set out in subsection (1) apply in addition to the circumstances in which the certification of a bargaining agent may be revoked pursuant to sections 27.12 to 27.14.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:Effect of Revocation: Rights of Employee Organizations and Employees--><Para TopMargin="10" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">Effect of Revocation: Rights of Employee Organizations and Employees</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Effect of revocation<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>27.16</B> Where, at the time the certification of a bargaining agent for a bargaining unit is revoked, a collective agreement or arbitral award binding on the employees in that bargaining unit is in force, the agreement or award shall thereupon cease to be in effect, except where another employee organization is substituted as a party to the agreement or award on the revocation of that certification.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Determination of rights of bargaining agent<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>27.17</B> Where the certification of a bargaining agent for a bargaining unit is revoked by the Board pursuant to section 27.12, 27.13 or 27.15, any question as to any right or duty of that bargaining agent or of any new bargaining agent replacing it shall, on application by either organization, be determined by the Board.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Direction<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>27.18</B> Where the certification of a bargaining agent for a bargaining unit is revoked by the Board pursuant to section 27.12, 27.13, 27.14 or 27.15 and as a result thereof a collective agreement or arbitral award binding on the employees in the bargaining unit ceases to be in effect or a collective agreement or arbitral award applying to the bargaining unit is void, the Board shall, on application to it by or on behalf of any employee and in accordance with any regulations made by it in respect thereof, direct the manner in which any right acquired by, or determined by the Board to have accrued to, an employee that is affected by the revocation is to be recognized and given effect to.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:Successor Rights--><Para TopMargin="10" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">Successor Rights</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Mergers, amalgamations and transfers of jurisdiction<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>27.19</B> Where, on a merger or an amalgamation of employee organizations or a transfer of jurisdiction among employee organizations otherwise than as a result of revocation of certification, any question arises concerning the rights, privileges and duties of an employee organization under this Part or under a collective agreement or arbitral award in respect of a bargaining unit or an employee therein, the Board, on application to it by any employee organization affected, shall examine the question and may, in accordance with any regulations made by it in respect thereof, declare or determine what rights, privileges and duties, if any, have been acquired or are retained, as the case may be, by that employee organization.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:Negotiation of Collective Agreements--><Para TopMargin="10" Italic="Yes" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">Negotiation of Collective Agreements</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:Notice to Bargain Collectively--><Para TopMargin="5" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">Notice to Bargain Collectively</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Notice to bargain collectively<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>28.</B> (1) Where the Board has certified an employee organization as bargaining agent for a bargaining unit, the bargaining agent may require the employer, on behalf of the employees in the bargaining unit, or the employer may require the bargaining agent, by notice in writing given in accordance with subsection (2), to commence bargaining collectively, with a view to the conclusion of a collective agreement.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>When notice may be given<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(2) Notice to bargain collectively may be given</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>a</I>) where no collective agreement or arbitral award is in force and no request for arbitration has been made by either of the parties in accordance with this Part, at any time; and</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>b</I>) where a collective agreement or arbitral award is in force, within the period of two months before the agreement or award ceases to operate.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:Where Notice Given--><Para TopMargin="10" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">Where Notice Given</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Commencement of collective bargaining<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>28.1</B> Where notice to bargain collectively has been given, the bargaining agent and the officers designated to represent the employer shall, without delay, but in any case within twenty days after the notice was given or within such further time as the parties may agree, meet and commence to bargain collectively in good faith and make every reasonable effort to conclude a collective agreement.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Continuation in force of terms and conditions<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>28.2</B> Where notice to bargain collectively has been given, any term or condition of employment applicable to the employees in the bargaining unit in respect of which the notice was given that may be embodied in a collective agreement and that was in force on the day the notice was given shall remain in force and shall be observed by the employer, the bargaining agent for the bargaining unit and the employees in the bargaining unit, except as otherwise provided by any agreement in that behalf that may be entered into by the employer and the bargaining agent, until such time as</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>a</I>) a collective agreement has been entered into by the parties and no request for arbitration in respect of that term or condition of employment, or in respect of any term or condition of employment proposed to be substituted therefor, has been made in the manner and within the time prescribed therefor by this Part; or</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>b</I>) a request for arbitration in respect of that term or condition of employment, or in respect of any term or condition of employment proposed to be substituted therefor, has been made in accordance with this Part and a collective agreement has been entered into or an arbitral award has been rendered in respect thereof.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:Collective Agreements--><Para TopMargin="10" Italic="Yes" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">Collective Agreements</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:Authority to Enter into Agreement--><Para TopMargin="5" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">Authority to Enter into Agreement</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Authority of employer<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>28.3</B> The employer may enter, with the bargaining agent for a bargaining unit, into a collective agreement applicable to employees in that bargaining unit.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:Provisions of Collective Agreement--><Para TopMargin="10" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">Provisions of Collective Agreement</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Time within which agreement to be implemented<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>28.4</B> (1) The provisions of a collective agreement shall, subject to the appropriation by or under the authority of Parliament of any moneys that may be required, be implemented by the parties</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>a</I>) where a period within which the collective agreement is to be implemented is specified in the collective agreement, within that period; and</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>b</I>) where no period for implementation is specified in the collective agreement, within a period of ninety days from the date of its execution or, on application by either party to the agreement, within such longer period as may appear reasonable to the Board.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Term or condition requiring legislative implementation<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(2) No collective agreement shall provide, directly or indirectly, for the alteration or elimination of any existing term or condition of employment or the establishment of any new term or condition of employment</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>a</I>) the alteration or elimination of which or the establishment of which, as the case may be, would require or have the effect of requiring the enactment or amendment of any legislation by Parliament, except for the purpose of appropriating moneys required for its implementation; or</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>b</I>) that has been or after the coming into force of this Part is, as the case may be, established pursuant to the <I>Royal Canadian Mounted Police Superannuation Act</I>.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:Duration and Effect--><Para TopMargin="10" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">Duration and Effect</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>When agreement effective<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>28.5</B> (1) A collective agreement has effect in respect of a bargaining unit on and after</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>a</I>) where an effective date is specified, that day; and</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>b</I>) where no effective date is specified, the first day of the month next following the month in which the agreement is executed.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Where no provision as to term of agreement<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(2) Where a collective agreement contains no provision as to its term, or is for a term of less than one year, the collective agreement shall be deemed to be for a term of one year from the day on and after which it has effect pursuant to subsection (1).</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Saving provision<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(3) Nothing in subsection (2) shall be construed as preventing the amendment or revision of any provision of a collective agreement, other than a provision relating to the term of the collective agreement, that, under the agreement, may be amended or revised during the term thereof.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Binding effect of agreement<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>28.6</B> A collective agreement is, subject to and for the purposes of this Part, binding on the employer, on the bargaining agent that is a party thereto and its constituent elements, and on the employees in the bargaining unit in respect of which the bargaining agent has been certified, effective on and after the day on and after which it has effect pursuant to subsection 28.5(1).</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:DIVISION III--><Para TopMargin="10" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">DIVISION III</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:PROVISIONS APPLICABLE TO RESOLUTION OF DISPUTES--><Para TopMargin="5" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">PROVISIONS APPLICABLE TO RESOLUTION OF DISPUTES</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Provisions applicable to resolution of dispute<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>29.</B> Where the employer and the bargaining agent for a bargaining unit have bargained collectively in good faith with a view to concluding a collective agreement but have failed to reach agreement, sections 29.01 and 29.02 and sections 29.06 to 29.17 apply to the resolution of the dispute.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:Conciliation--><Para TopMargin="10" Italic="Yes" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">Conciliation</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Request for conciliation<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>29.01</B> Where the employer or a bargaining agent advises the Board by notice in writing of the inability of the parties to reach agreement on any term or condition of employment that may be embodied in a collective agreement and that it desires the assistance of a conciliator in reaching agreement, the Chairperson may appoint a conciliator who shall, forthwith after the appointment, confer with the parties and endeavour to assist them in reaching agreement.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Report of conciliator<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>29.02</B> A conciliator shall, within fourteen days from the date of the conciliator’s appointment or within such longer period as the Chairperson may determine, report the success or failure of the conciliation to the Chairperson.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:Arbitration--><Para TopMargin="10" Italic="Yes" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">Arbitration</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Board to appoint panels<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>29.03</B> (1) The Board shall appoint two panels, one panel to consist of at least three persons representative of the interests of the employer and the other to consist of at least three persons representative of the interests of employees.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Tenure of members of panels<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(2) A member of a panel appointed by the Board under subsection (1) shall be appointed to hold office for such term as the Board considers appropriate.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Eligibility<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(3) A person is not eligible to hold office as a member of a panel if the person is not eligible to be a member of the Board or, if the person is a member of the Board, unless the person is a member of the Board pursuant to a selection under section 29.04.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Board for arbitration<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>29.04</B> (1) In respect of each dispute referred to arbitration, the Board shall be deemed to consist, for the period of the arbitration proceedings and for the purposes of the arbitration only, of a member of the Board and two other persons, one each selected by the Board from each panel appointed under subsection 29.03(1).</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Deemed membership on Board during arbitration proceedings<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(2) A person selected by the Board from a panel under subsection (1) shall be deemed to be a member of the Board for the period of the arbitration proceedings in respect of which the person is selected.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Qualifications to serve on Board for arbitration<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(3) No person shall act as a member of the Board in respect of a matter referred to arbitration if the person has at any time during the six months immediately preceding the day of the selection of that person under subsection (1) acted in respect of any matter concerning employer-employee relations as solicitor, counsel or agent of the employer or of any employee organization that has an interest in the matter referred to arbitration.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Chairperson may appoint outside arbitrator<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>29.05</B> (1) Notwithstanding anything in this Part, if the Chairperson considers it advisable to do so, the Chairperson may appoint an arbitrator in place of the Board in respect of any matters in dispute referred to arbitration under this Part.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Eligibility<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(2) A person is not eligible to be appointed arbitrator under subsection (1) if the person</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>a</I>) is not eligible to be a member of the Board;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>b</I>) is a member of the Board or member of a panel appointed by the Board under subsection 29.03(1); or</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>c</I>) is not eligible under subsection 29.04(3) to act as a member of the Board in respect of a matter referred to arbitration.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Powers of arbitrator<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(3) An arbitrator appointed under this section has all the powers of the Board set out in paragraphs 26.1(<I>b</I>) to (<I>d</I>).</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Sections 29.08 to 29.17 apply<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(4) Sections 29.08 to 29.17 apply, with such modifications as the circumstances require, in respect of matters in dispute referred to an arbitrator appointed under subsection (1).</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:Request for Arbitration--><Para TopMargin="10" Italic="Yes" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">Request for Arbitration</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Request for arbitration<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>29.06</B> (1) Where the parties to collective bargaining have bargained collectively in good faith with a view to concluding a collective agreement but have been unable to reach agreement on any term or condition of employment of employees in the relevant bargaining unit that may be embodied in an arbitral award, either party may, by notice in writing to the Secretary of the Board given in accordance with subsection (2), request arbitration in respect of that term or condition of employment.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>When notice may be given<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(2) The notice referred to in subsection (1) may be given</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>a</I>) at any time, where no collective agreement has been entered into by the parties and no request for arbitration has been made by either party since the commencement of the bargaining; or</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>b</I>) not later than seven days after any collective agreement is entered into by the parties, in any other case.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Notice to be given<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(3) Where arbitration is requested by notice under subsection (1), the party making the request shall</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>a</I>) specify in the notice the terms and conditions of employment in respect of which it requests arbitration and its proposals concerning the award to be made by the Board in respect thereof; and</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>b</I>) annex to the notice a copy of any collective agreement entered into by the parties.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Request for arbitration by other party<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>29.07</B> (1) Where notice under section 29.06 is received by the Secretary of the Board from any party requesting arbitration, the Secretary shall forthwith send a copy of the notice to the other party, who shall within seven days after receipt thereof advise the Secretary, by notice in writing, of any matter, additional to the matters specified in the notice under section 29.06, that was a subject of negotiation between the parties during the period before the arbitration was requested but on which the parties were unable to reach agreement and in respect of which, being a matter that may be embodied in an arbitral award, that other party requests arbitration.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Notice to include proposal concerning award<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(2) Where arbitration in respect of any matter is requested by notice under subsection (1), the party making the request shall include in the notice its proposal concerning the award to be made by the Board in respect thereof.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:Consideration of Dispute and Award--><Para TopMargin="10" Italic="Yes" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">Consideration of Dispute and Award</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Matters constituting terms of reference<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>29.08</B> (1) Subject to section 29.11, the matters in dispute specified in the notice under section 29.06 and in any notice under section 29.07 constitute the terms of reference of the Board in relation to the request for arbitration and the Board shall, after considering the matters in dispute together with any other matter that the Board considers necessarily incidental to the resolution of the matters in dispute, render an arbitral award in respect thereof.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Where agreement subsequently reached<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(2) Where, at any time before an arbitral award is rendered, the parties reach agreement on any matter in dispute referred to the Board under subsection (1) and enter into a collective agreement in respect thereof, the matters in dispute so referred to the Board shall be deemed not to include that matter and no arbitral award shall be rendered by the Board in respect thereof.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Factors to be taken into account by Board<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>29.09</B> In the conduct of proceedings before it and in rendering an arbitral award in respect of a matter in dispute, the Board shall consider</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>a</I>) the need of the employer for qualified employees,</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>b</I>) the need to maintain appropriate relationships in the conditions of employment between different grade levels within an occupation and between occupations of employees,</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>c</I>) the need to establish terms and conditions of employment that are fair and reasonable in relation to the qualifications required, the work performed, the responsibility assumed and the nature of the services rendered, and</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>d</I>) any other factor that appears to it to be relevant to the matter in dispute,</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="0">and, so far as is consistent with the requirements of the employer, the Board shall give due regard to maintaining comparability between the conditions of employment of employees and those of persons in similar employment.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Parties to be heard<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>29.1</B> Subject to this Part, the Board shall, before rendering an arbitral award in respect of a matter in dispute, give full opportunity to both parties to present evidence and make submissions to it.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:Arbitral Award Matters--><Para TopMargin="10" Italic="Yes" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">Arbitral Award Matters</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Award not to require legislative implementation<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>29.11</B> (1) Subsection 28.4(2) applies, with such modifications as the circumstances require, in relation to an arbitral award.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Matters not to be dealt with by award<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(2) No arbitral award shall deal with the standards, procedures or processes governing the appointment, appraisal, promotion, demotion, transfer, lay-off or release of employees, or with any term or condition of employment of employees that was not a subject of negotiation between the parties during the period before arbitration was requested in respect thereof.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Award to be limited<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(3) An arbitral award shall deal only with terms and conditions of employment of employees in the bargaining unit in respect of which the request for arbitration was made.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:Making of Arbitral Award--><Para TopMargin="10" Italic="Yes" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">Making of Arbitral Award</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Award to be signed<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>29.12</B> (1) An arbitral award shall be signed by the member of the Board who is not a member selected from a panel appointed under section 29.03 and copies thereof shall be transmitted to the parties to the dispute and no report or observations thereon shall be made or given by either of the members selected from a panel appointed under section 29.03.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Decision<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(2) Subject to subsection (3), a decision of the majority of the members of the Board in respect of the matters in dispute shall be the arbitral award in respect of the matters in dispute.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Decision where majority cannot agree<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(3) Where the majority of the members of the Board cannot agree on the terms of the arbitral award to be rendered in respect thereof, the decision of the member of the Board who is not a member selected from a panel appointed under section 29.03 shall be the arbitral award in respect of the matters in dispute.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Form of award<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(4) An arbitral award shall, wherever possible, be made in such form</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>a</I>) as will be susceptible of being read and interpreted with, or annexed to and published with, any collective agreement dealing with other terms and conditions of employment of the employees in the bargaining unit in respect of which the arbitral award applies; and</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>b</I>) as will enable its incorporation into and implementation by regulations, by-laws, directives or other instruments that may be required to be made or issued by the employer or the relevant bargaining agent in respect thereof.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:Duration and Operation of Arbitral Awards--><Para TopMargin="10" Italic="Yes" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">Duration and Operation of Arbitral Awards</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Binding effect of arbitral award<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>29.13</B> (1) An arbitral award is, subject to and for the purposes of this Part, binding on the employer and on the bargaining agent that is a party thereto and on the employees in the bargaining unit in respect of which the bargaining agent has been certified, effective on and after the day on which the award is rendered or such later day as the Board may determine.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Retroactive application<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(2) A provision of an arbitral award made in respect of a term or condition of employment may be retroactive to the extent that it is capable of being retroactively applied, in whole or in part, to a day prior to the day on and after which the arbitral award becomes binding on the parties but not before the day on which notice to bargain collectively was given by either party.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Effect on previous collective agreement or award<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(3) Where, in relation to any or all of the provisions of an arbitral award made in respect of terms and conditions of employment, there was previously in effect a collective agreement or arbitral award, the previous collective agreement or arbitral award is displaced, to the extent of any conflict, for the term, determined in accordance with section 29.14, for which the subsequent award is operative.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Term of arbitral award<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>29.14</B> (1) The Board shall, in respect of every arbitral award, determine and specify therein the term for which the arbitral award is to be operative and, in making its determination, it shall take into account</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>a</I>) where a collective agreement applicable to the bargaining unit is in effect or has been entered into but is not yet in effect, the term of that collective agreement; and</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>b</I>) where no collective agreement applying to the bargaining unit has been entered into,</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="4" FirstLineIndent="0">(i) the term of any previous collective agreement that applied to the bargaining unit, or</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="4" FirstLineIndent="0">(ii) the term of any other collective agreement that to the Board appears relevant.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Limitation on term of award<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(2) No arbitral award, in the absence of the application thereto of any criterion referred to in paragraph (1)(<I>a</I>) or (b), shall be for a term of less than one year or more than two years from the day on and after which it becomes binding on the parties.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:Implementation of Arbitral Awards--><Para TopMargin="10" Italic="Yes" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">Implementation of Arbitral Awards</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Implementation of awards<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>29.15</B> The terms and conditions of employment that are the subject of an arbitral award shall, subject to the appropriation by or under the authority of Parliament of any moneys that may be required therefor, be implemented by the parties within a period of ninety days from the date on and after which it becomes binding on the parties or within such longer period as, on application to the Board by either party, appears reasonable to the Board.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:Completion and Variation of Arbitral Awards--><Para TopMargin="10" Italic="Yes" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">Completion and Variation of Arbitral Awards</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Reference back to Board<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>29.16</B> Where in respect of an arbitral award it appears to either of the parties that the Board has failed to deal with any matter in dispute referred to it, that party may, within seven days from the day the award is rendered, refer the matter back to the Board, and the Board shall thereupon deal with the matter.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Authority to amend or vary award<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>29.17</B> The Board may, on application jointly by both parties to an arbitral award, amend, alter or vary any provision of that award where it is made to appear to the Board that the amendment, alteration or variation thereof is warranted, having regard to circumstances that have arisen since the making of the award or of which the Board did not have notice at the time of the making thereof, or having regard to such other circumstances as the Board deems relevant.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:DIVISION IV--><Para TopMargin="10" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">DIVISION IV</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:GRIEVANCES--><Para TopMargin="5" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">GRIEVANCES</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:Right to Present Grievances--><Para TopMargin="5" Italic="Yes" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">Right to Present Grievances</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Right of employee<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>30.</B> (1) Subject to subsection (2), an employee is entitled to present a grievance if he or she feels aggrieved</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>a</I>) by the interpretation or application, in respect of the employee, of</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="4" FirstLineIndent="0">(i) a provision of a statute or regulation,  of a by-law, direction or other instrument made or issued by the employer, or of the Commissioner’s standing orders, dealing with terms and conditions of employment, or</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="4" FirstLineIndent="0">(ii) a provision of a collective agreement or an arbitral award; or</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>b</I>) as a result of any occurrence or matter affecting the employee’s terms and conditions of employment.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Limitation<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(2) An employee is not entitled to present any grievance relating to the interpretation or application in respect of the employee of a provision of a collective agreement or an arbitral award unless the employee has the approval of and is represented by the bargaining agent for the bargaining unit to which the collective agreement or arbitral award applies.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Right to be represented by employee organization<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(3) An employee who is not included in a bargaining unit for which an employee organization has been certified as bargaining agent may seek the assistance of and, if the employee chooses, may be represented by any employee organization in the presentation or reference to adjudication of a grievance.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Idem<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(4) No employee who is included in a bargaining unit for which an employee organization has been certified as bargaining agent may be represented by any employee organization, other than the employee organization certified as bargaining agent, in the presentation or reference to adjudication of a grievance.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Part IV and V may be the subject of a grievance<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(5) For greater certainty, subject to subsection (2), an employee may present a grievance relating to any sanction imposed or measure taken by the employer under Part IV or V of this Act.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:Adjudication of Grievances--><Para TopMargin="10" Italic="Yes" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">Adjudication of Grievances</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:Reference to Adjudication--><Para TopMargin="5" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">Reference to Adjudication</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Reference of grievance to adjudication<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>31.</B> (1) Where an employee has presented a grievance up to and including the final level in the grievance process and the grievance has not been dealt with to the satisfaction of the employee, the employee may refer the grievance to adjudication if the grievance is with respect to</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>a</I>) the interpretation or application, in respect of the employee, of</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="4" FirstLineIndent="0">(i) a provision of a statute or regulation, of a by-law, direction or other instrument made or issued by the employer, or of the Commissioner’s standing orders, dealing with terms and conditions of employment, or</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="4" FirstLineIndent="0">(ii) a provision of a collective agreement or an arbitral award;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>b</I>) disciplinary action against the employee resulting in suspension or a financial penalty;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>c</I>) the termination of employment of the employee, other than rejection on probation in respect of an initial appointment;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>d</I>) demotion of the employee;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>e</I>) where the employee has been denied an appointment, the employer’s evaluation of the skill, fitness and ability of the employee with respect to the employee’s qualification for the appointment; or</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>f</I>) subject to subsection 26(3), the employer’s classification of the employee.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Approval of bargaining agent<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(2) Where a grievance that may be presented by an employee to adjudication is a grievance relating to the interpretation or application in respect of the employee of a provision of a collective agreement or an arbitral award, the employee is not entitled to refer the grievance to adjudication unless the bargaining agent for the bargaining unit to which the collective agreement or arbitral award applies signifies in prescribed manner its approval of the reference of the grievance to adjudication and its willingness to represent the employee in the adjudication proceedings.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Commencement of certain grievance adjudication<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(3) A grievance with respect to a matter referred to in paragraph (1)(<I>f</I>) shall not be adjudicated under this Part unless the circumstances that cause the grievance are in existence after the day that is one year after this Part comes into force.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:Appointment of Adjudicators--><Para TopMargin="10" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">Appointment of Adjudicators</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Members of the Board to adjudicate<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>32.</B> The Board shall assign such members of the Board as may be required to hear and adjudicate on grievances referred to adjudication under this Part.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:Establishment of a Board of Adjudication--><Para TopMargin="10" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">Establishment of a Board of Adjudication</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Composition of board of adjudication<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>33.</B> (1) Where a grievance is referred to a board of adjudication, the board shall be composed of three persons, namely,</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>a</I>) a member of the Board, who shall be the chairperson of the board of adjudication; and</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>b</I>) two other persons, one nominated by each party.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Ineligible to be a member of the board<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(2) A person is not eligible to be a member of the board of adjudication described in subsection (1) if the person has any direct interest in or connection with the grievance, its handling or its disposition.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:Duty of the Board--><Para TopMargin="10" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">Duty of the Board</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Notice to specify whether adjudicator named, etc.<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>33.1</B> (1) Where a grievance has been referred to adjudication, the aggrieved employee shall, in the manner prescribed, give notice to the Board and shall specify in the notice whether an adjudicator is named in any applicable collective agreement or is otherwise selected by the parties or, if no such adjudicator is so named or selected, whether the employee requests the establishment of a board of adjudication.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Action to be taken by Board<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(2) Where a grievance has been referred to adjudication and the aggrieved employee has notified the Board as required by subsection (1), the Board shall, in the manner and within the time prescribed,</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>a</I>) where the grievance is one arising out of a collective agreement and an adjudicator is named therein, refer the matter to the adjudicator so named;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>b</I>) where the parties have selected an adjudicator, refer the matter to the adjudicator so selected;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>c</I>) where the establishment of a board of adjudication has been requested by the aggrieved employee and no objection thereto has been made by the employer within such time as may be prescribed, establish the board and refer the matter to it; and</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>d</I>) in any other case, refer the matter to an adjudicator selected by it.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Adjudication of certain matters<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(3) Notwithstanding section 32 and subsections (1) and (2), where a grievance respecting a matter referred to in paragraph 31(1)(<I>d</I>), (<I>e</I>) or (<I>f</I>) is referred to adjudication, the adjudication shall be by a single adjudicator selected by</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>a</I>) the employee and employer concerned; or</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>b</I>) the Chairperson, where the employer and employee are unable to agree on the selection of an adjudicator and either party makes a written request to the Chairperson to select an adjudicator.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Adjudicator re certain matters<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(4) A person selected to adjudicate a grievance respecting a matter referred to in paragraph 31(1)(<I>d</I>), (<I>e</I>) or (<I>f</I>)</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>a</I>) shall not be a member of the Board but has, for the purposes of the adjudication, all the powers, rights and privileges of the Board other than the power to make regulations of general application under section 26.07; and</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>b</I>) shall not have any direct interest in or in connection with the grievance, its handling or its disposition.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Powers of adjudicator<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>33.2</B> An adjudicator has, for the purposes of the adjudication of a grievance respecting a matter referred to in paragraph 31(1)(<I>a</I>), (<I>b</I>) or (<I>c</I>) that is referred to adjudication, the powers that the Board has under section 26.11, other than paragraph 26.11(<I>e</I>) or (<I>f</I>), in relation to the hearing or determination of a proceeding before it.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:Jurisdiction of Adjudicator--><Para TopMargin="10" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">Jurisdiction of Adjudicator</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Compliance with procedures<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>33.3</B> (1) Subject to any regulation made by the Board under paragraph 34.1(1)(<I>e</I>), no grievance shall be referred to adjudication and no adjudicator shall hear or render a decision on a grievance until all procedures established for the presentation of the grievance up to and including the final level in the grievance process have been complied with.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Decision requiring amendment<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(2) No adjudicator shall, in respect of any grievance, render any decision thereon the effect of which would be to require the amendment of a collective agreement or an arbitral award.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Binding effect<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(3) Where a grievance has been presented up to and including the final level in the grievance process and is not one that under section 31 may be referred to adjudication, the decision on the grievance taken at the final level in the grievance process is final and binding for all purposes of this Part and no further action under this Part may be taken thereon.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:Decision of Adjudicator--><Para TopMargin="10" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">Decision of Adjudicator</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Hearing of grievance<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>33.4</B> (1) Where a grievance is referred to adjudication, the adjudicator shall give both parties to the grievance an opportunity to be  heard.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Decision on grievance<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(2) After considering the grievance, the adjudicator shall render a decision and</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>a</I>) send a copy of the decision to each party, to the representative of each party and to the bargaining agent, if any, for the bargaining unit to which the aggrieved employee belongs; and</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>b</I>) deposit a copy of the decision with the Secretary of the Board.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Decision of board of adjudication<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(3) In the case of a board of adjudication, a decision of the majority of its members on a grievance is a decision of the board thereon, and the decision shall be signed by the chairperson of the board.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Implementation of decision by employer<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(4) Where a decision on any grievance referred to adjudication requires any action by the employer, the employer shall take that action.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Action to be taken by employee or bargaining agent<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(5) Where a decision on any grievance requires any action by an employee or a bargaining agent or both, the employee or bargaining agent or both, as the case may be, shall take that action.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Powers of Board with respect to decision on grievance<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(6) The Board may, in accordance with section 26.09, take such action as is contemplated by that section where the decision of an adjudicator on a grievance is not complied with within the period specified but shall not inquire into the basis or substance of the decision.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:Expenses of Adjudication--><Para TopMargin="10" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">Expenses of Adjudication</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Where adjudicator named or selected<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>33.5</B> (1) Where an adjudicator is named in any applicable collective agreement or has been otherwise selected by the parties or has been selected by the Board, the method of determining the adjudicator’s remuneration and of defraying such expenses as the adjudicator may incur shall be as established in the applicable collective agreement, but if there is no such agreement or if the agreement does not specify the method, the adjudicator’s remuneration and expenses shall be borne equally by the parties.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Exception<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(2) Where a grievance is referred to a board of adjudication, the remuneration and expenses of the nominee of each party shall be borne by the parties respectively.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Recovery<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(3) Any amount that by subsection (2) is payable to the Board by a bargaining agent may be recovered as a debt due to the Crown by the bargaining agent, which shall, for the purposes of this subsection, be deemed to be a person.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Adjudicator re certain grievances<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(4) Where a grievance respecting a matter referred to in paragraph 31(1)(<I>d</I>), (<I>e</I>) or (<I>f</I>) is referred to adjudication, the adjudicator’s remuneration and expenses shall be borne equally by the parties.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:Enforcement of Obligations of Employer and Employee Organizations--><Para TopMargin="10" Italic="Yes" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">Enforcement of Obligations of Employer and Employee Organizations</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Reference by employer or bargaining agent to Board<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>34.</B> (1) Where the employer and a bargaining agent have executed a collective agreement or are bound by an arbitral award and the employer or the bargaining agent seeks to enforce an obligation that is alleged to arise out of the agreement or award, and the obligation, if any, is not one the enforcement of which may be the subject of a grievance of an employee in the bargaining unit to which the collective agreement or arbitral award applies, either the employer or the bargaining agent may, in the prescribed manner, refer the matter to the Board.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Board shall hear and determine<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(2) Where a matter is referred to the Board pursuant to subsection (1), the Board shall hear and determine whether there is an obligation as alleged and whether, if there is, there has been a failure to observe or to carry out the obligation.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Hearing and determination of reference<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(3) The Board shall hear and determine any matter referred to it pursuant to subsection (1) as though the matter were a grievance, and subsection 33.3(2) and sections 33.4 and 33.5 apply to the hearing and determination of that matter.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:Regulations respecting Grievances--><Para TopMargin="10" Italic="Yes" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">Regulations respecting Grievances</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Regulations re procedures for presentation of grievances<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>34.1</B> (1) The Board may make regulations in relation to the procedure for the presentation of grievances, including regulations respecting</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>a</I>) the manner and form of presenting a grievance and, in the case of group grievances, the form of the consent of the employees concerned;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>b</I>) the maximum number of levels in each grievance process;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>c</I>) the manner in which employees are to be advised of the names of the persons whose decision on a grievance constitutes a level in the grievance process, including the final level;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>d</I>) the time within which a grievance may be presented at any level in a grievance process;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>e</I>) the circumstances in which any level below the final level in a grievance process may be eliminated;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>f</I>) the manner in which and the time within which a grievance may be referred to adjudication after it has been presented up to and including the final level in the grievance process;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>g</I>) the establishment of rules of procedure for hearing a grievance; and</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>h</I>) the specification of the time within which and the persons to whom notices and other documents must be sent or given under this Part, and when the notices are deemed to have been sent, given or received.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Application of regulations<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(2) Any regulations made by the Board under subsection (1) in relation to the procedure for the presentation of grievances do not apply in respect of employees included in a bargaining unit for which a bargaining agent has been certified by the Board, to the extent that such regulations are inconsistent with any provisions contained in a collective agreement entered into by the bargaining agent and the employer applicable to those employees.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Regulations re adjudication of grievances<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(3) The Board may make regulations in relation to the adjudication of grievances, including regulations respecting</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>a</I>) the manner in which and the time within which boards of adjudication are to be established;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>b</I>) the procedure to be followed by adjudicators; and</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>c</I>) the form of decisions rendered by adjudicators.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:DIVISION V--><Para TopMargin="10" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">DIVISION V</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:GENERAL--><Para TopMargin="5" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">GENERAL</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:Review of Orders--><Para TopMargin="5" Italic="Yes" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">Review of Orders</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Orders not subject to review by court<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>35.</B> (1) Subject to this Part, every order or decision of the Board is final and may not be questioned or reviewed in any court, except in accordance with the <I>Federal Court Act</I> on the grounds referred to in paragraph 18.1(4)(<I>a</I>), (<I>b</I>) or (<I>e</I>) of that Act.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Standing of Board<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(2) The Board has standing to appear in proceedings referred to in subsection (1) for the purpose of making submissions regarding the standard of review to be used with respect to decisions of the Board and the Board’s jurisdiction, policies and procedures.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>No review by injunction, etc.<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(3) Except as permitted by subsection (1), no order, decision or proceeding of the Board made or carried on under or purporting to be made or carried on under this Part may, on any ground, including the ground that the order, decision or proceeding is beyond the jurisdiction of the Board to make or carry on or that, in the course of any proceeding, the Board for any reason exceeded or lost its jurisdiction,</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>a</I>) be questioned, reviewed, prohibited or restrained; or</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>b</I>) be made the subject of any proceedings in or any process of any court, whether by way of injunction, <I>certiorari</I>, prohibition, <I>quo warranto</I> or otherwise.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Filing of order in Federal Court<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>35.1</B> For the purpose of enforcing an adjudicator’s order, any person who was a party to the proceedings that resulted in the order being made may, after the day provided in the order for compliance or, if no such day is provided for, after 30 days have elapsed since the day the order was made, file in the Federal Court a copy of the order that is certified to be a true copy, and an order so filed becomes an order of that Court and may be enforced as such.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:Offences Relating to Strikes--><Para TopMargin="10" Italic="Yes" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">Offences Relating to Strikes</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Participation by employee in strike<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>35.2</B> No employee shall participate in a strike.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Declaration or authorization of strike<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>35.3</B> No employee organization shall declare or authorize a strike of employees and no officer or representative of an employee organization shall counsel or procure the declaration or authorization of a strike of employees or the participation of employees in a strike, the effect of which is or would be to involve the participation of an employee in a strike in contravention of section 35.2.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Offences and punishment: employee<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>35.4</B> (1) Every employee who contravenes section 35.2 is guilty of an offence and liable on summary conviction to a fine of not more than $1,000.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Idem: officer or representative<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(2) Every officer or representative of an employee organization who contravenes section 35.3 is guilty of an offence and liable on summary conviction to a fine of not more than $1,000.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Idem: employee organization<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(3) Every employee organization that contravenes section 35.3 is guilty of an offence and liable on summary conviction to a fine of not more than $1,000 for each day that any strike declared or authorized by it in contravention of that section is or continues in effect.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Prosecution of employee organization<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>35.5</B> A prosecution for an offence referred to in section 35.4 may be brought against an employee organization and in the name of that organization, and for the purposes of any such prosecution an employee organization shall be deemed to be a person and any act or thing done or omitted by an officer or representative of an employee organization within the scope of his or her authority to act on behalf of the employee organization shall be deemed to be an act or thing done or omitted by the employee organization.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:Consent to Prosecution--><Para TopMargin="10" Italic="Yes" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">Consent to Prosecution</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Consent<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>35.6</B> No prosecution arising out of an alleged failure by any person to observe any prohibition contained in section 26.01, 26.02 or 26.03 and no prosecution for an offence referred to in section 35.4 shall be instituted except with the consent of the Board.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:Protection of Members of the Board and Staff--><Para TopMargin="10" Italic="Yes" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">Protection of Members of the Board and Staff</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Evidence respecting information obtained<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>35.7</B> No member of the Board, no adjudicator, conciliator or officer or employee of or person appointed by the Board and no arbitrator appointed under section 29.05 shall be required to give evidence in any civil action, suit or other proceeding respecting information obtained in the discharge of his or her duties under this Part.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:Witness Fees--><Para TopMargin="10" Italic="Yes" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">Witness Fees</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Payment of witness fees<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>35.8</B> A person who is summoned by the Board or an arbitrator appointed under section 29.05 to attend as a witness in any proceedings thereof taken pursuant to this Part and who so attends is entitled to be paid an allowance for expenses, determined in accordance with the scale for the time being in force with respect to witnesses in civil suits in the superior court of the province in which the proceedings are being taken.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:Oaths and Solemn Affirmations--><Para TopMargin="10" Italic="Yes" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">Oaths and Solemn Affirmations</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Oath or solemn affirmation to be taken<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>35.9</B> Before commencing his or her functions, a person appointed under this Act shall take an oath or make a solemn affirmation in the following form before a commissioner of oaths or other person having authority to administer oaths or solemn affirmations:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">I, ...................., do swear (<I>or</I> solemnly affirm) that I will faithfully, truly and impartially, to the best of my judgment, skill and ability, execute and perform the office of .....................</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:Provision of Facilities and Staff--><Para TopMargin="10" Italic="Yes" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">Provision of Facilities and Staff</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Facilities and staff<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>36.</B> The Board shall provide an arbitrator appointed under section 29.05 and an adjudicator with quarters and staff and such other facilities as are necessary to enable the arbitrator or adjudicator to carry out their respective functions under this Part.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:Superannuation--><Para TopMargin="10" Italic="Yes" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">Superannuation</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Application of <I>Public Service Superannuation Act</I><br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>36.1</B> Unless the Governor in Council otherwise orders in any case or class of cases, a person appointed under this Part shall be deemed not to be employed in the Public Service for the purposes of the <I>Public Service Superannuation Act</I>.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:Report to Parliament--><Para TopMargin="10" Italic="Yes" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">Report to Parliament</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Annual report<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>36.2</B> As soon as possible after the end of each year, the Board shall prepare a report on the administration of this Part during that year and shall cause the report to be laid before each House of Parliament on any of the first fifteen days on which that House sits after the report has been prepared.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>7.</B> Subsection 40(3) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Answer not receivable<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(3) No answer or statement made in response to a question described in subsection (2) shall be used or receivable in any criminal or civil proceedings.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>8.</B> Subsection 41(9) of the Act is repealed.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>9.</B> Section 42 of the Act is repealed.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>10.</B> Sections 43 to 45.17 of the Act are replaced by the following:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Formal disciplinary action<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>43.</B> (1) Where it is established to the satisfaction of an appropriate officer that a member has contravened the Code of Conduct and the appropriate officer is of the opinion that, having regard to the gravity of the contravention and to the surrounding circumstances, informal disciplinary action under section 41 would not be sufficient, the appropriate officer shall impose any one or more of the following sanctions on the member, namely,</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>a</I>) dismissal from the Force;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>b</I>) direction to resign from the Force and, in default of resigning within fourteen days after being directed to do so, dismissal from the Force;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>c</I>) demotion; or</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>d</I>) forfeiture of pay for a period not exceeding ten work days.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Informal disciplinary action<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(2) In addition to imposing a sanction under subsection (1), an appropriate officer may take any one or more of the informal disciplinary actions referred to in paragraphs 41(1)(<I>a</I>) to (<I>g</I>).</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Restriction<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(3) The sanction referred to in paragraph <keep>(1)(<I>c</I>)</keep> shall not be imposed on an inspector or a constable.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Limitation period<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(4) No sanction shall be imposed by an appropriate officer under this section in respect of an alleged contravention of the Code of Conduct by a member after the expiration of one year from the time the contravention and the identity of that member became known to the appropriate officer.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>11.</B> Part V of the Act is replaced by the following:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:PART V--><Para TopMargin="10" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">PART V</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:DISCHARGE AND DEMOTION--><Para TopMargin="5" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">DISCHARGE AND DEMOTION</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Ground for discharge or demotion<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>44.</B> (1) Any officer or any other member may be discharged or demoted on the ground, in this Part referred to as the “ground of unsuitability”, that the officer or member has repeatedly failed to perform the officer’s or member’s duties under this Act in a manner fitted to the requirements of the officer’s or member’s position, notwithstanding that the officer or member has been given reasonable assistance, guidance and supervision in an attempt to improve the performance of those duties.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Limitation<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(2) No officer or other member may be demoted under this Part by more than one rank or level.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Exceptions<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(3) No inspector or constable may be demoted under this Part.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Notice of intention<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>45.</B> (1) Before any officer or any other member is discharged or demoted under this Part, the appropriate officer shall serve the officer or other member with a notice in writing of the intention to discharge or demote the officer or the other member, as the case may be.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Contents of notice<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(2) A notice of intention served on an officer or other member under subsection (1) shall include particulars of the acts or omissions constituting the ground of unsuitability on which the discharge or demotion, as the case may be, is based.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Opportunity to examine material<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(3) An officer or other member who is served with a notice under subsection (1) shall be given a full and ample opportunity to examine the material relied on in support of the discharge or demotion, as the case may be.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Effective date<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(4) An officer or other member who is served with a notice under subsection (1) shall be discharged or demoted on the day specified in the notice.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:Resignation--><Para TopMargin="10" Italic="Yes" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">Resignation</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Resignation from Force<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>45.1</B> Nothing in this Part shall be construed as preventing the Commissioner from offering a member against whom a ground of unsuitability has been established pursuant to this Part the opportunity of resigning from the Force.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>12.</B> Subsection 45.36(2) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Statement not admissible<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(2) No answer or statement made, in the course of attempting to dispose of a complaint informally, by the complainant or the member or other person whose conduct is the subject-matter of the complaint shall be used or receivable in any criminal or civil proceedings.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>13.</B> Paragraph 45.45(8)(<I>b</I>) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>b</I>) any answer or statement made in response to a question described in subsection 24.1(7) or 40(2);</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>14.</B> Subsection 45.45(10) of the Act is repealed.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>15.</B> Subsection 46(1) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Definition of “board”<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>46.</B> (1) In this section and sections 47 to 47.3, “board” means a board of inquiry appointed under section 24.1 and, except for the purposes of subsection (4), includes the Public Service Staff Relations Board and the  Commission.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>16.</B> Section 47.1 of the Act is replaced by the following:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Representation<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>47.1</B> (1) Subject to any rules made pursuant to subsection (3), a member may be represented or assisted by any other member in any</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>a</I>) presentation of a grievance under Part II; or</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>b</I>) proceeding before a board, other than the Commission.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Privilege<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(2) Where a member is represented or assisted by another member pursuant to subsection (1), communications passing in confidence between the two members in relation to the grievance or proceeding are, for the purposes of this Act, privileged as if they were communications passing in professional confidence between the member and the member’s solicitor.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Rules<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(3) The Commissioner may make rules prescribing</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>a</I>) the members or members of any class of members who may not represent or assist another member in any grievance or proceeding referred to in subsection (1); and</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>b</I>) the circumstances in which a member may not represent or assist another member in any grievance or proceeding referred to in subsection (1).</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>17.</B> Subsection 47.2(2) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Service by mail<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2">(2) Any notice, decision or other document required by this Act to be served by a person or a board on the Commissioner, an appropriate officer or the Commission Chairman is sufficiently served if it is sent by or on behalf of that person or board by prepaid first class mail addressed to the Commissioner, the appropriate officer or the Commission Chairman, as the case may be.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>18.</B> Sections 47.4 and 47.5 of the Act are repealed.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>19.</B> Section 50 of the Act is replaced by the following:</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Offences<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>50.</B> Every person is guilty of an offence punishable on summary conviction who</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>a</I>) on being duly summoned as a witness or otherwise under Part I, II or VII, makes default in attending;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>b</I>) being in attendance as a witness in any proceeding under Part I, II or VII</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><MarginalNote>Offences<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="4" FirstLineIndent="0" Hyphenate="ON" TextAlign="Justify">(i) refuses to take an oath or solemn affirmation required of that person,</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="4" FirstLineIndent="0">(ii) refuses to produce any document or thing under that person’s control and required to be produced by that person, or</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="4" FirstLineIndent="0">(iii) refuses to answer any question that requires an answer;</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>c</I>) at any proceeding under Part I, II or VII, uses insulting or threatening language or causes any interference or disturbance; or</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="No"><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="2" FirstLineIndent="0">(<I>d</I>) prints observations or uses words likely to influence improperly a board of inquiry under Part I, the Commission under Part VII,  or witnesses at any proceeding under Part I, II or VII or to bring any such proceeding into disrepute, or in any other manner whatever displays contempt of any such proceeding.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:TRANSITIONAL PROVISION--><Para TopMargin="10" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">TRANSITIONAL PROVISION</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Transitional provision<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2" Bold="Yes"><B>20.</B> Any regulation that was made under section 21 of the <I>Royal Canadian Mounted Police Act</I> and that is not consistent with that Act, as amended by this Act, ceases to be in force at the coming into force of this Act.</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="N" Align="Yes" KeepWith="Next"><!--Heading:COMING INTO FORCE--><Para TopMargin="10" Hyphenate="OFF" TextAlign="Center">COMING INTO FORCE</Para></Block><Block LineCnt="Y" Align="Yes"><MarginalNote>Coming into force<br/></MarginalNote><Para TopMargin="5" LeftMargin="0" FirstLineIndent="2"><B>21.</B> <B>This Act comes into force 90 days after the day on which it receives royal assent.</B></Para></Block><Block Align="Yes"><Para Style="BPT_ImprintE"><br/><br/>Published under authority of the Senate of Canada</Para></Block><Block Align="Yes" LineCnt="N"><Para NoLineBreak="Yes" NoHtml="Yes" Leading="0" Size="0" TopMargin="0" BottomMargin="0"></Para></Block></Bill_Part></Bill>
